<Document id="0000332" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002542.htm">
 
<Focus>Aspirin overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0572036</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Acetylsalicylic acid overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000332-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Aspirin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Aspirin is a nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug (NSAID) used to relieve mild to moderate aches and pains, swelling, and fever. Aspirin overdose occurs when someone accidentally or intentionally takes more than the recommended amount of this medicine. This can happen in two ways: If a person takes a very large dose of aspirin at one time, it is called an acute overdose., If a normal daily dose of aspirin builds up in the body over time and causes symptoms, it is called a chronic overdose. This may happen if your kidneys do not work correctly or when you are dehydrated. Chronic overdoses are usually seen in older people during hot weather.,  This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with overdoses, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000332-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Aspirin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Airways and lungs: Rapid breathing, Slow, labored breathing, Wheezing ,  Eyes, ears, nose, and throat: Ringing in the ears, Blurred vision ,  Nervous system: Agitation, confusion, incoherence (not understandable), Collapse, Coma (lack of responsiveness), Seizures,  Drowsiness , Headache (severe), Unsteadiness, problems moving ,  Skin: Rash ,  Stomach and intestines: Diarrhea, Heartburn, Nausea, vomiting (sometimes bloody), Stomach pain (possible bleeding in the stomach and intestines) ,  Symptoms of chronic overdose may include: Fatigue, Slight fever, Confusion, Collapse, Rapid heart beat, Uncontrollable  rapid breathing , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000332-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Aspirin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>A toxic dose of aspirin is 200 to 300 mg/kg (milligrams per kilogram of body weight), and ingestion of 500 mg/kg is potentially lethal. In chronic overdose a lower level of aspirin in the body can result in serious illness. Much lower levels can affect children. If treatment is delayed or the overdose is large enough, symptoms will continue to get worse. Breathing becomes extremely fast or may stop. Seizures, high fevers, or death may occur. How well you do depends greatly on how much aspirin your body has absorbed and how much is flowing through your blood. If you take a large amount of aspirin but come quickly to the emergency room, treatments may help keep your blood levels of aspirin very low. If you do not get to the emergency room fast enough, the level of aspirin in your blood can become dangerously high.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000332-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Aspirin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>A toxic dose of aspirin is 200 to 300 mg/kg (milligrams per kilogram of body weight), and ingestion of 500 mg/kg is potentially lethal. In chronic overdose a lower level of aspirin in the body can result in serious illness. Much lower levels can affect children. If treatment is delayed or the overdose is large enough, symptoms will continue to get worse. Breathing becomes extremely fast or may stop. Seizures, high fevers, or death may occur. How well you do depends greatly on how much aspirin your body has absorbed and how much is flowing through your blood. If you take a large amount of aspirin but come quickly to the emergency room, treatments may help keep your blood levels of aspirin very low. If you do not get to the emergency room fast enough, the level of aspirin in your blood can become dangerously high.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>