<Document id="0000328" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002752.htm">
 
<Focus>Asphalt cement poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032343</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Asphalt</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pavement</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000328-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Asphalt cement poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Asphalt is a brownish-black liquid petroleum material that hardens when it cools. Asphalt cement poisoning occurs when someone swallows asphalt. If hot asphalt gets on the skin, serious injury can occur.  This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000328-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Asphalt cement poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Below are symptoms of asphalt poisoning in different parts of the body. EYES, EARS, NOSE, AND THROAT Loss of vision, Severe pain in the throat, Severe pain or burning in the nose, eyes, ears, lips, or tongue,  HEART AND BLOOD Collapse, Low blood pressure that develops rapidly (shock),  LUNGS AND AIRWAYS Breathing difficulty (from breathing in asphalt), Throat swelling (which may also cause breathing difficulty),  SKIN Burns, Irritation, Holes (ulcers) in the skin or tissues under the skin,  STOMACH AND INTESTINES Blockage in the intestines,  Blood in the stool , Burns of the food pipe (esophagus), Severe&#160; abdominal pain , Vomiting (may contain blood), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000328-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Asphalt cement poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000328-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Asphalt cement poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on how much asphalt they swallowed and how quickly they receive treatment. The faster medical help is given, the better the chance for recovery. Hot asphalt cools very quickly and is difficult to get off the skin. Serious burns can easily occur from the extreme heat. Construction workers who work with asphalt should wear protective clothing. Asphalt is hard to swallow, but it may cause serious damage. Delayed injury may occur, including a hole forming in the throat, esophagus, or stomach. This can lead to severe bleeding and infection. Surgical procedures may be needed to treat these complications. If asphalt gets in the eye, ulcers may develop in the cornea, the clear part of the eye. This can cause blindness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000328-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Asphalt cement poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on how much asphalt they swallowed and how quickly they receive treatment. The faster medical help is given, the better the chance for recovery. Hot asphalt cools very quickly and is difficult to get off the skin. Serious burns can easily occur from the extreme heat. Construction workers who work with asphalt should wear protective clothing. Asphalt is hard to swallow, but it may cause serious damage. Delayed injury may occur, including a hole forming in the throat, esophagus, or stomach. This can lead to severe bleeding and infection. Surgical procedures may be needed to treat these complications. If asphalt gets in the eye, ulcers may develop in the cornea, the clear part of the eye. This can cause blindness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>