<Document id="0000749" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001494.htm">
 
<Focus>Cervical polyps</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0007855</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000749-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cervical polyps are fingerlike growths on the lower part of the uterus that connects with the vagina ( cervix ).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000749-2" qtype="causes">What causes Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of cervical polyps is not known. They may occur with: An abnormal response to increased levels of the female hormone estrogen,  Chronic  inflammation, Clogged blood vessels in the cervix,  Cervical polyps are common. They are often found in women over age 40 who have had many children. Polyps are rare in young women who have not started having their period (menstruation).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000749-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>Polyps do not always cause symptoms. When symptoms are present, they may include: Very heavy menstrual periods, Vaginal bleeding after douching or intercourse,  Abnormal vaginal bleeding  after  menopause  or between periods, White or yellow mucus (leukorrhea), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000749-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a pelvic exam. Some smooth, red or purple fingerlike growths will be seen on the cervix. Most often, the provider will remove the polyp with a gentle tug and send it for testing. Most of the time, the biopsy will show cells that are consistent with a benign polyp. Rarely, there may be abnormal, precancerous, or cancer cells in a polyp.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000749-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>The provider can remove polyps during a simple outpatient procedure.  Smaller polyps may be removed with gentle twisting., Electrocautery may be needed to remove larger polyps.,  The removed polyp tissue should be sent to a lab for further tests.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000749-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most polyps are not cancerous (benign) and are easy to remove. Polyps do not grow back most of the time. Women who have polyps are at risk of growing more polyps.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000749-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>There may be bleeding and slight cramping for a few days after removal of a polyp. Some cervical cancers may first appear as a polyp. Certain uterine polyps&#160;may be associated with uterine cancer.&#160;
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000749-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have: Abnormal bleeding from the vagina, including bleeding after sex or between periods, Abnormal discharge from the vagina, Abnormally heavy periods , Bleeding or spotting after menopause,  Contact your provider to schedule regular gynecological exams. Ask how often you should receive a  Pap test .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000749-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Cervical polyps ?</Question>
			<Answer>See your provider to treat infections as soon as possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>