<Document id="0000239" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003167.htm">
 
<Focus>Ankle pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238656</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pain - ankle</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000239-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ankle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ankle pain involves any discomfort in one or both ankles.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000239-2" qtype="causes">What causes Ankle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ankle pain is often due to an ankle sprain. An  ankle sprain  is an injury to the ligaments, which connect bones to one another., In most cases, the ankle is twisted inward, causing small tears in the ligaments. The tearing leads to swelling and bruising, making it difficult to bear weight on the joint. , The ligament injuries are more common on the outside of your ankle but the inside ligaments can tear also.,  In addition to ankle sprains, ankle pain can be caused by: Damage or swelling of tendons (which join muscles to bone) or cartilage (which cushions joints),  Infection in the ankle joint ,  Osteoarthritis ,  gout ,  rheumatoid arthritis ,  Reiter syndrome , and other types of arthritis ,  Problems in areas near the ankle that can cause you to feel pain in the ankle include: 
   Blockage of blood vessels in the leg, Heel pain or injuries,  Tendinitis  around the ankle joint, Nerve injuries (such as tarsal tunnel syndrome or  sciatica ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000239-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Ankle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000239-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Ankle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Go to the hospital if: You have severe pain even when you are NOT bearing weight., You suspect a broken bone (the joint looks deformed or you cannot put any weight on the leg)., You can hear a popping sound and have immediate pain in the joint., You can't move your ankle back and forth.,  Contact your provider if: Swelling does not go down within 2 to 3 days., You have symptoms of infection. The area becomes red, more painful, or warm, or you have a fever over 100&#176;F (37.7&#176;C)., The pain does not go away after several weeks., Other joints are also involved., You have a history of arthritis and are having new symptoms., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>