<Document id="0000628" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002579.htm">
 
<Focus>Caffeine overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0573204</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000628-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Caffeine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Caffeine is a substance that exists naturally in certain plants. It can also be man-made and added to food products. It stimulates the central nervous system and is a diuretic, which means it increases urination. Caffeine  overdose  occurs when someone takes in more than a normal or recommended amount. This can be by accident or on purpose. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with overdoses, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000628-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Caffeine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of caffeine overdose in adults may include: Breathing trouble , Changes in alertness, 
   Agitation,  confusion , hallucinations,  Convulsions  (seizures), Diarrhea, Dizziness, Fever,  Increased thirst ,  Increased urination ,  Irregular heartbeat ,  Muscle twitching , Nausea, vomiting, Rapid heartbeat, Sleeping trouble,  Symptoms in babies may include: 
   Muscles that are very tense, then very relaxed
   , 
   Nausea, vomiting
   , 
   Rapid, deep breathing
   ,  Rapid heartbeat ,  Shock , Tremors,  The acute symptoms of caffeine intoxication (overdose, poisoning) and generalized anxiety disorder are almost identical.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000628-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Caffeine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000628-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Caffeine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>A brief hospital stay may be necessary to complete treatment. In severe cases, death may result from convulsions or an irregular heartbeat.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000628-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Caffeine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>A brief hospital stay may be necessary to complete treatment. In severe cases, death may result from convulsions or an irregular heartbeat.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>