<Document id="0000874" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003317.htm">
 
<Focus>Cloudy cornea</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1856661</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Corneal opacification</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Corneal edema</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000874-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cloudy cornea ?</Question>
			<Answer>A cloudy cornea is a loss of transparency of the cornea.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000874-2" qtype="causes">What causes Cloudy cornea ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cornea is the front wall of the eye. It is normally clear. It helps focus the light entering the eye. Causes of cloudy cornea include: Inflammation, Sensitivity to non-infectious bacteria or toxins, Infection, Keratitis, Trachoma, River blindness, Corneal ulcers, Swelling (edema), Acute glaucoma, Birth injury, Fuchs dystrophy, Dryness of the eye due to Sj&#246;gren syndrome, vitamin A deficiency, or LASIK eye surgery, Corneal dystrophy (inherited metabolic disease), Keratoconus, Injury to the eye, including chemical burns and welding injury, Tumors or growths on the eye, Pterygium, Bowen disease ,  Clouding may affect all or part of the cornea. It leads to different amounts of  vision loss . You may not have any symptoms in the early stages.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000874-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Cloudy cornea ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000874-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Cloudy cornea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: The outer surface of your eye appears cloudy., You have trouble with your vision.,  Note: You will need to see an ophthalmologist for vision or eye problems. However, your primary care provider may also be involved if the problem could be due to a whole-body (systemic) disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000874-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Cloudy cornea ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>