<Document id="0000400" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000824.htm">
 
<Focus>Basal cell skin cancer</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0751676</CUI>
			<CUI>C0007117</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Basal cell carcinoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rodent ulcer</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Skin cancer - basal cell</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cancer - skin - basal cell</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nonmelanoma skin cancer</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Basal cell NMSC</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Basal cell epithelioma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000400-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Basal cell cancer is the most common form of cancer in the United States. Most skin cancers are basal cell cancer. Other common types of skin cancer are: Squamous cell cancer ,  Melanoma , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000400-2" qtype="causes">What causes Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>The top layer of the skin is called the epidermis. The bottom layer of the epidermis is the basal cell layer. With basal cancer, cells in this layer are the ones that become cancerous. Most basal cell cancers occur on skin that is regularly exposed to sunlight or other ultraviolet radiation. This type of skin cancer is most common in people over age 50. But it can also occur in younger people who have had extensive sun exposure. Basal cell cancer is almost always slow-growing. It rarely spreads to other parts of the body. You are more likely to develop basal cell cancer if you have: Light-colored or freckled skin, Blue, green, or grey eyes, Blond or red hair, Overexposure to x-rays or other forms of radiation, Many moles, Close relatives who have or had skin cancer, Many severe sunburns early in life, Long-term daily sun exposure (such as the sun exposure received by people who work outside) ,  Other risk factors include: Smoking, Weakened immune system, such as being on medicines that suppress the immune system after an organ transplant, Inherited skin diseases, such as  nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome , Having had  photodynamic therapy , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000400-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Basal cell cancer usually grows slowly and is often painless. It may not look that different from your normal skin. You may have a skin bump or growth that is: Pearly or waxy, White or light pink, Flesh-colored or brown, A red, scaly patch of skin ,  In some cases, the skin is just slightly raised, or even flat. You may have: A skin sore that bleeds easily, A sore that does not heal, Oozing or crusting spots in a sore, A scar-like sore without having injured the area, Irregular blood vessels in or around the spot, A sore with a depressed (sunken) area in the middle , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000400-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your doctor will check your skin and look at the size, shape, color, and texture of any suspicious areas. If your doctor thinks you might have skin cancer, a piece of skin will be removed. This is called a  skin biopsy . The sample is sent to a lab for examination under a microscope. A skin biopsy must be done to confirm basal cell cancer or other skin cancers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000400-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the size, depth, and location of the skin cancer and your overall health. Each treatment has its risks and benefits. You and your doctor can discuss the treatment that's right for you. Treatment may involve any of the following: Excision: Cutting out the skin cancer and stitching the skin together, Curettage and electrodessication: Scraping away cancer cells and using electricity to kill any that remain; used to treat cancers that are not large or deep; often curettage is used alone without electrodessication,  Cryosurgery : Freezing the cancer cells, which kills them; used to treat cancers that are not large or deep, Medicine: Skin creams that have medicine; used to treat cancers that are not large or deep,  Mohs surgery : Removing a layer of skin and looking at it immediately under a microscope, then removing layers of skin until there are no signs of the cancer; usually used for skin cancers on the nose, ears, and other areas of the face, Photodynamic therapy: Using a light-activated chemical to treat cancers that are not large or deep,  Radiation therapy : May be used if a basal cell cancer cannot be treated with surgery,  Chemotherapy : May be used in the rare instances of basal cell cancer that has spread to other parts of the body or that cannot be treated with surgery, Biologic therapies ( immunotherapies ): Medicines that target and kill basal cell skin cancer and are used when standard treatments do not work , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000400-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can ease the stress of illness by joining a  cancer support group . Sharing with others who have common experiences and problems can help you not feel alone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000400-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of these cancers are cured when treated early. Some basal cell cancers return in the same location. Smaller ones are less likely to come back. Basal cell skin cancer almost never spreads beyond the original location. Left untreated, however, it may spread into surrounding areas and nearby tissues and bone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000400-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000400-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider for an appointment if you have a sore or spot on your skin that changes in: Appearance, Color, Size, Texture,  Also contact your provider if a spot becomes painful or swollen, or if it starts to bleed or itch.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000400-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Basal cell skin cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>The American Cancer Society recommends that a provider examine your skin every year if you are older than 40 and every 3 years if you are 20 to 40 years old. You should also examine your own skin once a month. Use a hand mirror for hard-to-see places. Contact your doctor if you notice anything unusual. The best way to prevent skin cancer is to  reduce your exposure to sunlight . Always use sunscreen: Apply sunscreen with sun protection factor (SPF) of at least 30, even when you are going outdoors for a short time., Apply a large amount of sunscreen on all exposed areas, including ears and feet., Look for sunscreen that blocks both UVA and UVB light., Use a water-resistant sunscreen., Apply sunscreen at least 30 minutes before going out. Follow package instructions about how often to reapply. Be sure to reapply after swimming or sweating., Use sunscreen in winter and on cloudy days too.&#160; ,  Other measures to help you avoid too much sun exposure: Ultraviolet light is most intense between 10 a.m. and 4 p.m. Try to avoid the sun during these hours.&#160;, Protect the skin by wearing wide-brim hats, long-sleeve shirts, long skirts, or pants. You can also buy sun-protective clothing., Avoid surfaces that reflect light more, such as water, sand, concrete, and areas that are painted white., The higher the altitude, the faster your skin burns., Do not use sun lamps and tanning beds (salons). Spending 15 to 20 minutes at a tanning salon is as dangerous as a day spent in the sun. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>