<Document id="0000027" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001306.htm">
 
<Focus>ABO incompatibility</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238580</CUI>
			<CUI>C0860218</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000027-1" qtype="information">What is (are) ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>A, B, AB, and O are the 4 major blood types. The types are based on small substances (molecules) on the surface of the blood cells. When people who have&#160;one blood type receive blood from someone with a different blood type, it may cause their immune system to react. This is called ABO incompatibility. Due to modern testing techniques, this problem is very rare.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000027-2" qtype="causes">What causes ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>The different blood types are: Type A, Type B, Type AB, Type O ,  People who have one blood type may form proteins ( antibodies ) that cause their immune system to react against one or more of the other blood types.  Being exposed to another type of blood can cause a reaction. This is important when someone needs to receive a blood transfusion or have an organ transplant. The blood types must be compatible to avoid an ABO incompatibility reaction. For example: People with type A blood will react against type B or type AB blood., People with type B blood will react against type A or type AB blood., People with type O blood will react against type A, type B, or type AB blood., People with type AB blood will not react against type A, type B, type AB, or type O blood. ,  Type O blood does not cause an immune response when it is given to people with type A, type B, or type AB blood. This is why type O blood cells can be given to people of any blood type. People with type O blood are called universal donors. But people with type O can only receive type O blood. Both blood and plasma transfusions must be matched to avoid an immune reaction. Before anyone receives blood, both the blood and the person receiving it are tested carefully to avoid a reaction. Usually, a reaction occurs because of a clerical error causing someone to receive incompatible blood.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000027-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following are symptoms of ABO incompatible  transfusion reactions : Low back pain, Blood in urine, Chills, Feeling of "impending doom", Fever, Nausea and vomiting, Shortness of breath, Increased heart rate, Pain at infusion site, Chest pain, Dizziness, Bronchospasm (spasm of the muscles lining the lung; causes cough), Yellow skin and whites of the eyes ( jaundice ), Acute kidney failure, Low blood pressure,  Disseminated intravascular coagulation (DIC) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000027-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam. Blood tests will usually show: The  bilirubin level  is high, The  complete blood count  (CBC) shows damage to red blood cells or  anemia , The recipient's and donor's blood are not compatible, Elevated lactate dehydrogenase (LDH), Elevated  blood urea nitrogen (BUN)  and blood  creatinine ; in case of renal injury, Prolonged prothrombin time or partial thromboplastin time (findings of DIC), Positive  direct antiglobulin test  (DAT),  Urine tests show the presence of hemoglobin due to breakdown of red blood cells.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000027-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of any reaction, transfusion should be stopped immediately. Treatment may also include: 
   Medicines used to treat allergic reactions (antihistamines)
   , 
   Medicines used to treat swelling and allergies (steroids)
   , Fluids given through a vein (intravenously), 
   Medicines to raise blood pressure if it drops too low
   , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000027-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>ABO incompatibility can be a very serious problem that can result in death. With the right and timely treatment, a full recovery is expected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000027-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications that may result include: Kidney failure, Low blood pressure needing intensive care, Death, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000027-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have recently had a blood transfusion or transplant and you have symptoms of ABO incompatibility.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000027-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent ABO incompatibility ?</Question>
			<Answer>Careful testing of donor and&#160;recipient blood types before transfusion or transplant can prevent this problem.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>