<Document id="0000207" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000482.htm">
 
<Focus>Analgesic nephropathy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0149938</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Phenacetin nephritis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nephropathy - analgesic</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000207-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Analgesic nephropathy involves damage to one or both kidneys caused by overexposure to mixtures of medicines, especially over-the-counter pain medicines (analgesics).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000207-2" qtype="causes">What causes Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Analgesic nephropathy involves damage within the internal structures of the kidney. It is caused by long-term use of analgesics (pain medicines), especially over-the-counter (OTC) medicines that contain phenacetin or acetaminophen, and nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), such as aspirin, ibuprofen, or naproxen. This condition frequently occurs as a result of self-medicating, often for some type of chronic pain such as headache or arthritis. Risk factors include: Use of OTC analgesics containing more than one active ingredient, Taking 6 or more pills a day for 3 years, Chronic headaches, painful menstrual periods, backache, or musculoskeletal pain, Emotional or behavioral changes, History of dependent behaviors including smoking, alcohol use, and excessive use of tranquilizers, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000207-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>There may be no symptoms in the beginning. Over time, as the kidneys are injured by the medicine, symptoms of  kidney disease  will develop, including: Fatigue, weakness,  Increased urinary frequency or urgency , 
   Blood in the urine
   ,  Flank pain  or back pain,  Decreased urine output ,  Decreased alertness , including drowsiness, confusion, and lethargy, 
   Decreased sensation, numbness (especially in the legs), Nausea, vomiting, Easy bruising or bleeding, Swelling (edema) throughout the body, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000207-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will examine you and ask about your symptoms. During the exam, your provider may find: Your blood pressure is high., When listening with a stethoscope, your heart and lungs have abnormal sounds., You have swelling, especially in the lower legs., Your skin shows premature aging.,  Tests that may be done include: Complete blood count , CT scan of kidney,  Intravenous pyelogram  (IVP),  Toxicology screen ,  Urinalysis , 
  Kidney ultrasound
  , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000207-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>The primary goals of treatment are to prevent further damage of the kidneys and to treat kidney failure. Your provider may tell you to stop taking all suspect painkillers, particularly OTC medicines. To treat kidney failure, your provider may suggest diet changes and fluid restriction. Eventually,  dialysis  or a  kidney transplant  may be needed. Counseling may help you develop alternative methods of controlling chronic pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000207-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>The damage to the kidney may be acute and temporary, or chronic and long term.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000207-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications that may result from analgesic nephropathy include: Acute kidney failure ,  Chronic kidney failure , Kidney disorder in which the spaces between the kidney tubules become inflamed
   ( interstitial nephritis )
   , Tissue death in areas where the openings of the collecting ducts enter the kidney and where urine flows into the ureters
   ( renal papillary necrosis )
   , Urinary tract infections that are ongoing or keep coming back, High blood pressure,  Cancer  of the kidney or ureter, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000207-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have any of the following: Symptoms of analgesic nephropathy, especially if you have been using painkillers for a long time, Blood or solid material in your urine, Amount of your urine has decreased, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000207-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Analgesic nephropathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Follow your provider's instructions when using medicines, including OTCs. Do not take more than the recommended dose without asking your provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>