<Document id="0000251" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001074.htm">
 
<Focus>Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3263723</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cruciate ligament injury - anterior</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ACL injury</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Knee injury - anterior cruciate ligament (ACL)</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000251-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>An anterior cruciate ligament injury is the over-stretching or tearing of the anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) in the knee. A tear may be partial or complete.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000251-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>The knee joint is located where the end of the thigh bone (femur) meets the top of the shin bone (tibia). Four main ligaments connect these two bones: Medial collateral ligament (MCL) runs along the inside of the knee. It prevents the knee from bending inward., Lateral collateral ligament (LCL) runs along the outside of the knee. It prevents the knee from bending outward., Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) is in the middle of the knee. It prevents the shin bone from sliding out in front of the thigh bone., Posterior cruciate ligament (PCL) works with the ACL. It prevents the shin bone from sliding backward under the femur. ,  Women are more likely to have an ACL tear than men.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000251-3" qtype="causes">What causes Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>An ACL injury can occur if you: Get hit very hard on the side of your knee, such as during a football tackle, Overextending your knee joint, Quickly stop moving and change direction while running, landing from a jump, or turning ,  Basketball, football, soccer, and skiing are common sports linked to ACL tears. ACL injuries often occur with other injuries. For example, an ACL tear often occurs along with tears to the MCL and the shock-absorbing cartilage in the knee (meniscus). Most ACL tears occur in the middle of the ligament, or the ligament is pulled off the thigh bone. These injuries form a gap between the torn edges, and do not heal on their own.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000251-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>Early symptoms: A "popping" sound at the time of injury, 
   Obvious&#160; knee swelling  within 6 hours of injury, Pain, especially when you try to put weight on the injured leg, Difficulty in continuing with your sport, Feeling of instability,  Those who have only a mild injury may notice that the knee feels unstable or seems to "give way" when using it.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000251-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>The knee joint is located where the end of the thigh bone (femur) meets the top of the shin bone (tibia). Four main ligaments connect these two bones: Medial collateral ligament (MCL) runs along the inside of the knee. It prevents the knee from bending inward., Lateral collateral ligament (LCL) runs along the outside of the knee. It prevents the knee from bending outward., Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) is in the middle of the knee. It prevents the shin bone from sliding out in front of the thigh bone., Posterior cruciate ligament (PCL) works with the ACL. It prevents the shin bone from sliding backward under the femur. ,  Women are more likely to have an ACL tear than men.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000251-6" qtype="considerations">What to do for Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>The knee joint is located where the end of the thigh bone (femur) meets the top of the shin bone (tibia). Four main ligaments connect these two bones: Medial collateral ligament (MCL) runs along the inside of the knee. It prevents the knee from bending inward., Lateral collateral ligament (LCL) runs along the outside of the knee. It prevents the knee from bending outward., Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) is in the middle of the knee. It prevents the shin bone from sliding out in front of the thigh bone., Posterior cruciate ligament (PCL) works with the ACL. It prevents the shin bone from sliding backward under the femur. ,  Women are more likely to have an ACL tear than men.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000251-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider right away if you have a serious knee injury. Get immediate medical attention if the foot is cool and blue after a knee injury. This means that the knee joint may be dislocated, and blood vessels to the foot may be injured. This is a medical emergency.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000251-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Anterior cruciate ligament (ACL) injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>Use proper techniques when playing sports or exercising. Some college sports programs teach athletes how to reduce stress placed on the ACL. This involves a series of warm up exercises and jumping drills. There are jumping and landing exercises that have been shown to reduce ACL injuries. The use of knee braces during vigorous athletic activity (such as football) is controversial. It has not been shown to reduce the number of knee injuries, but not specifically ACL injuries.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>