<Document id="0000205" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001130.htm">
 
<Focus>Anal fissure</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0016167</CUI>
			<CUI>C2227930</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Fissure in ano</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000205-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Anal fissure ?</Question>
			<Answer>An anal fissure is a small split or tear in the thin moist tissue ( mucosa ) lining the lower rectum (anus).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000205-2" qtype="causes">What causes Anal fissure ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anal fissures are very common in infants, but they may occur at any age. In adults, fissures may be caused by passing large, hard stools, or having diarrhea for a long time. Other factors may include: Decreased blood flow to the area, Too much tension in the sphincter muscles that control the anus ,  The condition affects males and females equally. Anal fissures are also common in women after childbirth and in people with  Crohn disease .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000205-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Anal fissure ?</Question>
			<Answer>An anal fissure can be seen as a crack in the anal skin when the area is stretched slightly. The fissure is almost always in the middle. Anal fissures may cause painful bowel movements and bleeding. There may be blood on the outside of the stool or on the toilet paper (or baby wipes) after a bowel movement. Symptoms may begin suddenly or develop slowly over time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000205-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Anal fissure ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a  rectal exam  and look at the anal tissue. Other medical tests that may be done include: Anoscopy  -- examination of the anus, anal canal, and lower rectum,  Sigmoidoscopy  -- examination of the lower part of large intestine,  Biopsy  -- removal of rectal tissue for examination,  Colonoscopy  -- examination of the colon, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000205-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Anal fissure ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most fissures heal on their own and do not need treatment. To prevent or treat anal fissures in infants, be sure to change diapers often and clean the area gently. CHILDREN AND ADULTS Worrying about pain during a bowel movement may cause a person to avoid them. But not having bowel movements will only cause the stools to become even harder, which can make the anal fissure worse. Prevent hard stools and constipation by: Making dietary changes -- eating more fiber or  bulk , such as fruits, vegetables, and grains, Drinking more fluids, Using stool softeners ,  Ask your provider about the following ointments or creams to help soothe the affected skin: Numbing cream, if pain interferes with normal bowel movements, Petroleum jelly, Zinc oxide, 1% hydrocortisone cream, Preparation H, and other products ,  A  sitz bath  is a warm water bath used for healing or cleansing. Sit in the bath 2 to 3 times a day. The water should cover only the hips and buttocks. If the anal fissures do not go away with home care methods, treatment may involve: Botulinum toxin injections into the muscle in the anus (anal sphincter), Minor surgery to relax the anal muscle, Prescription creams, such as nitrates or calcium channel blockers, applied over the fissure to help relax the muscles , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000205-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Anal fissure ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anal fissures often heal quickly without any more problems. People who develop fissures once are more likely to have them in the future.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>