<Document id="0000608" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000883.htm">
 
<Focus>Bullous pemphigoid</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0030805</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000608-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Bullous pemphigoid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bullous pemphigoid is a skin disorder characterized by  blisters .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000608-2" qtype="causes">What causes Bullous pemphigoid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bullous pemphigoid is an  autoimmune disorder  that occurs when the body's immune system attacks and destroys healthy body tissue by mistake. Specifically, the immune system attacks the proteins that attach the top layer of skin (epidermis) to the bottom layer of skin. This disorder usually occurs in older persons and is rare in young people. Symptoms come and go. The condition often goes away within 5 years. In some cases, the condition is triggered by a medicine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000608-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Bullous pemphigoid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people with this disorder have itchy skin that may be severe. In most cases, there are blisters, called  bullae . Blisters are usually located on the arms, legs, or middle of the body. In rare cases, blisters can form in the mouth., The blisters may break open and form open sores ( ulcers ). , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000608-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Bullous pemphigoid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will examine the skin and ask about the symptoms. They will review your list of medicines. Tests that may be done to help diagnose this condition include: Blood tests,  Skin biopsy  of the blister or the area next to it
  , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000608-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Bullous pemphigoid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anti-inflammatory medicines called corticosteroids may be prescribed. They may be taken by mouth or applied to the skin. More powerful medicines may be used to help suppress the immune system if steroids do not work, or to allow lower steroid doses to be used. Antibiotics in the tetracycline family may be useful.  Niacin  (a B complex vitamin) is sometimes given along with tetracycline. Your provider may suggest self-care measures. These may include: Applying anti-inflammatory creams to the skin, Using mild soaps and applying moisturizer to the skin after bathing, Protecting the affected skin from sun exposure and injury , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000608-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Bullous pemphigoid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bullous pemphigoid usually responds well to treatment. The medicine can often be stopped after several years. The disease sometimes returns after treatment is stopped.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000608-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Bullous pemphigoid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Skin infection is the most common complication. Complications resulting from treatment may also occur, especially from taking corticosteroids.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000608-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Bullous pemphigoid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have:  Unexplained blisters on your skin, An itchy rash that continues despite home treatment, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>