<Document id="0000578" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003075.htm">
 
<Focus>Breathing difficulty</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1299586</CUI>
			<CUI>C0013404</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Shortness of breath</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Breathlessness</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Difficulty breathing</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dyspnea</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000578-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Breathing difficulty ?</Question>
			<Answer>Breathing difficulty may involve: Difficult breathing&#160;, Uncomfortable breathing, Feeling like you are not getting enough air, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000578-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Breathing difficulty ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no standard definition for difficulty breathing. Some people feel breathless with only mild exercise (for example, climbing stairs), even though they don't have a medical condition. Others may have advanced lung disease, but may never feel short of breath. Breathing difficulty is a subjective feeling; only the person feeling it can decide if it is present. Wheezing  is one form of breathing difficulty in which you make a high-pitched sound when you breathe out.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000578-3" qtype="causes">What causes Breathing difficulty ?</Question>
			<Answer>Shortness of breath has many different causes. For example, heart disease can cause breathlessness if your heart is unable to pump enough blood to supply oxygen to your body. If your brain, muscles, or other body organs do not get enough oxygen, a sense of breathlessness may occur. Breathing difficulty may also be due to problems with the lungs, airways, or other health problems. Problems with the lungs: Blood clot in the arteries of the lungs ( pulmonary embolism ), Swelling and mucus buildup in the smallest air passages in the lungs ( bronchiolitis ),  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease  (COPD), such as chronic bronchitis or emphysema,  Pneumonia , High blood pressure in the arteries of the lungs ( pulmonary hypertension ), Other lung disease ,  Problems with the airways leading to the lungs: Blockage of the air passages in your nose, mouth, or throat, Choking on something stuck in the airways, Swelling around the vocal cords ( croup ), Inflammation of the tissue (epiglottis) that covers the windpipe ( epiglottitis ) ,  Problems with the heart: Chest pain due to poor blood flow through the blood vessels of the heart ( angina ),  Heart attack , Heart defects from birth ( congenital heart disease ),  Heart failure , Heart rhythm disturbances ( arrhythmias ) ,  Other causes: Allergies  (such as to mold, dander, or pollen), High altitudes where there is less oxygen in the air, Compression of the chest wall, Dust in the environment, Emotional distress, such as anxiety,  Hiatal hernia  (condition in which part of the stomach extends through an opening of the diaphragm into the chest),  Obesity ,  Panic attacks , Anemia (low hemoglobin), Blood problems (when your blood cells cannot pick up oxygen normally; the disease methemoglobinemia is an example), Neuromuscular problems leading to weakness of the breathing muscles, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000578-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Breathing difficulty ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no standard definition for difficulty breathing. Some people feel breathless with only mild exercise (for example, climbing stairs), even though they don't have a medical condition. Others may have advanced lung disease, but may never feel short of breath. Breathing difficulty is a subjective feeling; only the person feeling it can decide if it is present. Wheezing  is one form of breathing difficulty in which you make a high-pitched sound when you breathe out.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000578-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Breathing difficulty ?</Question>
			<Answer>Go to the emergency room or call the local emergency number (such as 911) if: Breathing difficulty comes on suddenly or seriously interferes with your breathing and even talking, Someone completely stops breathing ,  See your provider if any of the following occur with breathing difficulties: Chest discomfort, pain, or pressure. These are symptoms of angina., Fever., Shortness of breath after only slight activity or while at rest., Shortness of breath that wakes you up at night or requires you to sleep propped up to breathe., Shortness of breath with simple talking., Tightness in the throat or a barking, croupy cough., You have breathed in or choked on an object (foreign object aspiration or ingestion)., Wheezing., Significant worsening of baseline shortness of breath., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000578-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Breathing difficulty ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>