<Document id="0000647" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000887.htm">
 
<Focus>Calorie count - Fast food</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Weight loss - calorie count - fast food</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Overweight - calorie count - fast food</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Obesity - calorie count - fast food</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000647-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Calorie count - Fast food</Question>
			<Answer>Fast food is easy and available almost everywhere. However, a lot of fast food is high in calories, saturated fat, and salt. Yet sometimes, you may need the convenience of fast food. You do not have to  avoid fast food completely . You simply need to make healthier choices. For example, you can include a salad with your meal (be careful with creamy dressing or fried toppings). You can also choose baked or grilled instead of fried options. You can find nutrition information for most fast food chains online or in the restaurant. Some fast food chains offer healthier options on their menus. Use this information to help you make better choices when you choose fast food. Here is a list of some popular fast food items, their serving sizes, and the number of calories in each.  FOOD ITEM SERVING SIZE CALORIES Breakfast Foods 
 
 Dunkin Donuts 
 
 Egg and Cheese Wrap 1 sandwich 170 Bacon, Egg, and Cheese on an English muffin 1 sandwich 400 Chicken, Bacon, and Cheese on a croissant 1 sandwich 330 Cornbread donut 1 donut 380 Burger King 
 
 Ham, Egg and Cheese CROISSAN'WICH 1 sandwich 500 Sausage, Egg and Cheese Biscuit 1 sandwich 410 Egg-Normous Burrito 1 burrito 820 McDonalds 
 
 Fruit and Maple Oatmeal 1 bowl 320 Egg McMuffin 1 sandwich 310 Bacon, Egg and Cheese McGriddles 1 sandwich 430 Big Breakfast 1 meal 760 Popeyes 
 
 Grits 1 order 370 Egg Biscuit 1 biscuit 510 Egg and Sausage Biscuit 1 biscuit 690 Burgers, Wraps, and Sandwiches 
 
 Burger King 
 
 Hamburger 1 sandwich 260 Cheeseburger 1 sandwich 300 Bacon Cheeseburger 1 sandwich 340 Whopper 1 sandwich 670 Mozzarella Sticks 4 sticks 330 French fries Small 320 Chicken Garden Salad (with dressing) 1 salad 870 Original Chicken Sandwich 1 sandwich 680 McDonalds 
 
 Hamburger 1 sandwich 250 Cheeseburger 1 sandwich 300 Quarter Pounder with Cheese 1 sandwich 520 Big Mac 1 sandwich 550 Chicken McNuggets 6 pieces 250 McChicken 1 sandwich 400 Filet-O-Fish 1 sandwich 380 Wendy's 
 
 Double Stack 1 sandwich 410 Dave's Single 1 sandwich 590 Dave's Triple 1 sandwich 1160 Baconator 1 sandwich 960 Grilled Asiago Ranch Club 1 sandwich 490 Spicy Chicken Sandwich 1 sandwich 500 Taco Salad (with dressing) 1 salad 690 In 'n Out Burger 
 
 Hamburger with onion 1 sandwich 390 Cheeseburger with onion 1 sandwich 480 Double-double with onion 1 sandwich 670 French fries 1 order 395 Chocolate shake 15 oz. 570 Subway 
 
 Veggie Delite 6" sandwich 200 Subway Club 6" sandwich 310 Sweet Onion Teriyaki 6" sandwich 320 Rotisserie-style Chicken 6" sandwich 330 Tuna 6" sandwich 430 Steak and Cheese 6" sandwich 320 Chicken 
 
 KFC 
 
 Kentucky Grilled Chicken Breast 1 piece 210 Honey BBQ Sandwich 1 sandwich 320 Original Recipe Chicken Breast 1 piece 390 Extra Crispy Chicken Breast 1 piece 530 Mashed Potatoes with Gravy 1 side 130 Popeyes 
 
 Chicken Sandwich - Classic 1 sandwich 700 Butterfly Shrimp 8 pieces 420 Mashed Potatoes with Gravy Regular size 110 Mashed Potatoes with Gravy Large size 330 Chick-Fil-A 
 
 Grilled Chicken Sandwich 1 sandwich 380 Chick-fil-A Cool Wrap 1 wrap 660 Chick-fil-A Grilled Chicken Sandwich 1 sandwich 520 Mac and Cheese 1 side 450 Tex-Mex 
 
 Taco Bell 
 
 Chicken Soft Taco 1 taco 160 Burrito Supreme - Chicken 1 burrito 370 Quesarito Burrito - Steak 1 burrito 650 Power Bowl - Steak 1 bowl 480 Chipotle Mexican Grill 
 
 Burrito Bowl, Chicken and Toppings, No Rice 1 bowl 580 Steak Burrito Bowl 1 bowl 920 Chicken Burrito 1 burrito 1190 Chicken Tacos 3 tacos 1100 Del Taco 
 
 Stuffed Quesadilla Taco - Chicken 1 taco 320 Beer Battered Fish Taco 1 taco 200 Spicy Grilled Chicken Burrito 1 burrito 520 Epic Cali Bacon Burrito &#8211; Carne Asada 1 burrito 1050 Pizza 
 
 Domino's 
 
 Pacific Veggie Hand Tossed Crust Pizza 1 slice medium pizza 350 Thin Crust Cheese Pizza One quarter of a medium pizza 150 Buffalo Chicken Hand Tossed Crust Pizza 1 slice medium pizza 410 Papa John's 
 
 Cheese Original Crust Pizza 1 slice medium (1/8) pizza 210 Pepperoni Original Crust Pizza 1 slice medium (1/8) pizza 230 The Works Original Crust Pizza 1 slice medium (1/8) pizza 230 Little Caesars 
 
 Cheese Pizza 1 slice large (1/8) pizza 250 Pepperoni Pizza 1 slice large (1/8) pizza 290 Italian Cheese Bread 1 piece 150</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>