<Document id="0000797" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000660.htm">
 
<Focus>Chlamydia infections in women</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0008149</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000797-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chlamydia infections in women ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chlamydia is an infection&#160;that can be passed from one person to another through sexual contact. This type of infection is known as sexually transmitted infection (STI).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000797-2" qtype="causes">What causes Chlamydia infections in women ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chlamydia is caused by the bacteria  Chlamydia trachomatis.  Both males and females may have this infection. However, they may not have symptoms. As a result, you may become infected or pass the infection to your partner without knowing it. You are more likely to become infected with chlamydia if you have: Sex without using a condom, Had multiple sexual partners, Been infected with chlamydia before , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000797-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Chlamydia infections in women ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many women do not have symptoms. But some have: Burning when they urinate, Pain in the lower part of the belly, possibly with fever, Painful intercourse,  Vaginal discharge  or bleeding after intercourse , Rectal pain, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000797-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Chlamydia infections in women ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000797-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Chlamydia infections in women ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chlamydia can be treated with an antibiotic. Some of these are safe to take if you are pregnant. Common side effects include: Nausea , Upset stomach,  Diarrhea ,  Both you and your partner need to take the antibiotics. Finish all of them, even if you feel better and still have some left., All of your sexual partners should be treated. Have them take the medicines even if they do not have symptoms. This will prevent you from passing the STIs back and forth.,  You and your partner are asked to abstain from sexual intercourse during the time of treatment. Gonorrhea  often occurs with chlamydia. Therefore, treatment for gonorrhea is often given at the same time. Safe sex practices are needed to prevent becoming infected with chlamydia or spreading it to others.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000797-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Chlamydia infections in women ?</Question>
			<Answer>Antibiotic treatment almost always works. You and your partner should take the medicines as directed. If chlamydia spreads into your uterus and fallopian tubes, it can cause scarring. Scarring can make it harder for you to get pregnant. You can help prevent this by: Finishing your antibiotics when you are treated, Making sure your sexual partners also take antibiotics.You may ask your provider for a prescription for your partner without your partner being seen by the provider, Talking to your provider about being tested for chlamydia and seeing your provider if you have symptoms, Wearing condoms and practicing  safe sex , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000797-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Chlamydia infections in women ?</Question>
			<Answer>Make an appointment with your provider if: You have symptoms of chlamydia, You are worried that you might have chlamydia, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>