<Document id="0000183" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000298.htm">
 
<Focus>Amebiasis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002438</CUI>
			<CUI>C0013370</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Amebic dysentery</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intestinal amebiasis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000183-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amebiasis is an infection of the intestines. It is caused by the microscopic parasite  Entamoeba histolytica .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000183-2" qtype="causes">What causes Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>E histolytica  can live in the large intestine (colon) without causing damage to the intestine. In some cases, it invades the colon wall, causing  colitis , acute dysentery, or long-term (chronic) diarrhea. The infection can also spread through the bloodstream to the liver. In rare cases, it can spread to the lungs, brain, or other organs. This condition occurs worldwide. It is most common in tropical areas that have crowded living conditions and poor sanitation. Africa, Mexico, parts of South America, and India have major health problems due to this condition. The parasite may spread: Through food or water contaminated with stool, Through fertilizer made of human waste, From person to person, particularly by contact with the mouth or rectal area of an infected person,  Risk factors for severe amebiasis include: Alcohol use, Cancer, Malnutrition, Older or younger age, Pregnancy, Recent travel to a tropical region, Use of corticosteroid medicine to suppress the immune system,  In the United States, amebiasis is most common among those who live in institutions or people who have traveled to an area where amebiasis is common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000183-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people with this infection do not have symptoms. If symptoms occur, they are seen 7 to 28 days after being exposed to the parasite. Mild symptoms may include: Abdominal cramps, Diarrhea: passage of 3 to 8 semiformed stools per day, or passage of soft stools with mucus and occasional blood
   , Fatigue, Excessive gas, Rectal pain while having a bowel movement ( tenesmus ),  Unintentional weight loss ,  Severe symptoms may include: Abdominal tenderness,  Bloody stools , including passage of liquid stools with streaks of blood, passage of 10 to 20 stools per day
   , Fever, Vomiting, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000183-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam. You will be asked about your medical history, especially if you have recently traveled overseas.  Examination of the abdomen may show  liver enlargement  or tenderness in the abdomen (typically in the right upper quadrant). Tests that may be ordered include: Blood test for amebiasis, Examination of the inside of the lower large bowel ( sigmoidoscopy ), Stool test,  Microscope examination of stool samples , usually with multiple samples over several days, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000183-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on how severe the infection is. Usually, antibiotics are prescribed. If you are vomiting, you may be given medicines through a vein ( intravenously ) until you can take them by mouth. Medicines to stop diarrhea are usually not prescribed because they can make the condition worse. After antibiotic treatment, your stool will likely be rechecked to make sure the infection has been cleared.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000183-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Outcome is usually good with treatment. Usually, the illness lasts about 2 weeks, but it can come back if you do not get treated.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000183-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications of amebiasis may include: Liver abscess  (collection of parasites and pus in the liver), Medicine side effects, including nausea, Spread of the parasite through the blood to the liver, lungs, brain, or other organs, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000183-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have diarrhea that does not go away or gets worse.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000183-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Amebiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>When traveling in countries where sanitation is poor, drink purified or boiled water. Do not eat uncooked vegetables or unpeeled fruit. Wash your hands after using the bathroom and before eating.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>