<Document id="0000046" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001072.htm">
 
<Focus>Achilles tendinitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0263933</CUI>
			<CUI>C0149846</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tendinitis of the heel</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000046-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Achilles tendinitis occurs when the tendon that connects the back of your leg to your heel becomes swollen and painful near the bottom of the foot. This tendon is called the Achilles tendon. It allows you to push your foot down. You use your Achilles tendon when walking, running, and jumping. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000046-2" qtype="causes">What causes Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are two large muscles in the calf. These create the power needed to push off with the foot or go up on the toes. The large Achilles tendon connects these muscles to the heel. Heel pain  is most often due to overuse of the foot. Rarely, it is caused by an injury.  Tendinitis  due to overuse is most common in younger people. It can occur in walkers, runners, or other athletes.  Achilles tendinitis may be more likely to occur if: There is a sudden increase in the amount or intensity of an activity., Your calf muscles are very tight (not stretched out)., You run on hard surfaces, such as concrete., You run too often., You jump a lot (such as when playing basketball)., You do not wear shoes that give your feet proper support., Your foot suddenly turns in or out. ,  Tendinitis from arthritis is more common in middle-aged and older adults. A bone spur or growth may form in the back of the heel bone. This may irritate the Achilles tendon and cause pain and swelling. Flat feet will put more tension on the tendon.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000046-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include pain in the heel and along the length of the tendon when walking or running. The area may feel painful and stiff in the morning. The tendon may be painful to touch or move. The area may be swollen and warm. You may have trouble standing up on your toes. You may also have trouble finding shoes that fit comfortably due to pain in the back of your heel.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000046-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam. They will look for tenderness along the tendon and pain in the area of the tendon when you stand on your toes. X-rays can help diagnose bone problems. An  MRI &#160;scan of the foot may be done if you are considering surgery or there is a chance that you have a tear in the Achilles tendon. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000046-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main treatments for Achilles tendinitis do not involve surgery. It is important to remember that it may take at least 2 to 3 months for the pain to go away. Try putting ice on the Achilles tendon area for 15 to 20 minutes, 2 to 3 times per day. Remove the ice if the area gets numb. Changes in activity may help manage the symptoms: Decrease or stop any activity that causes pain., Run or walk on smoother and softer surfaces., Switch to biking, swimming, or other activities that put less stress on the Achilles tendon. ,  Your provider or physical therapist can show you stretching exercises or eccentric loading exercises for the Achilles tendon. You may also need to make changes in your footwear, such as:  Using a brace, boot or cast to keep the heel and tendon still and allow the swelling to go down, Placing heel lifts in the shoe under the heel, Wearing shoes that are softer in the areas over and under the heel cushion ,  Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), such as aspirin and ibuprofen, can help ease pain or swelling. Other treatment include injections, such as platelet rich plasma or steroids, to reduce the inflammation. However, the tendon can become even weaker following injection and should be protected after the injections. If these treatments do not improve symptoms, you may need surgery to remove inflamed tissue and abnormal areas of the tendon. If there is a bone spur irritating the tendon, surgery can be used to remove the spur. Extracorporeal shock wave therapy (ESWT) may be an alternative to surgery for people who have not responded to other treatments. This treatment uses low-dose sound waves.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000046-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, lifestyle changes help improve symptoms. Keep in mind that symptoms may return if you do not limit activities that cause pain, or if you do not maintain the strength and flexibility of the tendon.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000046-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Achilles tendinitis may make you more likely to have an Achilles rupture. This condition most often causes a sharp pain that feels as if you have been hit in the back of the heel with a stick. Surgical repair is often necessary. However, the surgery may&#160;not be as successful as usual because there is already damage to the tendon.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000046-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You have pain in the heel around the Achilles tendon that is worse with activity., You have sharp pain and are unable to walk or push-off without extreme pain or weakness., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000046-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Achilles tendinitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Exercises to keep your calf muscles strong and flexible will help reduce the risk for tendinitis. Overusing a weak or tight Achilles tendon makes you more likely to develop tendinitis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>