<Document id="0000519" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002485.htm">
 
<Focus>Boric acid poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0161695</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Borax poisoning</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000519-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Boric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Boric acid is a dangerous poison. Poisoning from this chemical can be acute or chronic. Acute boric acid poisoning usually occurs when someone swallows powdered roach-killing products that contain the chemical. Boric acid is a caustic chemical. If it contacts tissues, it can cause injury. Chronic poisoning occurs in those who are repeatedly exposed to boric acid. For example, in the past, boric acid was used to disinfect and treat wounds. People who repeatedly received such treatment got sick, and some died. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000519-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Boric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main symptoms of boric acid poisoning are blue-green vomit, diarrhea, and a bright red rash on the skin. Other symptoms may include: Blisters ,  Collapse ,  Coma &#160;(lack of responsiveness),  Seizures ,  Drowsiness , Fever, Headache, Lack of desire to do anything (lethargy), Low blood pressure, Restlessness, Significantly  decreased urine output  (or none), Sloughing of skin,  Twitching of facial muscles , arms, hands, legs, and feet , Weakness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000519-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Boric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000519-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Boric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>The infant death rate from boric acid poisonings is high. However, boric acid poisoning is considerably rarer than in the past because the substance is no longer used as a disinfectant in nurseries. It is also no longer commonly used in medical preparations. Boric acid is an ingredient in some vaginal suppositories used for yeast infections, although this is NOT a standard treatment. Swallowing a large amount of boric acid can have severe effects on many parts of the body. Damage to the esophagus and stomach continues to occur for several weeks after the boric acid was swallowed. Death from complications may occur as long as several months later. Holes (perforations) in the esophagus and stomach may result in serious infections in both the chest and abdominal cavities, which may result in death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000519-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Boric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>The infant death rate from boric acid poisonings is high. However, boric acid poisoning is considerably rarer than in the past because the substance is no longer used as a disinfectant in nurseries. It is also no longer commonly used in medical preparations. Boric acid is an ingredient in some vaginal suppositories used for yeast infections, although this is NOT a standard treatment. Swallowing a large amount of boric acid can have severe effects on many parts of the body. Damage to the esophagus and stomach continues to occur for several weeks after the boric acid was swallowed. Death from complications may occur as long as several months later. Holes (perforations) in the esophagus and stomach may result in serious infections in both the chest and abdominal cavities, which may result in death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>