<Document id="0000453" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007555.htm">
 
<Focus>Birth control - slow release methods</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2703065</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Contraception - hormonal methods</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progestin implants</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progestin injections</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Skin patch</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Vaginal ring</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000453-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Birth control - slow release methods ?</Question>
			<Answer>PROGESTIN IMPLANTS A progestin implant is a small rod that is implanted under the skin, most often on the inside of the arm. The rod releases a small amount of the progestin daily into the bloodstream. It takes about a minute to insert the rod. The procedure is done using a local anesthetic in a doctor's office. The rod can stay in place for 3 years. However, it can be removed at any time. Removal usually takes only a few minutes. After the implant has been inserted: You may have some bruising around the site for a week or more., You should be protected from getting pregnant within 1 week., You can use these implants while breastfeeding. ,  Progestin implants work better than birth control pills to prevent pregnancy. Very few women who use these implants are likely to get pregnant. Your regular menstrual cycles should return within 3 to 4 weeks after these implants are removed. PROGESTIN INJECTIONS Injections or shots that contain the hormone progestin also work to prevent pregnancy. A single shot works for up to 90 days. These injections are given into the muscles of the upper arm or buttocks. Side effects that may occur include: Changes in menstrual cycles or extra bleeding or spotting. Around one half of women who use these injections have no menstrual cycles., Breast tenderness, weight gain, headaches, or  depression . ,  Progestin injections work better than birth control pills to prevent pregnancy. Very few women who use progestin injections are likely to get pregnant. Sometimes the effects of these hormone shots last longer than 90 days. If you are planning to become pregnant in the near future, you might want to consider a different birth control method. SKIN PATCH The skin patch is placed on your shoulder, buttocks, or another area of your body. A new patch is applied once a week for 3 weeks. Then you go 1 week without a patch. Estrogen levels are higher with the patch than with birth control pills or the vaginal ring. Because of this, there may be an increased risk for  blood clots in the legs  or  lungs  with this method. The FDA has issued a warning about the patch and the higher risk for a blood clot traveling to a lung. The patch slowly releases both estrogen and progestin into your blood. Your health care provider will prescribe this method for you. The patch works better than birth control pills to prevent pregnancy. Very few women who use the patch are likely to get pregnant. The skin patch contains estrogen. Along with the higher risk for blood clots, there is a rare risk for high blood pressure, heart attack, and  stroke . Smoking increases these risks even more. VAGINAL RING The vaginal ring is a flexible device. This ring is about 2 inches (5 cm) wide and is placed into the vagina. It releases the hormones progestin and estrogen. Your provider will prescribe this method, but you will insert the ring yourself., It will stay in the vagina for 3 weeks. At the end of the third week, you will take the ring out for 1 week. DO NOT remove the ring until the end of the 3 weeks. ,  Side effects with the ring may include: Nausea and breast tenderness, which are less severe than with birth control pills or patches.,  Vaginal discharge  or vaginitis., Breakthrough bleeding and spotting (may occur more often than with birth control pills). ,  The vaginal ring contains estrogen. As a result, there is a rare risk for high blood pressure, blood clots, heart attack, and stroke. Smoking increases these risks even more. The vaginal ring slowly releases both estrogen and progestin into your blood.  The vaginal ring works better than birth control pills to prevent pregnancy. Very few women who use the vaginal ring is likely to get pregnant. HORMONE-RELEASING IUDS An intrauterine device ( IUD ) is a small plastic T-shaped device used for birth control. It is inserted into the uterus. IUDs prevent sperm from fertilizing an egg. A newer type of IUD releases a low dose of a hormone into the uterus each day for a period of 3 to 5 years. This increases the effectiveness of the device as a birth control method. It also has the added benefits of reducing or stopping menstrual flow. It may help protect against cancer (endometrial cancer) in women who are at risk of developing the disease. There are several different IUDs of this type. Some are specially shaped for women who have never been pregnant. You have choices for what type of IUD to have. Talk with your provider about which  type may be best for you .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000453-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Birth control - slow release methods ?</Question>
			<Answer>PROGESTIN IMPLANTS A progestin implant is a small rod that is implanted under the skin, most often on the inside of the arm. The rod releases a small amount of the progestin daily into the bloodstream. It takes about a minute to insert the rod. The procedure is done using a local anesthetic in a doctor's office. The rod can stay in place for 3 years. However, it can be removed at any time. Removal usually takes only a few minutes. After the implant has been inserted: You may have some bruising around the site for a week or more., You should be protected from getting pregnant within 1 week., You can use these implants while breastfeeding. ,  Progestin implants work better than birth control pills to prevent pregnancy. Very few women who use these implants are likely to get pregnant. Your regular menstrual cycles should return within 3 to 4 weeks after these implants are removed. PROGESTIN INJECTIONS Injections or shots that contain the hormone progestin also work to prevent pregnancy. A single shot works for up to 90 days. These injections are given into the muscles of the upper arm or buttocks. Side effects that may occur include: Changes in menstrual cycles or extra bleeding or spotting. Around one half of women who use these injections have no menstrual cycles., Breast tenderness, weight gain, headaches, or  depression . ,  Progestin injections work better than birth control pills to prevent pregnancy. Very few women who use progestin injections are likely to get pregnant. Sometimes the effects of these hormone shots last longer than 90 days. If you are planning to become pregnant in the near future, you might want to consider a different birth control method. SKIN PATCH The skin patch is placed on your shoulder, buttocks, or another area of your body. A new patch is applied once a week for 3 weeks. Then you go 1 week without a patch. Estrogen levels are higher with the patch than with birth control pills or the vaginal ring. Because of this, there may be an increased risk for  blood clots in the legs  or  lungs  with this method. The FDA has issued a warning about the patch and the higher risk for a blood clot traveling to a lung. The patch slowly releases both estrogen and progestin into your blood. Your health care provider will prescribe this method for you. The patch works better than birth control pills to prevent pregnancy. Very few women who use the patch are likely to get pregnant. The skin patch contains estrogen. Along with the higher risk for blood clots, there is a rare risk for high blood pressure, heart attack, and  stroke . Smoking increases these risks even more. VAGINAL RING The vaginal ring is a flexible device. This ring is about 2 inches (5 cm) wide and is placed into the vagina. It releases the hormones progestin and estrogen. Your provider will prescribe this method, but you will insert the ring yourself., It will stay in the vagina for 3 weeks. At the end of the third week, you will take the ring out for 1 week. DO NOT remove the ring until the end of the 3 weeks. ,  Side effects with the ring may include: Nausea and breast tenderness, which are less severe than with birth control pills or patches.,  Vaginal discharge  or vaginitis., Breakthrough bleeding and spotting (may occur more often than with birth control pills). ,  The vaginal ring contains estrogen. As a result, there is a rare risk for high blood pressure, blood clots, heart attack, and stroke. Smoking increases these risks even more. The vaginal ring slowly releases both estrogen and progestin into your blood.  The vaginal ring works better than birth control pills to prevent pregnancy. Very few women who use the vaginal ring is likely to get pregnant. HORMONE-RELEASING IUDS An intrauterine device ( IUD ) is a small plastic T-shaped device used for birth control. It is inserted into the uterus. IUDs prevent sperm from fertilizing an egg. A newer type of IUD releases a low dose of a hormone into the uterus each day for a period of 3 to 5 years. This increases the effectiveness of the device as a birth control method. It also has the added benefits of reducing or stopping menstrual flow. It may help protect against cancer (endometrial cancer) in women who are at risk of developing the disease. There are several different IUDs of this type. Some are specially shaped for women who have never been pregnant. You have choices for what type of IUD to have. Talk with your provider about which  type may be best for you .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>