<Document id="0000705" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001614.htm">
 
<Focus>Cat-scratch disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1384489</CUI>
			<CUI>C0007361</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CSD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cat-scratch fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bartonellosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000705-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cat-scratch disease is an infection with bartonella bacteria. It is transmitted by cat scratches, cat bites, or flea bites.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000705-2" qtype="causes">What causes Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cat-scratch disease is caused by the bacteria  Bartonella henselae . The disease is spread through contact with an infected cat (a bite or scratch) or exposure to cat fleas. It also can be spread through contact with cat saliva on broken skin or mucosal surfaces like those in the nose, mouth, and eyes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000705-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>A person who has had contact with an infected cat may show symptoms, including: Bump ( papule ) or blister ( pustule ) at site of injury (usually the first sign), Fatigue, Fever (in some people), Headache, Lymph node swelling ( lymphadenopathy ) near the site of the scratch or bite, Overall discomfort ( malaise ) ,  Less common symptoms may include: Loss of appetite , Sore throat, Weight loss , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000705-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you have swollen lymph nodes and a scratch or bite from a cat, your health care provider may suspect cat-scratch disease. A physical exam may also reveal an  enlarged spleen . Sometimes, an infected lymph node may form a tunnel ( fistula ) through the skin and drain (leak fluid). This disease is hard to diagnose, in part because it is rare. The  Bartonella henselae  immunofluorescence assay (IFA) blood test can detect the infection caused by these bacteria. The results of this test will be considered along with other information from your medical history, lab tests, or biopsy. A  lymph node biopsy  may also be done to look for other causes of swollen glands.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000705-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most often, cat-scratch disease is not serious. Medical treatment may not be needed. In some cases, treatment with antibiotics such as azithromycin can be helpful. Other antibiotics may be used, including:  Clarithromycin, Rifampin, Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole, Ciprofloxacin,  In people with  HIV/AIDS  and others, who have a weak immune system, cat-scratch disease can be more serious. Treatment with antibiotics may be needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000705-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>People who have a healthy immune system should recover fully without treatment. People with a weak immune system need antibiotic treatment to recover.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000705-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with weak immune systems may develop complications such as: Encephalopathy (loss of brain function),  Neuroretinitis  (inflammation of the retina and optic nerve of the eye),  Osteomyelitis  (bone infection),  Parinaud syndrome  (red, irritated, and painful eye) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000705-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have enlarged lymph nodes and you have been exposed to a cat.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000705-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Cat-scratch disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>To prevent cat-scratch disease: Wash your hands thoroughly with soap and water after playing with your cat. Wash any bites or scratches thoroughly., Play gently with cats so they don't scratch and bite., Don't allow a cat to lick your skin, eyes, mouth, or open wounds or scratches., Use flea control measures to lower the risk your cat develops the disease., Don't handle feral cats. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>