<Document id="0000641" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000421.htm">
 
<Focus>Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1306839</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate deposition disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CPPD disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute CPPD arthritis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pseudogout</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000641-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate (CPPD) arthritis is a joint disease that can cause attacks of arthritis. Like gout, crystals form in the joints. But in this arthritis, the crystals are not formed from uric acid.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000641-2" qtype="causes">What causes Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Deposition of calcium pyrophosphate dihydrate (CPPD) causes this form of  arthritis . The buildup of this chemical forms crystals in the cartilage of joints. This leads to attacks of  joint swelling  and pain in the knees, wrists, ankles, shoulders, and other joints. In contrast to gout, the metatarsal-phalangeal joint of the big toe is not affected. Among older adults, CPPD is a common cause of sudden (acute) arthritis in one joint. The attack is caused by: Injury to the joint, Medical stress,  CPPD arthritis mainly affects the elderly because joint degeneration and  osteoarthritis  increases with age. Such joint damage increases the tendency of CPPD deposition. However, CPPD arthritis is more common in people with: Hemochromatosis , Parathyroid disease, Dialysis-dependent renal failure, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000641-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, CPPD arthritis does not cause any symptoms. Instead, x-rays of affected joints such as knees show characteristic deposits of calcium. Some people with chronic CPPD deposits in large joints may have the following symptoms: Pain, Swelling, Warmth, Redness ,  Attacks of joint pain can last for months. There may be no symptoms between attacks. In some people CPPD arthritis causes severe damage to a joint. CPPD arthritis can also occur in the spine, both lower and upper. Pressure on spinal nerves may cause pain in the arms or legs. Because the symptoms are similar, CPPD arthritis can be confused with: Gouty arthritis (gout) , Osteoarthritis,  Rheumatoid arthritis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000641-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most arthritic conditions show similar symptoms. Carefully testing the joint fluid for crystals can help the doctor detect the condition. You may undergo the following tests: Joint fluid exam to detect white blood cells and calcium pyrophosphate crystals,  Joint x-rays  to look for joint damage and calcium deposits in joint spaces, Other joint imaging tests such as CT scan, MRI or ultrasound, if required, Blood tests to screen for conditions that are linked to calcium pyrophosphate arthritis, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000641-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment may involve removing fluid to relieve pressure in the joint. A needle is placed into the joint and fluid is aspirated. Some common treatment options are: Steroid injections: to treat severely swollen joints, Oral steroids: to treat multiple swollen joints, Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medicines (NSAIDs): to ease the pain, Colchicine: to treat attacks of CPPD arthritis, For chronic CPPD arthritis in multiple joints, methotrexate or hydroxychloroquine may be helpful, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000641-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people do well with treatment to reduce the acute joint pain. A medicine such as colchicine may help prevent repeat attacks. There is no treatment to remove the&#160;CPPD crystals.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000641-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Permanent joint damage can occur without treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000641-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have attacks of joint swelling and joint pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000641-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Calcium pyrophosphate arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known way to prevent this disorder. However, treating other problems that may cause CPPD arthritis may make the condition less severe. Regular follow-up visits may help prevent permanent damage of the affected joints.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>