<Document id="0000470" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000102.htm">
 
<Focus>Blastomycosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0005716</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>North American blastomycosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gilchrist's disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000470-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Blastomycosis is an infection caused by breathing in the  Blastomyces dermatitidis  fungus. The fungus is found in decaying wood and soil.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000470-2" qtype="causes">What causes Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can get blastomycosis by contact with moist soil, most commonly where there is rotting wood and leaves. The fungus enters the body through the lungs, where the infection starts. The fungus can then spread to other parts of the body. The disease may affect the skin, bones and joints, and other areas. Blastomycosis is rare. It is found in the central and southeastern United States, and in Canada, India, Israel, Saudi Arabia, and Africa. The key risk factor for the disease is contact with infected soil. It most often affects people with weakened immune systems, such as those with  HIV/AIDS  or who have had an organ transplant, but it can also infect healthy people. Men are more likely to be affected than women.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000470-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lung infection may not cause any symptoms. Symptoms may be seen if the infection spreads. Symptoms may include: Joint pain,  Chest pain ,  
 Cough (may produce brown or bloody mucus), Fatigue,  
 Fever, Night sweats, General discomfort, uneasiness, or ill feeling ( malaise ), Muscle pain,  Unintentional weight loss ,  Most people develop skin symptoms when the infection spreads. You may get papules, pustules, or nodules on exposed body areas. The pustules: May look like warts or ulcers, Are usually painless, Vary in color from gray to violet, May appear in the nose and mouth, Bleed easily and form ulcers , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000470-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical examination. You'll be asked about your medical history and symptoms. If the provider suspects you have a fungal infection, diagnosis can be confirmed by these tests: Chest CT scan ,  Chest x-ray , Skin  biopsy ,  Sputum culture  and examination, Urinary  antigen  detection, Tissue biopsy and culture,  Urine culture , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000470-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>You may not need to take medicine for a mild blastomycosis infection that stays in the lungs. The provider may recommend the following antifungal medicines when the disease is severe or spreads outside of the lungs. Fluconazole, Itraconazole, Ketoconazole,  Amphotericin B may be used for severe infections. Follow up regularly with your provider to make sure the infection does not return.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000470-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with minor skin sores (lesions) and mild lung infections usually recover completely. The infection can lead to death if not treated.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000470-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications of blastomycosis may include: Large sores with pus ( abscesses ), Skin sores can lead to scarring and loss of skin color (pigment), Return of the infection (relapse or disease recurrence), Side effects from drugs such as amphotericin B, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000470-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have symptoms of blastomycosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000470-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Avoiding travel to areas where the infection is known to occur may help prevent exposure to the fungus, but this may not always be possible. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>