<Document id="0000394" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000862.htm">
 
<Focus>Balanitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0004690</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Balanoposthitis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000394-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Balanitis is swelling of the foreskin and head of the  penis .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000394-2" qtype="causes">What causes Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Balanitis is most often caused by poor hygiene in uncircumcised men. Other possible causes include: Diseases, such as  reactive arthritis  and lichen sclerosus atrophicus ,  Infection ,  Harsh soaps ,  Not rinsing soap off properly while bathing ,  Uncontrolled diabetes , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000394-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Redness of foreskin or penis 
 , Other rashes on the head of the penis, Foul-smelling discharge, Painful penis and foreskin, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000394-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider may diagnose the problem with only an exam. However, you may need skin tests for viruses, fungi, or bacteria. A  skin biopsy  may also be needed. An exam by a dermatologist may be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000394-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the cause of the balanitis. Antibiotic pills or creams are used to treat balanitis that is caused by bacteria., Steroid creams may help balanitis that occurs with skin diseases., Anti-fungal cream will be prescribed if it is due to a fungus.,  In severe cases,  circumcision  may be the best option. If you cannot pull back (retract) the foreskin to clean it, you may need to be circumcised.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000394-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most cases of balanitis can be controlled with medicated creams and good hygiene. Surgery is not needed most of the time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000394-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Long-term swelling or infection can: Scar and narrow the opening of the penis (meatal stricture), Make it difficult and painful to retract the foreskin to expose the tip of the penis (a condition called phimosis), Make it difficult to move the foreskin over the head of the penis (a condition called paraphimosis), Affect the blood supply to the tip of the penis, Increase the risk of  penile cancer , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000394-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tell your provider if you have any signs of balanitis, including swelling of the foreskin or pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000394-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Balanitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Good hygiene can prevent most cases of balanitis. When you bathe, pull back the foreskin to clean and dry the area under it.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>