<Document id="0000097" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001182.htm">
 
<Focus>Adrenoleukodystrophy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0162309</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>X-linked Adrenoleukodystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Adrenomyeloneuropathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Childhood cerebral adrenoleukodystrophy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>ALD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Schilder-Addison Complex</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000097-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adrenoleukodystrophy describes several closely related disorders that disrupt the breakdown of certain fats. These disorders are often passed down (inherited) in families.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000097-2" qtype="causes">What causes Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adrenoleukodystrophy is usually passed down from parent to child as an  X-linked genetic trait . It affects mostly males. Some women who are carriers can have milder forms of the disease. It affects about 1 in 20,000 people from all races. Some cases of adrenoleukodystrophy occur when the gene mutates on its own. This is called sporadic and is not inherited. The condition results in the buildup of very-long-chain fatty acids in the nervous system, adrenal gland, and testes. This disrupts normal activity in these parts of the body.  There are three major categories of disease: Childhood cerebral form -- appears in mid-childhood (at ages 4 to 8), Adrenomyelopathy -- occurs in men in their 20s or later in life, Impaired adrenal gland function (called Addison disease or Addison-like phenotype) -- adrenal gland does not produce enough steroid hormones, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000097-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Childhood cerebral type symptoms include: Changes in muscle tone, especially muscle spasms and uncontrolled movements,  Crossed eyes , Handwriting that gets worse, Difficulty at school, Difficulty understanding what people are saying, Hearing loss,  Hyperactivity , Worsening nervous system damage, including coma, decreased fine motor control, and paralysis&#160;

 
 ,  Seizures ,  Swallowing difficulties ,  Visual impairment or blindness ,  Adrenomyelopathy symptoms include: Difficulty controlling urination, Possible worsening muscle weakness or leg stiffness, Problems with thinking speed and visual memory,  Adrenal gland failure (Addison type) symptoms include: Coma, Decreased appetite, Increased skin color, Loss of weight and&#160;muscle mass (wasting), Muscle weakness, Vomiting, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000097-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests for this condition include: Blood levels of very long chain fatty acids and hormones that are produced by the adrenal gland, Chromosome study to look for changes (mutations) in the  ABCD1  gene, MRI of the head , Skin biopsy, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000097-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adrenal dysfunction may be treated with steroids (such as cortisol) if the adrenal gland is not producing enough hormones. A specific treatment for X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy is not available. A bone marrow transplant may stop worsening of the condition. Supportive care and careful monitoring of impaired adrenal gland function may help in improving comfort and quality of life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000097-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>The childhood form of X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy is a progressive disease. It leads to a long-term coma (vegetative state) about 2 years after nervous system symptoms develop. The child can live in this condition for as long as 10 years until death occurs. The other forms of this disease are milder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000097-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer> These complications can occur: Adrenal crisis, Vegetative state, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000097-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if: Your child develops symptoms of X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy, Your child has X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy and is getting worse, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000097-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Adrenoleukodystrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling is recommended for&#160;couples with a family history of X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy. Mothers of affected sons have an 85% chance of being a carrier for this condition. Prenatal diagnosis of X-linked adrenoleukodystrophy is also available. It is done by&#160;testing cells from  chorionic villus sampling  or  amniocentesis . These tests look&#160;for either a known genetic change in the family or for very long chain fatty acid levels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>