<Document id="0000403" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001666.htm">
 
<Focus>Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0000744</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Abetalipoproteinemia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acanthocytosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Apolipoprotein B deficiency</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000403-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome is a rare disease passed down through families. The person is unable to fully absorb dietary fats through their intestines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000403-2" qtype="causes">What causes Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome is caused by changes in the  MTTP  gene that tells the body to create lipoproteins (molecules of fat combined with  protein ). These variants make it hard for the body to properly digest fat and essential vitamins.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000403-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Balance and coordination difficulties, Curvature of spine, Decreased vision that gets worse over time, Developmental delay, Failure to thrive (grow) in infancy, Muscle weakness, Poor muscle coordination that usually develops after age 10, Protruding abdomen, Slurred speech, Stool abnormalities, including fatty stools that appear pale in color, frothy stools, and abnormally foul-smelling stools, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000403-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>There may be damage to the retina of the eye ( retinitis pigmentosa ). Tests that may be done to help diagnose this condition include: Apolipoprotein B  blood test, Blood tests to look for vitamin deficiencies (fat-soluble vitamins A, D, E, and K), "Burr-cell" malformation of the red cells (acanthocytosis),  Complete blood count  (CBC), Cholesterol studies,  Electromyography ,  Eye exam ,  Nerve conduction velocity , Stool sample analysis ,  Genetic testing may be available for genetic variants in the  MTTP  gene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000403-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment involves large doses of vitamin supplements containing fat-soluble vitamins ( vitamin A ,  vitamin D ,  vitamin E , and  vitamin K ). Linoleic acid supplements are also recommended. People with this condition should talk to a dietitian. Diet changes are needed to prevent stomach problems. This may involve limiting intake of some types of fat. Supplements of medium-chain triglycerides are taken under the supervision of a health care provider. They should be used with caution, because they may cause liver damage.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000403-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on the amount of brain and nervous system problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000403-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Blindness , Mental deterioration, Loss of function of peripheral nerves, uncoordinated movement (ataxia), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000403-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if your infant or child has symptoms of this disease. Genetic counseling can help families understand the condition and the risks of inheriting it, and learn how to care for the person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000403-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Bassen-Kornzweig syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>High doses of fat-soluble vitamins may slow the progression of some problems, such as retina damage and decreased vision.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>