<Document id="0000036" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000852.htm">
 
<Focus>Acanthosis nigricans</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0000889</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000036-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Acanthosis nigricans ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acanthosis nigricans (AN) is a skin disorder in which there is darker, thick, velvety skin in body folds and creases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000036-2" qtype="causes">What causes Acanthosis nigricans ?</Question>
			<Answer>AN can affect otherwise healthy people. It can also be related to medical problems, such as: Genetic disorders, including  Down syndrome  and  Alstr&#246;m syndrome , Hormone imbalances that occur in diabetes and obesity, often called insulin resistance, Cancer, such as cancer of the digestive system, liver, kidney, bladder, or lymphoma, Some medicines, including hormones such as human growth hormone or birth control pills
 , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000036-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Acanthosis nigricans ?</Question>
			<Answer>AN usually appears slowly and doesn't cause any symptoms other than skin changes. Eventually, dark, velvety skin with very visible markings and creases appears in the armpits, groin and neck folds, and over the joints of the fingers and toes. Sometimes, the lips, palms, soles of the feet, or other areas are affected. These symptoms are more common in people with cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000036-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Acanthosis nigricans ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can usually diagnose AN by looking at your skin. A  skin biopsy  may be needed in rare cases. If there is no clear cause of AN, your provider may order tests. These may include: Blood tests to check blood sugar level or insulin level,  Endoscopy , 
   X-rays
   , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000036-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Acanthosis nigricans ?</Question>
			<Answer>No treatment is needed, as AN only causes a change in skin color. If the condition is affecting your appearance, using moisturizers containing ammonium lactate, tretinoin, or hydroquinone can help lighten the skin. Your provider may also suggest laser treatment. It is important to treat any underlying medical problem that may be causing these skin changes. When AN is related to obesity, losing weight often improves the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000036-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Acanthosis nigricans ?</Question>
			<Answer>AN often disappears if the cause can be found and treated.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000036-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Acanthosis nigricans ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you develop areas of thick, dark, velvety skin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>