<Document id="0000525" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001585.htm">
 
<Focus>Bowlegs</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0544755</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T190</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Genu varum</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000525-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bowlegs is a condition in which the knees stay wide apart when a person stands with the feet and ankles together. It is considered normal in children under 18 months. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000525-2" qtype="causes">What causes Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>Infants are born bowlegged because of their folded position in the mother's womb. Bowed legs begin to straighten once the child starts to walk and the legs begin to bear weight (about 12 to 18 months old). By around age 3, the child can most often stand with the ankles apart and the knees just touching. If the bowed legs are still present, the child is called bowlegged. Bowlegs may be caused by illnesses, such as: Abnormal bone development,  Blount disease , Fractures that&#160;do not&#160;heal correctly, Lead or fluoride poisoning,  Rickets , which is caused by a lack of  vitamin D , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000525-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Knees that&#160;do not&#160;touch when standing with feet together (ankles touching), Bowing of legs is same on both sides of the body (symmetrical), Bowed legs continue beyond age 3 , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000525-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>A health care provider can often diagnose bowlegs by looking at the child. The distance between the knees is measured while the child is lying on the back. Blood tests may be needed to rule out rickets. X-rays  may be needed if: The child is 3 years old or older., The bowing is getting worse., Bowing is not the same on both sides., Other test results suggest disease., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000525-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>No treatment is recommended for bowlegs unless the condition is extreme. The child should be seen by the provider at least every 6 months. Special shoes, braces, or casts can be tried if the condition is severe or the child also has another disease. It is unclear how well these work. At times, surgery is done to correct the deformity in an adolescent with severe bowlegs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000525-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>In many cases the outcome is good, and there is most often no problem walking.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000525-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bowlegs that does not go away and is not treated may lead to arthritis in the knees or hips over time. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000525-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if your child shows ongoing or worsening bowed legs after age 3.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000525-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Bowlegs ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known way to prevent bowlegs, other than to avoid rickets. Make sure your child is exposed to sunlight and gets the proper amount of vitamin D in their diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>