<Document id="0000648" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000888.htm">
 
<Focus>Calorie count - sodas and energy drinks</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Weight loss - calorie count - sodas and energy drinks</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Overweight - calorie count - sodas and energy drinks</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Obesity - calorie count - sodas and energy drinks</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000648-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Calorie count - sodas and energy drinks</Question>
			<Answer>It is easy to have a few servings of soda or energy drinks a day without thinking about it. Like other  sweetened drinks , the calories from these drinks can add up quickly. Most provide little or no nutrients and contain large amounts of added sugar. Soda and energy drinks can also have large amounts of caffeine and other stimulants, so it is best to limit how much you drink.  Here is a list of some popular sodas and energy drinks, their serving sizes, and the number of calories in each.  BEVERAGE SERVING SIZE CALORIES Soda 
 
 7 Up 12 oz 150 A&amp;W Root Beer 12 oz 160 Barq's Root Beer 12 oz 170 Canada Dry Ginger Ale 12 oz 120 Cherry Coca-Cola 12 oz 150 Coca-Cola Classic 12 oz 150 Coca-Cola Zero 12 oz 0 Diet Coca-Cola 12 oz 0 Diet Dr. Pepper 12 oz 0 Diet Pepsi 12 oz 0 Dr. Pepper 12 oz 150 Fanta Orange 12 oz 160 Fresca Soda Water 12 oz 0 Mountain Dew 12 oz 170 Mountain Dew Code Red 12 oz 170 Mug Root Beer 12 oz 160 Orange Crush 12 oz 195 Pepsi 12 oz. 150 Sierra Mist 12 oz 150 Sprite 12 oz 140 Vanilla Coca-Cola 12 oz 150 Wild Cherry Pepsi 12 oz 160 Energy Drinks 
 
 AMP Energy Strawberry Limeade 16 oz 220 AMP Energy Boost Original 16 oz 220 AMP Energy Boost Sugar Free 16 oz 10 Full Throttle Original 16 oz 230 Monster Energy Drink (Low Carb) 16 oz 10 Monster Energy Drink 16 oz 220 Red Bull Energy Drink 16 oz 200 Red Bull Energy Drink Sugar Free 16 oz 20 Rockstar Energy Drink 16 oz 260</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>