<Document id="0000432" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001582.htm">
 
<Focus>Bezoar</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1321581</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Trichobezoar</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hairball</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000432-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>A bezoar is a ball of swallowed foreign material most often composed of hair or fiber. It collects in the stomach and fails to pass through the intestines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000432-2" qtype="causes">What causes Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chewing on or eating hair or fuzzy materials (or indigestible materials such as plastic bags) can lead to the formation of a bezoar. The rate is very low. The risk is greater among people with intellectual disability or emotionally disturbed children. Generally, bezoars are mostly seen in females aged 10 to 19 years.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000432-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Indigestion , Stomach upset or distress,  Nausea  and vomiting, Diarrhea, Pain, Gastric ulcers , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000432-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>The child may have a  lump in the abdomen  that can be felt by the health care provider. A  barium swallow x-ray  will show the mass in the stomach. Sometimes, a scope is used (endoscopy) to directly view the bezoar in the stomach.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000432-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>The bezoar may need to be surgically removed, especially if it is large. In some cases, small bezoars may be removed through a scope placed through the mouth into the stomach. This is similar to an  EGD  (esophagogastroduodenoscopy) procedure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000432-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>Full recovery is expected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000432-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>Persistent vomiting can lead to  dehydration .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000432-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you suspect your child has a bezoar.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000432-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Bezoar ?</Question>
			<Answer>If your child has had a hair bezoar in the past, trim the child's hair short so they cannot put the ends in the mouth. Keep indigestible materials away from a child who has a tendency to put items in the mouth. Be sure to remove the child's access to fuzzy or fiber-filled materials.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>