<Document id="0000638" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002580.htm">
 
<Focus>Calcium channel blocker overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0573229</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000638-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Calcium channel blocker overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Calcium-channel blockers are a type of medicine used to treat high blood pressure and heart rhythm disturbances. They are one of several classes of drugs used to treat the heart and related conditions. These medicines are a common cause of poisoning. Calcium-channel blocker overdose occurs when someone takes more than the normal or recommended amount of this medicine. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with overdoses, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000638-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Calcium channel blocker overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of a calcium-channel blocker  overdose  include: Agitation (hyperactivity) and delirium (confused thinking and possible hallucinations), Breathing difficulty, Confusion, Constipation, Lightheadedness,  dizziness , Drowsiness, Increased blood sugar,  Irregular heartbeat ,  Nausea  and vomiting, Rapid heartbeat,  Slow heartbeat , Slurred speech, Shock (extremely low blood pressure), Weakness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000638-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Calcium channel blocker overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000638-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Calcium channel blocker overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Taking too much of a calcium-channel blocker can be very dangerous. Death can occur, especially with verapamil. If the person's heart rate and blood pressure can be corrected, survival is likely. Survival depends on how much and what type of this medicine the person took and how quickly they receive treatment. An overnight hospital stay may be required even in less serious cases, as some long-acting drug preparations remain in the body for many hours. Risk factors for a more severe outcome, including multiple organ failure and death, include: Co-ingestion with other drugs which affect the heart; for example, digoxin, calcium channel blockers, tricyclic antidepressants, People with other health conditions, such as congestive heart failure and heart rhythm disturbances,  Verapamil (a type of calcium channel blocker) overdose is associated with the highest mortality risk.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000638-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Calcium channel blocker overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Taking too much of a calcium-channel blocker can be very dangerous. Death can occur, especially with verapamil. If the person's heart rate and blood pressure can be corrected, survival is likely. Survival depends on how much and what type of this medicine the person took and how quickly they receive treatment. An overnight hospital stay may be required even in less serious cases, as some long-acting drug preparations remain in the body for many hours. Risk factors for a more severe outcome, including multiple organ failure and death, include: Co-ingestion with other drugs which affect the heart; for example, digoxin, calcium channel blockers, tricyclic antidepressants, People with other health conditions, such as congestive heart failure and heart rhythm disturbances,  Verapamil (a type of calcium channel blocker) overdose is associated with the highest mortality risk.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>