<Document id="0000326" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001326.htm">
 
<Focus>Aspergillosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0004030</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Aspergillus infection</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000326-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Aspergillosis is an infection or  allergic response  due to the aspergillus fungus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000326-2" qtype="causes">What causes Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Aspergillosis is caused by a fungus called aspergillus. The fungus is often found growing on dead leaves, stored grain, compost piles, or in other decaying vegetation. It can also be found on marijuana leaves. Although most people are often exposed to aspergillus, infections caused by the fungus rarely occur in people who have a healthy immune system. There are several forms of aspergillosis: Allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis is an allergic reaction to the fungus. This infection usually develops in people who already have lung problems such as asthma or cystic fibrosis.,  Aspergilloma  is a growth (fungus ball) that develops in an area of past lung disease or lung scarring such as  tuberculosis  or lung abscess., Invasive pulmonary aspergillosis is a serious infection with pneumonia. It can spread to other parts of the body. This infection occurs most often in people with a weakened immune system. This can be from cancer, AIDS, leukemia, an organ transplant, chemotherapy, or other conditions or medicines that lower the number or function of white blood cells or weaken the immune system. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000326-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms depend on the type of infection. Symptoms of allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis may include: Cough, Coughing up blood or brownish mucus plugs, Fever, General ill feeling (malaise),  Wheezing , Weight loss ,  Other symptoms depend on the part of the body affected, and may include: Bone pain , Chest pain, Chills,  Decreased urine output , Headaches, Increased phlegm production, which may be bloody, Shortness of breath, Skin sores (lesions), Vision problems , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000326-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical examination and ask about the symptoms. Tests to diagnose aspergillus infection include: Aspergillus antibody test ,  Chest x-ray ,  Complete blood count ,  CT scan , Galactomannan (a sugar molecule shed from the fungus that is sometimes found in the blood), Immunoglobulin E (IgE) blood level, Lung function tests, Sputum stain and culture for fungus (looking for aspergillus), Tissue  biopsy , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000326-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>A fungus ball is usually not treated with antifungal medicines unless there is bleeding into the lung tissue. In such a case, surgery and medicines are needed. Invasive aspergillosis is treated with several weeks of an antifungal medicine. It can be given by mouth or IV (into a vein).  Endocarditis  caused by aspergillus is treated by surgically replacing the infected heart valves. Long-term antifungal medicines are also needed. Allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis is treated with medicines that suppress the immune system (immunosuppressive medicines), such as prednisone, typically in conjunction with antifungals.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000326-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>With treatment, people with allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis usually get better over time. It is common for the disease to come back (relapse) and need repeat treatment. If invasive aspergillosis does not get better with treatment using medicine, it eventually leads to death. The outlook for invasive aspergillosis also depends on the person's underlying disease and immune system health.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000326-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health problems from the disease or treatment include: Amphotericin B can cause kidney damage and unpleasant side effects such as fever and chills,  Bronchiectasis  (permanent scarring and enlargement of the small sacs in the lungs), Invasive lung disease can cause massive bleeding from the lung, Mucus plugs in the airways, Permanent airway blockage,  Respiratory failure , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000326-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you develop symptoms of aspergillosis or if you have a weakened immune system and develop a fever.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000326-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Aspergillosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Precautions should be taken when using medicines that suppress the immune system.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>