<Document id="0000956" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000530.htm">
 
<Focus>Congenital spherocytic anemia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2674218</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hereditary spherocytosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spherocytosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000956-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hereditary spherocytic anemia is a rare disorder of the surface layer (membrane) of red blood cells. It leads to red blood cells that are shaped like spheres, and premature breakdown of red blood cells ( hemolytic anemia ).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000956-2" qtype="causes">What causes Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>This disorder is caused by a defective gene. The defect results in an abnormal red blood cell membrane. The affected cells have a smaller surface area for their volume than normal red blood cells, and can break open easily. The  anemia  can vary from mild to severe. In severe cases the disorder may be found in early childhood. In mild cases it may go unnoticed until adulthood. This disorder is most common in people of northern European descent, but it has been found in all races.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000956-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Infants may have yellowing of the skin and eyes ( jaundice ) and pale coloring ( pallor ). Other symptoms may include: Fatigue , Irritability,  Shortness of breath ,  Weakness , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000956-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, the spleen is enlarged. Laboratory tests can help diagnose this condition. Tests may include: Blood smear to show abnormally shaped cells,  Bilirubin level ,  Complete blood count  to check for anemia,  Coombs test , LDH level, Haptoglobin level,  Osmotic fragility  or specialized testing to evaluate for the red blood cell defect,  Reticulocyte count , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000956-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Surgery to remove the spleen ( splenectomy ) cures the anemia but does not correct the abnormal cell shape. Families with a history of spherocytosis should have their children screened for this disorder. Children should wait until age 5 to have splenectomy because of the infection risk. In mild cases discovered in adults, it may not be necessary to remove the spleen. Children and adults should be given a pneumococcal vaccine before spleen removal surgery. They also should receive folic acid supplements. Additional vaccines may be needed based on the person's history.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000956-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome is usually good with treatment. After the spleen is removed, the life span of the red blood cell returns to normal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000956-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Gallstones , Much lower red blood cell production (aplastic crisis) caused by a viral infection, which can make anemia worse , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000956-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if: Your symptoms get worse., Your symptoms do not improve with new treatment., You develop new symptoms., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000956-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Congenital spherocytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>This is an inherited disorder and may not be preventable. Being aware of your risk, such as a family history of the disorder, may help you get diagnosed and treated early.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>