<Document id="0000807" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001642.htm">
 
<Focus>Choanal atresia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0008297</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000807-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Choanal atresia is a narrowing or blockage of the nasal airway by tissue. It is a congenital condition, meaning it is present at birth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000807-2" qtype="causes">What causes Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause of choanal atresia is unknown. It is thought to occur when the thin tissue separating the nose and mouth area during fetal development remains after birth. The condition is the most common nasal abnormality in newborn infants. Females get this condition about twice as often as males. More than half of affected infants also have other congenital problems. Choanal atresia is most often diagnosed shortly after birth while the infant is still in the hospital.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000807-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Newborns generally prefer to breathe through their nose. Typically, infants only breathe through their mouths when they cry. Babies with choanal atresia have difficulty breathing unless they are crying. Choanal atresia may affect one or both sides of the nasal airway. Choanal atresia blocking both sides of the nose causes acute breathing problems with bluish discoloration and breathing failure. Such infants may need  resuscitation  at delivery. More than one half of infants have a blockage on only one side, which causes less severe problems. Symptoms include: Chest retracts unless the child is breathing through mouth or crying.,  Difficulty breathing  following birth, which may result in cyanosis (bluish discoloration), unless infant is crying., Inability to nurse and breathe at same time., Inability to pass a catheter through each side of the nose into the throat., Persistent one-sided nasal blockage or discharge. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000807-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam may show an obstruction of the nose. Tests that may be done include: CT scan ,  Endoscopy  of the nose ,  Sinus x-ray , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000807-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The immediate concern is to resuscitate the baby if necessary. An airway may need to be placed so that the infant can breathe. In some cases,  intubation  may be needed. An infant can learn to mouth breathe, which can delay the need for immediate surgery. Surgery to remove the obstruction cures the problem. Surgery may be delayed if the infant can tolerate mouth breathing. The surgery may be done through the nose (transnasal) or through the mouth (transpalatal).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000807-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Full recovery is expected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000807-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Possible complications include: Aspiration  while feeding and attempting to breathe through the mouth ,  Respiratory arrest , Renarrowing of the area after surgery, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000807-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Choanal atresia, especially when it affects both sides, is generally diagnosed shortly after birth while the infant is still in the hospital. One-sided atresia may not cause symptoms, and the infant may be sent home without a diagnosis. If your infant has any of the problems listed here, consult your health care provider. The child may need to be checked by an ear, nose, and throat (ENT) specialist.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000807-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Choanal atresia ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known prevention.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>