<Document id="0000704" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002768.htm">
 
<Focus>Castor oil overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0572364</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Alphamul overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Emulsoil overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Laxopol overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Unisol overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000704-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Castor oil overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Castor oil is a yellowish liquid often used as a lubricant and in laxatives. This article discusses poisoning from swallowing a large amount (overdose) of castor oil. This is for information only and not for use in the treatment or management of an actual overdose. If you have an overdose, you should call your local emergency number (such as 911) or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States. Ricinus communis  (castor oil plant) contain the toxin ricin. Seeds or beans swallowed whole with the hard outer shell intact typically prevent absorption of significant toxin. Purified ricin derived from the castor bean is highly toxic and lethal in small doses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000704-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Castor oil overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of a castor oil overdose include: Abdominal cramps, Chest pain, Diarrhea, Dizziness, Hallucinations (rare), Fainting, Nausea, Shortness of breath, Skin rash, Throat tightness , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000704-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Castor oil overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000704-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Castor oil overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Normally, castor oil should cause few problems. Recovery is very likely. If nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea are not controlled, serious dehydration and electrolyte (body chemical and mineral) imbalances may occur. These can cause heart rhythm disturbances. Keep all chemicals, cleaners, and industrial products in their original containers and marked as poison, and out of the reach of children. This will reduce the risk for poisoning and overdose.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000704-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Castor oil overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Normally, castor oil should cause few problems. Recovery is very likely. If nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea are not controlled, serious dehydration and electrolyte (body chemical and mineral) imbalances may occur. These can cause heart rhythm disturbances. Keep all chemicals, cleaners, and industrial products in their original containers and marked as poison, and out of the reach of children. This will reduce the risk for poisoning and overdose.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>