<Document id="0000244" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001142.htm">
 
<Focus>Annular pancreas</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0149955</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000244-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Annular pancreas ?</Question>
			<Answer>An annular pancreas is a ring of pancreatic tissue that encircles the  duodenum  (the first part of the small intestine). The normal position of the pancreas is next to, but not surrounding the duodenum.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000244-2" qtype="causes">What causes Annular pancreas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Annular pancreas is problem present at birth (congenital defect). Symptoms occur when the ring of pancreas squeezes and narrows the small intestine so that food cannot pass easily or at all. Newborns may have symptoms of complete blockage of the intestine. However, up to one half of people with this condition do not have symptoms until adulthood. There are also cases that are not detected because the symptoms are mild. Conditions that may be associated with annular pancreas include: Down syndrome, Excess amniotic fluid during pregnancy  (polyhydramnios) , Other congenital gastrointestinal problems, Pancreatitis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000244-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Annular pancreas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Newborns may not feed well. They may spit up more than normal, not drink enough breast milk or formula, and cry. Adult symptoms may include: Fullness after eating,  Nausea or vomiting , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000244-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Annular pancreas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests include: Abdominal ultrasound ,  Abdominal x-ray , CT scan,  Upper GI and small bowel series , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000244-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Annular pancreas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment most often involves surgery to bypass the blocked part of the duodenum.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000244-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Annular pancreas ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome is most often good with surgery. Adults with an annular pancreas are at increased risk for pancreatic or biliary tract cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000244-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Annular pancreas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Obstructive jaundice,  Pancreatic cancer , Pancreatitis (inflammation of the pancreas), Peptic ulcer, Perforation (tearing a hole) of the intestine due to obstruction,  Peritonitis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000244-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Annular pancreas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you or your child has any symptoms of annular pancreas.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>