<Document id="0000979" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000698.htm">
 
<Focus>COPD flare-ups</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3540542</CUI>
			<CUI>C1517205</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>COPD exacerbation</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease exacerbation</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Emphysema exacerbation</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic bronchitis exacerbation</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000979-1" qtype="information">What is (are) COPD flare-ups ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease  (COPD) symptoms can worsen rapidly. You may find it hard to breathe. You may cough or wheeze more or produce more phlegm. You might also feel anxious and have trouble sleeping or doing your daily activities. This problem is called a COPD exacerbation or COPD flare-up.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000979-2" qtype="causes">What causes COPD flare-ups ?</Question>
			<Answer>Certain illnesses, colds, and lung infections from viruses or bacteria can lead to flare-ups. Other causes may include: Being around smoke or other pollutants, Weather changes, Doing too much activity, Being run-down, Feeling stressed or anxious,  You can often manage a flare-up right away with medicines and self-care. Work with your health care provider on an action plan for COPD exacerbations so that you know what to do. Get to know your usual COPD symptoms, sleep patterns, and when you have good or bad days. This can help you learn the difference between your normal COPD symptoms and signs of a flare-up.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000979-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of COPD flare-ups ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000979-5" qtype="prevention">How to prevent COPD flare-ups ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000979-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for COPD flare-ups ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>