<Document id="0000883" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000130.htm">
 
<Focus>Coal worker's pneumoconiosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032273</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Black lung disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pneumoconiosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Anthrosilicosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000883-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Coal worker's pneumoconiosis (CWP) is a lung disease that results from breathing in dust from coal, graphite, or man-made carbon over a long time. CWP is also known as black lung disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000883-2" qtype="causes">What causes Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>CWP occurs in two forms: simple and complicated (also called progressive massive fibrosis, or PMF). Your risk for developing CWP depends on how long you have been around coal dust. Most people with this disease are older than 50. Smoking does not increase your risk for developing this disease, but it may have an added harmful effect on the lungs. If CWP occurs with  rheumatoid arthritis , it is called  Caplan syndrome .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000883-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of CWP include: Cough ,  Shortness of breath , Coughing up of black sputum, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000883-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical examination and ask about your symptoms. Tests that may be done include: Chest x-ray ,  Chest CT scan ,  Lung function tests , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000883-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>&#160; Treatment may include any of the following, depending on how severe your symptoms are: Medicines to keep the airways open and reduce mucus, Pulmonary rehabilitation to help you learn ways to breathe better, Oxygen therapy,  You should also avoid further exposure to coal dust.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000883-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your provider about treating and managing coal worker's pneumoconiosis. Information can be found at the American Lung Association: Treating and Managing Coal Worker's Pneumoconiosis website:  www.lung.org/lung-health-diseases/lung-disease-lookup/black-lung/treating-and-managing .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000883-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Outcome for the simple form is usually good. It rarely causes disability or death. The complicated form may cause shortness of breath that worsens over time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000883-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Chronic  bronchitis ,  Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease  (COPD) ,  Cor pulmonale  (failure of the right side of the heart),  Respiratory failure , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000883-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Coal worker's pneumoconiosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wear a protective mask when working around coal, graphite, or man-made carbon. Follow directions to prevent high-level exposure. Companies should enforce the maximum permitted dust levels. Avoid smoking.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>