<Document id="0001351" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001468.htm">
 
<Focus>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013720</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001351-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ehlers-Danlos syndrome (EDS) is a group of inherited disorders marked by extremely loose joints,&#160;very stretchy ( hyperelastic ) skin that bruises easily, and easily damaged blood vessels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001351-2" qtype="causes">What causes Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are at least 13 types of EDS. A variety of gene changes (mutations) cause problems with collagen. This is the material that provides strength and structure to: Skin, Bone, Blood vessels, Internal organs,  The abnormal collagen leads to the symptoms associated with EDS. In some forms of the syndrome, the rupture of internal organs or abnormal heart valves can occur. Family history is a risk factor in some cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001351-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of EDS vary by type and may include: Back pain, Double-jointedness, Easily damaged, bruised, and stretchy skin, Easy scarring and poor wound healing, Flat feet, Increased joint mobility, joints popping, early arthritis,  Joint dislocation , Joint pain, Premature rupture of membranes during pregnancy, Very soft and velvety skin, Vision problems , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001351-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Examination by a health care provider may show: Deformed surface of the eye (cornea), Excess joint looseness and  joint hypermobility , Mitral valve in the heart does not close tightly ( mitral valve prolapse ), Gum infection ( periodontitis ), Rupture of intestines, uterus, or eyeball (seen only in vascular EDS, which is rare), Soft, thin, or very stretchy skin ,  Tests to diagnose EDS include: Collagen typing (performed on a  skin biopsy  sample), Collagen gene mutation testing,  Echocardiogram  (heart ultrasound), Lysyl hydroxylase or oxidase activity (to check collagen formation) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001351-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no specific cure for EDS. Individual problems and symptoms are evaluated and cared for appropriately. Physical therapy or evaluation by a doctor specializing in rehabilitation medicine is often needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001351-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with EDS generally have a normal life span. Intelligence is normal. Those with the rare vascular type of EDS are at greater risk for rupture of a major organ or blood vessel. These people have a high risk for sudden death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001351-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Possible complications of EDS include: Chronic joint pain, Early-onset arthritis, Failure of surgical wounds to close (or stitches tear out), Premature rupture of membranes during pregnancy, Rupture of major vessels, including a  ruptured aortic aneurysm  (only in vascular EDS), Rupture of a hollow organ such as the uterus or bowel (only in vascular EDS), Rupture of the eyeball (only in vascular EDS), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001351-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if you have a family history of EDS and you are concerned about your risk or are planning to start a family. Contact your provider for an appointment if you or your child has symptoms of EDS.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001351-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Ehlers-Danlos syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling  is recommended for prospective parents with a family history of EDS. Those planning to start a family should be aware of the type of EDS they have and how it is passed down to children. This can be determined through testing and evaluations suggested by your provider or genetic counselor. Identifying any significant health risks may help prevent severe complications by vigilant screening and lifestyle alterations.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>