<Document id="0001019" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000345.htm">
 
<Focus>Craniopharyngioma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0010276</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001019-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Craniopharyngioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>A craniopharyngioma is a noncancerous (benign)  tumor  that develops at the base of the brain near the pituitary gland.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001019-2" qtype="causes">What causes Craniopharyngioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of the tumor is unknown. This tumor most commonly affects children between 5 to 10 years of age. Adults can sometimes be affected. Boys and girls are equally likely to develop this tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001019-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Craniopharyngioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Craniopharyngioma causes symptoms by: Increasing pressure on the brain, usually from  hydrocephalus , Disrupting hormone production by the pituitary gland, Pressure or  damage to the optic nerve ,  Increased pressure on the brain can cause: Headache, Nausea, Vomiting (especially in the morning),  Damage to the pituitary gland causes hormone imbalances that can lead to excessive thirst and urination, and slow growth. When the optic nerve is damaged by the tumor, vision problems develop. These defects are often permanent. They may get worse after surgery to remove the tumor. Behavioral and learning problems may be present.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001019-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Craniopharyngioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical exam. Tests will be done to check for a tumor. These may include: Blood tests to measure hormone levels,  CT scan  or  MRI  scan of the brain, Examination of the nervous system, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001019-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Craniopharyngioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goal of the treatment is to relieve symptoms. Usually, surgery has been the main treatment for craniopharyngioma. However, radiation treatment instead of surgery or along with a smaller surgery may be the best choice for some people. In tumors that cannot be removed completely with surgery alone,  radiation therapy  is used. If the tumor has a classic appearance on CT scan, a biopsy may not be needed if treatment with radiation alone is planned. Stereotactic radiosurgery  is performed at some medical centers. This tumor is best treated at a center with experience in treating craniopharyngiomas.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001019-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Craniopharyngioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>In general, the&#160;outlook is good. There is an 80% to 90% chance of a cure if the tumor can be completely removed with surgery or treated with high doses of radiation. If the tumor returns, it will most often come back within the first 2 years after surgery. Outlook depends on several factors, including: Whether the tumor can be completely removed, Which nervous system problems and hormonal imbalances the tumor and treatment cause ,  Most of the problems with hormones and vision do not improve with treatment. Sometimes, the treatment may even make them worse.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001019-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Craniopharyngioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>There may be long-term hormone, vision, and nervous system problems after craniopharyngioma is treated. When the tumor is not completely removed, the condition may return.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001019-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Craniopharyngioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider for the following symptoms: Headache, nausea, vomiting, or balance problems (signs of increased pressure on the brain), Increased thirst and urination, Poor growth in a child, Vision changes, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>