<Document id="0001765" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000833.htm">
 
<Focus>Granuloma annulare</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085074</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001765-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Granuloma annulare ?</Question>
			<Answer>Granuloma annulare (GA) is a long-term ( chronic ) skin disease consisting of a rash with reddish bumps arranged in a circle or ring.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001765-2" qtype="causes">What causes Granuloma annulare ?</Question>
			<Answer>GA most often affects children and young adults. It is slightly more common in females. The condition is usually seen in otherwise healthy people. Sometimes, it may be associated with  diabetes  or thyroid disease. The exact cause of GA is unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001765-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Granuloma annulare ?</Question>
			<Answer>GA usually causes no other symptoms, but the rash may be slightly itchy. People usually notice a ring of small, firm bumps (papules) over the backs of the forearms, hands, or feet. Occasionally, they may find a number of rings. In rare cases, GA appears as a firm nodule under the skin of the arms or legs. In some cases, the rash spreads all over the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001765-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Granuloma annulare ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider may think you have a fungal infection when looking at your skin as the ring shape may look like  ringworm . A skin scraping and  KOH test  can be used to tell the difference between GA and a fungal infection. You may also need a  skin punch biopsy  to confirm the diagnosis of GA.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001765-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Granuloma annulare ?</Question>
			<Answer>GA can resolve on its own. You may not need treatment for GA, except for cosmetic reasons. Very strong steroid creams or ointments are sometimes used to clear up the rash more quickly. Injections of steroids directly into the rings may also be effective. Some providers may choose to freeze the bumps with liquid nitrogen. People with severe or widespread cases may need medicines that suppress the immune system. Laser and ultraviolet light therapy (phototherapy) may also help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001765-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Granuloma annulare ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, GA disappears without treatment within 2 years. The rings can remain for many years. The appearance of new rings years later is not uncommon.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001765-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Granuloma annulare ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you notice ring-like bumps anywhere on your skin that do not go away within a few weeks.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>