<Document id="0001469" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000774.htm">
 
<Focus>Ethylene glycol poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0413194</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Intoxication - ethylene glycol</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001469-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ethylene glycol is a colorless, odorless, sweet-tasting chemical. It is poisonous if swallowed. Ethylene glycol may be swallowed accidentally, or it may be taken deliberately in a suicide attempt or as a substitute for drinking alcohol (ethanol). Most ethylene glycol poisonings occur due to the ingestion of antifreeze. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001469-2" qtype="causes">What causes Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001469-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>The first symptom of ethylene glycol ingestion is similar to the feeling caused by drinking alcohol (ethanol). Within a few hours, more toxic effects become apparent. Symptoms may include nausea, vomiting, convulsions, stupor (decreased level of alertness), or even coma. Ethylene glycol toxicity should be suspected in anyone who is severely ill after drinking an unknown substance, especially if they at first appear drunk and you can't smell alcohol on their breath. An overdose of ethylene glycol can damage the brain, lungs, liver, and kidneys. The poisoning causes disturbances in the body's chemistry, including  metabolic acidosis  (increased acids in the bloodstream and tissues). The disturbances may be severe enough to cause profound  shock , organ failure, and death. As little as 120 milliliters (approximately 4 fluid ounces) of ethylene glycol may be enough to kill an average-sized man.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001469-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001469-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001469-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on how quickly treatment is received, the amount swallowed, the organs affected, and other factors. When treatment is delayed, this type of poisoning can be deadly. Complications may include: Brain and nerve damage, including seizures and changes in vision, Kidney failure, Shock (low blood pressure and depressed heart function), Coma, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001469-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001469-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001469-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Ethylene glycol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>