<Document id="0001568" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001136.htm">
 
<Focus>Femoral hernia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019288</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Femorocele</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Enteromerocele</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Crural hernia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001568-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Femoral hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>A  hernia  occurs when the contents of the abdomen push through a weak point or tear in the muscle wall of the belly. This layer of muscle holds the abdominal organs in place.  A femoral hernia is a bulge in the upper part of the thigh near the groin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001568-2" qtype="causes">What causes Femoral hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of the time, there is no clear cause of a hernia. Some hernias may be present at birth (congenital), but are not noticed until later in life. Some factors that contribute to the development of a hernia include: Chronic  constipation , Chronic  cough , Heavy lifting,  Obesity , Straining to urinate because of an  enlarged prostate ,  Femoral hernias tend to occur more often in women than in men.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001568-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Femoral hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>You may see a bulge in the upper thigh, just below the groin. Most femoral hernias cause no symptoms. You may have some groin discomfort. It may be worse when you stand, lift heavy objects, or strain. Sometimes, the first symptoms are: Sudden groin or thigh pain, Abdominal pain, Nausea, Vomiting,  This may mean that the intestine within the hernia is blocked. This is an emergency.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001568-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Femoral hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The best way to tell if there is a hernia is to have your health care provider perform a physical exam. If there is any doubt about the exam findings, an  ultrasound  or  CT scan  may be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001568-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Femoral hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the symptoms present with the hernia. If you feel sudden pain in your groin or thigh, a piece of intestine may be stuck in the hernia. This is called an incarcerated hernia. This problem needs treatment right away in an emergency room. You may need emergency surgery. When you have ongoing discomfort from a femoral hernia, talk to your provider about your treatment choices. Hernias often get larger as time passes. They do not go away on their own.  Compared to other types of hernias, femoral hernias more commonly have small intestine get stuck in the weak area.  Your surgeon may recommend  femoral hernia repair surgery . The surgery is done to avoid a possible medical emergency. If you do not have surgery right away: Increase your fiber intake and drink fluids to avoid constipation., Lose weight if you are overweight., See your provider if you have trouble urinating (men)., Use proper lifting techniques. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001568-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Femoral hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The chances of a femoral hernia coming back after surgery are low. If the intestine or other tissue becomes stuck, a portion of the intestine may need to be removed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001568-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Femoral hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider or go to the emergency room right away if: You suddenly develop pain in the hernia, and the hernia cannot be pushed back into the abdomen using gentle pressure., You develop nausea, vomiting, or abdominal pain., Your hernia becomes red, purple, dark, or discolored. ,  Contact your provider if you have a bulge in the upper thigh next to the groin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001568-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Femoral hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is difficult to prevent hernia. Making changes in your lifestyle can help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>