<Document id="0001211" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000691.htm">
 
<Focus>Diarrhea in infants</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011991</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Diarrhea - babies</Synonym>
		<Synonym>BRAT diet - infants</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001211-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Diarrhea in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>Causes of Diarrhea Diarrhea in babies usually does not last long. Most often, it is caused by a virus and goes away on its own. Your baby could also have diarrhea with: A change in your baby's diet or a change in the mother's diet if breastfeeding., Use of antibiotics by your baby, or use by the mother if breastfeeding., A bacterial infection. Your baby will need to take antibiotics to get better., A parasite infection. Your baby will need to take medicine to get better., Rare diseases such as cystic fibrosis.,  Diarrhea Causes Dehydration Infants and children under age 3 can become dehydrated quickly and get very sick. Dehydration means that your baby does not have enough water or liquids. Watch your baby closely for signs of dehydration, which include: Dry eyes and little to no tears when crying, Fewer wet diapers than usual, Less active than usual, lethargic, Irritable, Dry mouth, Dry skin that does not spring back to its usual shape after being pinched, Sunken eyes, Sunken fontanelle (the soft spot on top of the head),  Taking Care of Your Baby Make sure your baby gets plenty of liquids so your baby does not get dehydrated. Keep  breastfeeding  your baby if you are nursing. Breastfeeding helps prevent diarrhea, and your baby will recover quicker., If you are using formula, make it full strength unless your health care provider gives you different advice.,  If your baby still seems thirsty after or between feedings, talk to your provider about giving your baby Pedialyte or Infalyte. Your provider may recommend these extra liquids that contain electrolytes. Try giving your baby 1 ounce (2 tablespoons or 30 milliliters) of Pedialyte or Infalyte, every 30 to 60 minutes. Do not water down Pedialyte or Infalyte. Do not give sports drinks to young infants., Try giving your baby a Pedialyte popsicle.,  If your baby throws up, give them only a little bit of liquid at a time. Start with as little as 1 teaspoon (5 ml) of liquid every 10 to 15 minutes. Do not give solid foods when your baby is vomiting. Do not give your baby ant-diarrhea medicine unless your provider says it is OK. Feeding Your Baby If your baby was on solid foods before the diarrhea began, start with foods that are easy on the stomach, such as: Bananas, Crackers, Toast, Pasta, Cereal,  Do not give your baby food that may make diarrhea worse, such as: Apple juice, Milk, Fried foods, Full-strength fruit juice,  Preventing Diaper Rash Your baby might get  diaper rash  because of the diarrhea. To prevent diaper rash: Change your baby's diaper frequently., Clean your baby's bottom with water. Cut down on using baby wipes while your baby has diarrhea., Let your baby's bottom air dry., Use a diaper cream.,  Wash your hands well to keep you and other people in your household from getting sick. Diarrhea caused by germs can spread easily. When to Call the Doctor Call your provider if your baby is a newborn (under 3 months old) and has diarrhea. Also call if your child has signs of being dehydrated, including: Dry and sticky mouth, No tears when crying, No wet diaper for 6 hours, A sunken fontanelle (soft spot),  Know the signs that your baby is not getting better, including: Fever and diarrhea that last for more than 2 to 3 days, More than 8 stools in 8 hours, Vomiting continues for more than 24 hours, Diarrhea contains blood, mucus, or pus, Your baby is much less active than normal (is not sitting up at all or looking around), Your baby seems to have stomach pain, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001211-2" qtype="causes">What causes Diarrhea in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001211-3" qtype="causes">What causes Diarrhea in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001211-6" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Diarrhea in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001211-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Diarrhea in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>