<Document id="0001835" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007466.htm">
 
<Focus>Health screening - men age 65 and older</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Health maintenance visit - men - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Physical exam - men - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Yearly exam - men - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Checkup - men - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Men's health - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Preventive care exam - men - over age 65</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001835-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Health screening - men age 65 and older</Question>
			<Answer>Even if you feel fine, you should still see your provider for regular checkups. These visits can help you avoid problems in the future. For example, the only way to find out if you have  high blood pressure  is to have it checked regularly. High blood sugar and  high cholesterol  levels also may not have any symptoms in the early stages. A simple blood test can check for these conditions. There are specific times when you should see your provider or receive specific health screenings. The US Preventive Services Task Force publishes a list of recommended screenings. Below are screening guidelines for men age 65 and older. ABDOMINAL AORTIC ANEURYSM SCREENING If you are age 65 to 75 and have smoked, you should have an ultrasound to screen for  abdominal aortic aneurysms ., Other men should discuss this screening with their provider. ,  BLOOD PRESSURE SCREENING Have your  blood pressure  checked at least once every year. Watch for blood pressure screenings in your area. Ask your provider if you can stop in to have your blood pressure checked. You can also check your blood pressure using the automated machines at local grocery stores and pharmacies. Ask your provider if you need your blood pressure checked more often if You have diabetes,  heart disease ,  kidney problems , or are overweight or have certain other conditions, You have a first degree relative with high blood pressure, You are Black, Your blood pressure top number is from 120 to 129 mm Hg, or the bottom number is from 70 to 79 mm Hg,  CHOLESTEROL SCREENING If your cholesterol level is normal, your cholesterol should be checked every 5 years. You should have repeat testing sooner if: Changes occur in your lifestyle (including weight gain and diet), You have high cholesterol, diabetes, heart disease, kidney problems, or certain other health conditions,  COLORECTAL CANCER SCREENING Until age 75, you should have screening for  colorectal cancer  on a regular basis. If you are age 76 or older, you should ask your provider if you need to be screened. Several tests are available for  colorectal cancer screening : A stool-based fecal occult blood (gFOBT) or fecal immunochemical test ( FIT ) every year, A stool sDNA-FIT test every 1 to 3 years., Flexible  sigmoidoscopy  every 5 years or every 10 years with stool testing with FIT every year, CT colonography ( virtual colonoscopy ) every 5 years,  Colonoscopy  every 10 years ,  You may need a colonoscopy more often if you have risk factors for colorectal cancer, such as: Ulcerative colitis , A personal or family history of cancer of the colon or rectum, A history of growths in your colon called  adenomatous polyps ,  DENTAL EXAM Go to the dentist once or twice every year for an exam and cleaning. Your dentist will evaluate if you have a need for more frequent visits.,  DIABETES SCREENING You should be screened every 3 years. You may be tested more often if you have other risk factors for diabetes, such as: A first-degree relative with  diabetes , You are overweight or have obesity, high blood pressure, prediabetes, or a history of heart disease,  EYE EXAM  Have an eye exam every 1 to 2 years., Have an eye exam that includes an examination of your retina (back of your eye) at least every year if you have diabetes. ,  HEARING TEST  Have your hearing tested if you have symptoms of  hearing loss . ,  IMMUNIZATIONS Commonly needed vaccines include: Flu shot : get one every year,  COVID-19  vaccine: ask you provider what is best for you,  Pneumococcal vaccine : you should receive this vaccine,  Shingles  (herpes zoster) vaccine at or after age 50,  Tetanus-diphtheria and acellular pertussis (Tdap) vaccine : have as one of your tetanus-diphtheria vaccines if you did not receive it as an adolescent,  Tetanus-diphtheria : have a booster (or Tdap) every 10 years,  INFECTIOUS DISEASE SCREENING Screening for hepatitis C: All adults ages 18 to 79 should get a one-time test for  hepatitis C .,  Screening for human immunodeficiency virus ( HIV ): all people ages 15 to 65 should get a one-time test. Depending on your lifestyle and medical history, you may need to be screened for infections such as syphilis, chlamydia, and other infections. LUNG CANCER SCREENING You should have an annual screening for  lung cancer  with low-dose computed tomography (LDCT) if: You are age 50 to 80 years AND, You have a 20 pack-year smoking history AND, You currently smoke or have quit within the past 15 years,  OSTEOPOROSIS SCREENING If you have risk factors for  osteoporosis , you should discuss screening with your provider., Risk factors can include long-term steroid use, low body weight, smoking, heavy alcohol use, having a fracture after age 50, or a family history of hip fracture or osteoporosis.,  PHYSICAL EXAMS All adults should visit their provider from time to time, even if they are healthy. The purpose of these visits is to: Screen for diseases, Assess risk of future medical problems, Encourage a healthy lifestyle, Update vaccinations and other preventive care services, Maintain a relationship with a provider in case of an illness,  In addition: Your blood pressure should be checked at least every year., Your height, weight, and  body mass index (BMI)  should be checked at every exam.,  During your exam, your provider may ask you about: Depression and anxiety, Diet and exercise, including exercises to improve your balance and reduce your risk of falling, Alcohol and tobacco use, Safety, such as use of seat belts and smoke detectors, Whether you have had any falls or are afraid of falling, Your medicines and risk for interactions,  PROSTATE CANCER SCREENING If you're 55 through 69 years old, before having the test, talk to your provider about the pros and cons of having a  PSA test . Ask about: Whether screening decreases your chance of dying from  prostate cancer ., Whether there is any harm from prostate cancer screening, such as side effects from testing or overtreatment of cancer when discovered., Whether you have a higher risk of prostate cancer than others.,  For men 70 or older, most recommendations are against screening. If you choose to be tested, the PSA blood test is repeated over time (yearly or less often), though the best frequency is not known. Prostate examinations are no longer routinely done on men with no symptoms.,  SKIN EXAM Your provider may check your skin for signs of  skin cancer , especially if you're at high risk., People at high risk include those who have had skin cancer before, have close relatives with skin cancer, or have a weakened immune system. ,  TESTICULAR EXAM The US Preventive Services Task Force (USPSTF) now recommends against performing testicular self-exams. Doing testicular self-exams has been shown to have little to no benefit., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>