<Document id="0001604" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001329.htm">
 
<Focus>Fleas</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0277355</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Dog fleas</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Siphonaptera</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001604-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Fleas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fleas are small insects that feed on the blood of humans, dogs, cats, and other warm-blooded animals. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001604-2" qtype="causes">What causes Fleas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fleas prefer to live on dogs and cats. They may also be found on humans and other warm-blooded animals. Pet owners may not be affected by fleas until their pet has been gone for a period of time. Fleas look for other sources of food and begin to bite humans.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001604-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fleas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bites often occur on the legs and places where clothes fit close to the body, such as the waist, buttocks, thighs, and lower abdomen. Symptoms of flea bites include: Small red bumps, often three bumps together, that are very itchy, Blisters if the person has an allergy to flea bites, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001604-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Fleas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Usually, a diagnosis can be made when the health care provider examines the skin where the bites are. Questions may be asked about contact with animals such as cats and dogs. In rare cases, a skin biopsy is done to rule out other skin problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001604-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Fleas ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can use an over-the-counter 1% hydrocortisone cream to relieve itching. Antihistamines you take by mouth may also help with itching.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001604-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Fleas ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001604-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Fleas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Scratching can lead to a skin infection. Fleas can carry bacteria that cause diseases in humans, such as  typhus  and  plague . The bacteria can be transmitted to humans by flea bites.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001604-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Fleas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prevention may not always be possible. The goal is to get rid of the fleas. This can be done by treating your home, pets, and outside areas with chemicals (pesticides). Small children should not be in the home when pesticides are being used. Birds and fish must be protected when chemicals are sprayed. Home foggers and flea collars do not always work to get rid of fleas. Always consult your veterinarian for help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>