<Document id="0001644" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001588.htm">
 
<Focus>Fractured clavicle in the newborn</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0159658</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Fractured collar bone - newborn</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Broken collar bone - newborn</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001644-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Fractured clavicle in the newborn ?</Question>
			<Answer>A fractured clavicle in the newborn is a broken collar bone in a baby that was just delivered.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001644-2" qtype="causes">What causes Fractured clavicle in the newborn ?</Question>
			<Answer>A fracture of a newborn's collar bone (clavicle) can occur during a difficult vaginal delivery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001644-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fractured clavicle in the newborn ?</Question>
			<Answer>The baby will not move the painful, injured arm. Instead, the baby will hold it still against the side of the body. Lifting the baby under the arms causes the child pain. Sometimes, the fracture can be felt with the fingers, but the problem often can't be seen or felt. Within a few weeks, a hard lump may develop where the bone is healing. This lump may be the only sign that the newborn had a broken collar bone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001644-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Fractured clavicle in the newborn ?</Question>
			<Answer>A  chest x-ray  will show whether or not there is a broken bone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001644-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Fractured clavicle in the newborn ?</Question>
			<Answer>In general, there is no treatment other than lifting the child gently to prevent discomfort. If needed, the arm on the affected side may be kept still by simply pinning the sleeve to the clothes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001644-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Fractured clavicle in the newborn ?</Question>
			<Answer>Full recovery occurs without treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001644-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Fractured clavicle in the newborn ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most often, there are no complications. Because infants heal well, it may be impossible (even by x-ray) to tell that a fracture occurred.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001644-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Fractured clavicle in the newborn ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if your baby acts uncomfortable when you lift them.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>