<Document id="0001839" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000726.htm">
 
<Focus>Healthy food trends -- beans and legumes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001839-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Healthy food trends -- beans and legumes</Question>
			<Answer>TYPES OF LEGUMES Beans: Adzuki, Black beans, Black-eyed peas (actually a bean), Cannellini, Cranberry (not the same as cranberry fruit), Garbanzo (chickpeas), Great Northern, Kidney, Lima, Mung, Navy, Pinto,  Other legumes: Lentils, Peas, Soybeans (edamame),  WHY THEY ARE GOOD FOR YOU Beans and legumes are rich in plant protein, fiber, B-vitamins, iron, folate, calcium, potassium, phosphorus, and zinc. Most beans are also low in fat. Legumes are similar to meat in nutrients, but with lower iron levels and no saturated fats. The high protein in legumes makes them a great option in place of meat and dairy products.  Vegetarians often substitute legumes for meat . Legumes are a great source of  fiber  and may help you have regular bowel movements. Just 1 cup (240 mL) of cooked black beans will give you 15 grams (g) of fiber, which is over half the recommended daily amount for adults. Legumes are packed with nutrients. They are low in calories, but their fiber and protein make you feel full. The body uses the  carbohydrates  in legumes slowly, providing steady energy for the body, brain, and nervous system. Eating more legumes as part of a healthy diet can help lower blood sugar and blood pressure. Beans and legumes contain antioxidants that help prevent cell damage and fight disease and aging. The fiber and other nutrients benefit the digestive system and may even help prevent digestive cancers. HOW THEY ARE PREPARED Legumes can be added to any meal, for breakfast, lunch, or dinner. Once cooked, they can be eaten warm or cold. Most dry beans (except peas and lentils) need to be rinsed and soaked before cooking. Rinse beans in cold water and pick out any pebbles or stems., Cover the beans with 3 times their amount in water., Soak for 6 hours.,  You can also bring dried beans to a boil, take the pan off the burner, and let them soak for 2 hours. Soaking overnight or after boiling makes them less likely to give you gas. To cook your beans: Drain and add fresh water., Cook the beans according to the instructions on your package.,  To add cooked or canned beans to your diet: Add them to salsas, soups, salads, tacos, burritos, chili, or pasta dishes., Include them as a side dish at breakfast, lunch, or dinner., Mash them up for dips and spreads., Use bean flour for baking.,  To reduce the gas caused by eating beans: Always soak dried beans., Use canned beans. Drain and rinse them before consuming., If you do not eat a lot of beans, gradually add them to your diet. This helps your body get used to the extra fiber., Chew them well.,  WHERE TO FIND LEGUMES Legumes may be purchased at any grocery store or online. They don't cost a lot of money and can be stored for a long time. They come in bags (dried beans), cans (already cooked), or jars. RECIPE There are many delicious recipes using beans. Here is one you can try. Ingredients Two cans low-sodium black beans (15 oz.), or 425 g, Half medium onion, Two garlic cloves, Two tablespoons (30 mL) vegetable oil, Half teaspoon (2.5 mL) cumin (ground), Half teaspoon (2.5 mL) salt, One quarter teaspoon (1.2 mL) oregano (fresh or dried),  Instructions Carefully drain the liquid from one can of black beans. Pour the drained black beans into a bowl. Use a potato masher to mash the beans until they are no longer whole. Set the mashed beans aside. Chop the onion into one quarter inch pieces. Set the onions aside., Peel the garlic cloves and mince them finely. Set the garlic aside., In a medium saucepan, heat your cooking oil over medium high heat. Add the onions and saut&#233; for 1 to 2 minutes., Stir in the garlic and cumin and cook for 30 seconds more., Stir in the mashed black beans and the second can of black beans, including the juice., When the beans begin to boil, reduce the heat to low, stir in the salt and oregano and simmer for 10 minutes, uncovered.,  Source:  United States Department of Agriculture</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>