<Document id="0001833" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007464.htm">
 
<Focus>Health screening - men - ages 18 to 39</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Health maintenance visit - men - ages 18 to 39</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Physical exam - men - ages 18 to 39</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Yearly exam - men - ages 18 to 39</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Checkup - men - ages 18 to 39</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Men's health - ages 18 to 39</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Preventive care exam - men - ages 18 to 39</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001833-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Health screening - men - ages 18 to 39</Question>
			<Answer>Even if you feel fine, you should still see your provider for regular checkups. These visits can help you avoid problems in the future. For example, the only way to find out if you have  high blood pressure  is to have it checked regularly. High blood sugar and  high cholesterol  level also may not have any symptoms in the early stages. Simple blood tests can check for these conditions. There are specific times when you should see your provider or receive specific health screenings. The US Preventive Services Task Force publishes a list of recommended screenings. Below are screening guidelines for men ages 18 to 39. 
BLOOD PRESSURE SCREENING Your blood pressure should be checked at least once every 3 to 5 years if: Your  blood pressure  is in the normal range (top number less than 120 mm Hg and bottom number less than 80 mm Hg), You don't have risk factors for high blood pressure,  Ask your provider if you need your blood pressure checked more often if: The top number is from 120 to 129 mm Hg or the bottom number is from 70 to 79 mm Hg, You have  diabetes ,  heart disease ,  kidney problems , are overweight, or have certain other health conditions, You have a first-degree relative with high blood pressure, You are Black,  If the top number is 130 mm Hg or greater or the bottom number is 80 mm Hg or greater, this is considered stage 1 hypertension. Schedule an appointment with your provider to learn how you can reduce your blood pressure. Watch for blood pressure screenings in your neighborhood or workplace. Ask your provider if you can stop in to have your blood pressure checked. 
CHOLESTEROL SCREENING Cholesterol screening  should begin at: Age 35 for men with no known risk factors for coronary heart disease, Age 20 for men with known risk factors for coronary heart disease,  Repeat cholesterol screening should take place: Every 5 years for men with normal cholesterol levels, More often if changes occur in lifestyle (including weight gain and diet), More often if you have diabetes, heart disease, kidney problems, or certain other conditions,  DIABETES SCREENING You should be screened for  diabetes  starting at age 35 and then repeated every 3 years if you have no risk factors for diabetes. Screening may need to start earlier and be repeated more often if you have other risk factors for diabetes, such as: You have a first degree relative with diabetes., You are overweight or have obesity., You have high blood pressure, prediabetes, or a history of heart disease.,  
DENTAL EXAM
 Go to the dentist once or twice every year for an exam and cleaning. Your dentist will evaluate if you have a need for more frequent visits. ,  
EYE EXAM
 Have an eye exam every 5 to 10 years before age 40., If you have vision problems, have an eye exam every 2 years, or more often if recommended by your provider., Have an eye exam that includes an examination of your retina (back of your eye) at least every year if you have diabetes.,  
IMMUNIZATIONS Commonly needed vaccines include: Flu  shot : get one every year.,  COVID-19 vaccine:  ask your provider what is best for you.,  Tetanus-diphtheria and acellular pertussis (Tdap)  vaccine : have one at or after age 19 as one of your tetanus-diphtheria vaccines if you did not receive it as an adolescent.,  Tetanus-diphtheria : have a booster (or Tdap) every 10 years.,  Varicella vaccine : receive two doses if you never had  chickenpox  or the varicella vaccine.,  Hepatitis B vaccine : receive 2, 3, or 4 doses, depending on your exact circumstances.,  Measles, mumps, and rubella (MMR)  vaccine : receive one to two doses if you are not already immune to MMR. Your doctor can tell you if you are immune,  Ask your provider about the  human papillomavirus (HPV) &#160;vaccine if you have: Not received the HPV vaccine in the past, Not completed the full vaccine series (you should catch up on this shot),  Ask your provider if you should receive other immunizations if you have certain medical conditions, such as diabetes or are at increased risk for some diseases such as pneumonia. INFECTIOUS DISEASE SCREENING All adults ages 18 to 79 should get a one-time test for  hepatitis C ., All people ages 15 to 65 should get a one-time test for human immunodeficiency virus ( HIV ), Depending on your lifestyle and medical history, you may need to be screened for infections such as syphilis, chlamydia, and other infections.,  PHYSICAL EXAM All adults should visit their provider from time to time, even if they are healthy. The purpose of these visits is to: Screen for diseases, Assess risk of future medical problems, Encourage a healthy lifestyle, Update vaccinations and other preventive care services, Maintain a relationship with a provider in case of an illness,  Your height, weight, and  BMI  should be checked at every exam. During your exam, your provider may ask you about: Depression  and anxiety
   , Diet and exercise, Alcohol and tobacco use, Safety, such as use of seat belts and smoke detectors, Your medicines and risk for interactions,  TESTICULAR EXAM The US Preventive Services Task Force recommends against performing testicular self-exam. Doing testicular exams has been shown to have little to no benefit.,  SKIN SELF-EXAM Your provider may check your skin for signs of  skin cancer , especially if you're at high risk, such as if you have had skin cancer before., Have close relatives with skin cancer., Have a weakened immune system.,  OTHER SCREENING Talk with your provider about colon cancer screening if you have a strong family history of colon cancer or polyps, or if you have had inflammatory bowel disease or polyps yourself., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>