<Document id="0001952" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000566.htm">
 
<Focus>Hereditary ovalocytosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0427480</CUI>
			<CUI>C0013902</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ovalocytosis - hereditary</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001952-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hereditary ovalocytosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hereditary ovalocytosis is a rare condition passed down through families (inherited). The blood cells are oval-shaped instead of round. It is a form of  hereditary elliptocytosis .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001952-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hereditary ovalocytosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ovalocytosis is mainly found in Southeast Asian populations.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001952-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hereditary ovalocytosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Newborn infants with ovalocytosis may have  anemia  and  jaundice . Adults most often do not show symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001952-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hereditary ovalocytosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>An exam by your health care provider may show an enlarged spleen. This condition is diagnosed by looking at the shape of blood cells under a microscope. The following tests may also be done: Complete blood count  (CBC) to check for anemia or red blood cell destruction, Blood smear to determine cell shape,  Bilirubin level  (may be high), Lactate dehydrogenase level (may be high), Ultrasound of the abdomen (may show gallstones) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001952-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hereditary ovalocytosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>In severe cases, the disease may be treated by removal of the spleen ( splenectomy ).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001952-6" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hereditary ovalocytosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The condition may be associated with  gallstones  or kidney problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>