<Document id="0001956" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002861.htm">
 
<Focus>Heroin overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0572070</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Acetomorphine overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Diacetylmorphine overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Opiate overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Opioid overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001956-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Heroin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Heroin is a pain-killer derived from morphine. It is very addictive and known for causing significant withdrawal symptoms. It has been illegal in the United States since 1924. It is in the class of drugs known as  opioids . This article discusses heroin overdose. An overdose occurs when someone takes too much of a substance, usually a drug. This can happen by accident or on purpose. A heroin  overdose  may cause serious, harmful symptoms, or even death. About heroin overdose: Heroin overdoses in the United States rose sharply from 2006 to 2015, but since 2016 the number of deaths has trended down. There were 9,173 heroin-related deaths reported in 2021. In the United States, heroin is sold illegally, so there is no control over the quality or strength of the drug. Also, it is sometimes mixed with other poisonous or dangerous substances, such as fentanyl.  Most people who died from an overdose in the United States from 1999 to 2019 were aged 35 to 54. Many people who use heroin also abuse prescription pain medicines and other drugs. They may also abuse alcohol. These combinations of substances can be very dangerous. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with has overdosed, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001956-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Heroin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>People use heroin to get high because of its effects of short-lived euphoria and blissful apathy. But if they overdose on it, they get extremely sleepy and may become unconsciousness and stop breathing. Most deaths from heroin are due to not breathing. Below are symptoms of a heroin overdose in different parts of the body. AIRWAYS AND LUNGS No breathing, Shallow breathing,  Slow and difficult breathing ,  EYES, EARS, NOSE AND THROAT Dry mouth, Extremely small pupils, sometimes as small as the head of a pin (pinpoint pupils), Discolored tongue ,  HEART AND BLOOD Low blood pressure, Weak pulse ,  SKIN Bluish-colored nails and lips &#160;(cyanosis),  STOMACH AND INTESTINES Constipation ,  Spasms  of the stomach and intestines ,  NERVOUS SYSTEM Coma  (lack of responsiveness), Delirium (confusion), Disorientation,  Drowsiness ,  Uncontrolled muscle movements , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001956-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Heroin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001956-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Heroin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>If an antidote can be given, recovery from an  acute  overdose occurs within 24 to 48 hours. Heroin is often mixed with substances called adulterants. These can cause other symptoms and organ damage. A hospital stay may be necessary. If the person's breathing has been affected for a long time, they may breathe fluids into their lungs. This can lead to pneumonia and other lung complications. Individuals who become unconscious for longer periods of time and lie on hard surfaces may develop crush injuries to the skin and underlying tissue. This may lead to skin ulcers, infection, and deep scarring. Injecting any drug through a needle can cause serious infections. These include abscesses of the brain, lungs, and kidneys, and heart valve infection. Because heroin is commonly injected into a vein, a heroin user may develop problems related to sharing needles with other users. Sharing needles can lead to hepatitis, HIV infection, and AIDS.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001956-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Heroin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>If an antidote can be given, recovery from an  acute  overdose occurs within 24 to 48 hours. Heroin is often mixed with substances called adulterants. These can cause other symptoms and organ damage. A hospital stay may be necessary. If the person's breathing has been affected for a long time, they may breathe fluids into their lungs. This can lead to pneumonia and other lung complications. Individuals who become unconscious for longer periods of time and lie on hard surfaces may develop crush injuries to the skin and underlying tissue. This may lead to skin ulcers, infection, and deep scarring. Injecting any drug through a needle can cause serious infections. These include abscesses of the brain, lungs, and kidneys, and heart valve infection. Because heroin is commonly injected into a vein, a heroin user may develop problems related to sharing needles with other users. Sharing needles can lead to hepatitis, HIV infection, and AIDS.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>