<Document id="0001239" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001608.htm">
 
<Focus>Diphtheria</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0012546</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Respiratory diphtheria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pharyngeal diphtheria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Diphtheric cardiomyopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Diphtheric polyneuropathy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001239-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diphtheria is an  acute  infection caused by the bacterium  Corynebacterium diphtheriae .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001239-2" qtype="causes">What causes Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>The bacteria that cause diphtheria spread through respiratory droplets (such as from a cough or sneeze) of an infected person or someone who carries the bacteria but has no symptoms. The bacteria most commonly infect your nose and throat. The throat infection causes a gray to black, tough, fiber-like covering, which can block your airways. In some cases, diphtheria infects your skin first and causes  skin lesions . Once you are infected, the bacteria make dangerous substances called toxins. The toxins spread through your bloodstream to other organs, such as the heart and brain, and cause damage. Because of widespread vaccination (immunization) of children, diphtheria is now rare in many parts of the world.  Risk factors for diphtheria include crowded environments, poor hygiene, and lack of immunization.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001239-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms usually occur 1 to 7 days after the bacteria enter your body: 
   Fever and chills, Sore throat,  hoarseness , Painful swallowing, Croup-like (barking) cough, 
   Drooling (suggests airway blockage is about to occur),  Bluish coloration of the skin , Bloody, watery drainage from nose, Breathing problems, including difficulty breathing, fast breathing, high-pitched breathing sound (stridor), Skin sores (usually seen in tropical areas) ,  Sometimes there are no symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001239-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam and look inside your mouth. This may reveal a gray to black covering (pseudomembrane) in the throat,  enlarged lymph glands , and swelling of the neck or vocal cords. Tests used may include: Gram stain or  throat culture  to identify the diphtheria bacteria, Toxin assay (to detect the presence of the toxin made by the bacteria), Electrocardiogram ( ECG ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001239-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>If the provider thinks you have diphtheria, treatment will likely be started right away, even before test results come back. Diphtheria antitoxin is given as a shot into a muscle or through an IV (intravenous line). The infection is then treated with antibiotics, such as penicillin and erythromycin. You may need to stay in the hospital while getting the antitoxin. Other treatments may include: Fluids by IV, Oxygen, Bed rest, Heart monitoring, Insertion of a breathing tube, Correction of airway blockages,  People without symptoms who carry diphtheria should be treated with antibiotics.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001239-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diphtheria may be mild or severe. Some people do not have symptoms. In others, the disease can slowly get worse. Recovery from the illness is slow. People may die, especially when the disease affects the heart. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001239-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>The most common complication is inflammation of the heart muscle ( myocarditis ). The nervous system is also frequently and severely affected, which may result in temporary  paralysis . The diphtheria toxin can also damage the kidneys. There can also be an allergic response to the antitoxin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001239-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider right away if you have come in contact with a person who has diphtheria. Diphtheria is a rare disease. It is also a  reportable disease , and any cases are often publicized in the media. This helps you to know if diphtheria is present in your area.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001239-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Diphtheria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Routine childhood immunizations and adult boosters prevent the disease. Anyone who has come into contact with an infected person should get an  immunization  or booster shot against diphtheria, if they have not already received it. Protection from the vaccine lasts only 10 years. So it is important for adults to get a booster vaccine every 10 years. The booster is called tetanus-diphtheria ( Td ). (The shot also has vaccine medicine for an infection called  tetanus .) If you have been in close contact with a person who has diphtheria, contact your provider right away. Ask whether you need antibiotics to prevent getting diphtheria.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>