<Document id="0001512" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003027.htm">
 
<Focus>Face pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0015468</CUI>
			<CUI>C1962975</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001512-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Face pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Face pain may be dull and throbbing or an intense, stabbing discomfort in the face or forehead. It can occur in one or both sides. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001512-2" qtype="causes">What causes Face pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pain that starts in the face may be caused by a nerve problem, injury, or infection. Face pain may also begin in other places in the body.  Abscessed tooth  (ongoing throbbing pain on one side of the lower face that gets worse with eating or touching),  Cluster headache ,  Herpes zoster  (shingles) or herpes simplex (cold sores) infection, Injury to the face,  Migraine , Myofascial pain syndrome,  Sinusitis  or sinus infection (dull pain and tenderness around the eyes and cheekbones that gets worse when you bend forward),  Tic douloureux  (trigeminal neuralgia), Temporomandibular joint dysfunction syndrome ,  Sometimes the reason for the face pain is unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001512-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Face pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001512-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Face pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: Face pain is accompanied by chest, shoulder, neck, or arm pain. This could mean a  heart attack . Call 911 or your local emergency number.
   , Pain is throbbing, worse on one side of the face, and aggravated by eating. Contact a dentist.
   , Pain is persistent, unexplained, or accompanied by other unexplained symptoms. Contact your primary provider., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001512-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Face pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>