<Document id="0001005" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000722.htm">
 
<Focus>Could you have low testosterone?</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0241357</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Male menopause</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Andropause</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Testosterone deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Androgen deficiency of the aging male</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Late-onset hypogonadism</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001005-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Could you have low testosterone? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Testosterone  is a hormone made by the testicles. It is important for a man's sex drive and physical appearance.  Certain health conditions, medicines, or injury can lead to low testosterone (low-T). Testosterone levels also naturally drop with age. Low testosterone can affect sex drive, mood, and changes in muscle and fat. Treatment with testosterone therapy may help reduce symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001005-3" qtype="causes">What causes Could you have low testosterone? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Beginning around age 30 to 40, testosterone levels may start to slowly decrease. This occurs naturally.  Other causes of low testosterone include: Medicine side effects, such as from chemotherapy., Testicle injury or  cancer ., Problems with glands in the brain ( hypothalamus  and pituitary) that control hormone production.,  Low thyroid function ., Too much body fat ( obesity ). Ask your health care provider whether you need a test called free testosterone., Other disorders, chronic diseases, treatments, or infection., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001005-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Could you have low testosterone? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some men with low testosterone do not have any symptoms. Others may have: Low sex drive,  Problems having an erection , Low sperm count, Sleep problems such as  insomnia , Decrease in muscle size and strength,  Bone loss , Increase in body fat,  Depression , Trouble concentrating ,  Some symptoms may be a normal part of aging. For example, it is normal to feel less interested in sex as you get older. But, it is not usually normal to have no interest in sex. Symptoms may also be caused by other conditions, such as high blood pressure or  diabetes . If any of these symptoms are bothering you, talk with your provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001005-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Could you have low testosterone? ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider will likely have you get a  blood test  to check your testosterone level. You will also be checked for other causes of your symptoms. These include medicine side effects, thyroid problems, or depression.  If you have low testosterone, hormone therapy may help. The medicine used is man-made testosterone. This treatment is called testosterone replacement therapy, or TRT. TRT can be given as a pill, gel, patch, injection, or implant.  TRT may relieve or improve symptoms in some men. It may help keep bones and muscles strong. TRT seems to be more effective in young men with very low testosterone levels. TRT can also be helpful for older men.  TRT has risks. These may include: Infertility ,  Enlarged prostate  leading to difficulty urinating, Blood clots, Worsening cardiovascular disease, Sleep problems, Cholesterol problems,  At this time, it is unclear whether TRT increases the risk of prostate cancer or symptoms of benign prostatic hyperplasia. Cardiovascular risks are also unclear. However, based on inconclusive data, the FDA does warn of a possible increased risk of cardiovascular disease. Talk with your provider about whether TRT is right for you. If you do not notice any change in symptoms after treatment for 3 months, it is less likely that TRT treatment will benefit you. If you decide to start TRT, be sure to see your provider for regular checkups.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001005-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Could you have low testosterone? ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>