<Document id="0001539" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003092.htm">
 
<Focus>Fainting</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039070</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Passed out</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lightheadedness - fainting</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Syncope</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Vasovagal episode</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001539-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Fainting ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fainting is a brief loss of consciousness due to a drop in blood flow to the brain. The episode most often lasts less than a couple of minutes and you usually recover from it quickly. The medical name for fainting is syncope.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001539-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Fainting ?</Question>
			<Answer>When you faint, you not only  lose consciousness , you also lose muscle tone and the color in your face. Before fainting, you may feel weak, sweaty, or nauseated. You may have the sense that your vision is constricting (tunnel vision) or noises are fading into the background.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001539-3" qtype="causes">What causes Fainting ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fainting may occur while or after you: Cough very hard, Have a bowel movement, especially if you are straining, Have been standing in one place for too long, Urinate, especially at night or after lying down for a prolonged period,  Fainting can also be related to: Emotional distress, Fear, Severe pain ,  Other causes of fainting, some of which may be more serious, include: Certain medicines, including those used for anxiety, depression, and high blood pressure. These medicines may cause a drop in blood pressure., Drug or alcohol use., Heart disease, such as abnormal heart rhythm or heart attack and stroke., Rapid and deep breathing ( hyperventilation )., Low blood sugar (hypoglycemia)., Seizures., Sudden drop in blood pressure, such as from bleeding or being severely  dehydrated ., Standing up suddenly from a lying position.&#160;, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001539-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Fainting ?</Question>
			<Answer>When you faint, you not only  lose consciousness , you also lose muscle tone and the color in your face. Before fainting, you may feel weak, sweaty, or nauseated. You may have the sense that your vision is constricting (tunnel vision) or noises are fading into the background.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001539-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Fainting ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911 or the local emergency number if the person who fainted: Fell from a height, especially if injured or bleeding, Does not become alert quickly (within a couple of minutes), Is pregnant, Is over age 50, Has diabetes (check for medical identification bracelets), Feels chest pain, pressure, or discomfort, Has a pounding or irregular heartbeat, Has a loss of speech, vision problems, or is unable to move one or more limbs, Has convulsions, a tongue injury, or a loss of bladder or bowel control ,  Even if it is not an emergency situation, you should be seen by your provider if you have never fainted before, if you faint often, or if you have new symptoms with fainting. Call for an appointment to be seen as soon as possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001539-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Fainting ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>