<Document id="0001519" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001062.htm">
 
<Focus>Facial trauma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2228400</CUI>
			<CUI>C0015459</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Maxillofacial injury</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Midface trauma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Facial injury</Synonym>
		<Synonym>LeFort injuries</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001519-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Facial trauma is an injury of the face.&#160;It may include the facial bones such as the upper jaw bone (maxilla).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001519-2" qtype="causes">What causes Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Facial injuries can affect the upper jaw, lower jaw, cheek, nose, eye socket, or forehead. They may be caused by blunt force or be the result of a wound.  Common causes of injury to the face include: Car and motorcycle crashes, Wounds , Sports injuries, Violence , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001519-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Changes in feeling over the face, Deformed or uneven face or facial bones, Difficulty breathing through the nose due to swelling and bleeding, Double vision, Missing teeth, Swelling or bruising around the eyes that may cause vision problems , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001519-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam, which may show: Bleeding from the nose, eyes, or mouth, Nasal blockage, Breaks in the skin (lacerations), Bruising around the eyes or widening of the distance between the eyes, which may mean injury to the bones between the eye sockets, Changes in vision or the movement of the eyes, Improperly aligned upper and lower teeth,  The following may suggest bone fractures: Abnormal feelings on the cheek, Irregularities of the face that can be felt by touching, Movement of the upper jaw when the head is still,  A  CT scan of the head  and bones of the face may be done.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001519-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Surgery is done if the injury prevents normal functioning or causes a major deformity. The goal of treatment is to: Control bleeding, Create a clear airway, Treat the fracture and fix broken bone segments , Prevent scars, if possible, Prevent long-term double vision or sunken eyes or cheek bones, Rule out other injuries,  Treatment should be done as soon as possible if the person is stable and does not have a neck fracture.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001519-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people do very well with proper treatment. More surgery may be needed in 6 to 12 months to correct changes in appearance. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001519-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Bleeding, Uneven face, Infection, Brain and nervous system problems, Numbness or weakness, Loss of vision or double vision , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001519-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Go to the emergency room or call the local emergency number (such as 911) if you have a severe injury to your face.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001519-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Facial trauma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wear seat belts while driving. Use protective head gear when doing work or activities that could injure the face.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>