<Document id="0001824" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000028.htm">
 
<Focus>Head injury - first aid</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0018674</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Brain injury</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Head trauma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001824-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Head injury - first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>A head injury is any trauma to the scalp, skull, or brain. Head injury can be either closed or open (penetrating). A closed head injury means you received a hard blow to the head from striking an object, but the object did not penetrate the skull., An open, or penetrating, head injury means you were hit with an object that broke the skull and entered the brain. This is more likely to happen when you move at a high speed, such as going through the windshield during a car accident. It can also happen from a gunshot to the head. ,  Head injuries include: Concussion , most often in which the brain has been shaken, is the most common type of traumatic brain injury., Scalp wounds., Skull fractures. ,  Head injuries may cause bleeding: In the brain tissue, In the layers that surround the brain ( subarachnoid hemorrhage ,  subdural hematoma ,  epidural hematoma ) ,  Head injury is a common reason for an emergency room visit. A large number of people who suffer head injuries are children. Each year an estimated 1.5 million Americans sustain a traumatic brain injury (TBI). As a consequence of these injuries, 230,000 people are hospitalized and survive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001824-2" qtype="causes">What causes Head injury - first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Common causes of head injury include:  Accidents at home, work, outdoors, or while playing sports, Falls, Physical assault, Traffic accidents,  Most of these injuries are minor because the skull protects the brain. Some injuries are severe enough to require a stay in the hospital.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001824-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Head injury - first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Head injuries may cause bleeding in the brain tissue and the layers that surround the brain (subarachnoid hemorrhage, subdural hematoma, epidural hematoma). Symptoms of a head injury can occur right away or may develop slowly over several hours or days. Even if the skull is not fractured, the brain can hit the inside of the skull and be bruised. The head may look fine, but problems could result from bleeding or swelling inside the skull. The spinal cord is also likely to be injured from falls from a significant height or ejection from a vehicle. Some head injuries cause changes in brain function. This is called a traumatic brain injury. A concussion is a type of traumatic brain injury.  Symptoms of a concussion  can range from mild to severe.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001824-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Head injury - first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001824-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Head injury - first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001824-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Head injury - first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911 or the local emergency number right away if: There is severe head or face bleeding., The person is confused, tired, or unconscious., The person stops breathing., You suspect a serious head or  neck injury , or the person develops any signs or symptoms of a serious head injury. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001824-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Head injury - first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Not all head injuries can be prevented. The following  simple steps  can help keep you and your child safe: Always use safety equipment during activities that could cause a head injury. These include seat belts, bicycle or motorcycle helmets, and hard hats., Learn and follow  bicycle safety recommendations ., Do not drink and drive, and do not allow yourself to be driven by someone who you know or suspect has been drinking alcohol or is impaired in another way. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>