<Document id="0001857" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000063.htm">
 
<Focus>Heart attack first aid</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1304680</CUI>
			<CUI>C1273976</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>First aid - heart attack</Synonym>
		<Synonym>First aid - cardiopulmonary arrest</Synonym>
		<Synonym>First aid - cardiac arrest</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001857-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Heart attack first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>A  heart attack  is a medical emergency. Call 911 or the local emergency number if you think you or someone else is having a heart attack. The average person waits 3 hours before seeking help for symptoms of a heart attack. Many heart attack patients die before they reach a hospital. The sooner the person gets to the emergency room, the better the chance of survival. Prompt medical treatment reduces the amount of heart damage. This article discusses what to do if you think someone may be having a heart attack.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001857-2" qtype="causes">What causes Heart attack first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>A heart attack occurs when the blood flow that carries oxygen to the heart is blocked. The heart muscle becomes starved for oxygen and begins to die. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001857-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Heart attack first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of a heart attack can vary from person to person. They may be mild or severe. Women, older adults, and people with diabetes are more likely to have subtle or unusual symptoms. Symptoms in adults may include: Changes in mental status, especially in older adults.,  Chest pain  that feels like pressure, squeezing, or fullness. The pain is most often in the center of the chest. It may also be felt in the jaw, shoulder, arms, back, and stomach. It can last for more than a few minutes, or come and go., Cold sweat., Lightheadedness., Nausea (more common in women)., Indigestion., Vomiting., Numbness, aching, or tingling in the arm (usually the left arm, but the right arm may be affected alone, or along with the left).,  Shortness of breath ., Weakness or fatigue, especially in older adults and in women., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001857-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Heart attack first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001857-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Heart attack first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001857-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Heart attack first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911 or the local emergency number immediately if the person: Does not respond to you, Is not breathing, Has sudden chest pain or other symptoms of a heart attack, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001857-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Heart attack first aid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adults should take steps to control heart disease risk factors whenever possible. If you smoke, quit. Smoking more than doubles the chance of developing  heart disease ., Keep blood pressure, cholesterol, and  diabetes  in good control and follow your health care provider's orders., Lose weight if  obese  or overweight., Get regular exercise to improve heart health. (Talk to your provider before starting any new fitness program.), Eat a heart-healthy diet. Limit saturated fats, red meat, and sugars. Increase your intake of chicken, fish, fresh fruits and vegetables, and whole grains. Your provider can help you tailor a diet specific to your needs., Limit the amount of alcohol you drink. One drink a day is associated with reducing the rate of heart attacks, but two or more drinks a day can damage the heart and cause other medical problems., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>