<Document id="0001345" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001100.htm">
 
<Focus>Ectopic heartbeat</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0340464</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>PVB (premature ventricular beat)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Premature beats</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PVC (premature ventricular complex/contraction)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Extrasystole</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001345-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ectopic heartbeat ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ectopic heartbeats are changes in a heartbeat that is otherwise normal. These changes lead to extra or skipped heartbeats. There is often not a clear cause for these changes. They are common.  The two most common types of ectopic heartbeats are: Premature ventricular contractions (PVC), Premature atrial contractions (PAC) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001345-2" qtype="causes">What causes Ectopic heartbeat ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ectopic heartbeats are sometimes seen with: Changes in the blood, such as a low potassium level ( hypokalemia ), Decrease in blood supply to the heart,  When the heart is enlarged  or structurally abnormal,  Ectopic beats may be caused or made worse by smoking,  alcohol use ,  caffeine , stimulant medicines, and some street drugs. Ectopic heartbeats are rare in children without heart disease that was present at birth (congenital). Most extra heartbeats in children are PACs. These are often benign. In adults, ectopic heartbeats are common. They are most often due to PACs or PVCs. Your health care provider should look into the cause when they are frequent. Treatment is directed at symptoms and the underlying cause.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001345-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ectopic heartbeat ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Feeling your heartbeat ( palpitations ), Feeling like your heart stopped or skipped a beat, Feeling of occasional, forceful beats,  Note: There may be no symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001345-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Ectopic heartbeat ?</Question>
			<Answer>A  physical exam  may show an occasional uneven pulse. If the ectopic heartbeats do not occur very often, your provider may not find them during a physical exam. Blood pressure is most often normal. An  ECG  will be done. Often, no further testing is needed when your ECG is normal and the symptoms are not severe or worrisome. If your doctor wants to know more about your heart rhythm, they may order: A monitor that you wear that records and stores your heart rhythm for 24 to 48 hours ( Holter monitor ), A recording device that you wear, and records your heart rhythm whenever you feel a skipped beat ,  An  echocardiogram  may be ordered if your doctor suspects problems with the size or structure of your heart are the cause.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001345-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ectopic heartbeat ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following may help reduce ectopic heartbeats for some people: Limiting caffeine, alcohol, and tobacco , Regular exercise for people who are inactive,  For the most part, ectopic heartbeats do not need to be treated. The condition is only treated if your symptoms are severe or if the extra beats occur very often. The cause of the heartbeats, if it can be found, may also need to be treated.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001345-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Ectopic heartbeat ?</Question>
			<Answer>In some cases, ectopic heartbeats may mean you are at greater risk for serious abnormal heart rhythms, such as  ventricular tachycardia .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001345-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Ectopic heartbeat ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if:  You keep feeling the sensation of your heart pounding or racing ( palpitations )., You have palpitations with  chest pain  or other symptoms., You have this condition and your symptoms get worse or do not improve with treatment., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>