<Document id="0001755" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000453.htm">
 
<Focus>Gonococcal arthritis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2062407</CUI>
			<CUI>C0153216</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Disseminated gonococcal infection (DGI)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Disseminated gonococcemia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001755-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gonococcal arthritis is inflammation of a joint due to a gonorrhea infection. Gonococcal arthritis is a type of  septic arthritis . This is inflammation of a joint due to a bacterial infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001755-2" qtype="causes">What causes Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gonococcal arthritis is an infection of a joint. It occurs in people who have  gonorrhea , which is caused by the bacteria  Neisseria gonorrhoeae . Gonococcal arthritis is a complication of gonorrhea. Gonococcal arthritis affects women more often than men. It is most common among sexually active young adults. Gonococcal arthritis occurs when the bacteria spread through the blood to a joint. Sometimes, more than one joint is infected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001755-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of joint infection may include: Fever ,  Joint pain  for 1 to 4 days, Pain in the hands or wrists due to tendon inflammation,  Pain or burning during urination , Single joint pain, Skin rash (sores are slightly raised, pink to red, and may later contain pus or appear purple) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001755-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical examination and ask about the symptoms. Tests will be done to check for a gonorrhea infection. This may involve taking samples of tissue, joint fluids, or other body material and sending them to a lab for examination under a microscope. Examples of such tests include: Cervical Gram stain ,  Culture of joint aspirate ,  Joint fluid Gram stain ,  Throat culture , Urine test for gonorrhea , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001755-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The gonorrhea infection must be treated. There are two aspects of treating a sexually transmitted disease, especially one as easily spread as gonorrhea. The first is to cure the infected person. The second is to locate, test, and treat all sexual contacts of the infected person. This is done to prevent further spread of the disease. Some locations allow you to take counseling information and treatment to your partner(s) yourself. In other locations, the health department will contact your partner(s). A treatment routine is recommended by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC). Your provider will determine the best and most up-to-date treatment. A follow-up visit 7 days after treatment is important if the infection was complicated, to recheck blood tests and confirm that the infection was cured.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001755-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms usually improve within 1 to 2 days of starting treatment. Full recovery can be expected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001755-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Untreated, this condition may lead to persistent joint pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001755-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have symptoms of gonorrhea or gonococcal arthritis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001755-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Gonococcal arthritis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Not having sexual intercourse (abstinence) is the only sure method to prevent gonorrhea. A monogamous sexual relationship with a person who you know does not have any sexually transmitted disease (STD) can reduce your risk. Monogamous means you and your partner do not have sex with any other people. You can greatly lower your risk for infection with an STD by  practicing safer sex . This means using a condom every time you have sex. Condoms are available for both  men  and  women , but they are most commonly worn by the man. A condom must be used properly every time. Treating all sexual partners is essential to prevent re-infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>