<Document id="0001963" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001137.htm">
 
<Focus>Hiatal hernia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3489393</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T190</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hernia - hiatal</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001963-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hiatal hernia is a condition in which part of the stomach extends through an opening of the diaphragm into the chest. The diaphragm is the sheet of muscle that divides the chest from the abdomen.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001963-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of hiatal hernia is not known. The condition may be due to weakness of the supporting tissue. Your risk for the problem goes up with age,  obesity , and smoking. Hiatal hernias are very common. The problem occurs often in people over 50 years of age. This condition may be linked to  reflux  (backflow) of gastric acid from the stomach into the esophagus. Children with this condition are most often born with it (congenital). In infants, it often occurs with  gastroesophageal reflux .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001963-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Chest pain ,  Heartburn , worse when bending over or lying down, Swallowing difficulty ,  A hiatal hernia by itself rarely causes symptoms. Pain and discomfort are due to the upward flow of stomach acid, air, or bile. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001963-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests that may be used include: Barium swallow x-ray , Esophagogastroduodenoscopy ( EGD ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001963-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goals of treatment are to relieve symptoms and prevent complications. Treatments may include: Medicines to control stomach acid,  Surgery to repair the hiatal hernia  and prevent reflux ,  Other measures to reduce symptoms include: Avoiding large or heavy meals, Not lying down or bending over right after a meal, Reducing weight and not smoking, Raising the head of the bed 4 to 6 inches (10 to 15 centimeters) ,  If medicines and lifestyle measures do not help control symptoms, you may need surgery. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001963-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment can relieve most symptoms of hiatal hernia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001963-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Pulmonary (lung)  aspiration , Slow bleeding and  iron deficiency anemia  (due to a large hernia), Strangulation (closing off) of the hernia (very uncommon), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001963-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if: You have symptoms of a hiatal hernia., You have a hiatal hernia and your symptoms get worse or do not improve with treatment., You develop new symptoms. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001963-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Hiatal hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Controlling risk factors such as obesity may help prevent hiatal hernia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>