<Document id="0001505" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003032.htm">
 
<Focus>Eye pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0151827</CUI>
			<CUI>C1959630</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ophthalmalgia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pain - eye</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001505-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Eye pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pain in the eye may be described as a burning, throbbing, aching, or stabbing sensation in or around the eye. It may also feel like you have a foreign object in your eye. This article discusses eye pain that is not caused by injury or surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001505-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Eye pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pain in the eye can be an important symptom of a health problem. Make sure you tell your health care provider if you have eye pain that does not go away.  Tired eyes or some eye discomfort (eyestrain) is most often a minor problem and it will often go away with rest. These problems may be caused by the wrong eyeglass or contact lens prescription. Sometimes they are due to a problem with the eye muscles.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001505-3" qtype="causes">What causes Eye pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many things can cause pain in or around the eye. If the pain is severe, does not go away, or causes vision loss, seek medical attention immediately. Some things that can cause eye pain are: Infections, Inflammation, Contact lens problems, Dry eye, Acute glaucoma, Sinus problems, Neuropathy, Eyestrain, Headache, Flu, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001505-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Eye pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pain in the eye can be an important symptom of a health problem. Make sure you tell your health care provider if you have eye pain that does not go away.  Tired eyes or some eye discomfort (eyestrain) is most often a minor problem and it will often go away with rest. These problems may be caused by the wrong eyeglass or contact lens prescription. Sometimes they are due to a problem with the eye muscles.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001505-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Eye pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: The pain is severe (call immediately), or it continues for more than 2 days, You have decreased vision along with the eye pain, You have chronic diseases like arthritis or autoimmune problems, You have pain along with redness, swelling, discharge, or pressure in the eyes, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001505-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Eye pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>