<Document id="0001354" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003172.htm">
 
<Focus>Elbow pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0239266</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pain - elbow</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001354-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Elbow pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>



This article describes pain or other discomfort in the elbow that is not related to direct injury.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001354-2" qtype="causes">What causes Elbow pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Elbow pain can be caused by many problems. A common cause in adults is  tendinitis . This is inflammation and injury to the tendons, which are soft tissues that attach muscle to bone. People who play racquet sports are most likely to injure the tendons on the outside of the elbow. This condition is commonly called  tennis elbow . Golfers are more likely to injure the  tendons on the inside of the elbow . Other common causes of elbow tendinitis are gardening, playing baseball, using a screwdriver, or overusing your wrist and arm. Young children commonly develop "nursemaid elbow," which often occurs when someone is pulling on their straightened arm. The bones are stretched apart momentarily and a ligament slips in between. It becomes trapped when the bones try to snap back into place. As a result, the child will usually quietly refuse to use the arm, but often cries out when they try to bend or straighten the elbow. This condition is also called an elbow subluxation (a partial  dislocation ). This often gets better on its own when the ligament slips back into place. Surgery is usually not needed. Other common causes of elbow pain are: Bursitis  -- inflammation of a fluid-filled cushion beneath the skin,  Arthritis  -- narrowing of the joint space and loss of cartilage in the elbow, Elbow  strains , Infection of the elbow, Tendon tears -- biceps rupture , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001354-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Elbow pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001354-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Elbow pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You have a prolonged case of tendinitis that doesn't improve with home care., The pain is due to a direct elbow injury., There is obvious deformity., You can't use or move the elbow., You have fever or swelling and redness of your elbow., Your elbow is locked and can't straighten or bend., A child has elbow pain., There is a lot of swelling and bruising around the elbow., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001354-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Elbow pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>