<Document id="0001640" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000037.htm">
 
<Focus>Foreign body in the nose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0016542</CUI>
			<CUI>C2136996</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Something stuck in the nose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Objects in the nose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001640-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Foreign body in the nose ?</Question>
			<Answer>This article discusses first aid for a foreign object placed into the nose.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001640-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Foreign body in the nose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Curious young children may insert small objects into their nose in a normal attempt to explore their own bodies. Objects placed in the nose may include food, seeds, dried beans, small toys (such as marbles), crayon pieces, erasers, paper wads, cotton, beads, button batteries, and disc magnets. A foreign body in a child's nose can be there for a while without a parent being aware of the problem. The object may only be discovered when visiting your health care provider to find the cause of irritation, bleeding, infection, or difficulty breathing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001640-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Foreign body in the nose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms that your child may have a foreign body in his or her nose include:  Difficulty breathing  through the affected nostril, Feeling of something in the nose, Foul-smelling or bloody  nasal discharge , Irritability, particularly in infants, Irritation or pain in the nose , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001640-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Foreign body in the nose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Curious young children may insert small objects into their nose in a normal attempt to explore their own bodies. Objects placed in the nose may include food, seeds, dried beans, small toys (such as marbles), crayon pieces, erasers, paper wads, cotton, beads, button batteries, and disc magnets. A foreign body in a child's nose can be there for a while without a parent being aware of the problem. The object may only be discovered when visiting your health care provider to find the cause of irritation, bleeding, infection, or difficulty breathing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001640-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Foreign body in the nose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Get medical help right away for any of the following: The person cannot breathe well, Bleeding occurs and continues for more than 2 or 3 minutes after you remove the foreign object, despite placing gentle pressure on the nose, An object is stuck in both nostrils, You cannot easily remove an object from the person's nose, The object is sharp, is a button battery, or two paired disc magnets (one in each nostril), You think an infection has developed in the nostril where the object is stuck, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001640-6" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Foreign body in the nose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prevention measures may include: Cut food into appropriate sizes for small children., Discourage talking, laughing, or playing while food is in the mouth., Do not give foods such as hot dogs, whole grapes, nuts, popcorn, or hard candy to children under age 3., Keep small objects out of the reach of young children., Teach children to avoid placing foreign objects into their noses and other body openings., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>