<Document id="0001995" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000098.htm">
 
<Focus>Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019655</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001995-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acute pulmonary histoplasmosis is a respiratory infection that is caused by inhaling the  spores  of the fungus  Histoplasma capsulatum .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001995-2" qtype="causes">What causes Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>Histoplasma capsulatum&#160; is the name of the fungus that causes histoplasmosis. It is found in the central and eastern United States, eastern Canada, Mexico, Central America, South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. It is commonly found in the soil in river valleys. It gets into the soil mostly from bird and bat droppings. You can get sick when you breathe in spores that the fungus produces. Every year, thousands of people with a normal immune system worldwide are infected, but most do not become seriously sick. Most have no symptoms or have only a mild flu-like illness and recover without any treatment. Acute  pulmonary  histoplasmosis  may happen as an epidemic, with many people in one region becoming sick at the same time. People with  weakened immune systems  (see Symptoms section below) are more likely to: Develop the disease if exposed to the fungus, Have the disease come back, Have more symptoms, and more serious symptoms, than others who get the disease,  Risk factors include traveling to or living in the central or eastern United States near the Ohio and Mississippi river valleys and being exposed to the droppings of birds and bats. This threat is greatest after an old building is torn down and spores get into the air, or when exploring caves.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001995-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people with acute pulmonary histoplasmosis have no symptoms or only mild symptoms. The most common symptoms are: Chest pain ,  Chills ,  Cough ,  Fever ,  Joint pain  and stiffness,  Muscle aches  and stiffness,  Rash  (usually small sores on the lower legs), Shortness of breath
 ,  Acute pulmonary histoplasmosis can be a serious illness in the very young, older people, and people with a weakened immune system, including those who: Have  HIV/AIDS , Have had  bone marrow  or solid organ transplants, Take medicines that suppress their immune system,  Symptoms in these people may include: Inflammation around the heart (called  pericarditis ), Serious lung infections, Severe joint pain, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001995-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>To diagnose histoplasmosis, you must have the fungus or signs of the fungus in your body. Or your immune system must show that it is reacting to the fungus. Tests include:  Antibody tests for histoplasmosis, Biopsy of infection site,  Bronchoscopy  (usually only done if symptoms are severe or you have an abnormal immune system),  Complete blood count  (CBC) with differential,  Chest CT scan ,  Chest x-ray  (might show a lung infection or pneumonia),  Sputum culture  (this test often does not show the fungus, even if you are infected), Urine test for  Histoplasma capsulatum  antigen, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001995-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most cases of histoplasmosis clear up without specific treatment. People are advised to rest and take medicine to control fever. Your health care provider may prescribe medicine if you are sick for more than 4 weeks, have a weakened immune system, or are having breathing problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001995-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>When histoplasmosis lung infection is severe or gets worse, the illness may last up to many months. Even then, it is rarely fatal. The illness can get worse over time and become a long-term (chronic) lung infection (which doesn't go away).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001995-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>Histoplasmosis can spread to other organs through the bloodstream (dissemination). This is often seen in infants, young children, and people with a suppressed immune system.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001995-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You have symptoms of histoplasmosis, especially if you have a weakened immune system or have recently been exposed to bird or bat droppings, You are being treated for histoplasmosis and develop new symptoms, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001995-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Histoplasmosis - acute (primary) pulmonary ?</Question>
			<Answer>Avoid contact with bird or bat droppings if you are in an area where the spore is common, especially if you have a weakened immune system.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>