<Document id="0002670" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002502.htm">
 
<Focus>Morphine overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0572079</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002670-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Morphine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Morphine is a very strong painkiller. It is one of a number of chemicals called opioids or opiates, which were originally derived from the poppy plant and used for pain relief or their calming effects. Morphine overdose occurs when a person intentionally or accidentally takes too much of the medicine. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with has overdosed, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002670-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Morphine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>When you take the correct or prescribed dose of these medicines, side effects may occur. In addition to relieving pain, you may be drowsy, confused and in a daze, constipated, and possibly nauseated. When you take too much of this medicine, symptoms become much more serious. Symptoms may develop in many body systems: EYES, EARS, NOSE, AND THROAT: Pinpoint pupils,  GASTROINTESTINAL SYSTEM: Constipation, Nausea, Spasms (pain) of the stomach or intestinal tract, Vomiting,  HEART AND BLOOD VESSELS: Low blood pressure, Weak pulse,  NERVOUS SYSTEM: Coma  (unresponsiveness),  Drowsiness , Possible seizures,  RESPIRATORY SYSTEM: Difficulty breathing , Slow breathing that requires more effort, Shallow breathing,  No breathing ,  SKIN: Bluish-colored fingernails and lips  (cyanosis),  OTHER SYMPTOMS: Muscle damage from being immobile while unresponsive, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002670-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Morphine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002670-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Morphine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well the person does depends on the severity of the overdose and how quickly treatment is received. If the proper narcotic antagonist (drug to counteract the effects of narcotics) can be given, recovery from an acute overdose occurs within 24 to 48 hours. However, if there has been prolonged coma and shock (damage to multiple internal organs), a more serious outcome is possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002670-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Morphine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well the person does depends on the severity of the overdose and how quickly treatment is received. If the proper narcotic antagonist (drug to counteract the effects of narcotics) can be given, recovery from an acute overdose occurs within 24 to 48 hours. However, if there has been prolonged coma and shock (damage to multiple internal organs), a more serious outcome is possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>