<Document id="0002428" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003278.htm">
 
<Focus>Lordosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0024003</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Swayback</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arched back</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002428-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lordosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lordosis is the inward curve of the lumbar spine (just above the buttocks). A small degree of lordosis is normal. Too much curving is called swayback. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002428-2" qtype="causes">What causes Lordosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lordosis tends to make the buttocks appear more prominent. Children with hyperlordosis will have a large space underneath the lower back when lying face up on a hard surface. Some children have marked lordosis, but, most often fixes itself as the child grows. This is called benign juvenile lordosis. Spondylolisthesis  may cause lordosis. In this condition, a bone (vertebra) in the spine slips out of the proper position onto the bone below it. You may be born with this. It can develop after certain sports activities, such as gymnastics. It may develop along with arthritis in the spine. Much less common causes in children include: Achondroplasia , a disorder of bone growth that causes the most common type of dwarfism,  Muscular dystrophy , Other genetic conditions, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002428-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Lordosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002428-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Lordosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you notice that your child has an exaggerated posture or a curve in the back. Your provider must check to see if there is a medical problem.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002428-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Lordosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>