<Document id="0002167" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003260.htm">
 
<Focus>Indigestion</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013395</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Dyspepsia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Uncomfortable fullness after meals</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002167-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Indigestion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Indigestion (dyspepsia) is a mild discomfort in the upper belly or abdomen. It often occurs during or right after eating. It may feel like: Heat, burning, or pain in the area between the navel and the lower part of the breastbone, Unpleasant fullness that starts soon after a meal begins or when the meal is over ,  Bloating  and  nausea  are less common symptoms. Indigestion is NOT the same as  heartburn .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002167-2" qtype="causes">What causes Indigestion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of the time, indigestion is not a sign of a serious health problem unless it occurs with other symptoms. These may include: Bleeding, Trouble swallowing, Weight loss ,  Rarely, the discomfort of a heart attack is mistaken for indigestion. Indigestion may be triggered by: Drinking too many caffeinated beverages, Drinking too much alcohol, Eating spicy, fatty, or greasy foods, Eating too much (overeating), Eating too fast, Eating high-fiber foods, Smoking or chewing tobacco, Stress or being nervous ,  Other causes of indigestion are: Gallstones,  Gastritis  (when the lining of the stomach becomes inflamed or swollen), Swelling of the pancreas (pancreatitis), Ulcers (stomach or intestinal ulcer), Use of certain medicines such as antibiotics, aspirin, and over-the-counter pain medicines (NSAIDs, such as ibuprofen or naproxen) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002167-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Indigestion ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002167-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Indigestion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Get medical help right away if your symptoms include jaw pain,  chest pain , back pain,  heavy sweating , anxiety, or a feeling of impending doom. These are possible heart attack symptoms. Contact your provider if: Your indigestion symptoms change noticeably., Your symptoms last longer than a few days., You have  unexplained weight loss ., You have sudden, severe  abdominal pain ., You have trouble swallowing., You have yellow coloring of the skin and eyes (jaundice)., You vomit blood or pass blood in the stool (which may appear black)., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002167-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Indigestion ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>