<Document id="0002733" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002477.htm">
 
<Focus>Naphthalene poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0413168</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Moth balls</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Moth flakes</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Camphor tar</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002733-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Naphthalene poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Naphthalene is a white solid substance with a strong smell. Poisoning from naphthalene destroys or changes red blood cells so they cannot carry oxygen. This can cause organ damage. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002733-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Naphthalene poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Stomach problems may not occur until 2 days after coming in contact with the poison. They can include: Abdominal pain, Nausea and vomiting, Diarrhea ,  The person may also have a fever. Over time, the following symptoms also may occur: Coma , Confusion, Convulsions, Drowsiness, Headache, Increased heart rate ( tachycardia ), Low blood pressure,  Low urine output  (may stop completely),  Pain when urinating  (may be blood in the urine), Shortness of breath, Yellowing of skin (jaundice) ,   
 Note: People with a condition called  glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency  are more vulnerable to the effects of naphthalene.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002733-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Naphthalene poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>It can take several weeks or longer to recover from some of the poison's effects. If the person has  convulsions  and  coma , the outlook is not good.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002733-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Naphthalene poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>It can take several weeks or longer to recover from some of the poison's effects. If the person has  convulsions  and  coma , the outlook is not good.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>