<Document id="0002207" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001609.htm">
 
<Focus>Interstitial keratitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0155088</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Keratitis interstitial</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002207-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Interstitial keratitis is inflammation of the tissue of the cornea, the clear window on the front of the eye. This condition can lead to vision loss.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002207-2" qtype="causes">What causes Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Interstitial keratitis is a serious condition in which blood vessels grow into the cornea. Such growth can cause loss of the normal clearness of the cornea. This condition is often caused by infections. Syphilis is the most common cause of interstitial keratitis, but rare causes include: Autoimmune diseases, like  rheumatoid arthritis  and  sarcoidosis ,  Leprosy ,  Lyme disease ,  Tuberculosis ,  In the United States, most cases of syphilis are recognized and treated before this eye condition develops.  However, interstitial keratitis accounts for 10% of avoidable blindness in the least developed countries worldwide.&#160;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002207-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Eye pain , Excessive tearing, Sensitivity to light ( photophobia ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002207-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Interstitial keratitis can be easily diagnosed by  slit-lamp examination  of the eyes. Blood tests and  chest x-rays  will most often be needed to confirm the infection or disease that is causing the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002207-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The underlying disease must be treated. Treating the cornea with corticosteroid drops may minimize scarring and help keep the cornea clear. Once the active inflammation has passed, the cornea is left severely scarred and with abnormal blood vessels. The only way to restore vision at this stage is with a cornea transplant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002207-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diagnosing and treating interstitial keratitis and its cause early can preserve the clear cornea and good vision.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002207-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>A corneal transplant is not as successful for interstitial keratitis as it is for most other corneal diseases. The presence of blood vessels in the diseased cornea brings white blood cells to the newly transplanted cornea and increases the risk of rejection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002207-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with interstitial keratitis need to be followed closely by an ophthalmologist and a medical specialist with knowledge of the underlying disease.  A person with the condition should be checked immediately if: Pain gets worse, Redness increases, Vision decreases,  This is particularly crucial for people with corneal transplants.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002207-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Interstitial keratitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prevention consists of avoiding the infection that causes interstitial keratitis. If you do get infected, get prompt and thorough treatment and follow-up.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>