<Document id="0002095" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001594.htm">
 
<Focus>Hypervitaminosis D</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1442839</CUI>
			<CUI>C0242154</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Vitamin D toxicity</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002095-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypervitaminosis D is a condition that occurs after taking very high doses of  vitamin D .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002095-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause is excess intake of vitamin D. The doses need to be very high, far above what most health care providers normally prescribe. There has been a lot of confusion about vitamin D supplementation. The recommended daily allowance (RDA) for vitamin D is between 400 and 800 IU/day, according to age and pregnancy status. Higher doses may be needed for some people, such as those with vitamin D deficiency, hypoparathyroidism, and other conditions. However, most people do not need more than 2,000 IU of vitamin D a day. For most people, vitamin D toxicity only occurs with vitamin D doses above 10,000 IU per day.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002095-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>An excess of vitamin D can cause an abnormally high level of calcium in the blood ( hypercalcemia ). This can severely damage the kidneys, soft tissues, and bones over time. The symptoms include: Constipation ,  Decreased appetite  (anorexia),  Dehydration ,  Fatigue  and confusion, Frequent urination, Irritability,  Muscle weakness ,  Vomiting , Excessive thirst ( polydipsia ),  High blood pressure , Passing large amounts of urine ( polyuria ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002095-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider will examine you and ask about your symptoms. Tests that may be ordered include: Calcium level in the blood , Calcium level in the urine, 25-hydroxy vitamin D level, 1,25-dihydroxy vitamin D level,  Serum phosphorus level ,  X-ray of the bone , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002095-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider will likely tell you to stop taking vitamin D. In severe cases, other treatment may be needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002095-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recovery is expected, but permanent kidney damage can occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002095-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health problems that can result from taking too much vitamin D over a long time include: Dehydration, Hypercalcemia, Kidney damage,  Kidney stones , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002095-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You or your child shows symptoms of hypervitaminosis D and has been taking more vitamin D than the RDA, You or your child shows symptoms and has been taking a prescription or over-the-counter form of vitamin D, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002095-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Hypervitaminosis D ?</Question>
			<Answer>To prevent this condition, pay careful attention to the correct vitamin D dose. Use vitamin D supplements from reliable licensed sources. Many combination vitamin supplements contain vitamin D, so check the labels of all the supplements you are taking for vitamin D content.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>