<Document id="0002531" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000952.htm">
 
<Focus>Marijuana intoxication</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0006872</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cannabis intoxication</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intoxication - marijuana (cannabis)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pot</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mary Jane</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Weed</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Grass</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cannabis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002531-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Marijuana intoxication ?</Question>
			<Answer>Marijuana ("pot") intoxication is the euphoria, relaxation, and sometimes undesirable side effects that can occur when people  use marijuana . The ability to perform complex tasks may be adversely affected. Many users report excessive appetite after marijuana use. Most states in the United States permit marijuana to be used legally to treat  certain medical problems . Many states have also decriminalized or legalized its general use.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002531-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Marijuana intoxication ?</Question>
			<Answer>The intoxicating effects of marijuana include relaxation, sleepiness, and mild euphoria (getting high). Smoking marijuana leads to fast and predictable signs and symptoms. Eating marijuana can cause slower, and sometimes less predictable, effects. Marijuana can cause undesirable side effects, which increase with higher doses. These side effects include: Decreased short-term memory, Dry mouth, Impaired perception and motor skills, Red eyes ,  More serious side effects include panic, paranoia, or acute  psychosis , which may be more common with new users or in those who already have a psychiatric disease. The degree of these side effects varies from person to person, as well as with the amount and strength of marijuana used. Marijuana may be contaminated with more dangerous drugs that have more serious side effects than marijuana, but confirmed cases are exceedingly rare, and most reports in the US have turned out to be false. Like other agricultural products, Marijuana may also be contaminated with pesticides, microbes, or heavy metals. These contaminants can have serious side effects.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002531-3" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Marijuana intoxication ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment and care involves: Preventing injury, Reassuring those who have panic reactions due to the drug ,  Sedatives, called benzodiazepines, such as diazepam (Valium) or lorazepam (Ativan), may be given. Children who have more serious symptoms or those with serious side effects may need to stay in the hospital for treatment. Treatment may include heart and brain monitoring. In the emergency department, the person may receive: Activated charcoal, if the drug has been eaten, Blood and urine tests, Breathing support, including oxygen, tube through the mouth, and breathing machine (ventilator), Chest x-ray, Computerized axial tomography (CT, or advanced imaging) scan, ECG (electrocardiogram, or heart tracing), Fluids through the vein (intravenous, or IV), Medicines to relieve symptoms (see above) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002531-4" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Marijuana intoxication ?</Question>
			<Answer>








Uncomplicated marijuana intoxication rarely needs medical advice or treatment. Recurrent anxiety attacks may occur and require medications or other ongoing treatment.&#160;Occasionally, serious symptoms occur. However, these symptoms are rare and usually associated with other drugs or compounds mixed in with marijuana. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002531-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Marijuana intoxication ?</Question>
			<Answer>If someone who has been using marijuana develops any of the symptoms of intoxication, has trouble breathing, or cannot be awakened, call 911 or the local emergency number. If the person has stopped breathing or has no pulse, begin cardiopulmonary resuscitation (CPR) and continue it until help arrives.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>