<Document id="0002869" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001623.htm">
 
<Focus>Orbital pseudotumor</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085270</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Idiopathic orbital inflammatory syndrome (IOIS)</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002869-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Orbital pseudotumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Orbital pseudotumor is the swelling of tissue behind the eye in an area called the orbit. The orbit is the hollow space in the skull where the eye sits. The orbit protects the eyeball and the muscles and tissue that surround it. Orbital pseudotumor does not spread to other tissues or places in the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002869-2" qtype="causes">What causes Orbital pseudotumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause is unknown. It mostly affects young women, although it can occur at any age.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002869-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Orbital pseudotumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Pain in eye, and it may be severe, Restricted eye movement, Decreased vision, Double vision, Eye swelling (proptosis), Red eye (rare) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002869-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Orbital pseudotumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will examine your eye. If you have signs of pseudotumor, additional tests will be done to make sure you don't have other conditions that may look like pseudotumor. The two most common other conditions are: A cancerous tumor in the orbit, Thyroid eye disease,  Tests may include: CT scan of the head, MRI of the head,  Ultrasound  of the head,  Skull x-ray ,  Biopsy , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002869-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Orbital pseudotumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mild cases may go away without treatment. More severe cases most often respond well to corticosteroid treatment. If the condition is very bad, the swelling may put pressure on the eyeball and damage it. Surgery may be needed to remove part of the bones of the orbit to relieve the pressure. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002869-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Orbital pseudotumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most cases are mild and outcomes are good. Severe cases may not respond well to treatment and there may be some loss of vision. Orbital pseudotumor most often involves only one eye.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002869-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Orbital pseudotumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Severe cases of orbital pseudotumor may push the eye forward so much that the lids cannot cover and protect the cornea. This causes the eye to dry out. The cornea may become cloudy or develop an ulcer. Also, the eye muscles may not be able to properly aim the eye which can cause double vision. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002869-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Orbital pseudotumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with this condition need regular follow-up care with an eye doctor who is familiar with the treatment of orbital disease. Contact your provider right away if you have any of the following problems: Irritation of the cornea, Redness, Pain, Decreased vision, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>