<Document id="0002332" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001643.htm">
 
<Focus>Laryngeal nerve damage</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3179093</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Vocal cord paralysis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002332-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Laryngeal nerve damage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Laryngeal nerve damage is injury to one or both of the nerves that cause the voice box to function.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002332-2" qtype="causes">What causes Laryngeal nerve damage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Injury to the laryngeal nerves is uncommon. When it does occur, it can be from: A complication of neck or chest surgery (especially thyroid, lung, heart surgery, or cervical spine surgery), A breathing tube in the windpipe (endotracheal tube), A viral infection that affects the nerves, Tumors in the neck or upper chest, such as  thyroid  or  lung cancer , A neurological condition , Neck or chest trauma, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002332-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Laryngeal nerve damage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Difficulty speaking, Difficulty swallowing, Hoarseness,  Injury to the left and right laryngeal nerves at the same time can cause a breathing problem. This can be an urgent medical problem.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002332-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Laryngeal nerve damage ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will check to see how your vocal cords move. Abnormal movement may mean that a laryngeal nerve is injured. Tests may include: Bronchoscopy ,  CT scan  of the chest, Laryngoscopy,  MRI  of the brain, neck, and chest,  X-ray , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002332-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Laryngeal nerve damage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the cause of the injury. In some cases, no treatment may be needed and the nerve may recover on its own. Voice therapy is useful in some cases. If surgery is needed, the goal is to change the position of the paralyzed vocal cord to improve the voice. This can be done with: Arytenoid adduction (stitches to move the vocal cord toward the middle of the airway), Injections of collagen, Gelfoam, or another substance, Thyroplasty ,  If both the left and right nerves are damaged, a hole may need to be cut into the windpipe (tracheotomy) right away to allow breathing. This is followed by another surgery at a later date.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002332-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Laryngeal nerve damage ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook depends on the cause of the injury. In some cases, the nerve rapidly returns to normal. However, sometimes the damage is permanent.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002332-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Laryngeal nerve damage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have: Difficulty breathing (call right away), Unexplained hoarseness that lasts for more than 3 weeks , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>