<Document id="0002945" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001370.htm">
 
<Focus>Parainfluenza</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0030389</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002945-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>Parainfluenza refers to a group of viruses that lead to upper and lower respiratory infections.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002945-2" qtype="causes">What causes Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are four types of parainfluenza virus. They can all cause lower or&#160; upper respiratory infections &#160;in adults and children. The virus can cause  croup ,  bronchiolitis ,  bronchitis  and certain types of pneumonia. The exact number of parainfluenza cases is unknown. The number is suspected to be very high. Infections are most common in fall and winter. Parainfluenza infections are most severe in infants and become less severe with age. By school age, most children have been exposed to the parainfluenza virus. Most adults have antibodies against parainfluenza, although they can get repeat infections.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002945-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms vary depending on the type of infection. Cold-like symptoms consisting of a runny nose and mild cough are common. Life-threatening respiratory symptoms can be seen in young infants with bronchiolitis and those with weak immune system. In general, symptoms may include: Sore throat, Fever, Runny or stuffy nose, Chest pain, shortness of breath,  wheezing , Cough or croup, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002945-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam may show sinus tenderness, swollen glands, and a red throat. The health care provider will listen to the lungs and chest with a stethoscope. Abnormal sounds, such as crackling or wheezing, may be heard. Tests that may be done include: Arterial blood gases ,  Blood cultures  (to rule out other causes of pneumonia),  Chest x-ray ,  CT scan of the chest ,  Complete blood count (CBC) , Swab of nose for rapid viral test including the virus that causes COVID-19, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002945-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no specific treatment for the viral infection. Certain treatments are available for the symptoms of croup and bronchiolitis to make breathing easier. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002945-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most infections in adults and older children are mild and recovery takes place without treatment, unless the person is very old or has an abnormal immune system. Medical intervention may be necessary if  breathing difficulties  develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002945-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>Secondary bacterial infections are the most common complication.  Airway obstruction  in croup and bronchiolitis can be severe and even life threatening, especially in younger children.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002945-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You or your child develops croup, wheezing, or any other type of breathing difficulty., A child under 18 months develops any type of upper respiratory symptom., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002945-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Parainfluenza ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no vaccines available for parainfluenza. A few preventive measures that may help include: Avoid crowds to limit exposure during peak outbreaks., Wash your hands often., Limit exposure to day care centers and nurseries, if possible., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>