<Document id="0002906" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000884.htm">
 
<Focus>Overcoming job stress</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0344330</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002906-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Overcoming job stress ?</Question>
			<Answer>Almost everyone feels job stress at times, even if you like your job. You may feel stress about hours, coworkers, deadlines, or possible layoffs. Some stress is motivating and can help you achieve. But when job stress is constant, it can lead to health problems. Finding ways to relieve your stress can help you stay healthy and feel better.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002906-2" qtype="causes">What causes Overcoming job stress ?</Question>
			<Answer>Although the cause of job stress is different for every person, there are some common sources of stress in the workplace. These include: Workload.  This can include working long hours, having few breaks, or juggling a very heavy workload.,  Work roles.  It can cause stress if you do not have a clear work role, you have too many roles, or you have to answer to more than one person.,  Job conditions.  A job that is physically demanding or dangerous can be stressful. So can working at a job that exposes you to loud noise, pollution, or toxic chemicals.,  Management.  You may feel stress if management does not allow workers a say in making decisions, lacks organization, or has policies that are not family-friendly.,  Issues with others.  Problems with your boss or coworkers are a common source of stress.,  Fear for your future.  You may feel stress if you are worried about layoffs or not advancing in your career. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002906-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Overcoming job stress ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>