<Document id="0002907" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007287.htm">
 
<Focus>Overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0029944</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002907-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>An overdose may be mild, moderate, or serious. Symptoms, treatment, and recovery depend on the specific drug involved.  In the United States, call 1-800-222-1222 to speak with a  local poison control center . This hotline number will let you talk to experts in poisoning. They will give you further instructions. You should call if you have any questions about an overdose, poisoning, or poison prevention. You can call 24 hours a day, 7 days a week. At the emergency room, an examination will be performed. The following tests and treatments may be needed: Activated charcoal, Airway support, including oxygen, breathing tube through the mouth (intubation), and breathing machine (ventilator), Blood and urine tests, Chest x-ray, CT (computed axial tomography) scan, ECG (electrocardiogram, or heart tracing), Fluids through a vein (intravenous or IV), Laxative, Medicines to treat symptoms, including antidotes (if one exists) to reverse the effects of the overdose ,  A large overdose can cause a person to stop breathing and die if not treated right away. The person may need to be admitted to the hospital to continue treatment. Depending on the drug, or drugs taken, multiple organs may be affected. This may affect the person's outcome and chances of survival. If you receive medical attention before serious problems with your breathing occur, you should have few long-term consequences. You will probably be back to normal in a day. However, an overdose can be deadly or can result in permanent brain damage if treatment is delayed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002907-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>An overdose may be mild, moderate, or serious. Symptoms, treatment, and recovery depend on the specific drug involved.  In the United States, call 1-800-222-1222 to speak with a  local poison control center . This hotline number will let you talk to experts in poisoning. They will give you further instructions. You should call if you have any questions about an overdose, poisoning, or poison prevention. You can call 24 hours a day, 7 days a week. At the emergency room, an examination will be performed. The following tests and treatments may be needed: Activated charcoal, Airway support, including oxygen, breathing tube through the mouth (intubation), and breathing machine (ventilator), Blood and urine tests, Chest x-ray, CT (computed axial tomography) scan, ECG (electrocardiogram, or heart tracing), Fluids through a vein (intravenous or IV), Laxative, Medicines to treat symptoms, including antidotes (if one exists) to reverse the effects of the overdose ,  A large overdose can cause a person to stop breathing and die if not treated right away. The person may need to be admitted to the hospital to continue treatment. Depending on the drug, or drugs taken, multiple organs may be affected. This may affect the person's outcome and chances of survival. If you receive medical attention before serious problems with your breathing occur, you should have few long-term consequences. You will probably be back to normal in a day. However, an overdose can be deadly or can result in permanent brain damage if treatment is delayed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>