<Document id="0002762" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001443.htm">
 
<Focus>Necrotizing soft tissue infection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0149778</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Necrotizing fasciitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fasciitis - necrotizing</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Flesh-eating bacteria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Soft tissue gangrene</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gangrene - soft tissue</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002762-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Necrotizing soft tissue infection is a rare but very severe type of bacterial infection. It can destroy the muscles, skin, and underlying tissue. The word "necrotizing" refers to something that causes body tissue to die.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002762-2" qtype="causes">What causes Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many different types of bacteria can cause this infection. A very severe and usually deadly form of necrotizing soft tissue infection is due to the bacteria  Streptococcus pyogenes , which is sometimes called "flesh-eating bacteria" or strep. Necrotizing soft tissue infection develops when the bacteria enters the body, usually through a minor cut or scrape. The bacteria begin to grow and release harmful substances (toxins) that kill tissue and affect blood flow to the area. With flesh-eating strep, the bacteria also make chemicals that block the body's ability to respond to the organism. As the tissue dies, the bacteria enters the blood and rapidly spreads throughout the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002762-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: A small, red, painful lump or bump on the skin that spreads, A very painful bruise-like area then develops and grows rapidly, sometimes in less than an hour, The center becomes dark and dusky and then turns black and the tissue dies, The skin may break open and ooze fluid ,  Other symptoms may include: Feeling ill, Fever, Sweating, Chills, Nausea, Dizziness, Weakness, Shock , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002762-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider may be able to diagnose this condition by looking at your skin. Or, the condition may be diagnosed in an operating room by a surgeon. Tests that may be done include: Ultrasound ,  X-ray  or  CT scan , Blood tests,  Blood culture  to check for bacteria, An incision of the skin to see if pus is present ,  Skin tissue biopsy  and culture, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002762-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment is needed right away to prevent death. You'll likely need to stay in the hospital. Treatment includes: Powerful antibiotics given through a vein (IV), Surgery to drain the sore and remove dead tissue, Special medicines called donor immunoglobulins (antibodies) to help fight the infection in some cases,  Other treatments may include: Skin grafts after the infection goes away to help your skin heal and look better,  Amputation  if the disease spreads through an arm or leg, Hundred percent oxygen at high pressure ( hyperbaric oxygen therapy ) for certain types of bacterial infections, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002762-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well you do depends on: Your overall health (especially if you have diabetes), How fast you were diagnosed and how quickly you received treatment, The type of bacteria causing the infection, How quickly the infection spreads, How well treatment works,  This disease commonly causes scarring and skin deformity. Death can occur rapidly without proper treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002762-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications that may result from this condition include: Infection that spreads throughout your body, causing a  blood infection  (sepsis), which can be deadly, Scarring and disfigurement, Loss of your ability to use an arm or leg, Death, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002762-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>This disorder is severe and may be life threatening. Contact your provider right away if symptoms of infection occur around a skin injury, including: Drainage of pus or blood, Fever, Pain, Redness, Swelling, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002762-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Necrotizing soft tissue infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Always clean the skin thoroughly after a cut, scrape, or other skin injury.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>