<Document id="0002250" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002870.htm">
 
<Focus>Jack-in-the-pulpit poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0275186</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Arisaema triphyllum poisoning</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bog onion poisoning</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brown dragon poisoning</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Indian turnip poisoning</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wake robin poisoning</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wild turnip poisoning</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002250-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Jack-in-the-pulpit poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>A Jack-in-the-pulpit is a plant belonging to the species  Arisaema triphyllum . This article describes poisoning caused by eating parts of this plant. The roots are the most dangerous part of the plant. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002250-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Jack-in-the-pulpit poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Blisters in the mouth, Burning in mouth and throat, Diarrhea, Hoarse voice, Increased saliva production, Nausea and vomiting, Pain on swallowing, Redness, swelling, pain, and burning of the eyes, and possible corneal damage, Swelling of mouth and tongue,  Blistering and swelling in the mouth may be severe enough to prevent normal speaking and swallowing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002250-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Jack-in-the-pulpit poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002250-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Jack-in-the-pulpit poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>If contact with the person's mouth is not severe, symptoms most often clear up within a few days. For people who do have severe contact with the plant, a longer recovery time may be necessary. In rare cases, swelling may be severe enough to block the airways. DO NOT touch or eat any plant with which you are not familiar. Wash your hands after working in the garden or walking in the woods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002250-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Jack-in-the-pulpit poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>If contact with the person's mouth is not severe, symptoms most often clear up within a few days. For people who do have severe contact with the plant, a longer recovery time may be necessary. In rare cases, swelling may be severe enough to block the airways. DO NOT touch or eat any plant with which you are not familiar. Wash your hands after working in the garden or walking in the woods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>