<Document id="0002255" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002845.htm">
 
<Focus>Jellyfish stings</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0241955</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002255-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Jellyfish stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>Jellyfish are sea creatures. They have nearly see-through bodies with long, finger-like structures called tentacles. Stinging cells inside the tentacles can hurt you if you come in contact with them. Some stings can cause serious harm. Almost 2000 species of animals found in the ocean are either venomous or poisonous to humans, and many can produce severe illness or fatalities. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage a jellyfish sting. If you or someone you are with is stung, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002255-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Jellyfish stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of stings from different types of jellyfish are: LION'S MANE  Breathing difficulty, Muscle cramps, Skin burning and blistering (severe) ,  PORTUGUESE MAN-OF-WAR  Abdominal pain, Changes in pulse, Chest pain, Chills, Collapse (shock), Headache, Muscle pain and muscle spasms, Numbness and weakness, Pain in the arms or legs, Raised red spot where stung, Runny nose and watery eyes,  Swallowing difficulty , Sweating ,  SEA NETTLE  Mild skin rash (with mild stings), Muscle cramps and breathing difficulty (from a lot of contact) ,  SEA WASP OR BOX JELLYFISH Abdominal pain, Breathing difficulty, Changes in pulse, Chest pain, Collapse (shock), Headache, Muscle pain and muscle spasms, Nausea and vomiting, Pain in the arms or legs, Raised red spot where stung, Severe burning pain and sting site blistering, Skin tissue death, Sweating ,  For the great majority of bites, stings, or other forms of poisoning, the danger is either drowning after being stung or an allergic reaction to the venom.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002255-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Jellyfish stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002255-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Jellyfish stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most jellyfish stings improve within hours, but some stings can lead to skin irritation or rashes that last for weeks. Contact your provider if you continue to have itching at the sting site. Topical anti-inflammatory creams may be helpful. Portuguese man-of-war and sea nettle stings are rarely deadly. Certain box jellyfish stings can kill a person within minutes. Other box jellyfish stings can lead to death in 4 to 48 hours after a sting due to "Irukandji syndrome," a delayed reaction to the sting. It is important to carefully monitor box jellyfish sting victims for hours after a sting. Seek medical attention right away for any breathing difficulties, chest or abdominal pains, or profuse sweating.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002255-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Jellyfish stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most jellyfish stings improve within hours, but some stings can lead to skin irritation or rashes that last for weeks. Contact your provider if you continue to have itching at the sting site. Topical anti-inflammatory creams may be helpful. Portuguese man-of-war and sea nettle stings are rarely deadly. Certain box jellyfish stings can kill a person within minutes. Other box jellyfish stings can lead to death in 4 to 48 hours after a sting due to "Irukandji syndrome," a delayed reaction to the sting. It is important to carefully monitor box jellyfish sting victims for hours after a sting. Seek medical attention right away for any breathing difficulties, chest or abdominal pains, or profuse sweating.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>