<Document id="0002910" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002479.htm">
 
<Focus>Oxalic acid poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0161695</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002910-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Oxalic acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oxalic acid is a poisonous, colorless substance. It is chemical known as a caustic. If it contacts tissues, it can cause severe damage, such as burning or ulcers, on contact. This article discusses poisoning from swallowing oxalic acid. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002910-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Oxalic acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of oxalic acid poisoning include: Abdominal pain , Burns and blisters where the acid contacted the skin, lips, tongue, and gums, Chest pain,  Collapse , Drooling, Mouth pain,  Seizures ,  Shock &#160;(rapid drop in blood pressure), Throat pain and swelling, which leads to difficulty breathing,  Tremors  (unintentional trembling), Vomiting ,  Symptoms from getting oxalic acid on the skin or in the eyes include: Burning, Severe pain, Vision loss, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002910-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Oxalic acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002910-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Oxalic acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on the amount of poison swallowed, how concentrated the poison is, and how quickly treatment was received. The faster a person gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Severe damage to the mouth, gastrointestinal tract, or airway may occur and quickly cause death if not treated. Holes (perforations) in the esophagus and stomach may cause serious infections in both the chest and abdominal cavities, which may result in death. Surgery may be needed to repair the perforations.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002910-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Oxalic acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on the amount of poison swallowed, how concentrated the poison is, and how quickly treatment was received. The faster a person gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Severe damage to the mouth, gastrointestinal tract, or airway may occur and quickly cause death if not treated. Holes (perforations) in the esophagus and stomach may cause serious infections in both the chest and abdominal cavities, which may result in death. Surgery may be needed to repair the perforations.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>