<Document id="0002276" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001462.htm">
 
<Focus>Keratosis pilaris</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0263383</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002276-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Keratosis pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keratosis pilaris is a common skin condition in which a protein in the skin called keratin forms hard plugs within hair follicles.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002276-2" qtype="causes">What causes Keratosis pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keratosis pilaris is harmless ( benign ). It seems to run in families. It is more common in people who have very dry skin, or who have  atopic dermatitis  (eczema). The condition is generally worse in winter and often clears in the summer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002276-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Keratosis pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Small bumps that look like "goose bumps" on the back of the upper arms and thighs, Bumps feel like very rough sandpaper, Skin-colored bumps are the size of a grain of sand, Slight pinkness may be seen around some bumps, Bumps may appear on the face and be mistaken for acne , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002276-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Keratosis pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can usually diagnose this condition by looking at your skin. Tests are often not needed. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002276-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Keratosis pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment may include:  Moisturizing lotions to soothe the skin and help it look better, Skin creams that contain urea, lactic acid, glycolic acid, salicylic acid, tretinoin, or vitamin D, Steroid creams to reduce redness,  Improvement often takes months, and the bumps are likely to come back if you stop using the medicine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002276-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Keratosis pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keratosis pilaris may fade slowly with age.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002276-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Keratosis pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if the bumps are bothersome and do not get better with lotions you buy without a prescription. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>