<Document id="0002009" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000629.htm">
 
<Focus>Hookworm infection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019911</CUI>
			<CUI>C0002831</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hookworm disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ground itch</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ancylostoma duodenale infection</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Necator americanus infection</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Parasitic infection - hookworm</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002009-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hookworm infection is caused by roundworms. The disease affects the small intestine and lungs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002009-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>The infection is caused by infestation with any of the following roundworms: Necator americanus ,  Ancylostoma duodenale ,  Ancylostoma ceylanicum ,  Ancylostoma braziliense ,  The first two roundworms affect humans only. The last two types also occur in animals. Hookworm disease is common in the moist tropics and subtropics. In developing nations, the disease leads to the death of many children by weakening their immune system and increasing their risk for infections that their bodies would normally fight off. There is very little risk of getting the disease in the United States because of advances in sanitation and waste control. The important factor in getting the disease is walking barefoot on ground where there are feces of people who are infected with hookworm. The larvae (immature form of the worm) enter the skin. The larvae move to the lungs via the bloodstream and enter the airways. The worms are about one-half inch (1 centimeter) long. After traveling up the windpipe, the larvae are swallowed. After the larvae are swallowed, they infect the small intestine. They develop into adult worms and live there for 1 or more years. The worms attach to the intestinal wall and suck blood, which can result in iron deficiency anemia and protein loss. Adult worms and larvae are released in the feces.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002009-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Abdominal discomfort, Cough, Diarrhea,  Fatigue , Fever, Gas, Itchy rash,  Loss of appetite , Nausea, vomiting,  Pale skin ,  Most people have no symptoms once the worms enter the intestines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002009-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests that can help diagnose the infection include: Complete blood count  (CBC) with  differential ,  Stool ova and parasites exam , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002009-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goals of treatment are to: Cure the infection, Treat complications of anemia, Improve nutrition,  Parasite-killing drugs such as albendazole, mebendazole, or pyrantel pamoate are often prescribed. Symptoms and complications of anemia are treated, if needed. Your health care provider will likely recommend increasing the amount of  protein in your diet .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002009-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>You will have a complete recovery if you get treated before serious complications develop. Treatment gets rid of the infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002009-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health problems that may result from hookworm infection include: Iron deficiency anemia , caused by loss of blood, Nutritional deficiencies, Severe protein loss with fluid buildup in the abdomen ( ascites ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002009-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if symptoms of hookworm infection develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002009-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Hookworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Handwashing and wearing shoes will reduce the likelihood of infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>