<Document id="0002740" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003055.htm">
 
<Focus>Nasal flaring</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0277873</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Flaring of the alae nasi (nostrils)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nostrils - flaring</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002740-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nasal flaring ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nasal flaring occurs when the nostrils widen while breathing. It is often a sign of trouble breathing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002740-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Nasal flaring ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nasal flaring is seen mostly in infants and younger children. Any condition that causes difficulty breathing can cause nasal flaring. Many causes of nasal flaring are not serious, but some can be life threatening. In young infants, nasal flaring can be a sign of  respiratory distress . This is a serious lung condition that prevents enough oxygen from getting to the lungs and into the blood.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002740-3" qtype="causes">What causes Nasal flaring ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nasal flaring may be caused by any of the following: Asthma  flare-up, Blocked airway (any cause), Swelling and mucus buildup in the smallest air passages in the lungs ( bronchiolitis ), Problem breathing and a barking cough ( croup ), Swollen or inflamed tissue in the area that covers the windpipe ( epiglottitis ), Lung problems, such as infection or  long-term damage , Breathing disorder in newborns ( transient tachypnea of the newborn ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002740-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Nasal flaring ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nasal flaring is seen mostly in infants and younger children. Any condition that causes difficulty breathing can cause nasal flaring. Many causes of nasal flaring are not serious, but some can be life threatening. In young infants, nasal flaring can be a sign of  respiratory distress . This is a serious lung condition that prevents enough oxygen from getting to the lungs and into the blood.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002740-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Nasal flaring ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your health care provider if: There is any persistent, unexplained nasal flaring, especially in a young child. ,  Bluish color  develops in the lips, nail beds, or skin. This is a sign that  breathing difficulty  is severe. It may mean that an emergency condition is developing., You think that your child is having trouble breathing. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002740-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Nasal flaring ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>