<Document id="0002310" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001240.htm">
 
<Focus>Kyphosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265673</CUI>
			<CUI>C0022821</CUI>
			<CUI>C0022822</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T190</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Scheuermann disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Roundback</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hunchback</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Postural kyphosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002310-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Kyphosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kyphosis is a curving of the spine that causes a bowing or rounding of the back. This leads to a hunchback or slouching posture.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002310-2" qtype="causes">What causes Kyphosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kyphosis can occur at any age, although it is rare at birth. A type of kyphosis that occurs in young teens is known as Scheuermann disease. It is caused by the wedging together of several bones of the spine (vertebrae) in a row. The cause of this condition is unknown. Kyphosis can also occur in young teens who have  cerebral palsy . In adults, kyphosis can be caused by: Degenerative diseases of the spine (such as  arthritis  or disk degeneration), Fractures caused by  osteoporosis  (osteoporotic compression fractures), Injury (trauma), Slipping of one vertebra forward on another ( spondylolisthesis ),  Other causes of kyphosis include: Certain hormone ( endocrine ) diseases, Connective tissue disorders, Infection (such as  tuberculosis ),  Muscular dystrophy  (group of inherited disorders that cause muscle weakness and loss of muscle tissue),  Neurofibromatosis  (disorder in which nerve tissue tumors form),  Paget disease  (disorder that involves abnormal bone destruction and regrowth),  Polio ,  Scoliosis  (curving of the spine often looks like a C or S when viewed from behind),  Spina bifida  (birth defect in which the backbone and spinal canal don't close before birth), Tumors, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002310-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Kyphosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pain in the middle or lower back is the most common symptom. Other symptoms may include any of the following: Round back appearance, Tenderness and stiffness in the spine,  Fatigue , Difficulty breathing (in severe cases), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002310-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Kyphosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>
Physical examination by a health care provider confirms the abnormal curve of the spine. The provider will also look for any nervous system (neurological) changes. These include weakness, paralysis, or changes in sensation below the curve. Your provider will also check for differences in your reflexes. Tests that may be ordered include: Spine x-ray ,  Pulmonary function tests  (if kyphosis affects breathing),  MRI  (if there may be a tumor, infection, or nervous system symptoms), Bone density test (to check for osteoporosis), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002310-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Kyphosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the cause of the disorder: Congenital kyphosis needs corrective surgery at an early age., Scheuermann disease is treated with a brace and physical therapy. Sometimes surgery is needed for large (greater than 60 degrees), painful curves.,  Compression fractures  from osteoporosis can be left alone if there are no nervous system problems or pain. But the osteoporosis needs to be treated to help prevent future fractures. For severe deformity or pain from osteoporosis, surgery is an option., Kyphosis caused by infection or tumor needs prompt treatment, often with surgery and medicines.,  Treatment for other types of kyphosis depends on the cause. Surgery is needed if nervous system symptoms or constant pain develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002310-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Kyphosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Young teens with Scheuermann disease tend to do well, even if they need surgery. The disease stops once they stop growing. If the kyphosis is due to  degenerative joint disease  or multiple compression fractures, surgery is needed to correct the defect and improve pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002310-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Kyphosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Untreated kyphosis can cause any of the following: Decreased lung capacity, Disabling back pain, Nervous system symptoms, including leg weakness or paralysis, Round back deformity , Increased self-consciousness or body awareness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002310-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Kyphosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treating and preventing osteoporosis can prevent many cases of kyphosis in older adults. Early diagnosis and bracing for Scheuermann disease can reduce the need for surgery, but there is no way to prevent the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>