<Document id="0002194" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000033.htm">
 
<Focus>Insect bites and stings</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0021568</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bee sting</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bites - insects, bees, and spiders</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Black widow spider bite</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brown recluse bite</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Flea bite</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Honey bee or hornet sting</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lice bites</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mite bite</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Scorpion bite</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spider bite</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wasp sting</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Yellow jacket sting</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002194-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Insect bites and stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>Insect bites and stings can cause an immediate skin reaction. The bite from fire ants and the sting from bees, wasps, and hornets are most often painful. Bites caused by mosquitoes, fleas, and mites are more likely to cause itching than pain. Insect and spider bites cause more deaths from venom reactions than bites from snakes.&#160;Most deaths from insect bites are due to allergic reaction to the venom, rather than the toxins in the venom itself.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002194-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Insect bites and stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, bites and stings can be easily treated at home.  Some people have extreme allergic reactions that require immediate treatment to prevent death.  Certain spider bites, such as the  black widow  or brown recluse, can cause serious illness or death. Most spider bites are harmless. If possible, bring the insect or spider that bit you with you when you go for treatment so it can be identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002194-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Insect bites and stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms depend on the type of bite or sting. They may include: Pain, Redness, Swelling, Itching, Burning, Numbness, Tingling ,  Some people have severe, life-threatening allergic reactions to bee stings or insect bites. This is called  anaphylactic shock . This condition can occur very quickly and lead to rapid death if not treated quickly.  Symptoms of anaphylaxis can occur quickly and affect the whole body. They include: Abdominal pain or vomiting, Chest pain, Difficulty swallowing, Difficulty breathing, Face or mouth swelling, Fainting or lightheadedness, Rash or skin flushing, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002194-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Insect bites and stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, bites and stings can be easily treated at home.  Some people have extreme allergic reactions that require immediate treatment to prevent death.  Certain spider bites, such as the  black widow  or brown recluse, can cause serious illness or death. Most spider bites are harmless. If possible, bring the insect or spider that bit you with you when you go for treatment so it can be identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002194-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Insect bites and stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, bites and stings can be easily treated at home.  Some people have extreme allergic reactions that require immediate treatment to prevent death.  Certain spider bites, such as the  black widow  or brown recluse, can cause serious illness or death. Most spider bites are harmless. If possible, bring the insect or spider that bit you with you when you go for treatment so it can be identified.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002194-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Insect bites and stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911 or the local emergency number if someone with a sting has the following symptoms: Trouble breathing, wheezing, shortness of breath, Swelling anywhere on the face or in the mouth, Throat tightness or difficulty swallowing, Feeling weak, Turning blue ,  If you had a severe, bodywide reaction to a bee sting, your provider should send you to an allergist for skin testing and therapy. You should receive an emergency kit to carry with you wherever you go.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002194-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Insect bites and stings ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can help prevent insect bites and stings by doing the following: Avoid perfumes and floral-patterned or dark clothing when walking through woods, fields or other areas which are known to have large number of bees or other insects., Avoid rapid, jerky movements around insect hives or nests., Do not put hands in nests or under rotted wood where insects may gather., Use caution when eating outdoors, especially with sweetened beverages or in areas around garbage cans, which often attract bees., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>