<Document id="0002216" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000253.htm">
 
<Focus>Intestinal pseudo-obstruction</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0021847</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Primary intestinal pseudo-obstruction</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute colonic ileus</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Colonic pseudo-obstruction</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Idiopathic intestinal pseudo-obstruction</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ogilvie's syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic intestinal pseudo-obstruction</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002216-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Intestinal pseudo-obstruction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Intestinal pseudo-obstruction is a condition in which there are symptoms of blockage of the intestine (bowels) without any physical blockage.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002216-2" qtype="causes">What causes Intestinal pseudo-obstruction ?</Question>
			<Answer>In intestinal pseudo-obstruction, the intestine is unable to contract and push food, stool, and air through the digestive tract. The disorder most often affects the small intestine, but can also occur in the large intestine. The condition may&#160;start suddenly or be a chronic or long-term problem. It is most common in children and older people. The cause of the problem is often unknown. Risk factors include: Cerebral palsy  or other brain or nervous system disorders., Chronic kidney, lung, or heart disease., Staying in bed for long periods of time (bedridden)., Taking drugs that slow intestinal movements. These include narcotic (pain) medicines and drugs used when you are not able to keep urine from leaking out., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002216-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Intestinal pseudo-obstruction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Abdominal pain , Bloating, Constipation,  Nausea  and vomiting, Swollen abdomen ( abdominal distention ),  Weight loss , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002216-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Intestinal pseudo-obstruction ?</Question>
			<Answer>During a physical exam, the health care provider will most often see abdominal bloating. Tests include: Abdominal x-ray , Anorectal manometry,  Barium swallow , barium small bowel follow-through, or  barium enema , Blood tests for nutritional or vitamin deficiencies,  Colonoscopy ,  CT scan , Antroduodenal manometry, Gastric emptying radionuclide scan, Intestinal radionuclide scan , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002216-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Intestinal pseudo-obstruction ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following treatments may be tried: Colonoscopy  may be used to remove air from the large intestine., Fluids can be given through a vein to replace fluids lost from vomiting or diarrhea., Nasogastric suction involving a nasogastric (NG) tube placed through the nose into the stomach can be used to remove air from the bowel., Neostigmine may be used to treat intestinal pseudo-obstruction that is only in the large bowel (Ogilvie syndrome)., Special diets often do not work. However, vitamin B12 and other vitamin supplements should be used for people with vitamin deficiency., Stopping the medicines that may have caused the problem (such as narcotic drugs) may help.,  In severe cases, surgery may be needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002216-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Intestinal pseudo-obstruction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most cases of acute pseudo-obstruction get better in a few days with treatment. In chronic forms of the disease, symptoms can come back and get worse over many years.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002216-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Intestinal pseudo-obstruction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Diarrhea , Rupture (perforation) of the intestine, Vitamin deficiencies, Weight loss, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002216-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Intestinal pseudo-obstruction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have abdominal pain that does not go away or other symptoms of this disorder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>