<Document id="0002261" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000876.htm">
 
<Focus>Jock itch</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1384589</CUI>
			<CUI>C0040253</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Fungal infection - groin</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Infection - fungal - groin</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Itching in the groin</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ringworm - groin</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tinea cruris</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tinea of the groin</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002261-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Jock itch ?</Question>
			<Answer>Jock itch is an infection of the groin area caused by a fungus. The medical term is tinea cruris or ringworm of the groin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002261-2" qtype="causes">What causes Jock itch ?</Question>
			<Answer>Jock itch occurs when a type of fungus grows and spreads in the groin area. Jock itch occurs mostly in adult men and teenage boys. Some people who have this infection also have  athlete's foot  or another kind of  ringworm . The fungus that causes jock itch thrives in warm, moist areas. Jock itch can be triggered by friction from clothes and prolonged moistness in the groin area, such as from sweating. A fungal infection of the feet can spread to the groin area by pulling up pants if the waistband gets contaminated with fungus from the feet. Jock itch can be passed from one person to another by direct skin-to-skin contact or contact with unwashed clothing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002261-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Jock itch ?</Question>
			<Answer>Jock itch usually stays around the creases of the upper thigh and does not involve the scrotum or penis. Jock itch may spread to near the anus, causing anal itching and discomfort. Symptoms include: Red, raised, scaly patches that may blister and ooze. The patches often have sharply-defined edges with scale at the edges., Abnormally dark or light skin. Sometimes, these changes are permanent., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002261-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Jock itch ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can usually diagnose jock itch based on how your skin looks. Tests are usually not necessary. If tests are needed, they may include: A simple office test called a  KOH exam  to check for fungus
   ,  Skin culture , A  skin biopsy  may also be performed with a special stain called PAS to identify fungus and yeast
   , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002261-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Jock itch ?</Question>
			<Answer>Jock itch usually responds to self-care within a couple of weeks: Keep the skin clean and dry in the groin area., Do not wear clothing that rubs and irritates the area. Wear loose-fitting underwear., Wash athletic supporters frequently., Over-the-counter antifungal or drying powders can help control the infection. These contain medicine, such as miconazole, clotrimazole, terbinafine, or tolnaftate.,  You may need treatment by a provider if your infection lasts longer than 2 weeks, is severe, or frequently returns. The provider may prescribe: Stronger topical (applied to the skin) antifungal medicines or oral antifungal medicines, Antibiotics may be needed to treat bacterial infections that occur from scratching the area,  If you tend to get jock itch, continue to apply antifungal or drying powders after bathing, even when you do not have jock itch. Jock itch is more common in overweight people with deep, moist skin folds. Losing weight may help prevent the condition from coming back.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002261-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Jock itch ?</Question>
			<Answer>Jock itch usually responds promptly to treatment. It is often less severe than other tinea infections, such as athlete's foot, but may last a long time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002261-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Jock itch ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if jock itch does not respond to home care after 2 weeks or you have other symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>