<Document id="0002603" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000116.htm">
 
<Focus>Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0025500</CUI>
			<CUI>C1290375</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mesothelioma - benign</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mesothelioma - fibrous</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pleural fibroma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Solitary fibrous tumor of the pleura</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002603-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous ?</Question>
			<Answer>Solitary fibrous tumor (SFT) is a noncancerous&#160; tumor  of the lining of the lung and chest cavity, an area called the pleura. SFT used to be called localized fibrous mesothelioma.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002603-2" qtype="causes">What causes Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of SFT remains unknown. This type of tumor affects men and women equally. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002603-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous ?</Question>
			<Answer>About one half of the people with this type of tumor do not show any symptoms. If the tumor grows to a large size and pushes on the lung, it can lead to symptoms, such as: Chest pain , Chronic cough, Shortness of breath,  Clubbed appearance of the fingers , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002603-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous ?</Question>
			<Answer>SFT is usually found by accident when a  chest x-ray  is done for other reasons. If the health care provider suspects SFT, tests will be ordered. These may include: CT scan of the chest ,  Open lung biopsy ,  Pulmonary function tests ,  The diagnosis of SFT is difficult compared with the cancerous type of this disease, called  malignant mesothelioma , which is caused by exposure to asbestos (as cancer needs to be ruled out). SFT is not caused by asbestos exposure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002603-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous ?</Question>
			<Answer>SFT is usually treated by removing the tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002603-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome is expected to be good with prompt treatment. In rare cases, the tumor may return.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002603-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fluid escaping into the membranes around the lungs ( pleural effusion ) is a complication.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002603-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Mesothelioma - benign-fibrous ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if you notice symptoms of SFT.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>