<Document id="0002621" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002680.htm">
 
<Focus>Methanol poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0392621</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Wood alcohol poisoning</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002621-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Methanol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Methanol is a nondrinking type of alcohol used for industrial and automotive purposes. This article discusses poisoning from an overdose of methanol. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002621-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Methanol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Airway and lungs: Breathing difficulty, No breathing ,  Eyes: Blindness, complete or partial, sometimes described as "snow blindness",  Blurred vision , Dilation (widening) of the pupils ,  Heart and blood: Low blood pressure ,  Nervous system: Agitated behavior , Coma (unresponsiveness), Confusion, Difficulty walking, Dizziness, Headache, Seizures ,  Skin and nails: Bluish-colored lips and fingernails (cyanosis),  Stomach and intestines: Abdominal pain (severe), Diarrhea, Liver problems, including jaundice (yellow skin) and bleeding, Nausea, Pancreatitis (nausea, vomiting, and abdominal pain), Vomiting, sometimes bloody,  Other: Fatigue, Leg cramps, Weakness , Yellow skin (jaundice), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002621-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Methanol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002621-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Methanol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Methanol is extremely poisonous. As little as 2 tablespoons (30 milliliters) can be deadly to a child. About 2 to 8 ounces (60 to 240 milliliters) can be deadly for an adult. Blindness is common and often permanent despite medical care. Intake of methanol affects multiple organs. Organ damage may be permanent. How well the person does depends on how much poison is swallowed and how soon treatment is received.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002621-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Methanol poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Methanol is extremely poisonous. As little as 2 tablespoons (30 milliliters) can be deadly to a child. About 2 to 8 ounces (60 to 240 milliliters) can be deadly for an adult. Blindness is common and often permanent despite medical care. Intake of methanol affects multiple organs. Organ damage may be permanent. How well the person does depends on how much poison is swallowed and how soon treatment is received.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>