<Document id="0002661" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001472.htm">
 
<Focus>Mongolian blue spots</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2126244</CUI>
			<CUI>C2126380</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mongolian spots</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital dermal melanocytosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dermal melanocytosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002661-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mongolian blue spots ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dermal melanocytosis&#160;is the name of a kind of  birthmark  that is flat and blue, or blue-gray in color. They appear at birth or in the first few weeks of life.&#160;Dermal melanocytosis was formerly called Mongolian blue spots.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002661-2" qtype="causes">What causes Mongolian blue spots ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dermal melanocytosis is&#160;common among people of Asian, Native American, Hispanic, East Indian, and African descent. The color of the birth mark is from a collection of melanocytes in the deeper layers of the skin. Melanocytes are cells that make the pigment (color) in the skin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002661-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mongolian blue spots ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dermal melanocytosis is&#160;not cancerous and is not associated with disease. The markings may cover a large area of the back. The markings are usually: Blue or blue-gray spots on the back, buttocks, base of spine, shoulders, or other body areas, Flat with irregular shape and unclear edges, Normal in skin texture, 2 to 8 centimeters wide or larger ,  Dermal melanocytosis is&#160;sometimes mistaken for  bruises . This can raise a question about possible child abuse. It is important to recognize that dermal melanocytosis&#160;is a birthmark, not bruises.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002661-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Mongolian blue spots ?</Question>
			<Answer>No tests are needed. Your health care provider can diagnose this condition by looking at the skin. If your provider suspects an underlying disorder, further tests will be done.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002661-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Mongolian blue spots ?</Question>
			<Answer>No treatment is&#160;needed when dermal melanocytosis&#160;is a normal birthmark. If treatment is needed, lasers may be used. Spots&#160;may be&#160;a sign of an underlying disorder. If so,&#160;treatment for that problem will likely be recommended. Your provider can tell you more.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002661-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Mongolian blue spots ?</Question>
			<Answer>Spots that are normal birthmarks often fade in a few years. They are almost always gone by the teen years.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002661-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Mongolian blue spots ?</Question>
			<Answer>All birthmarks should be examined by a provider during the routine newborn examination.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>