<Document id="0002824" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003106.htm">
 
<Focus>Nosebleed</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0014591</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bleeding from the nose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epistaxis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002824-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nosebleed ?</Question>
			<Answer>A nosebleed is loss of blood from the tissue lining the nose. Bleeding most often occurs from one nostril only.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002824-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Nosebleed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nosebleeds are very common. Most nosebleeds occur because of minor irritations of the inside of the nostrils or colds. The nose contains many small blood vessels that bleed easily. Air moving through the nose can dry and irritate the membranes lining the inside of the nose. Crusts can form that bleed when irritated. Nosebleeds occur more often in the winter, when cold viruses are common and indoor air tends to be drier. Most nosebleeds occur on the front of the nasal septum. This is the piece of the tissue that separates the two sides of the nose. This type of nosebleed can be easy for a trained professional to stop. Less commonly, nosebleeds may occur higher on the septum or deeper in the nose such as in the sinuses or the base of the skull. Such nosebleeds may be harder to control. However, nosebleeds are rarely life threatening.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002824-3" qtype="causes">What causes Nosebleed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nosebleed can be caused by: Irritation due to allergies, colds,  sneezing  or sinus problems, Very cold or dry air, Blowing the nose very hard, or picking the nose, Injury to nose, including a  broken nose , or an object stuck in the nose, Sinus or pituitary surgery (transsphenoidal), Deviated septum (tissue that divides the nose into 2 nostrils), Chemical irritants including medicines or drugs that are sprayed or snorted, Overuse of decongestant nasal sprays, Oxygen treatment through nasal cannulas , Snorting cocaine or amphetamine,  Repeated nosebleeds may be a symptom of another disease such as high blood pressure, a bleeding disorder, or a tumor of the nose or sinuses. Blood thinners, such as warfarin (Coumadin), clopidogrel (Plavix), or aspirin, may cause or worsen nosebleeds.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002824-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Nosebleed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nosebleeds are very common. Most nosebleeds occur because of minor irritations of the inside of the nostrils or colds. The nose contains many small blood vessels that bleed easily. Air moving through the nose can dry and irritate the membranes lining the inside of the nose. Crusts can form that bleed when irritated. Nosebleeds occur more often in the winter, when cold viruses are common and indoor air tends to be drier. Most nosebleeds occur on the front of the nasal septum. This is the piece of the tissue that separates the two sides of the nose. This type of nosebleed can be easy for a trained professional to stop. Less commonly, nosebleeds may occur higher on the septum or deeper in the nose such as in the sinuses or the base of the skull. Such nosebleeds may be harder to control. However, nosebleeds are rarely life threatening.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002824-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Nosebleed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Get emergency care if: Bleeding does not stop after 20 minutes., Nose bleeding occurs after a head injury. This may suggest a skull fracture, and x-rays or other imaging should be taken., Your nose may be broken (for example, it looks crooked after a hit to the nose or other injury)., You are taking medicines to prevent your blood from clotting (blood thinners)., You have had nosebleeds in the past that needed specialist care to treat.,  Contact your health care provider if: You or your child has frequent nosebleeds, Your nose may be broken (for example, it looks crooked after a hit to the nose or other injury), Nosebleeds are not associated with a cold or other minor irritation, Nosebleeds occur after sinus or other surgery, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002824-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Nosebleed ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>