<Document id="0002389" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000872.htm">
 
<Focus>Lichen simplex chronicus</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0027822</CUI>
			<CUI>C0149922</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002389-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lichen simplex chronicus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lichen simplex chronicus&#160;(LSC) is a skin condition caused by  chronic  itching and scratching.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002389-2" qtype="causes">What causes Lichen simplex chronicus ?</Question>
			<Answer>LSC may occur in people who have: Skin allergies,  Eczema  (atopic dermatitis),  Psoriasis , Nervousness, anxiety, depression, and other emotional problems ,  The problem is common in adults but may also be seen in children.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002389-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Lichen simplex chronicus ?</Question>
			<Answer>LSC leads to scratching, which then causes more itching. It often follows this pattern: It may start when something rubs, irritates, or scratches the skin, such as clothing., The person begins to rub or scratch the itchy area. Constant scratching (often during sleep) causes the skin to thicken., The thickened skin itches, and this leads to more scratching. This then causes more thickening of the skin., The skin may become leathery and brownish in the affected area.,  Symptoms include: Itching  of the skin that may be long-term (chronic), intense, and that increases with stress, Leathery texture to the skin, Raw areas of skin,  Scaling ,  Skin lesion , patch, or plaque with sharp borders and a leathery texture, located on the ankle, wrist, back of the neck, rectum, anal area, forearms, thighs, lower leg, back of the knee, and inner elbow, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002389-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Lichen simplex chronicus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will look at your skin and ask if you have had&#160;chronic itching and scratching in the past. A  skin lesion biopsy  may be done to confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002389-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Lichen simplex chronicus ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main treatment is to reduce the itch. You may need to use these medicines on your skin: Lotion or steroid cream on the area to calm itching and irritation, Numbing medicine, Peeling ointments containing salicylic acid, lactic acid, or urea on patches of thick skin,  You may need to use dressings that moisturize, cover, and protect the area. These may be used with or without medicated creams. They are left in place for a week or more at a time. Wearing cotton gloves at night may prevent skin damage from scratching. To control itching and stress, you may need to take medicines by mouth, such as: Antihistamines, Other oral medicines that control itch or pain,  Steroids may be injected directly into the skin patches to reduce itching and irritation. You may need to take antidepressants and tranquilizers if the cause of your itching is emotional. Other measures include: Counseling to help you realize the importance of not scratching, Stress management, Behavior modification, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002389-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Lichen simplex chronicus ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can control LSC by reducing itch and controlling scratching. The condition may return or move to different areas on the skin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002389-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Lichen simplex chronicus ?</Question>
			<Answer>These complications of LSC can occur: Bacterial and fungal skin infection, Permanent changes in skin color, Permanent scar, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002389-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Lichen simplex chronicus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: Symptoms get worse, You develop new symptoms, especially signs of skin infection such as pain, redness, drainage from the area, or fever , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>