<Document id="0002168" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002657.htm">
 
<Focus>Indomethacin overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0572149</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Indocin</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002168-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Indomethacin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Indomethacin is a type of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug. It is used to relieve pain, swelling, and inflammation. Indomethacin overdose occurs when someone takes more than the normal or recommended amount of this medicine. This can be by accident or on purpose. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with has an  overdose , call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002168-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Indomethacin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Below are symptoms of an indomethacin overdose in different parts of the body. EYES, EARS, NOSE, AND THROAT Blurred vision ,  Ringing in the ears ,  BLADDER AND KIDNEYS Little or no urine output,  HEART AND BLOOD Chest pain,  High  or  low blood pressure , Increased heart rate,  STOMACH AND INTESTINES Diarrhea, Nausea (common), Possible bleeding in the stomach and intestines, Stomach pain, Vomiting (common, sometimes with blood),  LUNGS AND AIRWAYS Difficulty breathing, Wheezing,  NERVOUS SYSTEM Headache,  Agitation ,  Coma  (decreased level of consciousness and lack of responsiveness) in severe overdoses,  Confusion , Delirium (person is not making sense),  Drowsiness , Fatigue and weakness, Numbness and tingling, Seizures in severe overdoses,  Unsteadiness ,  SKIN Blistering rash, Bruising, Sweating, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002168-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Indomethacin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002168-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Indomethacin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on how much indomethacin was swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster&#160;the medical help is received, the better the chance for recovery. A mild overdose of this medicine does not usually cause serious problems. There may be some stomach pain and vomiting (possibly with blood). However, a large amount of internal bleeding is possible, and a blood transfusion may be needed. Endoscopy may be needed to stop the internal bleeding. In rare cases, there can be ringing in the ears and a bad headache. But these symptoms will likely pass as well. If kidney damage is severe, dialysis (kidney machine) may be needed until kidney function returns. In some cases, the damage is permanent. A large overdose can be very harmful to children and adults. Death may occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002168-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Indomethacin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on how much indomethacin was swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster&#160;the medical help is received, the better the chance for recovery. A mild overdose of this medicine does not usually cause serious problems. There may be some stomach pain and vomiting (possibly with blood). However, a large amount of internal bleeding is possible, and a blood transfusion may be needed. Endoscopy may be needed to stop the internal bleeding. In rare cases, there can be ringing in the ears and a bad headache. But these symptoms will likely pass as well. If kidney damage is severe, dialysis (kidney machine) may be needed until kidney function returns. In some cases, the damage is permanent. A large overdose can be very harmful to children and adults. Death may occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>