<Document id="0002096" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001021.htm">
 
<Focus>Hyphema</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0020581</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002096-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hyphema is blood in the front area (anterior chamber) of the eye. The blood collects behind the cornea and in front of the iris.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002096-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hyphema is most often caused by trauma to the eye. Other causes of bleeding in the front chamber of the eye include: Blood vessel abnormality, Cancer of the eye, Severe inflammation of the  iris , Advanced  diabetes , Blood disorders such as  sickle cell anemia , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002096-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Bleeding in the anterior chamber of the eye,  Eye pain , Light sensitivity,  Vision abnormalities ,  You may not be able to see a small hyphema when looking at your eye in the mirror. With a total hyphema, the collection of blood will block the view of the iris and pupil.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002096-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>You may need the following tests and exams: Eye exam, Intraocular pressure measurement ( tonometry ),  Ultrasound  testing , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002096-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment may not be needed in mild cases. The blood is absorbed in a few days. The outcome of the condition will likely be much worse if bleeding comes back or worsens, especially within 3 to 5 days. The health care provider may recommend the following to cut down the chance that there will be more bleeding: Bed rest, Eye patching, Sedating medicines ,  You may need to use eye drops to decrease the inflammation or lower the pressure in your eye. The eye doctor may need to remove the blood surgically, especially if pressure in the eye is very high or the blood is slow to absorb again. You may need to stay in a hospital.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002096-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome depends upon the amount of injury to the eye. People with  sickle cell disease  are more likely to have eye complications and must be watched closely. People with diabetes will probably need laser treatment for the problem. Severe vision loss can occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002096-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Acute glaucoma , Impaired vision, Recurring bleeding , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002096-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if you notice blood in the front of the eye or if you have an eye injury. You will need to be examined and treated by an eye doctor right away, especially if you have decreased vision.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002096-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Hyphema ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many eye injuries can be prevented by wearing safety goggles or other protective eye wear. Always wear eye protection while playing sports, such as racquetball, or contact sports, such as basketball.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>