<Document id="0002378" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001655.htm">
 
<Focus>Lesch-Nyhan syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0023374</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002378-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lesch-Nyhan syndrome is a disorder that is passed down through families (inherited). It affects how the body builds and breaks down purines. Purines are a normal part of human tissue that help make up the body's genetic blueprint. They are also found in many different foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002378-2" qtype="causes">What causes Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lesch-Nyhan syndrome is passed down as an X-linked, or  sex-linked trait . It occurs mostly in boys. People with this syndrome are missing or severely lacking an enzyme called hypoxanthine guanine phosphoribosyltransferase (HPRT). The body needs this substance to recycle purines. Without it, abnormally high levels of  uric acid  build up in the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002378-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Too much uric acid can cause gout-like swelling in some of the joints. In some cases, kidney and bladder stones develop. People with Lesch-Nyhan have delayed motor development followed by abnormal movements and increased reflexes. A striking feature of Lesch-Nyhan syndrome is self-destructive behavior, including chewing off fingertips and lips. It is unknown how the disease causes these problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002378-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>There may be a family history of this condition. The health care provider will perform a physical exam. The exam may show: Increased reflexes,  Spasticity  (having spasms),  Blood and urine tests may show high uric acid levels. A  skin biopsy  may show decreased levels of the HPRT1 enzyme.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002378-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>No specific treatment exists for Lesch-Nyhan syndrome. Medicine for treating gout can lower uric acid levels. However, treatment does not improve the nervous system outcome (for example, having increased reflexes and spasms). Some symptoms may be relieved with these medicines: Carbidopa/levodopa, Diazepam, Phenobarbital, Haloperidol,  Self-harm can be reduced by removal of teeth or by using a protective mouth guard designed by a dentist. You can help a person with this syndrome using stress-reduction and positive behavioral techniques.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002378-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome is likely to be poor. People with this syndrome usually need help walking and sitting. Most need a wheelchair.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002378-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Severe, progressive disability is likely.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002378-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if signs of this illness appear in your child or if there is a history of Lesch-Nyhan syndrome in your family.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002378-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Lesch-Nyhan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling  for prospective parents with a family history of Lesch-Nyhan syndrome is recommended. Testing can be done to see if a woman is a carrier of this syndrome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>