<Document id="0002667" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003119.htm">
 
<Focus>Morning sickness</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0312416</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Nausea in the morning - females</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Vomiting in the morning - females</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nausea during pregnancy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pregnancy nausea</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pregnancy vomiting</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Vomiting during pregnancy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002667-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Morning sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Morning sickness is  nausea and vomiting  that can occur at any time of the day during pregnancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002667-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Morning sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Morning sickness is very common. Most pregnant women have at least some nausea, and about one third have vomiting. Morning sickness most often begins during the first month of pregnancy and continues through the 14th to 16th week (3rd or 4th month). Some women have nausea and vomiting through their  entire pregnancy . Morning sickness does not hurt the baby in any way unless you lose weight, such as with  severe vomiting . Mild weight loss during the first trimester is not uncommon when women have moderate symptoms, and is not harmful to the baby. The amount of morning sickness during one pregnancy does not predict how you will feel in future pregnancies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002667-3" qtype="causes">What causes Morning sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of morning sickness is unknown. It may be caused by hormone changes or lower blood sugar during early pregnancy. Emotional stress, fatigue, traveling, or some foods can make the problem worse. Nausea in pregnancy is more common and can be worse with twins or triplets.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002667-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Morning sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Morning sickness is very common. Most pregnant women have at least some nausea, and about one third have vomiting. Morning sickness most often begins during the first month of pregnancy and continues through the 14th to 16th week (3rd or 4th month). Some women have nausea and vomiting through their  entire pregnancy . Morning sickness does not hurt the baby in any way unless you lose weight, such as with  severe vomiting . Mild weight loss during the first trimester is not uncommon when women have moderate symptoms, and is not harmful to the baby. The amount of morning sickness during one pregnancy does not predict how you will feel in future pregnancies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002667-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Morning sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: Morning sickness does not improve, despite trying home remedies., Nausea and vomiting continue beyond your 4th month of pregnancy. This happens to some women. In most cases this is normal, but you should have it checked out., You  vomit blood  or material that looks like coffee grounds. (Call immediately.), You vomit more than 3 times per day or you cannot keep food or liquid down., Your urine appears to be concentrated and dark, or you urinate very infrequently., You have excessive weight loss. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002667-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Morning sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>