<Document id="0003348" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000648.htm">
 
<Focus>Recognizing teen depression</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0349217</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011570</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011581</CUI>
			<CUI>C0344315</CUI>
			<CUI>C1579931</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003348-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Recognizing teen depression ?</Question>
			<Answer>One in five teenagers have  depression  at some point. Your teen may be depressed if they are feeling sad, blue, unhappy, or down in the dumps. Depression is a serious problem, even more so if these feelings have taken over your teen's life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003348-2" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Recognizing teen depression? ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003348-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Recognizing teen depression ?</Question>
			<Answer>If your teen is depressed, you may see some of the following common symptoms of depression. If these symptoms last for 2 weeks or longer, talk to your teen's health care provider. Frequent irritability with sudden bursts of anger., More sensitive to criticism., Complaints of headaches, stomach aches or other body problems. Your teen may go to the nurse's office at school a lot., Withdrawal from people like parents or some friends., Not enjoying activities they usually like., Feeling tired for much of the day., Sad or blue feelings most of the time. ,  Notice changes in your teen's daily routines that can be a sign of depression. Your teen's daily routines can change when they are depressed. You may notice that your teen has: Trouble sleeping or is sleeping more than normal, A change in eating habits, such as not being hungry or eating more than usual, A hard time concentrating, Problems making decisions ,  Changes in your teen's behavior may also be a sign of depression. They could be having problems at home or school: Drop in school grades, attendance, not doing homework, High-risk behaviors, such as reckless driving, unsafe sex, or shoplifting, Pulling away from family and friends and spends more time alone, Drinking or using drugs ,  Teens with depression may also have: Anxiety disorders ,  Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD) ,  Bipolar disorder , Eating disorders ( bulimia  or  anorexia ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>