<Document id="0003064" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002597.htm">
 
<Focus>Phenothiazine overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0573080</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003064-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Phenothiazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Phenothiazines are medicines used to treat serious mental and emotional disorders, and to reduce nausea. This article discusses an overdose of phenothiazines.  Overdose  occurs when someone takes more than the normal or recommended amount of a certain substance. This can be by accident or on purpose. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with overdoses, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003064-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Phenothiazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Below are symptoms of a phenothiazine overdose in different parts of the body. AIRWAYS AND LUNGS No breathing, Rapid breathing, Shallow breathing ,  BLADDER AND KIDNEYS Difficult or slow urination, Inability to completely empty the bladder (urinary retention) ,  EYES, EARS, NOSE, MOUTH, AND THROAT Blurred vision , Difficulty swallowing, Drooling, Dry mouth, Nasal congestion, Small or large pupils, Sores in the mouth, on the tongue or in the throat, Yellow eyes (icterus) ,  HEART AND BLOOD Low blood pressure (severe), Pounding heartbeat, Rapid heartbeat ,  MUSCLES AND JOINTS Muscle spasms, Muscle stiffness, Rapid, involuntary movements of the face (chewing, blinking, grimaces, and tongue movements) ,  NERVOUS SYSTEM Agitation, irritability,  confusion , Convulsions (seizures), Disorientation,  coma  (lack of responsiveness), Drowsiness, Fever, Low body temperature, Restlessness linked with repeated foot shuffling, rocking, or pacing ( akathisia ), Tremor, motor tics that the person cannot control ( dystonia ), Uncoordinated movement, slow movement, or shuffling (with long-term use or overuse), Weakness ,  REPRODUCTIVE SYSTEM Changes in menstrual patterns ,  SKIN Rash, Sun sensitivity, rapid sunburn, Skin color changes ,  STOMACH AND INTESTINES Constipation , Loss of appetite, Nausea,  Some of these symptoms may occur, even when the medicine is taken properly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003064-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Phenothiazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003064-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Phenothiazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recovery depends on the amount of damage. Survival past 2 days is usually a good sign. Nervous system symptoms may be permanent. The most serious side effects are usually due to damage to the heart. If heart damage can be stabilized, recovery is likely. Life threatening heart rhythm disturbances may be difficult to treat, and may result in death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003064-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Phenothiazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recovery depends on the amount of damage. Survival past 2 days is usually a good sign. Nervous system symptoms may be permanent. The most serious side effects are usually due to damage to the heart. If heart damage can be stabilized, recovery is likely. Life threatening heart rhythm disturbances may be difficult to treat, and may result in death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>