<Document id="0003630" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000222.htm">
 
<Focus>Small bowel bacterial overgrowth</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238427</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Overgrowth - intestinal bacteria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bacterial overgrowth - intestine</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003630-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Small bowel bacterial overgrowth ?</Question>
			<Answer>Small bowel bacterial overgrowth is a condition in which very large numbers of bacteria grow in the small intestine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003630-2" qtype="causes">What causes Small bowel bacterial overgrowth ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of the time, unlike the large intestine, the small intestine does not have a large number of bacteria. Excess bacteria in the small intestine may use up the nutrients needed by the body. As a result, a person may become  malnourished .  The breakdown of nutrients by the excess bacteria can also damage the lining of the small intestine. This can make it even harder for the body to absorb nutrients. Conditions that can lead to overgrowth of bacteria in the small intestine include:  Complications of diseases or surgery that create pouches or blockages in the small intestine.  Crohn disease  is one of these conditions., Diseases that lead to decreased movement of the small bowel, such as  diabetes  and  scleroderma ., Immunodeficiency, such as  AIDS  or immunoglobulin deficiency.,  Short bowel syndrome  caused by surgical removal of the small intestine., Small bowel diverticulosis, in which small, or, at times, large sacs occur in the wall of the intestine. These sacs allow too many bacteria to grow., Surgical procedures that create a loop of small intestine where excess bacteria can grow. An example is a Billroth II type of stomach removal ( gastrectomy ). , Some cases of irritable bowel syndrome (IBS)., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003630-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Small bowel bacterial overgrowth ?</Question>
			<Answer>The most common symptoms are: 
 Abdominal fullness
 , 
 Abdominal pain and cramps
 , 
 Bloating
 , 
 Diarrhea (most often watery)
 , 
 Gassiness
 ,  Other symptoms may include: 
 
 Fatty stool
 
 , 
 Weight loss
 , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003630-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Small bowel bacterial overgrowth ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask about your medical history. Tests may include: Blood chemistry tests (such as albumin level), Complete blood count ( CBC ),  Fecal fat test , Small intestine  endoscopy , Vitamin levels in the blood, Small intestine biopsy or culture, Special breath tests, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003630-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Small bowel bacterial overgrowth ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goal is to treat the cause of the bacterial overgrowth. Treatment may include: Antibiotics, Medicines that speed intestinal movement, Intravenous (IV) fluids, Nutrition given through a vein (total parenteral nutrition or TPN) in a malnourished person,  A lactose-free diet can be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003630-6" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Small bowel bacterial overgrowth ?</Question>
			<Answer>Severe cases lead to malnutrition. Other possible complications include: Dehydration ,  Excess bleeding or other problems due to vitamin deficiency ,  Liver disease ,  Osteomalacia  or  osteoporosis , Inflammation of the intestine, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>