<Document id="0003106" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002841.htm">
 
<Focus>Plant fertilizer poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032343</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Household plant food poisoning</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Plant food - household - poisoning</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003106-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Plant fertilizer poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Plant fertilizers and household plant foods are used to improve plant growth. Poisoning can occur if someone swallows these products. Plant fertilizers are mildly poisonous if small amounts are swallowed. Larger amounts can be harmful to children. Touching a large amount of plant fertilizer may cause severe burns. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003106-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Plant fertilizer poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of plant fertilizer poisoning include: Gray or blue-colored fingernails, lips, or palms of the hand, Burning skin, Burning of the throat, nose, and eyes, Dizziness, Fainting, Itchy skin,  Low blood pressure  (shock),  Seizures , Shortness of breath, Skin redness, Stomach pain, Stomach upset (nausea, vomiting, cramps), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003106-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Plant fertilizer poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003106-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Plant fertilizer poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fertilizers can be dangerous in large amounts. They will affect the amount of oxygen that your brain and other organs receive. How well someone does depends on how severe the poisoning is and how quickly treatment is received. The faster medical help is given, the better the chance for recovery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003106-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Plant fertilizer poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fertilizers can be dangerous in large amounts. They will affect the amount of oxygen that your brain and other organs receive. How well someone does depends on how severe the poisoning is and how quickly treatment is received. The faster medical help is given, the better the chance for recovery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>