<Document id="0003938" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002856.htm">
 
<Focus>Tick bite</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0241407</CUI>
			<CUI>C0005658</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003938-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tick bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ticks are bugs that can attach to you as you brush past bushes, plants, and grass. Once on you, ticks often move to a warm, moist place on your body, like the armpits, groin, and hair. There, they typically attach firmly to your skin and begin to draw blood. Avoiding ticks is important because they can infect you with bacteria and other organisms that cause illness. Ticks can be fairly large, about the size of a pencil eraser, or so small that they are almost impossible to see. There are about 850 different types of ticks. Most tick bites are harmless, but some can cause mild to serious health conditions. This article describes the effects of a tick bite. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage a tick bite. If you or someone you are with is bitten by a tick, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003938-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tick bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Watch for symptoms of tick-borne diseases in the weeks after a tick bite. These include muscle or joint aches, stiff neck, headache, weakness, fever, swollen lymph nodes, and other flu-like symptoms. Watch for a red spot or rash starting at the site of the bite (called "erythema migrans"). The symptoms below are from the bite itself, not from the diseases a bite may cause. Some of the symptoms are caused by one variety of tick or another, but may not be common to all ticks. Stopped breathing, Difficulty breathing, Blisters, Rash, Severe pain at site, lasting several weeks (from some kinds of ticks), Swelling at site (from some kinds of ticks),  Weakness ,  Uncoordinated movement , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003938-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Tick bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003938-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tick bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>After tick removal and skin cleansing, observe the area for the development of a circular rash called "erythema migrans" for up to 30 days following a tick bite. Contact your health care provider right away if a rash develops. A tick usually has to be attached for 2 to 3 days before transmitting Lyme disease, so removal of the tick within that time often prevents Lyme transmission. Other infections may occur earlier from a tick bite. Most tick bites are harmless. The outcome will depend on what type of infection the tick may have been carrying and how soon appropriate treatment was started. If you are bitten by a tick that carried a disease, long-term health effects may occur months or even years later. Personal protection against bites may be achieved by avoiding areas where ticks are known to be present and applying insect repellents. To protect yourself against ticks, try to stay away from areas where ticks are known to live. If you are in an area that harbors ticks, apply insect repellant to your body and wear protective clothing. Examine your skin for signs of tick bites or ticks after your travels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003938-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tick bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>After tick removal and skin cleansing, observe the area for the development of a circular rash called "erythema migrans" for up to 30 days following a tick bite. Contact your health care provider right away if a rash develops. A tick usually has to be attached for 2 to 3 days before transmitting Lyme disease, so removal of the tick within that time often prevents Lyme transmission. Other infections may occur earlier from a tick bite. Most tick bites are harmless. The outcome will depend on what type of infection the tick may have been carrying and how soon appropriate treatment was started. If you are bitten by a tick that carried a disease, long-term health effects may occur months or even years later. Personal protection against bites may be achieved by avoiding areas where ticks are known to be present and applying insect repellents. To protect yourself against ticks, try to stay away from areas where ticks are known to live. If you are in an area that harbors ticks, apply insect repellant to your body and wear protective clothing. Examine your skin for signs of tick bites or ticks after your travels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>