<Document id="0003060" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002526.htm">
 
<Focus>Phencyclidine overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2919094</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>PCP overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Angel dust overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sernyl overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003060-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Phencyclidine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Phencyclidine, or  PCP , is an illegal street drug. It can cause hallucinations and severe agitation. This article discusses overdose due to PCP. An overdose is when someone takes more than the normal or recommended amount of something, usually a drug. An overdose may result in serious, harmful symptoms or death. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual  overdose . If you or someone you are with overdoses, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003060-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Phencyclidine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of PCP overdose include: Agitation  (overly excited, violent behavior),  Altered state of consciousness , Catatonic trance (person does not talk, move, or react),  Coma ,  Convulsions  or seizures, Hallucinations, High blood pressure,  Side-to-side eye movements &#160;(nystagmus), Psychosis (loss of contact with reality),  Uncontrolled movement ,  Lack of coordination ,  People who have used PCP can be dangerous to themselves and others. DO NOT try to approach an agitated person who you think has used PCP. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003060-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Phencyclidine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003060-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Phencyclidine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome depends on several factors, including: The amount of PCP in the body, The time between taking the drug and receiving treatment,  Recovery from the  psychotic  state may take several weeks. The person should be in a quiet, darkened room. Long-term effects may include kidney failure and seizures. Repeated PCP use may cause long-term psychiatric problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003060-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Phencyclidine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome depends on several factors, including: The amount of PCP in the body, The time between taking the drug and receiving treatment,  Recovery from the  psychotic  state may take several weeks. The person should be in a quiet, darkened room. Long-term effects may include kidney failure and seizures. Repeated PCP use may cause long-term psychiatric problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>