<Document id="0003361" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001350.htm">
 
<Focus>Relapsing fever</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0424755</CUI>
			<CUI>C0035021</CUI>
			<CUI>C0015967</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tick-borne relapsing fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Louse-borne relapsing fever</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003361-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Relapsing fever is a bacterial infection transmitted by a louse or tick. It is characterized by repeated episodes of fever.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003361-2" qtype="causes">What causes Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Relapsing fever is an infection caused by several species of bacteria in the borrelia family. There are two major forms of relapsing fever: Tick-borne relapsing fever (TBRF) is transmitted by the ornithodoros tick. It occurs in Africa, Spain, Saudi Arabia, Asia, and certain areas in the western United States and Canada. The bacteria species associated with TBRF are  Borrelia duttonii ,  Borrelia hermsii , and  Borrelia parkeri ., Louse-borne relapsing fever (LBRF) is transmitted by  body lice . It is most common in Asia, Africa, and Central and South America. The bacteria species associated with LBRF is  Borrelia recurrentis . ,  Sudden fever occurs within 2 weeks of infection. In TBRF, multiple episodes of fever occur, and each may last up to 3 days. People may not have a fever for up to 2 weeks, and then it returns., In LBRF, the fever commonly lasts 3 to 6 days. It is often followed by a single, milder episode of fever.,  In both forms, the fever episode may end in "crisis." This consists of shaking chills, followed by intense sweating, falling body temperature, and low blood pressure. This stage may result in death. In the United States, TBRF often occurs west of the Mississippi River, particularly in the mountains of the West and the high deserts and plains of the Southwest. In the mountains of California, Utah, Arizona, New Mexico, Colorado, Oregon, and Washington, infections are usually caused by  Borrelia hermsii  and are often picked up in cabins in forests. The risk may now extend into the southeastern United States. LBRF is mainly a disease of the developing world. It is currently seen in Ethiopia and Sudan. Famine, war, and the movement of refugee groups can result in clusters of LBRF epidemics.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003361-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of relapsing fever include: Bleeding,  Coma , Headache, Joint aches, muscle aches, Nausea and vomiting, Sagging on one side of the face (facial droop), Stiff neck, Sudden high fever, shaking chills,  seizure , Vomiting, Weakness, unsteadiness while walking , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003361-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Relapsing fever should be suspected if someone coming from a high-risk area has repeated episodes of fever. This is largely true if the fever is followed by a "crisis" stage, and if the person may have been exposed to lice or soft-bodied ticks. Tests that may be done include: Blood smear to determine the cause of the infection, Blood antibody tests (sometimes used, but their usefulness is limited) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003361-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Antibiotics including penicillin and tetracycline are used to treat this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003361-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with this condition who have developed a coma, heart inflammation, liver problems, or pneumonia are more likely to die. With early treatment, the death rate is reduced.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003361-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>These complications may occur: Drooping of the face, Coma, Liver problems, Inflammation of the thin tissue that surrounds the brain and spinal cord, Inflammation of the heart muscle, which may lead to irregular heart rate, Pneumonia, Seizures, Stupor, Shock related to taking antibiotics (Jarisch-Herxheimer reaction, in which the rapid death of very large numbers of borrelia bacteria causes shock), Weakness, Widespread bleeding , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003361-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider right away if you develop a fever after returning from a trip. Possible infections need to be investigated in a timely manner.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003361-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Relapsing fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wearing clothing that fully covers the arms and legs when you are outdoors can help prevent TBRF infection. Insect repellent such as DEET on the skin and clothing also work. Tick and lice control in high-risk areas is another important public health measure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>