<Document id="0003770" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000792.htm">
 
<Focus>Substance use - amphetamines</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0237123</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Substance abuse - amphetamines</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Drug abuse - amphetamines</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Drug use - amphetamines</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003770-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Substance use - amphetamines ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amphetamines are drugs. They can be legal or illegal. They are legal when they are prescribed by a doctor and used to treat health problems such as  obesity ,  narcolepsy , or  attention deficit hyperactivity disorder  (ADHD). Using amphetamines can lead to addiction. Amphetamines are illegal when they are used without a prescription to get high or improve performance. In this case, they are known as street, or recreational drugs, and using them can lead to addiction. This article describes this aspect of amphetamines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003770-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Substance use - amphetamines ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amphetamines are drugs. They can be legal or illegal. They are legal when they are prescribed by a doctor and used to treat health problems such as  obesity ,  narcolepsy , or  attention deficit hyperactivity disorder  (ADHD). Using amphetamines can lead to addiction. Amphetamines are illegal when they are used without a prescription to get high or improve performance. In this case, they are known as street, or recreational drugs, and using them can lead to addiction. This article describes this aspect of amphetamines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003770-6" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Substance use - amphetamines ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment begins with recognizing there is a problem. Once you decide you want to do something about your drug use, the next step is to get help and support. Treatment programs use behavior change techniques through counseling (talk therapy). The goal is to help you understand your behaviors and why you use amphetamines. Involving family and friends during counseling can help support you and keep you from going back to using (relapsing). If you have severe withdrawal symptoms, you may need to stay at a live-in treatment program. There, your health and safety can be monitored as you recover. At this time, there is no medicine that can help reduce the use of amphetamines by blocking their effects. But, scientists are researching such medicines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003770-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Substance use - amphetamines ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>