<Document id="0003151" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001477.htm">
 
<Focus>Polymorphous light eruption</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0031736</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Polymorphic light eruption</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Photodermatosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PMLE</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003151-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Polymorphous light eruption ?</Question>
			<Answer>Polymorphous light eruption (PMLE) is a common skin reaction in people who are sensitive to sunlight (ultraviolet light).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003151-2" qtype="causes">What causes Polymorphous light eruption ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of PMLE is unknown. However, it may be genetic. Health care providers think it is a type of delayed  allergic reaction . It is common among young women who live in moderate (temperate) climates.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003151-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Polymorphous light eruption ?</Question>
			<Answer>Polymorphous means taking on different forms, and eruption means rash. As the name suggests, symptoms of PMLE are rash-like and are different in different people.  PMLE most often occurs in spring and early summer on areas of the body exposed to the sun. Symptoms usually appear within 1 to 4 days after exposure to sunlight. They include any of the following: Small bumps ( papules ) or  blisters , Redness or scaling of the skin, Itching or burning of the affected skin, Swelling, or even blisters (not often seen), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003151-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Polymorphous light eruption ?</Question>
			<Answer>Steroid creams or ointments containing vitamin D may be prescribed by your provider. They are used 2 or 3 times a day at the start of the eruption. Steroid or other types of pills may be used for more severe cases. Phototherapy may also be prescribed. Phototherapy is a medical treatment in which your skin is carefully exposed to ultraviolet light. This may help your skin become used to (sensitized to) the sun.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003151-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Polymorphous light eruption ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many people become less sensitive to sunlight&#160;over time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003151-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Polymorphous light eruption ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call for an appointment with your provider if PMLE symptoms do not respond to treatments.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003151-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Polymorphous light eruption ?</Question>
			<Answer>Protecting your skin from the sun  can help prevent PMLE symptoms: Avoid sun exposure during hours of peak sun ray intensity., Use sunscreen. Sun protection with broad spectrum sunblock that works against UVA rays is important., Apply generous amounts of sunscreen with a sun protection factor (SPF) of at least 30. Pay special attention to your face, nose, ears, and shoulders., Apply sunscreen 30 minutes before sun exposure so that it has time to penetrate the skin. Re-apply after swimming and every 2 hours while you are outdoors., Wear a sun hat., Wear sunglasses with UV protection., Use a lip balm with sunscreen., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>