<Document id="0003986" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000317.htm">
 
<Focus>Toxic nodular goiter</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0342127</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Toxic multinodular goiter</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Plummer disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003986-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>Toxic nodular goiter involves an enlarged thyroid gland. The gland&#160;contains&#160;areas that have increased in size and formed nodules. One or more of these nodules produce too much thyroid hormone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003986-2" qtype="causes">What causes Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>Toxic nodular goiter starts from an existing  simple goiter . It occurs most often in older adults. Risk factors include being female and over 55 years old. This disorder is rare in children. Most people who develop it have had a goiter with nodules for many years. Sometimes the thyroid gland is only slightly enlarged, and the goiter was not already diagnosed. Sometimes, people with toxic multinodular goiter will develop high thyroid levels for the first time. This may occur after: Taking iodine through a vein (intravenously) or by mouth. The iodine may be used as contrast for a  CT scan  or  heart catheterization  (most common), Taking medicines that contain iodine, such as amiodarone, Moving from a country with iodine deficiency to a country with a lot of iodine in the diet, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003986-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include any of the following: Fatigue , Frequent bowel movements,  Heat intolerance , Increased appetite, Increased sweating, Irregular menstrual period (in women),  Muscle cramps , Nervousness,  Restlessness , Weight loss,  Older adults may have symptoms that are less specific. These may include: Weakness and fatigue, Palpitations and chest pain or pressure, Changes in memory and mood,  Toxic nodular goiter does not cause the bulging eyes that can occur with Graves disease. Graves disease is an autoimmune disorder that leads to an overactive thyroid gland (hyperthyroidism).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003986-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>A  physical exam  may show one or many nodules in the thyroid. The thyroid is often enlarged. There may be a  rapid heart rate  or a tremor. Other tests that may be done include: Serum thyroid hormone levels ( T3 ,  T4 )
   ,  Serum TSH  (thyroid stimulating hormone)
   ,  Thyroid uptake and scan  or  radioactive iodine uptake ,  Thyroid ultrasound , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003986-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>Beta-blockers can control some of the symptoms of hyperthyroidism until thyroid hormone levels in the body are under control. Certain medicines can block or change how the thyroid gland uses iodine. These may be used to control the overactive thyroid gland in any of the following cases: Before surgery or radioiodine therapy occurs, As a long term treatment,  Radioiodine therapy may be used. Radioactive iodine is given by mouth. It concentrates in the overactive thyroid tissue and causes damage. In rare cases, thyroid replacement is needed afterward. Surgery to remove the thyroid may be done when: Very large goiter or a goiter is causing symptoms by making it hard to breathe or swallow, Thyroid cancer is present, Rapid treatment is needed, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003986-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>Toxic nodular goiter is mainly a disease of older adults. So, other  chronic  health problems may affect the outcome of this condition. An older adult may be less able to tolerate the effect of the disease on the heart. However, the condition is often treatable with medicines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003986-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>Heart complications: Heart failure , Irregular heartbeat ( atrial fibrillation ), 
   Rapid heart rate
   ,  Other complications: 
   Bone loss leading to  osteoporosis ,  Thyroid crisis or storm is a sudden worsening of hyperthyroidism symptoms. It may occur with infection or stress. Thyroid crisis may cause: 
   Abdominal pain
   , 
   Decreased mental alertness
   , 
   Fever
   ,  People with this condition need to go to the hospital right away. Complications of having a very large goiter may include difficulty breathing or swallowing. This is due to pressure on the airway passage (trachea) or esophagus, which lies behind the thyroid.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003986-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your health care provider if you have symptoms of this disorder listed above. Follow your provider's instructions for follow-up visits.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003986-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Toxic nodular goiter ?</Question>
			<Answer>To prevent toxic nodular goiter, treat hyperthyroidism and simple goiter as your provider suggests.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>