<Document id="0003785" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000199.htm">
 
<Focus>Superficial thrombophlebitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1510431</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Thrombophlebitis - superficial</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003785-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Thrombophlebitis is a swollen or inflamed vein due to a  blood clot . Superficial refers to veins just below the skin's surface.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003785-2" qtype="causes">What causes Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>This condition may occur after injury to the vein. It may also occur after having medicines given into your veins. If you have a high risk for blood clots, you may develop them for no apparent reason.  Risks for thrombophlebitis include: Cancer or liver disease,  Deep vein thrombosis , Disorders that involve increased blood clotting (may be inherited), Infection, Pregnancy, Sitting or staying still for a prolonged period, Use of birth control pills, Swollen, twisted, and enlarged veins ( varicose veins ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003785-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include any of the following: Skin redness, inflammation, tenderness, or pain along a vein just below the skin, Warmth of the area,  Limb pain , Hardening of the vein , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003785-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will diagnose this condition based mainly on the appearance of the affected area. Frequent checks of the pulse, blood pressure, temperature, skin condition, and blood flow may be needed. Ultrasound &#160;of the blood vessels&#160;helps confirm the condition. If there are signs of an infection,  skin  or  blood cultures  may be done.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003785-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>To reduce discomfort and swelling, your provider may recommend that you: Wear  support stockings , if your leg is affected., Keep the affected leg or arm raised above heart level., Apply a warm compress to the area.,  If you have a catheter or IV line, it will likely be removed if it is the cause of the thrombophlebitis. Medicines called NSAIDs, such as ibuprofen,&#160;may be prescribed to reduce pain and swelling. If  clots in the deeper veins  are also present, your provider may prescribe medicines to thin your blood. These medicines are called anticoagulants. Antibiotics are prescribed if you have an infection. Surgical removal (phlebectomy),  stripping , or sclerotherapy of the affected vein may be needed. These treat large varicose veins or to prevent thrombophlebitis in high-risk people.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003785-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>This is usually a short-term condition that does not cause complications. Symptoms often go away in 1 to 2 weeks. Hardness of the vein may remain for much longer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003785-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications are rare. Possible problems may include the following: 
   Infections ( cellulitis )
   , Deep vein thrombosis, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003785-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if you develop symptoms of this condition. Also contact your provider if you already have the condition and your symptoms worsen or do not get better with treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003785-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Superficial thrombophlebitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>In the hospital, swollen or inflamed veins can be prevented by: The nurse regularly changing the location of your IV line and removing it if swelling, redness, or pain develop, Walking and staying active as soon as possible after surgery or during a long-term illness,  When possible, avoid keeping your legs and arms still for long periods. Move your legs often or take a stroll during long plane trips or car trips. Try to avoid sitting or lying down for long periods without getting up and moving about.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>