<Document id="0003197" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003153.htm">
 
<Focus>Premenstrual breast changes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0558236</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Premenstrual tenderness and swelling of the breasts</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Breast tenderness - premenstrual</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Breast swelling - premenstrual</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003197-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Premenstrual breast changes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Premenstrual swelling and tenderness of both breasts often occurs during the second half of the menstrual cycle.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003197-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Premenstrual breast changes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of premenstrual breast tenderness may range from mild to severe. Symptoms usually: Are most severe just before each menstrual period, Improve during or right after the menstrual period ,  Breast tissue may have a dense, bumpy, "cobblestone" feel to the fingers. This feel is usually more in the outer areas, particularly near the armpit. There may also be an off and on or ongoing sense of breast fullness with dull, heavy pain, and tenderness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003197-3" qtype="causes">What causes Premenstrual breast changes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hormone changes during the menstrual cycle may lead to breast swelling. More estrogen is made early in the cycle and it peaks just before mid-cycle. This causes the breast ducts to grow in size. The progesterone level peaks near the 21st day (in a 28-day cycle). This causes growth of the breast lobules (milk glands). Premenstrual breast swelling is often linked with: Premenstrual syndrome  (PMS),  Fibrocystic breast disease  (benign breast changes) ,  Premenstrual breast tenderness and swelling probably occur to some degree in nearly all women. More severe symptoms may occur in many women during their childbearing years. Symptoms may be less in women taking birth control pills. Risk factors may include: Family history, High-fat diet, Too much caffeine , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003197-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Premenstrual breast changes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of premenstrual breast tenderness may range from mild to severe. Symptoms usually: Are most severe just before each menstrual period, Improve during or right after the menstrual period ,  Breast tissue may have a dense, bumpy, "cobblestone" feel to the fingers. This feel is usually more in the outer areas, particularly near the armpit. There may also be an off and on or ongoing sense of breast fullness with dull, heavy pain, and tenderness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003197-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Premenstrual breast changes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you: Have new, unusual, or changing lumps in breast tissue, Have one-sided (unilateral) lumps in breast tissue, Do not know how to properly perform breast self-examination, Are a woman, age 40 years or older, and have never had a screening mammogram, Have discharge from your nipple, particularly if it is a bloody or brown discharge, Have symptoms that interfere with your ability to sleep, and diet changes and exercise have not helped, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003197-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Premenstrual breast changes ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>