<Document id="0003431" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000879.htm">
 
<Focus>Rosacea</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0035854</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Acne rosacea</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003431-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Rosacea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rosacea is a chronic skin problem that makes your face turn red. It may also cause swelling and skin sores that look like  acne .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003431-2" qtype="causes">What causes Rosacea ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause is not known. You may be more likely to have this if you are: Age 30 to 50, Fair-skinned, A woman,  Rosacea causes swelling of the blood vessels just under the skin. It may be linked with other skin disorders ( acne vulgaris ,  seborrhea ) or eye disorders ( blepharitis ,  keratitis ).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003431-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Rosacea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Redness of the face, Blushing or flushing easily, A lot of spider-like blood vessels (telangiectasia) of the face, Red nose (may also be  bulbous  in appearance), Acne-like skin sores that may ooze or crust, Burning or stinging feeling in the face, Irritated, bloodshot, watery eyes ,  The condition is less common in men, but the symptoms tend to be more severe.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003431-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Rosacea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can often diagnose rosacea by doing a physical exam and asking questions about your medical history.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003431-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Rosacea ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known cure for rosacea. Your provider will help you identify the things that make your symptoms worse. These are called triggers. Triggers vary from person to person. Avoiding your triggers may help you prevent or reduce flare-ups. Some things you can do to help ease or prevent symptoms include: Avoid sun exposure. Use sunscreen every day., Avoid a lot of activity in hot weather., Try to reduce stress. Try deep breathing, yoga, or other relaxation techniques., Limit spicy foods, alcohol, and hot beverages. ,  Other triggers may include wind, hot baths, cold weather, specific skin products, exercise, or other factors. Antibiotics taken by mouth or applied to the skin may control acne-like skin problems. Ask your provider., Isotretinoin is a strong drug that your provider might consider. It is used in people who have severe rosacea that hasn't improved after treatment with other medicines., Rosacea is not acne and will not improve with over-the-counter acne treatment.,  In very bad cases, laser surgery may help reduce the redness. Surgery to remove some swollen nose tissue may also improve your appearance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003431-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Rosacea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rosacea is a harmless condition, but it may cause you to be self-conscious or embarrassed. It cannot be cured, but may be controlled with treatment. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003431-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Rosacea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Lasting changes in appearance (for example, a red, swollen nose), Lower self-esteem , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>