<Document id="0003567" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003171.htm">
 
<Focus>Shoulder pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0037011</CUI>
			<CUI>C0423670</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pain - shoulder</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003567-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Shoulder pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Shoulder pain is any pain in or around the shoulder joint.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003567-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Shoulder pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>The shoulder is the most movable joint in the human body. A group of four muscles and their tendons, called the rotator cuff, give the shoulder its wide range of motion. Swelling, damage, or bone changes around the rotator cuff can cause shoulder pain. You may have pain when lifting the arm above your head or moving it forward or behind your back.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003567-3" qtype="causes">What causes Shoulder pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>The most common cause of shoulder pain occurs when rotator cuff tendons become trapped under the bony area in the shoulder. The tendons become inflamed or damaged. This condition is called  rotator cuff tendinitis  or bursitis. Shoulder pain may also be caused by: Arthritis  in the shoulder joint, Bone spurs in the shoulder area,  Bursitis , which is inflammation of a fluid-filled sac (bursa) that normally protects the joint and helps it move smoothly, Broken shoulder bone, Dislocation of the shoulder, Shoulder separation,  Frozen shoulder , which occurs when the muscles, tendons, and ligaments inside the shoulder become stiff, making movement difficult and painful, Overuse or injury of nearby tendons, such as the bicep muscles of the arms, Nerve injury that leads to abnormal shoulder movement, Tears of the rotator cuff tendons , Poor shoulder posture and mechanics,  Sometimes, shoulder pain may be due to a problem in another area of the body, such as the neck or lungs. This is called referred pain. There is usually pain at rest and no worsening of pain when moving the shoulder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003567-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Shoulder pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>The shoulder is the most movable joint in the human body. A group of four muscles and their tendons, called the rotator cuff, give the shoulder its wide range of motion. Swelling, damage, or bone changes around the rotator cuff can cause shoulder pain. You may have pain when lifting the arm above your head or moving it forward or behind your back.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003567-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Shoulder pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sudden left shoulder pain can sometimes be a sign of a  heart attack . Call 911 or the local emergency number if you have sudden pressure or crushing pain in your shoulder, especially if the pain runs from your chest to the left jaw, arm or neck, or occurs with shortness of breath,  dizziness , or  sweating . Go to the hospital emergency room if you have just had a severe injury and your shoulder is very painful, swollen, bruised, or bleeding. Call your provider if you have: Shoulder pain with a  fever , swelling, or redness, Significant pain even with moving the shoulder with the arm or by someone else, Pain for more than 2 to 4 weeks, even after home treatment, Swelling of the shoulder, Red or blue color of the skin of the shoulder area , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003567-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Shoulder pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>