<Document id="0003610" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003840.htm">
 
<Focus>Skin lesion biopsy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0221198</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003610-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Skin lesion biopsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>A skin lesion biopsy is when a small amount of skin is removed so it can be examined under a microscope. The skin is tested to look for skin conditions or diseases. A skin biopsy can help your health care provider diagnose or rule out problems such as skin cancer or  psoriasis .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003610-7" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Skin lesion biopsy? ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003610-8" qtype="considerations">What to do for Skin lesion biopsy ?</Question>
			<Answer>You will go home with a bandage over the area. The biopsy area may be tender for a few days afterward. You may have a small amount of bleeding. Depending on what type of biopsy you had, you will be given instructions on how to care for: The skin biopsy area,  Stitches , if you have them
   ,  Skin graft or flap , if you have one
   ,  The goal is to keep the area clean and dry. Be careful not to bump or stretch the skin near the area, which can cause bleeding. If you have stitches, they will be taken out in about 3 to 14 days. If you have moderate bleeding, apply pressure to the area for 10 minutes or so. If the bleeding does not stop, call your provider right away. You should also call your provider if you have signs of infection, such as: More redness, swelling, or pain, Drainage coming from or around the incision that is thick, tan, green, or yellow, or smells bad (pus), Fever,  Once the wound heals, you may have a scar.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>