<Document id="0003816" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001358.htm">
 
<Focus>Sydenham chorea</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0152113</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>St. Vitus dance</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003816-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sydenham chorea is a movement disorder that occurs after infection with specific bacteria called group A streptococcus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003816-2" qtype="causes">What causes Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sydenham chorea is caused by an infection with bacteria called group A streptococcus. This is the bacteria that cause  rheumatic fever  (RF) and  strep throat . Group A streptococcus bacteria can react with a part of the brain called the basal ganglia to cause this disorder. The basal ganglia are a set of structures deep in the brain. They help control movement, posture, and speech. Sydenham chorea is a major sign of acute RF. The person may currently or recently have had the disease. Sydenham chorea may be the only sign of RF in some people. Sydenham chorea occurs most often in girls before puberty, but may be seen in boys.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003816-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sydenham chorea mainly involves jerky, uncontrollable and purposeless movements of the hands, arms, shoulder, face, legs, and trunk. These movements look like twitches, and disappear during sleep. Other symptoms may include: Changes in handwriting, Loss of fine motor control, especially of the fingers and hands, Loss of emotional control, with bouts of inappropriate crying or laughing,  Symptoms of RF may be present. These may include:  High fever , Heart problem, Joint pain or swelling, Skin lumps or skin rashes, Nosebleeds, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003816-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam. The provider will ask questions about your symptoms. If a Group A streptococcus infection is suspected, tests will be done to confirm the infection. These include: Throat swab , Anti-DNAse B blood test, Antistreptolysin O (ASO) blood test,  Further testing may include: Blood tests such as  ESR ,  CBC , MRI or CT scan of the brain, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003816-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Antibiotics are used to kill the Group A streptococcus bacteria. The provider may also prescribe antibiotics to prevent future RF infections. This is called preventive antibiotics, or antibiotic prophylaxis. Severe movement or emotional symptoms may need to be treated with medicines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003816-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sydenham chorea usually clears up in a few months. In rare cases, an unusual form of Sydenham chorea may begin later in life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003816-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>No complications are expected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003816-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if your child develops uncontrollable or jerky movements, especially if the child has recently had a sore throat.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003816-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Sydenham chorea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pay careful attention to children's complaints of sore throats and get early treatment to prevent acute RF. If there is a family history of RF, be watchful, because your children may be more likely to develop this infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>