<Document id="0003555" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000654.htm">
 
<Focus>Shin splints - self-care</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1696469</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Lower leg pain - self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pain - shins - self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Anterior tibial pain - self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Medial tibial stress syndrome - self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MTSS - self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Exercise-induced leg pain - self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tibial periostitis - self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Posterior tibial shin splints - self-care</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003555-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Shin splints - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Shin splints occur when you have pain in the front of your lower leg. The pain of shin splints is from the inflammation of the muscles, tendons, and bone tissue around your shin. Shin splints are a common problem for runners, gymnasts, dancers, and military recruits. However, there are things you can do to heal from shin splints and prevent them from getting worse.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003555-2" qtype="causes">What causes Shin splints - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Shin splints are an overuse problem. You get shin splints from overloading your leg muscles, tendons or shin bone. Most often, the activity that causes the injury is high impact and repetitive exercise of your lower legs. This is why runners, dancers, and gymnasts often get shin splints. Common situations that cause shin splints are: Sudden change in activity level, whether it is in intensity or duration, Running, especially on hills. If you are a new runner, you are at greater risk for shin splints., Increasing your days of training., Increasing the intensity of training, or going a longer distance., Doing exercise that has frequent stops and starts, such as dancing, basketball, or military training.,  You are more at risk for shin splints if you: Have flat feet or very rigid foot arches., Work out on hard surfaces, such as running on the street or playing basketball or tennis on a hard court., Do not wear the proper shoes., Wear worn out shoes. Running shoes lose over half of their shock absorbing ability after 250 miles (400 kilometers) of use., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003555-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Shin splints - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Pain in one or both legs, Sharp or dull, aching pain in the front of your shin, Pain when you push on your shins, Pain that gets worse during and after exercise, Pain that gets better with rest,  If you have severe shin splints, your legs may hurt even when you are not walking. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003555-6" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Shin splints - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003555-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Shin splints - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>