<Document id="0003546" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002051.htm">
 
<Focus>Sex-linked recessive</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Inheritance - sex-linked recessive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Genetics - sex-linked recessive</Synonym>
		<Synonym>X-linked recessive</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003546-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Sex-linked recessive</Question>
			<Answer>X-linked recessive diseases most often occur in males. Males have only one X chromosome. A single recessive gene on that X chromosome will cause the disease. The Y chromosome is the other half of the XY gene pair in the male. However, the Y chromosome doesn't contain most of the genes of the X chromosome. Because of that, it doesn't protect the male. Diseases such as  hemophilia  and Duchenne  muscular dystrophy  occur from a recessive gene on the X chromosome. TYPICAL SCENARIOS In each pregnancy, if the mother is a carrier of a certain disease (she has only one abnormal X chromosome) and the father is not a carrier for the disease, the expected outcome is: 25% chance of a healthy boy, 25% chance of a boy with disease, 25% chance of a healthy girl, 25% chance of a carrier girl without disease ,  If the father has the disease and the mother is not a carrier, the expected outcomes are: 50% chance of a having a healthy boy, 50% chance of a having a girl without the disease who is a carrier,  This means that none of his children would actually show the signs of the disease, but the trait could be passed to his grandsons. X-LINKED RECESSIVE DISORDERS IN FEMALES Females can get an X-linked recessive disorder, but this is very rare. An abnormal gene on the X chromosome from each parent would be required, since a female has two X chromosomes. This could occur in the two scenarios below. In each pregnancy, if the mother is a carrier and the father has the disease, the expected outcomes are: 25% chance of a healthy boy, 25% chance of a boy with the disease, 25% chance of a carrier girl, 25% chance of a girl with the disease ,  If both the mother and the father have the disease, the expected outcomes are: 100% chance of the child having the disease, whether boy or girl ,  The odds of either of these two scenarios are so low that X-linked recessive diseases are sometimes referred to as male only diseases. However, this is not technically correct. Female carriers can have a normal X chromosome that is abnormally inactivated. This is called "skewed X-inactivation." These females may have symptoms similar to those of males, or they may have only mild symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>