<Document id="0003768" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001422.htm">
 
<Focus>Subdural effusion</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0038538</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003768-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Subdural effusion ?</Question>
			<Answer>A subdural effusion is a collection of cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) trapped between the surface of the brain and the outer lining of the brain (the dura matter). If this fluid becomes infected, the condition is called a subdural empyema.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003768-2" qtype="causes">What causes Subdural effusion ?</Question>
			<Answer>A subdural effusion is a rare complication of  meningitis  caused by bacteria. Subdural effusion is more common in infants. Subdural effusion may also occur after head trauma.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003768-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Subdural effusion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Outward curving of a baby's skull's soft spot ( bulging fontanelle ), Abnormally wide spaces in the bony joints of a baby's skull ( separated sutures ), Increased head circumference, Low energy ( lethargy ), Persistent fever,  Seizures , Vomiting, Weakness or loss of movement on both sides of the body, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003768-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Subdural effusion ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask about the symptoms. To detect the subdural effusion, tests that may be done include: CT scan of the head , 
   Head size (circumference) measurements
   ,  MRI scan of the head ,  Ultrasound  of the head
   , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003768-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Subdural effusion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Surgery to drain the effusion is often necessary. In rare cases, a permanent drainage device (shunt) is needed to drain fluid. Antibiotics may need to be given through a vein. Treatment may include: Surgery to drain the effusion, Drainage device, called a shunt, left in place for a short time or longer time, Antibiotics given through a vein to treat the infection, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003768-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Subdural effusion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Full recovery from a subdural effusion is expected. If nervous system problems continue, they are generally due to the meningitis, not the effusion. Long-term antibiotics are usually not needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003768-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Subdural effusion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications of surgery may include: 
   Bleeding
   , 
   Brain damage
   , 
   Infection
   , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003768-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Subdural effusion ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: 
  Your child has recently been treated for meningitis and symptoms continue
  , 
  New symptoms develop
  , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>