<Document id="0003764" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001616.htm">
 
<Focus>Subconjunctival hemorrhage</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0038534</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003764-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Subconjunctival hemorrhage is a bright red patch appearing in the white of the eye. This condition is one of several disorders called red eye.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003764-2" qtype="causes">What causes Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>The white of the eye (sclera) is covered with a thin layer of clear tissue called the bulbar  conjunctiva . A subconjunctival hemorrhage occurs when a small blood vessel breaks open and bleeds within the conjunctiva. The blood is often very visible, but since it is confined within the conjunctiva, it does not move and cannot be wiped away. The problem may occur without injury. It is often first noticed when you wake up and look in a mirror. Some things that may cause a subconjunctival hemorrhage include: Sudden increases in pressure in the head or neck, such as violent sneezing or coughing, Having  high blood pressure  or taking blood thinners, Rubbing the eyes, Viral infection, Certain eye surgeries or injuries,  A subconjunctival hemorrhage is common in newborn infants. In this case, the condition is thought to be caused by the pressure changes across the infant's body during childbirth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003764-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>A bright red patch appears on the white of the eye. The patch does not cause pain and there is no discharge from the eye. Vision does not change. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003764-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam and look at your eyes. Blood pressure should be tested. If you have other areas of bleeding or bruising, more specific tests may be needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003764-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>No treatment is needed. You should have your blood pressure checked regularly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003764-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>A subconjunctival hemorrhage most often goes away on its own in about 2 to 3 weeks. The white of the eye may look yellow as the problem goes away. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003764-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, there are no complications. Rarely, a total subconjunctival hemorrhage may be a sign of a serious vascular disorder in older people.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003764-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if a bright red patch appears on the white of the eye.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003764-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Subconjunctival hemorrhage ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known prevention.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>