<Document id="0003923" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007615.htm">
 
<Focus>Thrush in newborns</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0006849</CUI>
			<CUI>C1299921</CUI>
			<CUI>C0006840</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Candidiasis - oral - newborn</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Oral thrush - newborn</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fungal infection - mouth - newborn</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Candida - oral - newborn</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003923-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Thrush in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Thrush is a yeast infection of the tongue and mouth. This common infection can be passed between a mother and baby during breastfeeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003923-2" qtype="causes">What causes Thrush in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Certain germs normally live in our bodies. While most germs are harmless, some can cause infection.  Thrush occurs when too much of a yeast (a type of fungus) called  Candida albicans  grows in a baby's mouth. Germs called bacteria and fungi naturally grow in our bodies. Our immune system helps keep these germs in check. But babies do not have fully-formed immune systems. That makes it easier for too much yeast to grow.  Thrush often occurs when mother or baby has taken antibiotics. Antibiotics treat infections from bacteria. They can also kill good bacteria, and this allows yeast to grow. The yeast thrives in warm, moist areas. The baby's mouth and the mother's nipples are perfect places for a yeast infection.  Babies can also get a yeast infection on the diaper area at the same time. The yeast gets in the baby's stool and can cause a  diaper rash .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003923-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Thrush in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of thrush in the baby include: White, velvety sores in the mouth and on the tongue, Sores that may bleed when wiped, Redness in the mouth, Diaper rash, Mood changes, such as being very fussy, Refusing to nurse because of soreness ,  Some babies may not feel anything at all. Symptoms of thrush in the mother include: Deep-pink, cracked, and sore nipples, Tenderness and pain during and after nursing , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003923-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Thrush in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can often diagnose thrush by looking at your baby's mouth and tongue. The sores are easy to recognize.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003923-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Thrush in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your baby might not need any treatment. Thrush often goes away on its own in a few days. Your provider may prescribe antifungal medicine to treat thrush. You paint this medicine on your baby's mouth and tongue. If you have a yeast infection on your nipples, your provider may recommend an over-the-counter or prescription antifungal cream. You put this on your nipples to treat the infection. If both you and your baby have the infection, you both need to be treated at the same time. Otherwise, you can pass the infection back and forth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003923-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Thrush in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Thrush in babies is very common and can easily be treated. Let your provider know if thrush keeps coming back. It may be a sign of another health issue.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003923-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Thrush in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: Your baby has symptoms of thrush, Your baby refuses to eat, You have symptoms of a yeast infection on your nipples , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003923-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Thrush in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>You may not be able to prevent thrush, but these steps may help: If you bottle feed your baby, clean and sterilize all equipment, including nipples., Clean and sterilize pacifiers and other toys that go in your baby's mouth., Change diapers often to help prevent yeast from causing diaper rash., Be sure to treat your nipples if you have a yeast infection., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>