<Document id="0003133" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002885.htm">
 
<Focus>Poinsettia plant exposure</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2220266</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Christmas flower poisoning</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lobster plant poisoning</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Painted leaf poisoning</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003133-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Poinsettia plant exposure ?</Question>
			<Answer>Poinsettia plants, commonly used during the holidays, are not poisonous. In most cases, eating this plant does not result in a trip to the hospital. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003133-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Poinsettia plant exposure ?</Question>
			<Answer>Poinsettia plant exposure can affect many parts of the body. EYES (IF DIRECT CONTACT OCCURS)  Burning, Redness ,  STOMACH AND INTESTINES (SYMPTOMS ARE MILD)  Nausea and vomiting, Stomach ache ,  SKIN Skin rash and itching , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003133-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Poinsettia plant exposure ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003133-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Poinsettia plant exposure ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well the person does depends on the amount of poison swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster the person gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. This plant is not considered toxic. People most often make a full recovery. DO NOT touch or eat any unfamiliar plant. Wash your hands after working in the garden or walking in the woods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003133-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Poinsettia plant exposure ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well the person does depends on the amount of poison swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster the person gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. This plant is not considered toxic. People most often make a full recovery. DO NOT touch or eat any unfamiliar plant. Wash your hands after working in the garden or walking in the woods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>