<Document id="0003339" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001348.htm">
 
<Focus>Rat-bite fever</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0034686</CUI>
			<CUI>C0005658</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Streptobacillary fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Streptobacillosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Haverhill fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epidemic arthritic erythema</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spirillary fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sodoku</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003339-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rat-bite fever is a rare bacterial disease spread by the bite of an infected rodent.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003339-2" qtype="causes">What causes Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rat-bite fever can be caused by either of two different bacteria,  Streptobacillus moniliformis  or  Spirillum minus.  Both of these are found in the mouths of rodents. The disease is most often seen in: Asia, Europe, North America,  Most people get rat-bite fever through contact with urine or fluids from the mouth, eye, or nose of an infected animal. This most commonly occurs through a bite or scratch. Some cases may occur simply through contact with these fluids. A rat is usually the source of the infection. Other animals that may cause this infection include: Gerbils, Squirrels, Weasels, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003339-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms depend on the bacteria that caused the infection. Symptoms due to  Streptobacillus moniliformis  may include: Chills, Fever, Joint pain, redness, or swelling, Rash ,  Symptoms due to  Spirillum minus  may include: Chills, Fever, Open sore at the site of the bite,  Rash  with red or purple patches&#160;and bumps, Swollen lymph nodes near the bite ,  Symptoms from either organism usually resolve within 2 weeks. Untreated, the symptoms, such as fever or joint pain, can keep returning for many weeks or longer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003339-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical examination and ask about your symptoms. If the provider suspects rat bite fever, tests will be done to detect the bacteria in: Skin, Blood, Joint fluid, Lymph nodes ,  Blood antibody tests  and other techniques may also be used.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003339-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rat-bite fever is treated with antibiotics (typically oral) for 7 to 14 days.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003339-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook is excellent with early treatment. If it is not treated, the death rate can be as high as 25%.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003339-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rat-bite fever may cause these complications:  Abscesses  of the brain or soft tissue, Infection of the heart valves, Inflammation of the parotid (salivary) glands, Inflammation of the tendons, Inflammation of the heart lining , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003339-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You or your child has had recent contact with a rat or other rodent, The person who was bitten has symptoms of rat-bite fever , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003339-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Rat-bite fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Avoiding contact with rats or rat-contaminated dwellings may help prevent rat-bite fever. Taking antibiotics by mouth promptly after a rat bite may also help prevent this illness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>