<Document id="0003596" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000376.htm">
 
<Focus>Skilled nursing facilities after joint replacement</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003596-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Skilled nursing facilities after joint replacement</Question>
			<Answer>Who Needs to Go to a Skilled Nursing or Rehabilitation Facility? Before you can go home after surgery, you must be able to: Safely get around using a cane, walker, or crutches., Get in and out of a chair and bed without needing much help., Walk around enough that you will be able to move safely in your home, such as between where you sleep, your bathroom, and your kitchen., Go up and down stairs, if there is no way to avoid them.,  Other factors may also prevent you from going directly home from the hospital. Your surgery may be more complicated., You do not have enough help at home., Because of your living condition, you need to be stronger or more mobile before going home., Sometimes infections, problems with your surgical wound, or other medical issues will prevent you from going right home., Other medical problems, such as diabetes, lung problems, and heart problems, have slowed down your recovery.,  Choosing the Right Facility for you At a facility, a provider will supervise your care. Other trained providers will help you grow stronger, including: Registered nurses will care for your wound, give you the right medicines, and help you with other medical problems., Physical therapists will teach you how to make your muscles stronger. They will help you learn to get up and sit down safely from a chair, toilet, or bed. They will also teach you how to climb steps, keep your balance, and use a walker, cane, or crutches., Occupational therapists will teach you the skills you need to do everyday tasks such as putting on your socks or getting dressed.,  Visit 2 or 3 facilities. Choose more than one facility at which you would be comfortable. When visiting, ask the staff questions such as: Do they care for people who have had a joint replacement? Can they tell you how many? A good facility should be able to show you data that shows they provide quality care., Do they have physical therapists who work there? Make sure the therapists have experience helping people after joint replacement., Will the same 1 or 2 therapists treat you most days?, Do they have a plan (also called a pathway, or protocol) for taking care of people after joint replacement?, Do they provide therapy every day of the week, including Saturday and Sunday? How long do therapy sessions last?, If your primary care provider or your orthopedic surgeon does not visit the facility, will there be a provider in charge of your care? How often does that provider check in with you?, A good facility will take the time to teach you and your family or caregivers about the care you will need in your home after you leave the facility. Ask how and when they provide this training., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>