<Document id="0003279" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001553.htm">
 
<Focus>Psychosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0033975</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003279-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Psychosis occurs when a person loses contact with reality. The person may:  Have false beliefs about what is taking place, or who one is (delusions), See or hear things that are not there (hallucinations), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003279-2" qtype="causes">What causes Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medical problems that can cause psychosis include: Alcohol  and certain illegal drugs, both during use and during withdrawal, Brain diseases, such as  Parkinson disease   and  Huntington disease , Brain tumors or cysts,  Dementia  (including  Alzheimer disease ), HIV and other infections that affect the brain, Some prescription drugs, such as steroids and stimulants, Some types of  epilepsy , Stroke,  Psychosis may also be found in: Most people with  schizophrenia , Some people with  bipolar disorder  (manic-depressive) or severe depression, Some personality disorders, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003279-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>A person with psychosis may have any of the following: Disorganized thought and speech, False beliefs that are not based on reality (delusions), especially unfounded fear or suspicion, Hearing, seeing, or feeling things that are not there ( hallucinations ), Thoughts that "jump" between unrelated topics (disordered thinking) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003279-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Psychiatric evaluation and testing are used to diagnose the cause of the psychosis. Laboratory testing and brain scans may not be needed, but sometimes can help pinpoint the diagnosis. Tests may include: Blood tests for abnormal  electrolyte  and hormone levels,  Blood tests for syphilis  and other infections, Drug screens,  MRI  of the brain, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003279-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the cause of the psychosis. Care in a hospital is often needed to ensure the person's safety. Antipsychotic drugs, which reduce hallucinations and delusions and improve thinking and behavior, are helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003279-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on the cause of the psychosis. If the cause can be corrected, the outlook is often good. In this case, treatment with antipsychotic medicine may be brief. Some chronic conditions, such as schizophrenia, may need lifelong treatment with antipsychotic drugs to control symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003279-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Psychosis can prevent people from functioning normally and caring for themselves. Left untreated, people can sometimes harm themselves or others.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003279-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider or mental health professional if you or a member of your family is losing contact with reality. If there is any concern about safety, take the person to the emergency room to be seen by a doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003279-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Psychosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prevention depends on the cause. For example, avoiding alcohol prevents psychosis caused by alcohol use.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>