<Document id="0003211" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000486.htm">
 
<Focus>Preterm labor</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022876</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003211-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Preterm labor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Labor that begins before week 37 is called "preterm" or "premature." About 1 out of every 10 babies born in the United States is born preterm. A preterm birth is one of the major reasons babies are born disabled or die. But  good prenatal care  improves the chances that a preterm baby will do well.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003211-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Preterm labor ?</Question>
			<Answer>You need to see a health care provider right away if you have: Spotting or cramps in your abdomen,  Contractions  with lower back pain or pressure in your groin or thighs, Fluid that leaks from your vagina in a trickle or a gush, Bright red bleeding from your vagina, A thick, mucous-filled discharge from your vagina with blood in it, Your water breaks (ruptured membranes), More than 5 contractions per hour, or contractions that are regular and painful, Contractions that get longer, stronger, and closer together, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003211-3" qtype="causes">What causes Preterm labor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Researchers do not know what actually causes preterm labor in most women. However, we do know that certain conditions can increase the risk of preterm labor, including: A previous preterm delivery, A history of cervical surgery, such as a LEEP or cone biopsy, Being pregnant with twins, Infection in the mother or in the membranes around the baby, Certain birth defects in the baby, High blood pressure in the mother, The bag of water breaks early, Too much amniotic fluid, First trimester bleeding ,  The mother's health problems or lifestyle choices that can lead to preterm labor include: Cigarette smoking, Illegal drug use, often cocaine and amphetamines, Physical or severe psychological stress, Poor weight gain during pregnancy, Obesity ,  Problems with the placenta, uterus, or cervix that can lead to preterm labor include: When the cervix does not stay closed on its own (cervical incompetence), When the shape of the uterus is not normal, Poor function of the placenta, placental abruption, and placenta previa , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003211-4" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Preterm labor? ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003211-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Preterm labor ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>