<Document id="0003594" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000572.htm">
 
<Focus>Skiers thumb - aftercare</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0425040</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Sprained thumb</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Stable thumb</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ulnar collateral ligament injury</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gamekeeper's thumb</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003594-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Skiers thumb - aftercare ?</Question>
			<Answer>With this injury, the main ligament in your thumb is stretched or torn. The ligament is a strong and flexible tissue that attaches one bone to another bone. This injury can be caused by any kind of fall with your thumb stretched out. It often occurs during skiing. At home, be sure to follow your health care provider's instructions on how to take care of your thumb so that it heals well.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003594-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Skiers thumb - aftercare ?</Question>
			<Answer>With this injury, the main ligament in your thumb is stretched or torn. The ligament is a strong and flexible tissue that attaches one bone to another bone. This injury can be caused by any kind of fall with your thumb stretched out. It often occurs during skiing. At home, be sure to follow your health care provider's instructions on how to take care of your thumb so that it heals well.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003594-3" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Skiers thumb - aftercare ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003594-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Skiers thumb - aftercare ?</Question>
			<Answer>Make an ice pack by putting ice in a plastic bag and wrapping a cloth around it.  Do not put the bag of ice directly on your skin. Cold from the ice can damage your skin., Ice your thumb for about 20 minutes every hour while awake for the first 48 hours, then 2 to 3 times a day. ,  For pain, you can use ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin, and others) or naproxen (Aleve, Naprosyn, and others). You can buy these medicines without a prescription. If you have heart disease, high blood pressure, kidney disease, liver disease, or have had stomach ulcers or bleeding, talk with your provider before using these medicines., Do not take more than the amount recommended on the bottle or more than your provider advises you to take., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003594-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Skiers thumb - aftercare ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>