<Document id="0003187" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001368.htm">
 
<Focus>Pregnancy and herpes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019340</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>HSV</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congenital herpes</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Herpes - congenital</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Birth-acquired herpes</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Herpes during pregnancy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003187-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pregnancy and herpes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Newborn infants can become infected with herpes virus during pregnancy, during labor or delivery, or after birth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003187-2" qtype="causes">What causes Pregnancy and herpes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Newborn infants can become infected with herpes virus: In the uterus (this is unusual), Passing through the birth canal (birth-acquired herpes, the most common method of infection), Right after birth (postpartum) from being kissed or having other contact with someone who has  herpes mouth sores ,  If the mother has an active outbreak of  genital herpes  at the time of delivery, the baby is more likely to become infected during birth. Some mothers may not know they have herpes sores inside the vagina. Some women have had herpes infections in the past, but are not aware of it, and may pass the virus to their baby. Herpes type 2 (genital herpes) is the most common cause of herpes infection in newborn babies. But herpes type 1 (oral herpes) can also occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003187-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pregnancy and herpes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herpes may only appear as a skin infection. Small, fluid-filled blisters ( vesicles ) may appear. These blisters break, crust over, and finally heal. A mild scar may remain. Herpes infection may also spread throughout the body. This is called disseminated herpes. In this type, the herpes virus can affect many parts of the body. Herpes infection in the brain is called herpes encephalitis, The liver, lungs, and kidneys may also be involved, There may or may not be blisters on the skin ,  Newborn infants with herpes that has spread to the brain or other parts of the body are often very sick. Symptoms include: Skin sores, fluid-filled blisters, Bleeding easily, Breathing difficulties such as rapid breathing and short periods without breathing, which can lead to nostril flaring, grunting, or  blue appearance , Yellow skin and whites of the eyes, Weakness, Low body temperature (hypothermia), Poor feeding, Seizures,  shock , or&#160; coma ,  Herpes that is caught shortly after birth has symptoms similar to those of birth-acquired herpes. Herpes the baby gets in the uterus can cause: Eye disease, such as inflammation of the retina (chorioretinitis), Severe brain damage, Skin sores (lesions) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003187-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pregnancy and herpes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests for birth-acquired herpes include: Checking for the virus by scraping from vesicle or  vesicle culture ,  EEG ,  MRI of the head ,  Spinal fluid culture ,  Additional tests that may be done if the baby is very sick include: Blood gas  analysis, Coagulation studies ( PT , PTT),  Complete blood count , Electrolyte measurements, Tests of liver function , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003187-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pregnancy and herpes ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is important to tell your health care provider at your first prenatal visit if you have a history of genital herpes. If you have frequent herpes outbreaks, you'll be given a medicine to take during the last month of pregnancy to treat the virus. This helps prevent an outbreak at the time of delivery., C-section is recommended for pregnant women who have an active outbreak of herpes sores and are in labor., You may have some prodromal symptoms before a sore appears. You may experience itching in the affected area, "tingling" or "pinching" sensations, muscle tenderness, shooting pains in the buttocks, legs, or groin, and nerve pain in the leg. Be sure to notify your provider if you are having these sensations., For women with a first-episode genital herpes infection during the third trimester of pregnancy, C-section may be offered due to the possibility of prolonged viral shedding.,  Herpes virus infection in infants is generally treated with antiviral medicine given through a vein (intravenous). The baby may need to be on the medicine for several weeks. Treatment may also be needed for the effects of herpes infection, such as shock or seizures. Because these babies are very ill, treatment is often done in the hospital intensive care unit.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003187-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Pregnancy and herpes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Infants with systemic herpes or encephalitis often do poorly. This is despite antiviral medicines and early treatment. In infants with skin disease, the vesicles may keep coming back, even after treatment is finished. Affected children may have developmental delay and learning disabilities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003187-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Pregnancy and herpes ?</Question>
			<Answer>If your baby has any symptoms of birth-acquired herpes, including skin blisters with no other symptoms, have the baby seen by the provider right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003187-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Pregnancy and herpes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Practicing safe sex  can help prevent the mother from getting genital herpes. People with  cold sores  (oral herpes) should not come in contact with newborn infants. To prevent transmitting the virus, caregivers who have a cold sore should wear a mask and wash their hands carefully before coming in contact with an infant. Mothers should speak to their providers about the best way to minimize the risk of transmitting herpes to their infant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>