<Document id="0003994" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000988.htm">
 
<Focus>Tracheitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040584</CUI>
			<CUI>C1868703</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bacterial tracheitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute bacterial tracheitis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003994-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tracheitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tracheitis is a bacterial infection of the windpipe (trachea).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003994-2" qtype="causes">What causes Tracheitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bacterial tracheitis is most often caused by the bacteria  Staphylococcus aureus.  It often follows a  viral upper respiratory infection . It affects mostly young children. This may be due to their tracheas being smaller and more easily blocked by swelling. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003994-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tracheitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Deep  cough  (similar to that caused by  croup ), Difficulty breathing, High  fever , High-pitched breathing sound ( stridor ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003994-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tracheitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam and listen to the child's lungs. The muscles between the ribs may pull in as the child tries to breathe. This is called  intercostal retractions . Tests that may be done to diagnose this condition include: Blood oxygen level,  Nasopharyngeal culture  to look for bacteria, Tracheal culture to look for bacteria,  X-ray  of the trachea or neck, Tracheoscopy, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003994-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Tracheitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The child often needs to have a tube placed into the airways to help with breathing. This is called an endotracheal tube. Bacterial debris often needs to be removed from the trachea at that time. The child will receive antibiotics through a vein. The health care team will closely monitor the child's breathing and use oxygen, if needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003994-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tracheitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>With prompt treatment, the child should recover.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003994-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Tracheitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Airway obstruction  (can lead to death),  Toxic shock syndrome  if the condition was caused by the bacteria staphylococcus, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003994-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Tracheitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tracheitis is an emergency medical condition. Go to the emergency room right away if your child has had a recent upper respiratory infection and suddenly has a high fever, a cough that gets worse, or trouble breathing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>