<Document id="0003137" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000027.htm">
 
<Focus>Poison ivy - oak - sumac rash</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0162451</CUI>
			<CUI>C0860456</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003137-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Poison ivy - oak - sumac rash ?</Question>
			<Answer>Poison ivy, oak, and sumac  are plants that commonly cause an allergic skin reaction. This is also called an allergic contact dermatitis. The result is most often an itchy, red  rash  with bumps or blisters.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003137-2" qtype="causes">What causes Poison ivy - oak - sumac rash ?</Question>
			<Answer>The rash is caused by skin contact with the oils (resin) of certain plants. The oils most often enter the skin rapidly. POISON IVY This is one of the most frequent causes of skin rash among children and adults who spend time outdoors., The plant has 3 shiny green leaves and a red stem. ,  Poison ivy typically grows in the form of a vine, often along riverbanks. It can be found throughout much of the United States. POISON OAK This plant grows in the form of a shrub and has 3 leaves similar to poison ivy. Poison oak is mostly found on the West Coast. POISON SUMAC This plant grows as a woody shrub. Each stem contains 7 to 13 leaves arranged in pairs. Poison sumac grows abundantly along the Mississippi River. AFTER CONTACT WITH THESE PLANTS The rash does not spread by the fluid from the blisters. Therefore, once a person has washed the oil off the skin, the rash does not often spread from person to person., The plant oils may remain for a long time on clothing, pets, tools, shoes, and other surfaces. Contact with these items can cause rashes in the future if they are not cleaned well. ,  Smoke from burning these plants can cause the same reaction.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003137-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Poison ivy - oak - sumac rash ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Extreme  itching , Red, streaky, patchy rash where the plant touched the skin, Red bumps, which may form large, weeping blisters,  The reaction can vary from mild to severe. In rare cases, the person with the rash needs to be treated in the hospital. The worst symptoms are often seen during days 4 to 7 after coming in contact with the plant. The rash may last for 1 to 3 weeks.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003137-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Poison ivy - oak - sumac rash ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003137-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Poison ivy - oak - sumac rash ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003137-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Poison ivy - oak - sumac rash ?</Question>
			<Answer>Get emergency medical treatment right away if:  The person is suffering from a severe allergic reaction, such as swelling or difficulty breathing, or has had a severe reaction in the past. , The person has been exposed to the smoke of burning poison ivy, oak or sumac.,  Contact your provider if: Itching is severe and cannot be controlled., The rash affects your face, lips, eyes, or genitals., The rash shows signs of infection, such as pus, yellow fluid leaking from blisters, odor, or increased tenderness. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003137-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Poison ivy - oak - sumac rash ?</Question>
			<Answer>These steps can help you avoid contact: Wear long sleeves, long pants, and socks when walking in areas where these plants may grow., Apply skin products, such as Ivy Block lotion, beforehand to reduce the risk of a rash.,  Other steps include: Learn to identify poison ivy, oak, and sumac. Teach children to identify them as soon as they are able to learn about these plants. , Remove these plants if they grow near your home (but never burn them). , Be aware of plant resins carried by pets. , Wash skin, clothing and other items as soon as possible after you think you may have come in contact with the plant., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>