<Document id="0003947" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003043.htm">
 
<Focus>Tinnitus</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040264</CUI>
			<CUI>C1963249</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ringing in the ears</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Noises or buzzing in the ears</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ear buzzing</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003947-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tinnitus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tinnitus is the medical term for "hearing" noises in your ears. It occurs when there is no outside source of the sounds. Tinnitus is often called "ringing in the ears." It may also sound like blowing, roaring, buzzing, hissing, humming, whistling, or sizzling. The noises heard can be soft or loud. The person may even think they're hearing air escaping, water running, the inside of a seashell, or musical notes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003947-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Tinnitus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tinnitus is common. Almost everyone notices a mild form of tinnitus once in a while. It usually lasts a few minutes. However, constant or recurring tinnitus may be stressful and may make it harder to focus or sleep. Tinnitus can be: Subjective, which means that the sound is only heard by the person, Objective, which means that the sound is heard by both the affected person and the examiner (using a stethoscope near the person's ear, head, or neck), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003947-3" qtype="causes">What causes Tinnitus ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known exactly what causes a person to "hear" sounds with no outside source of the noise. However, tinnitus can be a symptom of almost any ear problem, including: Ear infections , Foreign objects or  wax in the ear ,  Hearing loss ,  Meniere disease  -- an inner ear disorder that involves hearing loss and dizziness, Problem with the eustachian tube (tube that runs between the middle ear and the throat),  Antibiotics, aspirin, or other drugs may also cause ear noises. Alcohol, caffeine, or smoking may worsen tinnitus if the person already has it. Sometimes, tinnitus is a sign of high blood pressure, an allergy, or  anemia . In rare cases, tinnitus is a sign of a serious problem such as a tumor or  aneurysm . Other risk factors for tinnitus include temporomandibular joint disorder ( TMJ ), diabetes, thyroid problems, obesity, and head injury. Tinnitus is common in war veterans and in adults age 65 years or older. Children can also be affected, especially those with severe hearing loss.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003947-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Tinnitus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tinnitus is common. Almost everyone notices a mild form of tinnitus once in a while. It usually lasts a few minutes. However, constant or recurring tinnitus may be stressful and may make it harder to focus or sleep. Tinnitus can be: Subjective, which means that the sound is only heard by the person, Objective, which means that the sound is heard by both the affected person and the examiner (using a stethoscope near the person's ear, head, or neck), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003947-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Tinnitus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if: Ear noises start after a  head injury ., The noises occur with other unexplained symptoms, like dizziness, feeling off balance, nausea, or vomiting., You have unexplained ear noises that bother you even after you try self-help measures., The noise is only in one ear and it continues for several weeks or longer. , If the noises are pulsatile (rhythmic noise that follows a steady beat)., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003947-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tinnitus ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>