<Document id="0003717" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001548.htm">
 
<Focus>Stereotypic movement disorder</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0038273</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Motor stereotypies</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003717-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Stereotypic movement disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Stereotypic movement disorder is a condition in which a person makes repetitive, purposeless movements. These can be hand waving, body rocking, or head banging. The movements interfere with normal activity or may cause bodily harm.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003717-2" qtype="causes">What causes Stereotypic movement disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Stereotypic movement disorder is more common among boys than girls. The movements often increase with stress, frustration, and boredom. The cause of this disorder, when it doesn't occur with other conditions, is unknown. Stimulant drugs such as cocaine and amphetamines can cause a severe, short period of movement behavior. This may include picking, hand wringing, head tics, or lip-biting. Long-term stimulant use may lead to longer periods of the behavior. Head injuries may also cause stereotypic movements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003717-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Stereotypic movement disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of this disorder may include any of the following movements: Biting self, Hand shaking or waving, Head banging, Hitting own body, Mouthing of objects, Nail biting, Rocking , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003717-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Stereotypic movement disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>A&#160;health care provider&#160;can usually diagnose this condition with a physical exam. Tests should be done to rule out other causes including:  Autism spectrum disorder ,  Chorea disorders ,  Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) ,  Tourette syndrome  or other tic disorder , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003717-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Stereotypic movement disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment should focus on the cause, specific symptoms, and the person's age. The environment should be changed so that it is safer for&#160;people who may injure themselves. Behavioral techniques and psychotherapy may be helpful. Medicines may also help reduce symptoms related to this condition. Antidepressants have been used in some cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003717-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Stereotypic movement disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook depends on the cause. Stereotypic movements due to drugs usually go away on their own after a few hours. Long-term use of stimulants can lead to longer periods of stereotypic movement behavior. The movements usually go away once the drug is stopped. Stereotypic movements due to head injury may be permanent. The movement problems usually don't progress to other disorders (such as seizures).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003717-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Stereotypic movement disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Severe stereotypic movements may interfere with normal social functioning.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003717-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Stereotypic movement disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if your child has repeated odd movements that last longer than a few hours.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>