<Document id="0003397" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001282.htm">
 
<Focus>Retrograde ejaculation</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0403673</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Ejaculation retrograde</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dry climax</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003397-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Retrograde ejaculation occurs when semen goes backward into the bladder. Normally, it moves forward and out of the penis through the urethra during ejaculation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003397-2" qtype="causes">What causes Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Retrograde ejaculation is uncommon. It most often occurs when the opening of the bladder (bladder neck) does not close. This causes semen to go backward into the bladder rather than forward out of the penis. Retrograde ejaculation may be caused by: Diabetes , Some medicines, including drugs used to treat  high blood pressure  and some mood-altering drugs, Medicines or surgery to treat prostate or urethra problems, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003397-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Cloudy urine after orgasm, Little or no semen is released during ejaculation , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003397-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>A  urinalysis  that is taken soon after ejaculation will show a large amount of sperm in the urine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003397-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider may recommend that you stop taking any medicines that may cause retrograde ejaculation. This can make the problem go away. Retrograde ejaculation that is caused by diabetes or surgery may be treated with drugs such as pseudoephedrine or imipramine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003397-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>If the problem is caused by a medicine, normal ejaculation will often come back after the drug is stopped. Retrograde ejaculation caused by surgery or diabetes often can't be corrected. This is most often not a problem unless you are trying to conceive. Some men do not like how it feels and seek treatment. Otherwise, there is no need for treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003397-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>The condition may cause  infertility . However, semen can often be removed from the bladder and used during assistive reproductive techniques. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003397-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you are worried about this problem or are having trouble conceiving a child.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003397-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Retrograde ejaculation ?</Question>
			<Answer>To avoid this condition: If you have diabetes, maintain good control of your&#160;blood sugar., Avoid drugs that can cause this problem., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>