<Document id="0003099" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000871.htm">
 
<Focus>Pityriasis rosea</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032026</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003099-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pityriasis rosea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pityriasis rosea is a common type of skin rash most often seen in young adults.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003099-2" qtype="causes">What causes Pityriasis rosea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pityriasis rosea is believed to be caused by a virus. It occurs most often in the fall and spring. Although pityriasis rosea may occur in more than one person in a household at a time, it is not thought to spread from one person to another. Females seem to be more affected than males.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003099-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pityriasis rosea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Attacks most often last 4 to 8 weeks. Symptoms may disappear by 3 weeks or last as long as 12 weeks. The rash starts with a single large  patch  called a herald patch. After several days, more skin rashes will appear on the chest, back, arms, and legs. The skin rashes: Are often pink or pale red, Are oval in shape, May be scaly, May follow lines in the skin or appear in a "Christmas tree" pattern, May itch ,  Other symptoms may include: Headache, Fatigue, Sore throat, Mild fever, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003099-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pityriasis rosea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can often diagnose pityriasis rosea by the way the rash looks. In rare cases, the following tests are needed: 
   A blood test to be sure it is not a form of syphilis, which can cause a similar rash
   , 
   A  skin biopsy  to confirm the diagnosis
   , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003099-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pityriasis rosea ?</Question>
			<Answer>If symptoms are mild, you may not need treatment. Your provider may suggest gentle bathing, mild lubricants or cream, or mild hydrocortisone creams to soothe your skin. Antihistamines taken by mouth may be used to reduce itching. You can buy antihistamines at the store without a prescription. Moderate sun exposure or ultraviolet (UV) light treatment may help make the rash go away more quickly. However, you must be careful to avoid sunburn.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003099-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Pityriasis rosea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pityriasis rosea often goes away within 4 to 8 weeks. It usually doesn't come back.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003099-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Pityriasis rosea ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if you have symptoms of pityriasis rosea.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>