<Document id="0003082" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001538.htm">
 
<Focus>Pica</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0031873</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003082-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pica is a pattern of eating non-food materials, such as&#160;dirt or paper.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003082-2" qtype="causes">What causes Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pica is seen more in young children than adults. Up to one third of children ages 1 to 6 years have these eating behaviors. It is unclear how many children with pica intentionally consume dirt (geophagy). Pica can also occur during pregnancy. In some cases, a lack of certain nutrients, such as iron and zinc, may trigger the unusual cravings. Pica may also occur in adults who crave a certain texture in their mouth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003082-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children and adults with pica may eat: 
   Animal feces
   , 
   Clay
   , 
   Dirt
   , 
   Hairballs
   , 
   Ice
   , 
   Paint
   , 
   Sand
   ,  This pattern of eating must last for at least 1 month to fit the diagnosis of pica. Depending on what is being eaten and how much, symptoms of other problems may be present, such as: Belly pain, nausea, and bloating caused by blockage in the stomach or intestine, Fatigue, behavior problems, school problems and other findings of lead poisoning or poor nutrition, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003082-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no single test for pica. Because pica can occur in people who have poor nutrition, the health care provider may test blood levels of iron and zinc. Blood tests can also be done to test for  anemia . Lead levels should always be checked in children who may have eaten paint or objects covered in lead paint dust to screen for lead poisoning. The provider may also test for infection if the person has been eating contaminated soil or animal waste.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003082-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment should first address any missing nutrients or other medical problems, such as lead poisoning. Treating pica involves behaviors, the environment, and family education. One form of treatment associates the pica behavior with negative consequences or punishment (mild aversion therapy). Then the person gets rewarded for eating normal foods. Medicines may help reduce the abnormal eating behavior if pica is part of a developmental disorder such as intellectual disability.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003082-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment success varies. In many cases, the disorder lasts several months and then disappears on its own. In some cases, it may continue into the teen years or adulthood, especially when it occurs with developmental disorders.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003082-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications include: Bezoar  (a mass of undigestible material trapped inside the body, most often in the stomach), Infection, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003082-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you notice that a child (or adult) is eating nonfood materials.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003082-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Pica ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no specific prevention. Getting adequate nutrition may help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>