<Document id="0003883" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003160.htm">
 
<Focus>Testicle pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1963192</CUI>
			<CUI>C0039591</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pain - testicle</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Orchalgia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Epididymitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Orchitis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003883-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Testicle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Testicle pain is discomfort in one or both  testicles . The pain can spread into the lower abdomen.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003883-2" qtype="causes">What causes Testicle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>The testicles are very sensitive. Even a minor injury can cause pain. In some conditions, abdominal pain may occur before testicle pain. Common causes of testicle pain include: Injury., Infection or swelling of the sperm ducts ( epididymitis ) or testicles ( orchitis )., Twisting of the testicles that can cut off the blood supply ( testicular torsion ). It is most common in young men between 10 and 20 years old. It is a medical emergency that needs to be treated as soon as possible. If surgery is performed within 4 hours, most testicles can be saved. ,  Mild pain may be caused by fluid collection in the scrotum, such as: Enlarged veins in the scrotum ( varicocele )., Cyst in the epididymis that often contains dead sperm cells ( spermatocele )., Fluid surrounding the testicle ( hydrocele )., Pain in the testicles may also be caused by a hernia or kidney stone.,  Testicular cancer  is almost always painless. But any testicle lump should be checked out by your health care provider, whether or not there is pain. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003883-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Testicle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003883-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Testicle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sudden, severe testicle pain needs immediate medical care. Contact your provider right away or go to an emergency room if: Your pain is severe or sudden., You have had an injury or trauma to the scrotum, and you still have pain or swelling after 1 hour., Your pain is accompanied by nausea or vomiting. ,  Also call your provider right away if: You feel a lump in the scrotum., You have a fever., Your scrotum is warm, tender to the touch, or red., You have been in contact with someone who has the mumps. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003883-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Testicle pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>