<Document id="0003574" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000527.htm">
 
<Focus>Sickle cell anemia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002895</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Anemia - sickle cell</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemoglobin SS disease (Hb SS)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sickle cell disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003574-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sickle cell anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sickle cell disease is a disorder passed down through families. The red blood cells that are normally shaped like a disk take on a sickle or crescent shape. Red blood cells carry oxygen throughout the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003574-2" qtype="causes">What causes Sickle cell anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sickle cell disease is caused by an abnormal type of hemoglobin called hemoglobin S. Hemoglobin is a protein inside red blood cells that carries oxygen. Hemoglobin S changes the red blood cells. The red blood cells become fragile and shaped like crescents or sickles., The abnormal cells deliver less oxygen to the body's tissues., They can also easily get stuck in small blood vessels and break into pieces. This can interrupt healthy blood flow and cut down even more on the amount of oxygen flowing to body tissues.,  Sickle cell disease is inherited from both parents. If you get the sickle cell gene from only one parent, you will have  sickle cell trait . People with sickle cell trait do not have the symptoms of sickle cell disease. Sickle cell disease is much more common in people of African and Mediterranean descent. It is also seen in people from South and Central America, the Caribbean, and the Middle East.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003574-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sickle cell anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms usually do not occur until after the age of 4 months. Almost all people with sickle cell disease have painful episodes called crises. These can last from hours to days. Crises can cause pain in the lower back, leg, joints, and chest. Some people have one episode every few years. Others have many episodes each year. The crises can be severe enough to require a hospital stay. When sickle cell disease becomes more severe, symptoms may include: Fatigue , Paleness, Rapid heart rate, Shortness of breath, Yellowing of the eyes and skin ( jaundice ) ,  Younger children with sickle cell disease have attacks of  abdominal pain . The following symptoms may occur because small blood vessels become blocked by the abnormal cells: Painful and prolonged erection ( priapism ), Poor eyesight or blindness, Problems with thinking or confusion caused by small strokes,  Ulcers  on the lower legs (in adolescents and adults) ,  Over time, the spleen stops working. As a result, people with sickle cell disease may have symptoms of infections such as: Bone infection ( osteomyelitis ), Gallbladder infection (cholecystitis), Lung infection (pneumonia), Urinary tract infection ,  Other signs and symptoms include: Delayed growth and puberty, Painful joints caused by arthritis, Heart or liver failure due to too much iron (from blood transfusions), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003574-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Sickle cell anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests commonly done to diagnose and monitor people with sickle cell disease include: Bilirubin , Blood oxygen saturation, Complete blood count ( CBC ),  Hemoglobin electrophoresis ,  Serum creatinine , Serum potassium,  Sickle cell test , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003574-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sickle cell anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goal of treatment is to manage and control symptoms, and to limit the number of crises. People with sickle cell disease need ongoing treatment, even when not having a crisis. People with this condition should take folic acid supplements. Folic acid helps make new red blood cells. Treatment for a sickle cell crisis includes: Blood transfusions (may also be given regularly to prevent stroke), Pain medicines, Plenty of fluids ,  Other treatments for sickle cell disease may include: Hydroxyurea (Hydrea), which helps reduce the number of pain episodes (including breathing problems and risk for stroke) in some people, Antibiotics, which help prevent bacterial infections that are common in children with sickle cell disease, Medicines that reduce the amount of iron in the body, Newer therapies to reduce the frequency and severity of pain crises have been approved,  Treatments that may be needed to manage complications of sickle cell disease include: Dialysis  or  kidney transplant  for kidney disease, Counseling for psychological complications,  Gallbladder removal  in people with gallstone disease,  Hip replacement  for  avascular necrosis  of the hip, Surgery for eye problems, Treatment for overuse or abuse of narcotic pain medicines, Wound care for leg ulcers ,  Bone marrow or stem cell transplants can cure sickle cell disease, but this treatment is not an option for most people. People with sickle cell disease often cannot find well-matched stem cell donors. People with sickle cell disease should have the following vaccinations to lower the risk for infection: Haemophilus influenzae vaccine (Hib), Pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV), Pneumococcal polysaccharide vaccine (PPV) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003574-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Sickle cell anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Joining a  support group  where members share common issues can relieve the stress of a chronic disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003574-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Sickle cell anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>In the past, people with sickle cell disease often died between ages 20 and 40. Thanks to modern care, people now can live to the age of 50 and beyond. Causes of death include organ failure and infection. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003574-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Sickle cell anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have: Any symptoms of infection (fever, body aches, headache, fatigue), Pain crises, Painful and long-term erection (in men) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>