<Document id="0003504" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000963.htm">
 
<Focus>Seborrheic dermatitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0036508</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Dandruff</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Seborrheic eczema</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cradle cap</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003504-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Seborrheic dermatitis is a common inflammatory skin condition. It causes flaky, white to yellowish  scales  to form on oily areas such as the scalp, face, or inside the ear. It can occur with or without reddened skin. Cradle cap  is the term used when seborrheic dermatitis affects the scalp of infants.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003504-2" qtype="causes">What causes Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of seborrheic dermatitis is unknown. It may be due to a combination of factors: Oil gland activity, Yeasts called Malassezia, which live on the skin, mainly in areas with more oil glands, Changes in skin barrier function, Your genes ,  Risk factors include: Stress or fatigue, Weather extremes, Oily skin, or skin problems such as acne, Heavy alcohol use, or using lotions that contain alcohol, Obesity, Nervous system disorders, including  Parkinson disease , traumatic brain injury, or  stroke , Having  HIV/AIDS , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003504-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Seborrheic dermatitis can occur on several body areas. It often forms where the skin is oily or greasy. Common areas include the scalp, eyebrows, eyelids, creases of the nose, lips, behind the ears, in the outer ear, and middle of the chest. In general, symptoms of seborrheic dermatitis include: Skin lesions  with scales,  Plaques  over large area, Greasy, oily areas of skin, Skin scales -- white and flaking, or yellowish, oily, and sticky dandruff, Itching -- may become more itchy if infected, Mild redness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003504-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diagnosis is based on the appearance and location of the skin lesions. Further tests, such as  skin biopsy , are rarely needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003504-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Flaking and dryness can be treated with over-the-counter dandruff or medicated shampoos. You can buy these at the drugstore without a prescription. Look for a product that says on the label it treats seborrheic dermatitis or dandruff. Such products contain ingredients such as salicylic acid, coal tar, zinc, resorcinol, ketoconazole, or selenium sulfide. Use the shampoo according to label instructions. For severe cases, your health care provider will likely prescribe a shampoo, cream, ointment, or lotion containing either a stronger dose of the above medicines or containing any of the following medicines: Ketoconazole, Ciclopirox, Sodium sulfacetamide, A corticosteroid, Tacrolimus or pimecrolimus (medicines that suppress the immune system),  Phototherapy, a medical procedure in which your skin is carefully exposed to ultraviolet light, may be needed. Sunlight may improve seborrheic dermatitis. In some people, the condition gets better in the summer, especially after outdoor activities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003504-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Seborrheic dermatitis is a chronic (life-long) condition that comes and goes, but it can be controlled with treatment.  Severity of seborrheic dermatitis can be lessened by controlling risk factors and paying careful attention to skin care. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003504-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The condition may result in: Psychological distress, low self-esteem, embarrassment, Secondary bacterial or fungal infections, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003504-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call for an appointment with your provider if your symptoms don't respond to self-care or over-the-counter treatments. Also call if patches of seborrheic dermatitis drain fluid or pus, form crusts, or become very red or painful. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003504-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Seborrheic dermatitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>