<Document id="0003337" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003259.htm">
 
<Focus>Rash - child under 2 years</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0015230</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Baby rash</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Miliaria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Prickly heat</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003337-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Rash - child under 2 years ?</Question>
			<Answer>A rash is a change in the color or texture of the skin. A skin rash can be: Bumpy, Flat, Red, skin-colored, or slightly lighter or darker than skin color, Scaly, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003337-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Rash - child under 2 years ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most bumps and blotches on a newborn baby are harmless and clear up by themselves. The most common skin problem in infants is diaper rash. Diaper rash is an irritation of the skin caused by dampness, urine, or feces. Most babies who wear diapers will have some type of diaper rash at some point. Other skin disorders can cause rashes. These are most often not serious unless they occur with other symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003337-3" qtype="causes">What causes Rash - child under 2 years ?</Question>
			<Answer>Causes may include: Diaper rash (rash in the diaper area)  is a skin irritation caused by long-term dampness and by urine and feces touching the skin., Yeast diaper rash is caused by a type of yeast called Candida, which also causes thrush in the mouth. The rash looks different from a regular diaper rash. It is very red, and there are usually small red bumps on the outer edges of the rash. This rash requires treatment with medicine., Heat rash, or prickly heat, is caused by the blockage of the pores that lead to the sweat glands. It is most common in very young children but can occur at any age. It is more common in hot and humid weather. The sweat is held within the skin and forms little red bumps or occasionally small  blisters .,  Erythema toxicum  can cause flat red splotches (usually with a white, pimple-like bump in the middle) that appear in up to one half of all babies. This rash rarely appears after 5 days of age, and most often disappears in 7 to 14 days. It is nothing to worry about., Baby acne is caused by exposure to the mother's hormones. Red bumps, sometimes with white dots in the center, may be seen on a newborn's face. Acne most often occurs between 2 and 4 weeks of age, but may appear up to 4 months after birth and can last for 12 to 18 months.,  Cradle cap  (seborrheic dermatitis) causes greasy, scaling, crusty patches on the scalp that appear in a baby's first 3 months. It most often goes away by itself, but some cases may require treatment with medicine.,  Eczema  is a condition of the skin in which areas are dry, scaly, red (or darker than normal skin color), and itchy. When it goes on for a long time the areas become thickened. It is often associated with asthma and allergies, although it can often occur without either of these. Eczema often runs in families.,  Hives  are red welts that often seem to move around on the body. For example, if you drew a circle to mark one of the welts, a few hours later that circle would not have a welt in it, but there may be welts on other parts of the body. They differ in size and shape. Hives may last for a few weeks. The cause is often uncertain., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003337-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Rash - child under 2 years ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most bumps and blotches on a newborn baby are harmless and clear up by themselves. The most common skin problem in infants is diaper rash. Diaper rash is an irritation of the skin caused by dampness, urine, or feces. Most babies who wear diapers will have some type of diaper rash at some point. Other skin disorders can cause rashes. These are most often not serious unless they occur with other symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003337-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Rash - child under 2 years ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your child's provider if your child has: A  fever  or other unexplained symptoms associated with the rash, Any areas that look wet, oozing, or red, which are signs of infection, A rash that extends beyond the diaper area, A rash that is worse in the skin creases, A rash, spots, blister, or discoloration and is younger than 3 months, Blisters, No improvement after 3 days of home treatment, Significant scratching, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003337-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Rash - child under 2 years ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>