<Document id="0003657" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002488.htm">
 
<Focus>Sodium hypochlorite poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238430</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bleach</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Clorox</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Carrel-Dakin solution</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003657-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sodium hypochlorite poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sodium hypochlorite is a chemical commonly found in bleach, water purifiers, and cleaning products. Sodium hypochlorite is a caustic chemical. If it contacts tissues, it can cause injury. Swallowing sodium hypochlorite can lead to poisoning. Breathing sodium hypochlorite fumes may also cause poisoning, especially if the product is mixed with ammonia. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003657-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sodium hypochlorite poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Watered-down (diluted) sodium hypochlorite generally causes only mild stomach irritation. Swallowing larger amounts can cause more serious symptoms. Industrial-strength bleach contains much higher concentrations of sodium hypochlorite, which may cause severe injury. NEVER mix ammonia with sodium hypochlorite (bleach or bleach-containing products). This common household error produces chlorine, which is a toxic gas that can cause choking and serious breathing problems.  Symptoms of sodium hypochlorite poisoning may include: Burning, tearing red eyes, Burns of the esophagus, Chest pain or tightness,  Coma  (lack of responsiveness), Coughing (from the fumes),  Delirium  (agitation and confusion), Drooling, Gagging sensation, Low blood pressure, Pain in the mouth or throat, Skin irritation of the exposed area, burns, or blistering, Shock (extremely low blood pressure), Slow heartbeat, Stomach or abdominal pain, Throat swelling, which leads to difficulty breathing, Vomiting, sometimes bloody, Weakness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003657-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Sodium hypochlorite poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003657-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Sodium hypochlorite poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Swallowing, smelling, or touching small amounts of household bleach will likely not cause any significant problems. However, more severe problems can occur with industrial-strength bleach, or from mixing bleach with ammonia. How well a person does depends on the amount of poison swallowed and how quickly treatment was received. The faster a person gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Cancer of the esophagus is a high risk for people who live after ingesting sodium hypochlorite, especially industrial strength.&#160; Without prompt treatment, extensive damage to the mouth, throat, eyes, lungs, esophagus, nose, and stomach are possible, and may continue to occur for several weeks after the poison was swallowed. Holes (perforations) in the esophagus and stomach may cause serious infections in both the chest and abdominal cavities, which may result in death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003657-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Sodium hypochlorite poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Swallowing, smelling, or touching small amounts of household bleach will likely not cause any significant problems. However, more severe problems can occur with industrial-strength bleach, or from mixing bleach with ammonia. How well a person does depends on the amount of poison swallowed and how quickly treatment was received. The faster a person gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Cancer of the esophagus is a high risk for people who live after ingesting sodium hypochlorite, especially industrial strength.&#160; Without prompt treatment, extensive damage to the mouth, throat, eyes, lungs, esophagus, nose, and stomach are possible, and may continue to occur for several weeks after the poison was swallowed. Holes (perforations) in the esophagus and stomach may cause serious infections in both the chest and abdominal cavities, which may result in death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>