<Document id="0003755" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003049.htm">
 
<Focus>Stuffy or runny nose - adult</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1260880</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Nose - congested</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Congested nose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Runny nose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Postnasal drip</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rhinorrhea: nasal congestion</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003755-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Stuffy or runny nose - adult ?</Question>
			<Answer>A stuffy or congested nose occurs when the tissues lining it become swollen. The swelling is due to inflamed blood vessels.  The problem may also include nasal discharge or "runny nose." If excess mucus runs down the back of your throat (postnasal drip), it may cause a cough or sore throat.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003755-2" qtype="causes">What causes Stuffy or runny nose - adult ?</Question>
			<Answer>A stuffy or runny nose may be caused by: Common cold ,  Flu ,  Sinus infection ,  The congestion typically goes away by itself within a week. Congestion also can be caused by: Hay fever  or other allergies, Use of some nasal sprays or drops bought without a prescription for more than 3 days (may make nasal stuffiness worse),  Nasal polyps , sac-like growths of inflamed tissue lining the nose or sinuses, Pregnancy,  Vasomotor rhinitis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003755-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Stuffy or runny nose - adult ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003755-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Stuffy or runny nose - adult ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for any of the following:  A stuffy nose with swelling of the forehead, eyes, side of the nose, or cheek, or that occurs with blurred vision, More throat pain, or white or yellow spots on the tonsils or other parts of the throat, Discharge from the nose that has a bad smell, comes from only one side, or is a color other than white or yellow,  Cough  that lasts longer than 10 days, or produces yellow-green or gray mucus, Nasal discharge following a head injury, Symptoms that last more than 3 weeks, Nasal discharge with  fever , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003755-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Stuffy or runny nose - adult ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>