<Document id="0003552" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001175.htm">
 
<Focus>Sheehan syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0242342</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Postpartum hypopituitarism</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Postpartum pituitary insufficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hypopituitarism Syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003552-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sheehan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sheehan syndrome is a condition that can occur in a woman who bleeds severely during childbirth. Sheehan syndrome is a type of  hypopituitarism .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003552-2" qtype="causes">What causes Sheehan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Severe bleeding during childbirth can cause tissue in the pituitary gland to die. This gland does not work properly as a result. The pituitary gland is at the base of the brain. It makes hormones that stimulate growth, production of breast milk, reproductive functions, the thyroid, and the adrenal glands. A lack of these hormones can lead to a variety of symptoms. Conditions that increase the risk of bleeding during childbirth and Sheehan syndrome include multiple pregnancy (twins or triplets) and problems with the placenta. The placenta is the organ that develops during pregnancy to feed the fetus. The condition is rare today due to advances in obstetric care.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003552-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sheehan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of Sheehan syndrome may include: Inability to breastfeed (breast milk never "comes in"), Fatigue, Lack of menstrual bleeding, Loss of pubic and armpit (axillary) hair,  Low blood pressure ,  Note: Other than not being able to breastfeed, symptoms may not develop for several years after the delivery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003552-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Sheehan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests done may include: Blood tests to measure hormone levels,  MRI of the head  to rule out other pituitary problems, such as a tumor, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003552-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sheehan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment involves estrogen and progesterone hormone replacement therapy. These hormones must be taken at least until the normal age of menopause. Thyroid and adrenal hormones must also be taken. These will be needed for the rest of your life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003552-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Sheehan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook with early diagnosis and treatment is excellent.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003552-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Sheehan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>This condition can be life threatening if not treated.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003552-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Sheehan syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Severe loss of blood during childbirth can often be prevented by proper medical care. Otherwise, Sheehan syndrome is not preventable.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>