<Document id="0003677" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000029.htm">
 
<Focus>Spinal injury</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0037937</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Spinal cord injury</Synonym>
		<Synonym>SCI</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003677-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Spinal injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>The spinal cord contains the nerves that carry messages between your brain and the rest of the body. The cord passes through your neck and back. A  spinal cord injury  is very serious because it can cause loss of movement (paralysis), function, and sensation below the site of the injury.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003677-2" qtype="causes">What causes Spinal injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>A spinal cord injury may be caused by incidents such as:  Bullet or stab wound, Fracture of the spine, Traumatic injury to the face, neck, head, chest, or back (for example, a car accident), Diving accident,  Electric shock , Extreme twisting of the middle of the body, Sports injury, Falls, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003677-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Spinal injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of a spinal cord injury may include any of the following: Head that is in an unusual position, Numbness or tingling that spreads down an arm or leg, Weakness, Difficulty walking,  Paralysis  (loss of movement) of arms or legs, Loss of bladder or bowel control,  Shock  (pale, clammy skin, bluish lips and fingernails, acting dazed or semiconscious), Lack of alertness (unconsciousness), Stiff neck, headache, or neck pain, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003677-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Spinal injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003677-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Spinal injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003677-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Spinal injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your local emergency number (such as 911) if you think someone has a spinal cord injury.&#160;DO NOT move the person unless there is urgent danger.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003677-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Spinal injury ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following may lower your risk for spinal injury: Wear seat belts., Do not drink and drive., Do not dive into pools, lakes, rivers, and other bodies of water, particularly if you cannot determine the depth of the water or if the water is not clear., Do not tackle or dive into a person with your head., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>