<Document id="0003774" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000796.htm">
 
<Focus>Substance use - marijuana</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0237123</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Substance abuse - marijuana</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Drug abuse - marijuana</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Drug use - marijuana</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cannabis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Grass</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hashish</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mary Jane</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pot</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Weed</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003774-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Substance use - marijuana ?</Question>
			<Answer>Marijuana comes from a plant called hemp. Its scientific name is  Cannabis sativa . The main, active ingredient in marijuana is THC (short for delta-9-tetrahydrocannabinol). This ingredient is found in the leaves and flowering parts of the marijuana plant. Hashish is a substance taken from the tops of female marijuana plants. It contains the highest amount of THC. Marijuana is called by many other names, including cannabis, grass, hashish, joint, Mary Jane, pot, reefer, weed. Some states in the United States permit marijuana to be used legally to  treat certain medical problems . Other states have also legalized its recreational use. This article is on the recreational use of marijuana, which may lead to abuse.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003774-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Substance use - marijuana ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment begins with recognizing there is a problem. Once you decide you want to do something about your marijuana use, the next step is getting help and support. Treatment programs use behavior change techniques through counseling (talk therapy). Some programs use 12-step meetings to help people learn how not to relapse. The goal is to help you understand your behaviors and why you use marijuana. Involving family and friends during counseling can help support you and keep you from going back to using (relapsing). If you have severe withdrawal symptoms, you may need to stay at a residential treatment program. There, your health and safety can be monitored as you recover. At this time, there is no medicine that can help reduce the use of marijuana by blocking its effects. But, scientists are researching such medicines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003774-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Substance use - marijuana ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>