<Document id="0003486" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000285.htm">
 
<Focus>Sclerosing cholangitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0008311</CUI>
			<CUI>C0008313</CUI>
			<CUI>C0566602</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Primary sclerosing cholangitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>PSC</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003486-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sclerosing cholangitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sclerosing cholangitis refers to swelling (inflammation), scarring, and destruction of the  bile  ducts inside and outside of the liver.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003486-2" qtype="causes">What causes Sclerosing cholangitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause of this condition is unknown in most cases. The disease may be seen in people who have: Inflammatory bowel disease (IBD) such as  ulcerative colitis  and  Crohn disease ,  Autoimmune disorders ,  Chronic pancreatitis  (inflamed pancreas),  Sarcoidosis  (a disease that causes inflammation in various parts of the body),  Genetic factors may also be responsible. Sclerosing cholangitis occurs more often in men than women. This disorder is rare in children. Sclerosing cholangitis may also be caused by: Choledocholithiasis  (gallstones in the bile duct), Infections in the liver, gallbladder, and bile ducts, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003486-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sclerosing cholangitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The first symptoms are usually: Fatigue, Itching, Yellowing of the skin and eyes (jaundice) ,  However, some people have no symptoms. Other symptoms may include: Enlarged liver ,  Enlarged spleen , Loss of appetite and weight loss, Repeat episodes of  cholangitis  (an infection of the bile duct that causes fever, jaundice and pain in the right upper abdomen), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003486-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Sclerosing cholangitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Even though some people do not have symptoms, blood tests shows that they have abnormal liver function. Your health care provider will look for: Diseases that cause similar problems, Diseases that often occur with this condition (especially IBD), Gallstones,  Tests that show cholangitis include: Abdominal CT scan ,  Abdominal ultrasound ,  Endoscopic retrograde cholangiopancreatography  (ERCP),  Liver biopsy , Magnetic resonance cholangiopancreatography (MRCP), Percutaneous transhepatic cholangiogram ( PTC ), Blood tests for liver enzymes ( liver function tests ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003486-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sclerosing cholangitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medicines that may be used include: Cholestyramine (such as Prevalite) to treat itching, Ursodeoxycholic acid (ursodiol) to improve liver function, Fat-soluble vitamins (D, E, A, K) to replace what is lost from the disease itself, Antibiotics to treat infections in the bile ducts,  These surgical procedures may be done: Inserting a long, thin tube with a balloon at the end to open up narrowing ( endoscopic  balloon dilation of strictures), Placement of a drain or tube for major narrowing (strictures) of bile ducts,  Proctocolectomy  (removal of colon and rectum, for those who have both ulcerative colitis and sclerosing cholangitis)&#160;does not affect the progression of primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC), Liver transplant, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003486-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Sclerosing cholangitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well people do varies. The disease tends to get worse over time. Sometimes people develop: Ascites  (buildup of fluid in the space between the lining of the abdomen and abdominal organs) and  varices  in the esophagus or stomach (enlarged veins), Biliary  cirrhosis  (liver scarring due to inflammation of the bile ducts), Liver failure, Persistent jaundice,  Some people develop infections of the bile ducts that keep returning. People with this condition have a high risk for developing cancer of the bile ducts (cholangiocarcinoma). They should be checked regularly with a liver imaging test and blood tests. People who also have IBD may have an increased risk for developing cancer of the colon or rectum and should have periodic colonoscopy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003486-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Sclerosing cholangitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Bleeding esophageal varices , Cancer in the bile ducts ( cholangiocarcinoma ),  Cirrhosis  and liver failure, Infection of the biliary system ( cholangitis ), Narrowing of the bile ducts, Vitamin deficiencies , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>