<Document id="0004071" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001332.htm">
 
<Focus>Typhoid fever</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0041466</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Enteric fever</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004071-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Typhoid fever is an infection that causes fever,&#160; diarrhea , and a  rash . It is most commonly caused by bacteria called  Salmonella typhi  ( S typhi ).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004071-2" qtype="causes">What causes Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>S typhi  is spread through contaminated food, drink, or water. If you eat or drink something that is contaminated with the bacteria, the bacteria enter your body. They travel into your intestines, and then into your blood. In the blood, they travel to your lymph nodes, gallbladder, liver, spleen, and other parts of the body. Some people become carriers of  S typhi  and continue to release the bacteria in their stools, sometimes for years, spreading the disease. Typhoid fever is common in developing countries. Most cases in the United States are brought in from other countries where typhoid fever is common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004071-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Early symptoms include fever, general ill-feeling, and abdominal pain. High fever (103&#176;F, or 39.5&#176;C) or higher and severe diarrhea occur as the disease gets worse. Some people develop a rash called "rose spots," which are small red spots on the abdomen and chest. Other symptoms that occur include: Bloody stools , Chills, Agitation,  confusion , delirium, seeing or hearing things that are not there ( hallucinations ), Difficulty paying attention (attention deficit), Nosebleeds, Severe fatigue, Slow, sluggish, weak feeling , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004071-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask about the symptoms.  A  complete blood count  (CBC) will show a high number of white blood cells. A  blood culture  during the first week of the fever can show  S typhi  bacteria. Other tests that can help diagnose this condition include: ELISA  blood test to look for  antibodies  to the  S typhi  bacteria, Fluorescent antibody study to look for substances that are specific to  S typhi  bacteria,  Platelet count  (platelet count may be low),  Stool culture , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004071-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fluids and  electrolytes  may be given by IV (into a vein) or you may be asked to drink water with electrolyte packets. Antibiotics are given to kill the bacteria. There are increasing rates of antibiotic resistance throughout the world, so your provider will check current recommendations before choosing an antibiotic.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004071-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms usually improve in 2 to 4 weeks with treatment. The outcome is likely to be good with early treatment, but becomes poor if complications develop. Symptoms may return if the treatment has not completely cured the infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004071-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health problems that may develop include: Intestinal hemorrhage (severe  GI bleeding ), Intestinal perforation,  Kidney failure ,  Peritonitis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004071-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have any of the following: You know you have been exposed to someone who has typhoid fever, You have been in an area where there are people who have typhoid fever and you develop symptoms of typhoid fever, You have had typhoid fever and the symptoms return, You develop severe abdominal pain,  decreased urine output , or other new symptoms , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004071-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Typhoid fever ?</Question>
			<Answer>A vaccine is recommended for travel outside of the United States to places where there is typhoid fever. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention website has information about where typhoid fever is common --  www.cdc.gov/typhoid-fever/index.html . Ask your provider if you should bring electrolyte packets in case you get sick. When traveling, drink only boiled or bottled water and eat well-cooked food. Wash your hands thoroughly before eating. Water treatment, waste disposal, and protecting the food supply from contamination are important public health measures. Carriers of  S typhi  must not be allowed to work as food handlers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>