<Document id="0004331" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003175.htm">
 
<Focus>Wrist pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0221785</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pain - wrist</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pain - carpal tunnel</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Injury - wrist</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arthritis - wrist</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gout - wrist</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pseudogout - wrist</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004331-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Wrist pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wrist pain is any pain or discomfort in the wrist.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004331-2" qtype="causes">What causes Wrist pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Carpal tunnel syndrome:  A common cause of wrist pain is  carpal tunnel syndrome . The carpal tunnel is an area in your wrist that is created by wrist bones and which contains the median nerve and tendons. You may feel aching, burning, numbness, or tingling in your palm, wrist, thumb, or fingers. The thumb muscle can become weak, making it difficult to grasp things. Pain may go up to your elbow. Carpal tunnel syndrome occurs when the median nerve gets compressed at the wrist because of swelling of structures in the carpal tunnel or narrowing due to the bones of the carpal tunnel. This is the nerve in the wrist that allows feeling and movement to parts of the hand. Swelling can occur if you: Do repetitive movements with your wrist, such as typing on a computer keyboard, using a computer mouse, playing racquetball or handball, sewing, painting, writing, or using a vibrating tool, Are pregnant, menopausal, or overweight, Have diabetes, premenstrual syndrome, an underactive thyroid, or rheumatoid arthritis ,  Injury:  Wrist pain with bruising and swelling is often a sign of an injury. Signs of a possible  broken bone  include deformed joints and inability to move the wrist, hand, or a finger. There can also be cartilage injuries in the wrist. Other common injuries include  sprain ,  strain ,  tendinitis , and  bursitis . Arthritis: Arthritis  is another common cause of wrist pain, swelling, and stiffness. There are many types of arthritis: Osteoarthritis  occurs with age and overuse.,  Rheumatoid arthritis  generally affects both wrists.,  Psoriatic arthritis  usually accompanies psoriasis., Infectious arthritis is a medical emergency. Signs of an infection include redness and warmth of the wrist, fever above 100&#176;F (37.7&#176;C), and recent illness. ,  Other Causes Gout : This occurs when your body produces too much uric acid, a waste product. The uric acid forms crystals in the joints, rather than being excreted in the urine.,  Pseudogout : This occurs when calcium pyrophosphate crystals deposit in the joints, causing pain, redness, and swelling. The wrists and knees are most often affected. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004331-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Wrist pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004331-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Wrist pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Get emergency care if: You are unable to move your wrist, hand or a finger., Your wrist, hand, or fingers are misshapen., You are bleeding significantly. ,  Contact your health care provider right away if you have any of the following: Fever  over 100&#176;F (37.7&#176;C),  Rash ,  Swelling  and redness of your wrist and you have had a recent illness (like a virus or other infection),  Contact your provider for an appointment if you have any of the following: Swelling, redness or stiffness in one or both wrists,  Numbness , tingling, or  weakness  in the wrist, hand, or fingers with pain, Lost any muscle mass in the wrist, hand, or fingers, Still have pain even after following self-care treatments for 2 weeks , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004331-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Wrist pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>