<Document id="0004066" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000328.htm">
 
<Focus>Type 2 diabetes - self-care</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011860</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004066-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Type 2 diabetes - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Type 2 diabetes is a life-long (chronic) disease. If you have type 2 diabetes, the insulin your body normally makes has trouble transmitting a signal to muscle and fat cells. Insulin is a hormone made by the pancreas to control blood sugar. When your body's insulin isn't able to signal correctly, the sugar from food stays in the blood and the sugar (glucose) level can get too high. Most people with type 2 diabetes are overweight when they're diagnosed. The changes in the way the body handles blood sugar that lead to type 2 diabetes usually happens slowly. Everyone with diabetes should receive proper education and support about the best ways to manage their diabetes. Ask your health care provider about seeing a certified diabetes care and education specialist.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004066-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Type 2 diabetes - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>You may not have any symptoms. If you do have symptoms, they may include: Hunger, Thirst, Urinating a lot, getting up more often than usual at night to urinate, Blurry vision, More frequent or long lasting infections, Trouble having an erection, Trouble healing cuts on your skin , Red skin rashes in parts of your body , Tingling or loss of sensation in your feet, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004066-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Type 2 diabetes - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004066-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Type 2 diabetes - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>