<Document id="0004295" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003070.htm">
 
<Focus>Wheezing</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0043144</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Sibilant rhonchi</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004295-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Wheezing ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wheezing is a high-pitched whistling sound during breathing. It occurs when air moves through narrowed breathing tubes in the lungs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004295-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Wheezing ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wheezing is a sign that a person may be having breathing problems. The sound of wheezing is most obvious when breathing out (exhaling). It may also be heard when breathing in (inhaling). Wheezing most often comes from the small breathing tubes (bronchial tubes) deep in the lungs. But it may be due to a blockage in larger airways or in people with certain vocal cord problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004295-3" qtype="causes">What causes Wheezing ?</Question>
			<Answer>Causes of wheezing may include any of the following: Asthma , Breathing a foreign object into the airways to the lungs, Damage and widening of the large airways in the lungs ( bronchiectasis ), Swelling and mucus buildup in the smallest air passages in the lungs ( bronchiolitis ), Swelling and mucus buildup in the main passages that carry air to the lungs ( bronchitis ),  COPD  (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease), especially when a respiratory infection is present,  Acid reflux disease , Heart failure (cardiac asthma), Insect sting that causes an  allergic reaction , Certain medicines (particularly aspirin), Infection of the lungs ( pneumonia ),  
 Smoking 
 , Viral infection, especially in infants younger than age 2, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004295-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Wheezing ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wheezing is a sign that a person may be having breathing problems. The sound of wheezing is most obvious when breathing out (exhaling). It may also be heard when breathing in (inhaling). Wheezing most often comes from the small breathing tubes (bronchial tubes) deep in the lungs. But it may be due to a blockage in larger airways or in people with certain vocal cord problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004295-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Wheezing ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your health care provider if wheezing: Occurs for the first time, Occurs with significant  shortness of breath ,  bluish skin ,  confusion , or mental status changes 
 , Keeps occurring without explanation, Is caused by an allergic reaction to a bite or medicine,  If wheezing is severe or occurs with severe shortness of breath, you should go directly to the nearest emergency department.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004295-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Wheezing ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>