<Document id="0004031" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001331.htm">
 
<Focus>Trichomoniasis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040921</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Trichomonas vaginitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>STD - trichomonas vaginitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>STI - trichomonas vaginitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sexually transmitted infection - trichomonas vaginitis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004031-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Trichomoniasis is a sexually transmitted infection caused by the parasite  Trichomonas vaginalis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004031-2" qtype="causes">What causes Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Trichomoniasis ("trich") is found worldwide. In the United States, most cases occur in women between ages 16 and 35.  Trichomonas vaginalis  is spread through sexual contact with an infected partner, either&#160;through penis-to-vagina intercourse or vulva-to-vulva contact. The parasite cannot survive in the mouth or rectum. The disease can affect both men and women, but the symptoms differ. The infection usually does not cause symptoms in men and goes away on its own in a few weeks.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004031-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Women may have these symptoms: Discomfort with intercourse, Itching of the inner thighs, Vaginal discharge (thin, greenish-yellow, frothy or foamy),  Vaginal&#160;or vulvar itching , or swelling of the labia, Vaginal odor (foul or strong smell),  Men who have symptoms may have: Burning after urination or ejaculation, Itching of urethra, Slight discharge from urethra,  Occasionally, some men with trichomoniasis may develop: Swelling and irritation in the prostate gland ( prostatitis )., Swelling in the epididymis ( epididymitis ), the tube that connects the testicle with the vas deferens. The vas deferens connects the testicles to the urethra., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004031-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>In women, a pelvic examination shows red blotches on the vaginal wall or  cervix . Examining the vaginal discharge under a microscope may show signs of inflammation or infection-causing germs in vaginal fluids. A  Pap test  may also diagnose the condition, but is not required for diagnosis. The disease can be hard to diagnose in men. Men are treated if the infection is diagnosed in any of their sexual partners. They may also be treated if they keep having symptoms of urethral burning or itching, even after getting treatment for  gonorrhea  and  chlamydia .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004031-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Antibiotics, most often metronidazole (Flagyl) or tinidazole (Tindamax), are commonly used to cure the infection. DO NOT drink alcohol while taking the medicine and for 48 hours afterward. Doing so can cause: Severe nausea, Abdominal pain, Vomiting,  Avoid sexual intercourse until you have finished treatment. Your sexual partners should be treated at the same time, even if they have no symptoms. If you have been diagnosed with a sexually transmitted infection (STI), you should be screened for other STIs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004031-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>With proper treatment, you are likely to fully recover.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004031-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Long-term infection may cause changes in the tissue on the cervix. These changes may be seen on a routine Pap smear. Treatment should be started and the Pap test repeated 3 to 6 months later. Treating trichomoniasis helps prevent it from spreading to sexual partners. Trichomoniasis is common among people with HIV/AIDS. This condition has been linked to premature&#160;delivery in pregnant women. More research about trichomoniasis in pregnancy is still needed. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004031-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have any unusual vaginal discharge or irritation. Also call if you suspect that you have been exposed to the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004031-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Trichomoniasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Practicing safer sex  can help reduce the risk of sexually transmitted infections, including trichomoniasis. Other than total abstinence, condoms remain the best and most reliable protection against sexually transmitted infections. Condoms must be used consistently and correctly to be effective.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>