<Document id="0004055" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000787.htm">
 
<Focus>Tuberous sclerosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0041341</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Adenoma sebaceum</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004055-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tuberous sclerosis is a genetic disorder that affects the skin, brain/nervous system, kidneys, heart, and lungs. The condition can also cause tumors to grow in the brain. These tumors have a tuber or root-shaped appearance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004055-2" qtype="causes">What causes Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tuberous sclerosis is genetic condition. Changes (mutations) in one of two genes,  TSC1  and  TSC2 , are responsible for most cases. Only one parent needs to pass on the mutation for the child to get the disease. However, two-thirds of cases are due to new mutations. In most cases, there is no family history of tuberous sclerosis. This condition is one of a group of diseases called neurocutaneous syndromes. Both the skin and  central nervous system  (brain and spinal cord) are involved. There are no known risk factors, other than having a parent with tuberous sclerosis. In that case, each child has a 50% chance of inheriting the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004055-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Skin symptoms include: Areas of the skin that are white (due to decreased pigment) and have either an ash leaf or confetti appearance, Red patches on the face containing many blood vessels (facial angiofibromas), Raised patches of skin with an orange-peel texture (shagreen spots), often on the back,  Brain symptoms include: Autism  spectrum disorders, Developmental delays,  Intellectual disability ,  Seizures ,  Other symptoms include: Pitted tooth enamel., Rough growths under or around the fingernails and toenails., Rubbery noncancerous tumors on or around the tongue. , Lung disease known as LAM (lymphangioleiomyomatosis). This is more common in women. In many cases, there are no symptoms. In other people, this can lead to shortness of breath, coughing blood, and lung collapse. ,  The symptoms vary from person to person. Some people have normal intelligence and no seizures. Others have intellectual disabilities or difficult-to-control seizures.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004055-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Signs may include: Abnormal heart rhythm ( arrhythmia ), Calcium deposits in the brain, Noncancerous tumors in the brain, Rubbery growths on the tongue or gums, Tumor-like growth (hamartoma) on the retina, pale patches in the eye,  Tumors  in the kidneys,  Tests may include: CT scan of the head ,  Chest CT ,  Echocardiogram  (ultrasound of the heart),  MRI of the head ,  Ultrasound of the kidney , Ultraviolet light examination of the skin,  DNA testing for the two genes that can cause this disease ( TSC1  or  TSC2 ) is available. Regular ultrasound checks of the kidneys are important to make sure there is no tumor growth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004055-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known cure for tuberous sclerosis. Because the disease can differ from person to person, treatment is based on the symptoms. Depending on the severity of the intellectual disability, the child may need special education., Some seizures are controlled with medicine (vigabatrin is first line for infantile spasms). Other children may need surgery., Small growths on the face (facial angiofibromas) may be removed by laser treatment. These growths tend to come back, and repeat treatments will be needed., Cardiac rhabdomyomas commonly disappear after puberty. Surgery to remove them is usually not needed., Brain tumors can be treated with medicines called mTOR inhibitors (sirolimus, everolimus)., Kidney tumors are treated with surgery, or by reducing the blood supply using special x-ray techniques. mTOR inhibitors are being studied as another treatment for kidney tumors., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004055-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>For additional information and resources, contact the Tuberous Sclerosis Alliance at  www.tsalliance.org .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004055-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children with mild tuberous sclerosis most often do well. However, children with severe intellectual disability or uncontrollable seizures often need lifelong assistance. Sometimes when a child is born with severe tuberous sclerosis, one of the parents is found to have had a mild case of tuberous sclerosis that was not diagnosed. The tumors in this disease tend to be noncancerous (benign). However, some tumors (such as kidney or brain tumors) can become cancerous.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004055-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Brain tumors ( astrocytoma ), Heart tumors (rhabdomyoma), Severe intellectual disability, Uncontrollable seizures, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004055-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if: Either side of your family has a history of tuberous sclerosis ,  You notice symptoms of tuberous sclerosis in your child ,  Contact a genetic specialist if your child is diagnosed with cardiac rhabdomyoma. Tuberous sclerosis is the leading cause of this tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0004055-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Tuberous sclerosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling is recommended for couples who have a family history of tuberous sclerosis and who want to have children.  Prenatal diagnosis is available for families with a known gene mutation or history of this condition. However, tuberous sclerosis often appears as a new DNA mutation. These cases are not preventable.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>