<Document id="0004266" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002857.htm">
 
<Focus>Wasp sting</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0413119</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004266-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Wasp sting ?</Question>
			<Answer>This article describes the effects of a wasp sting. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage a sting. If you or someone you are with is stung, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004266-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Wasp sting ?</Question>
			<Answer>Below are symptoms of a wasp sting in different parts of the body. EYES, EARS, NOSE, AND THROAT Swelling of throat, lips, tongue, and mouth * ,  HEART AND BLOOD VESSELS Rapid heart rate, Severe decrease in blood pressure, Collapse ( shock ) * ,  LUNGS Difficulty breathing * ,  SKIN Hives *, Itching, Swelling and pain at site of sting ,  STOMACH AND INTESTINES Abdominal cramping, Diarrhea, Nausea and vomiting ,  Note:  The symptoms marked with an asterisk (*) are from an allergic reaction to the venom, not from the venom itself.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004266-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Wasp sting ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004266-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Wasp sting ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on how allergic they are to the insect sting and how quickly they receive treatment. The faster they get medical help, the better the chance for recovery. The chances of future total body reactions increase when local reactions become increasingly severe. People who are not allergic to wasps, bees, hornets or yellow jackets usually get better within 1 week. DO NOT put your hands or feet in nests or hives or other preferred hiding places. Avoid wearing bright colored clothing and perfumes or other fragrances if you will be in an area where wasps are known to congregate.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004266-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Wasp sting ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on how allergic they are to the insect sting and how quickly they receive treatment. The faster they get medical help, the better the chance for recovery. The chances of future total body reactions increase when local reactions become increasingly severe. People who are not allergic to wasps, bees, hornets or yellow jackets usually get better within 1 week. DO NOT put your hands or feet in nests or hives or other preferred hiding places. Avoid wearing bright colored clothing and perfumes or other fragrances if you will be in an area where wasps are known to congregate.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>