<Document id="0004006" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000730.htm">
 
<Focus>Transient ischemic attack</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0007787</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mini stroke</Synonym>
		<Synonym>TIA</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Little stroke</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cerebrovascular disease - TIA</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Carotid artery - TIA</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004006-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Transient ischemic attack ?</Question>
			<Answer>A transient ischemic attack (TIA) occurs when blood flow to a part of the brain stops for a brief time. A person will have stroke-like symptoms for up to 24 hours. In most cases, the symptoms last for 1 to 2 hours. A transient ischemic attack is a warning sign that a true  stroke  may happen in the future (often near future) if something is not done to prevent it.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004006-2" qtype="causes">What causes Transient ischemic attack ?</Question>
			<Answer>A TIA is different than a stroke. After a TIA, the blockage breaks up quickly and dissolves on its own. A TIA does not cause brain tissue to die. The loss of blood flow to an area of the brain can be caused by: A blood clot in an artery of the brain, A blood clot that travels to the brain from somewhere else in the body (for example, from the heart), An injury to blood vessels, Narrowing of a blood vessel in the brain or leading to the brain ,  High blood pressure  is the main risk factor for TIAs and stroke. Other major  risk factors  are: Irregular heartbeat called  atrial fibrillation ,  Diabetes , Family history of stroke, Being male,  High cholesterol , Tendency to have abnormal blood clotting, Increasing age, especially after age 55, Ethnicity (African Americans are more likely to die of stroke), Smoking, Alcohol use, Recreational drug use, History of prior TIA or stroke ,  People who have heart disease or  poor blood flow in their legs  caused by narrowed arteries are also more likely to have a TIA or stroke.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004006-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Transient ischemic attack ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms begin suddenly, last a short time (from a few minutes to 1 to 2 hours), and go away. They may occur again at a later time. The symptoms of a TIA are the same as the symptoms of a stroke, and include: Change in alertness (including sleepiness or unconsciousness), Changes in the senses (such as hearing, vision, taste, and touch), Mental changes (such as confusion, memory loss, difficulty writing or reading, trouble speaking or understanding others), Muscle problems (such as weakness, trouble swallowing, trouble walking), Dizziness or loss of balance and coordination, Lack of control over the bladder or bowels, Sensation problems (such as numbness or tingling on one side of the body) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004006-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Transient ischemic attack ?</Question>
			<Answer>While the symptoms and signs of a TIA may go away by the time you get to the hospital, it is important to be evaluated right away. In the event your symptoms don't go away, all treatments are more effective the sooner they are given. Someone with a TIA is also very likely to have a stroke in the following days to weeks. A TIA diagnosis may be made based on your medical history alone. Your health care provider will do a complete physical exam to check for heart and blood vessel problems. You will also be checked for nerve and muscle problems. Your provider will use a stethoscope to listen to your heart and arteries. An abnormal sound called a bruit may be heard when listening to the carotid artery in your neck or other artery. A bruit is caused by irregular blood flow. Tests will be done to rule out a stroke or other disorders that may cause the symptoms: You will likely have a  head CT scan  or  brain MRI . A stroke may show changes on these tests, but TIAs will not., You may have an  angiogram , CT angiogram, or MR angiogram to see which blood vessel is blocked or bleeding., You may have an  echocardiogram  if your provider thinks you may have a blood clot from the heart., You may have a 
    carotid duplex ultrasound . It can show if the carotid arteries in your neck have narrowed., You will likely have an electrocardiogram ( ECG ) and  heart rhythm monitoring  tests to check for an irregular heartbeat. ,  Your provider may do other tests to check for high blood pressure, heart disease including an irregular heartbeat, diabetes, high cholesterol, and other causes of, and risk factors for TIAs or stroke. You may have an EEG test to check if your symptoms are not due to a seizure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004006-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Transient ischemic attack ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you have had a TIA within the last 48 hours, you will likely be admitted to the hospital so that doctors can search for the cause and monitor you. High blood pressure, heart disease, diabetes, high cholesterol, and blood disorders will be treated as needed. You will be encouraged to make lifestyle changes to reduce your risk of further symptoms. Changes include  quitting smoking , exercising more, and eating healthier foods. You may receive blood thinners, such as  aspirin , heparin, warfarin (Coumadin), or direct acting oral anticoagulants (DOACs) to reduce blood clotting. Some people who have blocked neck arteries may need surgery ( carotid endarterectomy ). If you have an irregular heartbeat (atrial fibrillation) or other heart problems, you will be treated to avoid future complications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004006-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Transient ischemic attack ?</Question>
			<Answer>TIAs do not cause lasting damage to the brain. But, TIAs are a warning sign that you may have a true stroke in the coming days or months. Some people who have a TIA will have a stroke within 3 months. Half of these strokes happen during the 48 hours after a TIA. The stroke may occur that same day or at a later time. Some people have only a single TIA, and others have more than one TIA. You can reduce your chances of a future stroke by following up with your provider to manage your risk factors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004006-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Transient ischemic attack ?</Question>
			<Answer>A TIA is a medical emergency. Call 911 or the local emergency number right away. Do not ignore symptoms just because they go away. They may be a warning of a future stroke.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004006-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Transient ischemic attack ?</Question>
			<Answer>Follow your provider's instructions on how to prevent TIAs and strokes. You will likely be told to make lifestyle changes and take medicines to treat high blood pressure or high cholesterol.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>