<Document id="0000140" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a609023.html">

<Focus>Betaxolol</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000140-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Betaxolol and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Betaxolol is used alone or with other medications to control high blood pressure. Betaxolol is in a class of medications called beta blockers. It works by relaxing blood vessels and slowing heart rate to improve blood flow and decrease blood pressure. High blood pressure is a common condition and when not treated, can cause damage to the brain, heart, blood vessels, kidneys and other parts of the body. Damage to these organs may cause heart disease, a heart attack, heart failure, stroke, kidney failure, loss of vision, and other problems. In addition to taking medication, making lifestyle changes will also help to control your blood pressure. These changes include eating a diet that is low in fat and salt, maintaining a healthy weight, exercising at least 30 minutes most days, not smoking, and using alcohol in moderation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000140-2" qtype="usage">How should Betaxolol be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Betaxolol comes as a tablet to take by mouth. It is usually taken once a day. Take betaxolol at around the same time every day. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Take betaxolol exactly as directed. Do not take more or less of it or take it more often than prescribed by your doctor. Your doctor will probably start you on a low dose of betaxolol and may increase your dose after 1&#8211;2 weeks if your blood pressure is not controlled. Betaxolol controls high blood pressure but does not cure it. It may take 1&#8211;2 weeks or longer before the full benefit of betaxolol is noted. Continue to take betaxolol even if you feel well. Do not stop taking betaxolol without talking to your doctor. If you suddenly stop taking betaxolol, you may experience serious heart problems such as angina (chest pain), heart attack, or an irregular heartbeat. Your doctor will probably decrease your dose gradually over about 2 weeks and will monitor you carefully during this time. Your doctor may also tell you to limit physical activity while your dose is being decreased.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000140-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Betaxolol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking betaxolol, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to betaxolol, any other medications, or any of the ingredients in betaxolol tablets. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take while taking betaxolol. Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have heart failure or a slow or irregular heart rate. Your doctor may tell you not to take betaxolol., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had asthma or other lung disease; diabetes; psoriasis (a skin condition); hyperthyroidism (an overactive thyroid gland); pheochromocytoma (tumor on a small gland near the kidneys); or kidney, liver, or heart disease. Also tell your doctor if you have ever had a serious allergic reaction to a food or any other substance., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while taking betaxolol, call your doctor., if you are having surgery, including dental or eye surgery, tell your doctor, dentist, or eye doctor that you are taking betaxolol., you should know that betaxolol may make you drowsy. Do not drive a car or operate machinery until you know how this medication affects you., you should know that betaxolol may increase the risk of hypoglycemia (low blood sugar) and prevent the warning signs and symptoms that would tell you that your blood sugar is low. Let your doctor know if you are unable to eat or drink normally or are vomiting while you are taking betaxolol. You should know the symptoms of low blood sugar and what to do if you have these symptoms., you should know that if you have allergic reactions to different substances, your reactions may be worse while you are taking betaxolol, and your allergic reactions may not respond to the usual doses of injectable epinephrine., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000140-5" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Betaxolol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000140-6" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Betaxolol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Take the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not take a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000140-7" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Betaxolol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Betaxolol may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 extreme tiredness, difficulty falling asleep or staying asleep, unusual dreams, heartburn, nausea, diarrhea, joint pain, decreased sexual ability in men, cold hands and feet, numbness, burning, or tingling in the arms, legs, hands, or feet, rash,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, call your doctor immediately:
 difficulty breathing, especially during activity or when lying down, swelling of the arms, hands, feet, ankles, or lower legs, unexplained weight gain, fast, slow, pounding, or irregular heartbeat, chest pain,  Betaxolol may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while taking this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000140-8" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Betaxolol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000140-9" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Betaxolol ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. Symptoms of overdose may include:
 difficulty breathing, especially during activity or when lying down, swelling of the arms, hands, feet, ankles, or lower legs, unexplained weight gain, chest pain, fast, pounding, slow, or irregular heartbeat, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000140-10" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Betaxolol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Before you are tested for glaucoma (increased pressure in your eyes that may lead to vision loss), tell your doctor and the technician that you are taking betaxolol. Do not let anyone else take your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000140-11" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Betaxolol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kerlone &#174; &#182; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>