<Document id="0000956" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a697027.html">

<Focus>Penciclovir Cream</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000956-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Penciclovir Cream and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Penciclovir is used on the lips and faces of adults to treat cold sores caused by herpes simplex virus. Penciclovir does not cure herpes infections but decreases pain and itching if applied when the earliest symptoms first appear. This medication is sometimes prescribed for other uses; ask your doctor or pharmacist for more information.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000956-2" qtype="usage">How should Penciclovir Cream be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Penciclovir comes as a cream. It is usually used externally every 2 hours while you are awake for 4 days. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist or doctor to explain any part you do not understand. Use penciclovir exactly as directed. Do not use more or less of it or use it more often than prescribed by your doctor. Use this medication as soon as possible after symptoms appear. Clean and dry the area before applying the cream to avoid spreading the infection. Rub the cream in gently, using enough cream to cover all sores completely. Continue to use penciclovir even if you feel well. Do not stop using penciclovir without talking to your doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000956-3" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Penciclovir Cream ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before using penciclovir, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to penciclovir, acyclovir (Zovirax), or any other drugs., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications you are taking, including vitamins., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while taking penciclovir, call your doctor., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000956-4" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Penciclovir Cream ?</Question>
			<Answer>Apply the missed dose as soon as you remember it and apply any remaining doses for that day at evenly spaced intervals. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not apply a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000956-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Penciclovir Cream ?</Question>
			<Answer>Penciclovir may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 headache, irritation at the site of application, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000956-6" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Penciclovir Cream ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000956-7" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Penciclovir Cream ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Penciclovir should only be used on the lips and face. Avoid getting it in your eyes. Keep the infected area clean and dry. Do not let anyone else use your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. If you still have symptoms of infection after you finish the penciclovir, call your doctor. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000956-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Penciclovir Cream ?</Question>
			<Answer>Denavir &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>