<Document id="0000008" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a681004.html">

<Focus>Acetaminophen</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000008-1" qtype="important warning">What important warning or information should I know about Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Taking too much acetaminophen can cause liver damage, sometimes serious enough to require liver transplantation or cause death. You might accidentally take too much acetaminophen if you do not follow the directions on the prescription or package label carefully, or if you take more than one product that contains acetaminophen. To be sure that you take acetaminophen safely, you should
 not take more than one product that contains acetaminophen at a time. Read the labels of all the prescription and nonprescription medications you are taking to see if they contain acetaminophen. Be aware that abbreviations such as APAP, AC, Acetaminophen, Acetaminoph, Acetaminop, Acetamin, or Acetam. may be written on the label in place of the word acetaminophen. Ask your doctor or pharmacist if you don't know if a medication that you are taking contains acetaminophen., take acetaminophen exactly as directed on the prescription or package label. Do not take more acetaminophen or take it more often than directed, even if you still have fever or pain. Ask your doctor or pharmacist if you do not know how much medication to take or how often to take your medication. Call your doctor if you still have pain or fever after taking your medication as directed., be aware that you should not take more than 4000 mg of acetaminophen per day. If you need to take more than one product that contains acetaminophen, it may be difficult for you to calculate the total amount of acetaminophen you are taking.  Ask your doctor or pharmacist to help you., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had liver disease., not take acetaminophen if you drink three or more alcoholic drinks every day. Talk to your doctor about the safe use of alcohol while you are taking acetaminophen., stop taking your medication and call your doctor right away if you think you have taken too much acetaminophen, even if you feel well.,  Talk to your pharmacist or doctor if you have questions about the safe use of acetaminophen or acetaminophen-containing products.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000008-2" qtype="indication">Who should get Acetaminophen and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acetaminophen is used to relieve mild to moderate pain from headaches, muscle aches, menstrual periods, colds and sore throats, toothaches, backaches, reactions to vaccinations (shots), and to reduce fever. Acetaminophen may also be used to relieve the pain of osteoarthritis (arthritis caused by the breakdown of the lining of the joints). Acetaminophen is in a class of medications called analgesics (pain relievers) and antipyretics (fever reducers). It works by changing the way the body senses pain and by cooling the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000008-3" qtype="usage">How should Acetaminophen be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acetaminophen comes as a tablet, chewable tablet, capsule, suspension or solution (liquid), extended-release (long-acting) tablet, and orally disintegrating tablet (tablet that dissolves quickly in the mouth), to take by mouth, with or without food. Acetaminophen is available without a prescription, but your doctor may prescribe acetaminophen to treat certain conditions. Follow the directions on the package or prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. If you are giving acetaminophen to your child, read the package label carefully to make sure that it is the right product for the age of the child. Do not give children acetaminophen products that are made for adults. Some products for adults and older children may contain too much acetaminophen for a younger child. Check the package label to find out how much medication the child needs. If you know how much your child weighs, give the dose that matches that weight on the chart. If you don't know your child's weight, give the dose that matches your child's age. Ask your child's doctor if you don't know how much medication to give your child. Acetaminophen comes in combination with other medications to treat cough and cold symptoms. Ask your doctor or pharmacist for advice on which product is best for your symptoms. Check nonprescription cough and cold product labels carefully before using two or more products at the same time. These products may contain the same active ingredient(s) and taking them together could cause you to receive an overdose. This is especially important if you will be giving cough and cold medications to a child. Swallow the extended-release tablets whole; do not split, chew, crush, or dissolve them.  Place the orally disintegrating tablet ('Meltaways') in your mouth and allow it to dissolve, or chew it before swallowing. Shake the suspension well before each use to mix the medication evenly. Always use the measuring cup or syringe provided by the manufacturer to measure each dose of the solution or suspension. Do not switch dosing devices between different products; always use the device that comes in the product packaging. Stop taking acetaminophen and call your doctor if your symptoms get worse, you develop new or unexpected symptoms, including redness or swelling, your pain lasts for more than 10 days, or your fever gets worse or lasts more than 3 days. Also stop giving acetaminophen to your child and call your child's doctor if your child develops new symptoms, including redness or swelling, or if your child's pain lasts for longer than 5 days, or if a fever gets worse or lasts longer than 3 days. Do not give acetaminophen to a child who has a sore throat that is severe or does not go away, or that occurs along with fever, headache, rash, nausea, or vomiting. Call the child's doctor right away, because these symptoms may be signs of a more serious condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000008-5" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking acetaminophen, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to acetaminophen, any other medications, or any of the ingredients in the product. Ask your pharmacist or check the label on the package for a list of ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, or herbal products you are taking or plan to take while taking acetaminophen.  Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., The following nonprescription products may interact with acetaminophen: medications for pain, coughs, fever, and colds. Be sure to let your doctor and pharmacist know that you are taking these medications before you start taking acetaminophen. Do not start any of these medications while taking acetaminophen without discussing with your healthcare provider., tell your doctor if you have ever developed a rash after taking acetaminophen., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while taking acetaminophen, call your doctor., if you drink three or more alcoholic beverages every day, do not take acetaminophen. Ask your doctor or pharmacist about the safe use of alcoholic beverages while taking acetaminophen., you should know that combination acetaminophen products for cough and colds that contain nasal decongestants, antihistamines, cough suppressants, and expectorants should not be used in children younger than 2 years of age.  Use of these medications in young children can cause serious and life-threatening effects or death. In children 2 through 11 years of age, combination cough and cold products should be used carefully and only according to the directions on the label., if you have phenylketonuria (PKU, an inherited condition in which a special diet must be followed to prevent damage to your brain that can cause severe intellectual disability), you should know that some brands of acetaminophen chewable tablets may be sweetened with aspartame, a source of phenylalanine., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000008-6" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000008-7" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>This medication is usually taken as needed. If your doctor has told you to take acetaminophen regularly, take the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not take a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000008-8" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acetaminophen may cause side effects. Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of the following symptoms, stop taking acetaminophen and call your doctor immediately or get emergency medical attention:
 red, peeling or blistering skin, rash, hives, itching, swelling of the face, throat, tongue, lips, eyes, hands, feet, ankles, or lower legs , hoarseness , difficulty breathing or swallowing,  Acetaminophen may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while you are taking this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000008-9" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000008-10" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. If someone takes more than the recommended dose of acetaminophen, get medical help immediately, even if the person does not have any symptoms. Symptoms of overdose may include the following:
 nausea, vomiting, loss of appetite, sweating, extreme tiredness, unusual bleeding or bruising, pain in the upper right part of the stomach, yellowing of the skin or eyes, flu-like symptoms, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000008-11" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before having any laboratory test, tell your doctor and the laboratory personnel that you are taking acetaminophen. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about acetaminophen. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000008-12" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Actamin &#174; , Feverall &#174; , Panadol &#174; , Tempra Quicklets &#174; , Tylenol &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="13">
			<Question qid="0000008-13" qtype="brand names of combination products">What are the brand names of combination products of Acetaminophen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Actamin &#174; , Feverall &#174; , Panadol &#174; , Tempra Quicklets &#174; , Tylenol &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>