<Document id="0000576" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607014.html">

<Focus>Hepatitis B Vaccine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000576-1" qtype="information">What is Hepatitis B Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000576-2" qtype="why get vaccinated">Why get vaccinated with Hepatitis B Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hepatitis B vaccine can prevent hepatitis B. Hepatitis B is a liver disease that can cause mild illness lasting a few weeks, or it can lead to a serious, lifelong illness. Acute hepatitis B virus infection  is a short-term illness that can lead to fever, fatigue, loss of appetite, nausea, vomiting, jaundice (yellow skin or eyes, dark urine, clay-colored bowel movements), and pain in the muscles, joints, and stomach. Chronic hepatitis B virus infection  is a long-term illness that occurs when the hepatitis B virus remains in a person's body. Most people who go on to develop chronic hepatitis B do not have symptoms, but it is still very serious and can lead to liver damage (cirrhosis), liver cancer, and death. Chronically infected people can spread hepatitis B virus to others, even if they do not feel or look sick themselves. Hepatitis B is spread when blood, semen, or other body fluid infected with the hepatitis B virus enters the body of a person who is not infected. People can become infected with the virus through: Birth (if a pregnant person has hepatitis B, their baby can become infected), Sharing items such as razors or toothbrushes with an infected person, Contact with the blood or open sores of an infected person, Sex with an infected partner, Sharing needles, syringes, or other drug-injection equipment, Exposure to blood from needlesticks or other sharp instruments,  Most people who are vaccinated with hepatitis B vaccine are immune for life..</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000576-3" qtype="indication">Who should get Hepatitis B Vaccine and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000576-4" qtype="contraindication">Who should not get Hepatitis B Vaccine and what are its contraindications ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000576-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Hepatitis B Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Soreness where the shot was given or fever can happen after hepatitis B vaccination.,  People sometimes faint after medical procedures, including vaccination. Tell your provider if you feel dizzy or have vision changes or ringing in the ears. As with any medicine, there is a very remote chance of a vaccine causing a severe allergic reaction, other serious injury, or death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000576-6" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Hepatitis B Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000576-8" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Hepatitis B Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your healthcare provider. He or she can give you the vaccine package insert or suggest other sources of information., Call your local or state health department., Visit the website of the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for vaccine package inserts and additional information at  http://www.fda.gov/ vaccines-blood-biologics/vaccines ., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): Call  1-800-232-4636  ( 1-800-CDC-INFO ) or visit CDC's website at  http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines .,  Hepatitis B Vaccine Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Immunization Program. 10/15/2021.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000576-9" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Hepatitis B Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Engerix-B &#174; , Recombivax HB &#174; , PREHEVBRIO &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000576-10" qtype="brand names of combination products">What are the brand names of combination products of Hepatitis B Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Engerix-B &#174; , Recombivax HB &#174; , PREHEVBRIO &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>