<Document id="0000901" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a615036.html">

<Focus>Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000901-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>The combination of ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir is usually used in combination with ribavirin (Copegus, Rebetol), but sometimes it is used alone to treat a certain type of chronic (long-term) hepatitis C infection (swelling of the liver caused by a virus). Ombitasvir is a hepatitis C virus (HCV) NS5A inhibitor. It works by stopping the virus that causes hepatitis C from spreading inside the body. Paritaprevir is a protease inhibitor. It works by decreasing the amount of HCV in the body. Ritonavir is a protease inhibitor. It helps to increase the amount of paritaprevir in the body so that the medication will have a greater effect. It is not known if ombitasvir, paritaprevir, or ritonavir prevent the spread of hepatitis C to other people.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000901-2" qtype="usage">How should Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>The combination of ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir comes as a tablet to take by mouth. Take ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir every morning with food. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Take ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir at around the same times every day. Do not take more or less of it or take it more often than prescribed by your doctor. The combination of ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir controls HCV but does not cure it. It is usually taken for 12 weeks. Continue to take ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir even if you feel well. The length of your treatment depends on how well you respond to the medication and whether you experience severe side effects. Do not stop taking ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir without talking to your doctor. Ask your pharmacist or doctor for a copy of the manufacturer's information for the patient.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000901-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir, any other medications, or any of the ingredients in ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir tablets. If you have had a serious or life-threatening reaction to ritonavir (rash, blistering or peeling of the skin), your doctor will probably tell not to take ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir. Ask your pharmacist or check the Medication Guide for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor if you are taking alfuzosin (Uroxatral); apalutamide (Erleada); atorvastatin (Lipitor, in Caduet); carbamazepine (Carbatrol, Epitol, Equetro, Tegretol); cisapride (Propulsid; no longer available in U.S.); dronedarone (Multaq); efavirenz (Sustiva, in Atripla); ergot containing medicines such as dihydroergotamine mesylate (D.H.E. 45, Migranal), ergonovine, ergotamine (Ergomar, in Cafergot, in Migergot), and methylergonovine (Methergine); ethinyl estradiol oral contraceptives such as certain ('birth control pills'), patches, hormonal vaginal rings and other ethinyl estradiol products; everolimus (Afinitor, Zortress); lomitapide (Juxtapid); lovastatin (Altoprev); lurasidone (Latuda); midazolam (by mouth); phenobarbital; phenytoin (Dilantin, Phenytek); pimozide (Orap); ranolazine (Ranexa); rifampin (Rifadin, Rimactane, in Rifamate, in Rifater); sildenafil (Revatio) for treatment of pulmonary arterial hypertension; simvastatin (Flolipid, Zocor, in Vytorin); sirolimus (Rapamune); St. John's wort; tacrolimus (Astagraf XL, Envarsus XR, Prograf); or triazolam (Halcion). Also, tell your doctor if you are taking colchicine (Colcrys, Mitigare) and have liver or kidney disease. Your doctor will probably tell you not to take ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir if you are taking one or more of these medications., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention any of the following: acetaminophen and hydrocodone (Anexsia, Zyfrel); alprazolam (Xanax); angiotensin receptor blocker (ARB) such as candesartan (Atacand, in Atacand HCT), losartan (Cozaar, in Hyzaar), and valsartan (Diovan, in Diovan HCT, Exforge); anticoagulants ('blood thinners') such as warfarin (Coumadin, Jantoven); buprenorphine and naloxone (Suboxone, Zubsolv); calcium channel blockers such as amlodipine (Norvasc, in Caduet), diltiazem (Cardizem, Cartia), nifedipine (Adalat, Afeditab), and verapamil (Calan, Verelan); carisoprodol (Soma); cyclobenzaprine (Amrix); cyclosporine (Gengraf, Neoral, Sandimmune); diazepam (Valium); elagolix (Orilissa); encorafenib (Braftovi); fluticasone (Flonase, Flovent, in Advair); fostamatinib (Tavalisse); furosemide (Lasix); certain hormone replacement therapies (HRT); ibrutinib (Imbruvica); ivosidenib (Tibsovo); ketoconazole; metformin (Glucophage, Riomet); medications for irregular heartbeat such as amiodarone (Nexterone, Pacerone), bepridil (no longer available in the U.S.), digoxin (Lanoxin), disopyramide (Norpace), flecainide, lidocaine (Xylocaine), mexiletine, propafenone (Rythmol), and quinidine (in Nuedexta); omeprazole (Prilosec); pravastatin (Pravachol); quetiapine (Seroquel); rilpivirine (Edurant; in Complera); ritonavir (Norvir, in Kaletra) used in combination with other HIV protease inhibitors such as atazanavir (Reyataz, in Evotaz), darunavir (Prezista, in Prezcobix), and lopinavir (in Kaletra); salmeterol (Serevent, in Advair); and voriconazole (Vfend). Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have any type of liver disease other than hepatitis C. Your doctor may tell you not to take ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir., tell your doctor if you have ever had a liver transplant or if you have diabetes or human immunodeficiency virus (HIV)., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breastfeeding. If you become pregnant while taking ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir, call your doctor., you should know that ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir may decrease the effectiveness of hormonal contraceptives (birth control pills, patches, rings, implants, injections, and intrauterine devices). Use another form of birth control while you are taking ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir and for 2 weeks after your final dose. Talk to your doctor about types of birth control that will work for you during your treatment with ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir and until you can resume taking your hormonal contraceptive., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000901-5" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000901-6" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir ?</Question>
			<Answer>If it is 12 hours or less after you miss a dose of ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir, take the missed dose with a meal as soon as you remember it. However, if it is more than 12 hours since the time you should have taken your dos, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not take a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000901-7" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 difficulty falling asleep or staying asleep,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms or those listed in the IMPORTANT WARNING section, call your doctor immediately or get emergency medical treatment:
 rash, reddening of the skin, hives, itching, swelling of the face, throat, tongue, lips, eyes, hands, feet, ankles, or lower legs, weakness, confusion,  Ombitasvir, paritaprevir, and ritonavir may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while taking this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000901-8" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the carton it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). Do not remove the tablets from the daily dose pack provided by the manufacturer until ready to take them. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000901-9" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000901-10" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir ?</Question>
			<Answer>Do not let anyone else take your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000901-11" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Ombitasvir, Paritaprevir, and Ritonavir ?</Question>
			<Answer>Technivie &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>