<Document id="0000766" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a682084.html">

<Focus>Metaproterenol</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000766-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Metaproterenol and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Metaproterenol is used to prevent and treat wheezing, shortness of breath, coughing, and chest tightness caused by asthma, chronic bronchitis, emphysema, and other lung diseases. It relaxes and opens air passages in the lungs, making it easier to breathe.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000766-2" qtype="usage">How should Metaproterenol be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Metaproterenol comes as tablets and syrup to take by mouth and as a solution to inhale by mouth. It usually is used by oral inhalation every 4 hours to relieve symptoms or 3 to 4 times a day to prevent symptoms or by mouth three or four times a day. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Use metaproterenol exactly as directed. Do not use more or less of it or use it more often than prescribed by your doctor. Metaproterenol controls symptoms of asthma and other lung diseases but does not cure them. Continue to use metaproterenol even if you feel well. Do not stop using metaproterenol without talking to your doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000766-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Metaproterenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before using metaproterenol, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to metaproterenol or any other drugs., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription medications you are taking, especially atenolol (Tenormin); carteolol (Cartrol); labetalol (Normodyne, Trandate); metoprolol (Lopressor); nadolol (Corgard); phenelzine (Nardil); propranolol (Inderal); sotalol (Betapace); theophylline (Theo-Dur); timolol (Blocadren); tranylcypromine (Parnate); other medications for asthma, heart disease, or depression., tell your doctor and pharmacist what nonprescription medications and vitamins you are taking, including ephedrine, phenylephrine, phenylpropanolamine, or pseudoephedrine. Many nonprescription products contain these drugs (e.g., diet pills and medications for colds and asthma), so check labels carefully. Do not take any of these medications without talking to your doctor (even if you never had a problem taking them before)., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had irregular heartbeat, increased heart rate, glaucoma, heart disease, high blood pressure, an overactive thyroid gland, diabetes, or seizures., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while using metaproterenol, call your doctor., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are using metaproterenol., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000766-5" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Metaproterenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Use the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not use a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000766-6" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Metaproterenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Metaproterenol may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 tremor, nervousness, dizziness, weakness, headache, nausea,  If you experience any of the following symptoms, call your doctor immediately:
 increased difficulty breathing, rapid or increased heart rate, irregular heartbeat, chest pain or discomfort,  If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000766-7" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Metaproterenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). Do not use the solution if it is pink, yellow, or darker than usual or if it has floating particles. Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000766-8" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Metaproterenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000766-9" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Metaproterenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Do not let anyone else use your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000766-10" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Metaproterenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Alupent &#174; &#182; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>