<Document id="0000401" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a601141.html">

<Focus>Doxycycline Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000401-1" qtype="important warning">What important warning or information should I know about Doxycycline Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000401-2" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Doxycycline Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Your doctor may order certain lab tests to check your body's response to doxycycline injection. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about doxycycline injection. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000401-3" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Doxycycline Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before receiving doxycycline injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to doxycycline, minocycline (Dynacin, Minocin, Solodyn, Ximino), tetracycline (Achromycin V, in Pylera), demeclocycline, any other medications, or any of the ingredients in doxycycline injection. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention any of the following: anticoagulants ('blood thinners') such as warfarin (Jantoven),  carbamazepine (Epitol, Tegretol, others), penicillin (Bicillin, PfizerPen), phenobarbital, or phenytoin (Phenytek). Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had lupus (a disease in which the body attacks many of its own organs)., you should know that doxycycline injection may decrease the effectiveness of hormonal contraceptives (birth control pills, patches, rings, or injections). Talk to your doctor about using another form of birth control., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while receiving doxycycline injection, call your doctor., plan to avoid unnecessary or prolonged exposure to sunlight and to wear protective clothing, sunglasses, and sunscreen. Doxycycline injection may make your skin sensitive to sunlight., you should know that when doxycycline is used during pregnancy or in babies or children up to age 8, it can cause the teeth to become permanently stained and can cause problems with bone growth. Doxycycline injection should not be used in children under age 8 unless your doctor decides it is needed., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000401-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Doxycycline Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Doxycycline injection may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 nausea, loss of appetite, vomiting, diarrhea, difficulty or pain when swallowing, swollen tongue, swelling, redness, burning, itching, or irritation of the vagina, vaginal discharge, painful or difficult urination,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, call your doctor immediately:
 severe diarrhea (watery or bloody stools) that may occur up to 2 months or more after your treatment, headache, blurred vision, stomach cramps, fever, rash, hives, itching, swelling of the face, eyes, mouth, throat, tongue, or lips, difficulty breathing or swallowing,  Doxycycline injection may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while receiving this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000401-6" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Doxycycline Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000401-7" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Doxycycline Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000401-9" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Doxycycline Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Doxy 100 &#174; , Doxy 200 &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>