<Document id="0000585" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a682871.html">

<Focus>Hydrocortisone Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000585-1" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Hydrocortisone Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory. Your doctor will order certain lab tests to check your body's response to hydrocortisone injection. If you are having any skin tests such as allergy or tuberculosis tests, tell the doctor or technician that you are receiving hydrocortisone injection. Before having any laboratory test, tell your doctor and the laboratory personnel that you are using hydrocortisone injection. Do not let anyone else use your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000585-2" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Hydrocortisone Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before receiving hydrocortisone injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to hydrocortisone, any other medications, benzyl alcohol, or any of the ingredients in hydrocortisone injection. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention any of the following: aminoglutethimide (Cytadren; no longer available in U.S.); amphotericin B (Abelcet, Ambisome, Amphotec); anticoagulants ('blood thinners') such as warfarin (Coumadin, Jantoven); aspirin and other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) such as ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin) and naproxen (Aleve, Naprosyn) and selective COX-2 inhibitors such as celecoxib (Celebrex); carbamazepine (Equetro, Tegretol, Teril); cholinesterase inhibitors such as donepezil (Aricept, in Namzaric), galantamine (Razadyne), neostigmine (Bloxiverz), pyridostigmine (Mestinon, Regonol), and rivastigmine (Exelon); cholestyramine (Prevalite); cyclosporine (Gengraf, Neoral, Sandimmune); medications for diabetes including insulin; digoxin (Lanoxin); diuretics ('water pills'); erythromycin (E.E.S., Ery-Tab, Erythrocin, others); estrogens including hormonal contraceptives (birth control pills, patches, rings, implants, and injections); isoniazid (Laniazid, Rifamate, in Rifater); ketoconazole (Nizoral, Xolegel); phenobarbital; phenytoin (Dilantin, Phenytek); rifabutin (Mycobutin); and rifampin (Rifadin, Rimactane, in Rifamate, in Rifater). Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have a fungal infection (other than on your skin or nails). Your doctor will probably tell you not to use hydrocortisone injection. Also, tell your doctor if you have idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP; an ongoing condition that may cause easy bruising or bleeding due to an abnormally low number of platelets in the blood). Your doctor probably will not give you hydrocortisone intramuscularly, if you have ITP., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had tuberculosis (TB: a type of lung infection); cataracts (clouding of the lens of the eye); glaucoma (an eye disease); Cushing's syndrome (condition where the body produces too much of the hormone cortisol); diabetes; high blood pressure; heart failure; a recent heart attack; emotional problems, depression or other types of mental illness; myasthenia gravis (a condition in which the muscles become weak); osteoporosis (condition in which the bones become weak and fragile and can break easily); seizures; ulcers; or liver, kidney, heart, intestinal, or thyroid disease. Also tell your doctor if you have any type of untreated bacterial, parasitic, or viral infection anywhere in your body or a herpes eye infection (a type of infection that causes a sore on the eyelid or eye surface)., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while receiving hydrocortisone injection, call your doctor., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are receiving hydrocortisone injection., do not have any vaccinations (shots to prevent diseases) without talking to your doctor., you should know that hydrocortisone injection may decrease your ability to fight infection and may prevent you from developing symptoms if you get an infection. Stay away from people who are sick and wash your hands often while you are using this medication. Be sure to avoid people who have chicken pox or measles. Call your doctor immediately if you think you may have been around someone who had chicken pox or measles., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000585-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Hydrocortisone Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hydrocortisone injection may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 headache, dizziness, slowed healing of cuts and bruises, acne, thin, fragile, or dry skin, red or purple blotches or lines under the skin, skin depressions at the injection site, increased body fat or movement to different areas of your body, difficulty falling asleep or staying asleep, inappropriate happiness, extreme changes in mood changes in personality, extreme tiredness, depression, increased sweating, muscle weakness, joint pain, dizziness, irregular or absent menstrual periods, increased appetite, hiccups,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, call your doctor immediately:
 sore throat, fever, chills, cough, or other signs of infection, seizures, vision problems, swelling of the eyes, face, lips, tongue, throat, arms, hands, feet, ankles, or lower legs, swelling or pain in the stomach, difficulty breathing or swallowing, shortness of breath, sudden weight gain, rash, hives, itching, abnormal skin patches in the mouth, nose, or throat,  Hydrocortisone injection may cause children to grow more slowly. Your child's doctor will watch your child's growth carefully while your child is using hydrocortisone injection. Talk to your child's doctor about the risks of giving this medication to your child. People who use hydrocortisone injection for a long time may develop glaucoma or cataracts. Talk to your doctor about the risks of using hydrocortisone injection and how often you should have your eyes examined during your treatment. Hydrocortisone injection may increase your risk of developing osteoporosis. Talk to your doctor about the risks of using this medication. Hydrocortisone injection may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while using this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000585-5" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Hydrocortisone Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000585-6" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Hydrocortisone Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000585-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Hydrocortisone Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer> A-Hydrocort &#174; , Solu-Cortef &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>