<Document id="0000113" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a682809.html">

<Focus>Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) Vaccine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000113-2" qtype="usage">How should Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) Vaccine be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your doctor or a health care provider will administer this medicine. When used to protect against TB, it is injected into the skin. Keep the vaccination area dry for 24 hours after receiving the vaccine, and keep the area clean until you cannot tell the vaccination area from the skin around it. When used for bladder cancer, the medicine flows into your bladder through a tube or catheter. Avoid drinking fluids for 4 hours before your treatment. You should empty your bladder before treatment. During the first hour after the medication is infused, you will lie on your stomach, back, and sides for 15 minutes each. Then you will stand, but you should keep the medication in your bladder for another hour. If you cannot keep the medication in your bladder for the entire 2 hours, tell your health care provider. At the end of 2 hours you will empty your bladder in a seated manner for safety reasons. Your urine should be disinfected for 6 hours after the medication is administered. Pour a similar amount of undiluted bleach in the toilet after you urinate. Let it stand for 15 minutes before flushing. Various dosing schedules may be used. Your doctor will schedule your treatment. Ask your doctor to explain any directions you do not understand. When the vaccine is given to protect against TB, it usually is given only one time but may be repeated if there is not a good response in 2-3 months. Response is measured by a TB skin test.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000113-3" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before receiving BCG vaccine,
 tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to BCG vaccine or any other drugs., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications you are taking, especially antibiotics, cancer chemotherapy agents, steroids, tuberculosis medications, and vitamins., tell your doctor if you have had a recent smallpox vaccination or if you have had a positive TB test., tell your doctor if you have an immune disorder, cancer, fever, an infection, or an area of severe burns on your body., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while taking BCG vaccine, call your doctor immediately., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000113-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>BCG vaccine may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 swollen lymph nodes, small red areas at the site of injection. (These usually appear 10-14 days after injection and slowly decrease in size. They should disappear after about 6 months.), fever, blood in the urine, frequent or painful urination, upset stomach, vomiting,  If you experience any of the following symptoms, call your doctor immediately:
 severe skin rash, difficulty breathing or swallowing, wheezing, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000113-5" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000113-6" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000113-7" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Bacillus Calmette-Guerin (BCG) Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>TheraCys &#174;  BCG, TICE &#174;  BCG, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>