<Document id="0000721" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a697038.html">

<Focus>Loratadine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000721-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Loratadine and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Loratadine is used to temporarily relieve the symptoms of hay fever (allergy to pollen, dust, or other substances in the air) and other allergies. These symptoms include sneezing, runny nose, and itchy eyes, nose, or throat. Loratadine is also used to treat itching and redness caused by hives. However, loratadine does not prevent hives or other allergic skin reactions. Loratadine is in a class of medications called antihistamines. It works by blocking the action of histamine, a substance in the body that causes allergic symptoms. Loratadine is also available in combination with pseudoephedrine (Sudafed, others). This monograph only includes information about the use of loratadine alone. If you are taking the loratadine and pseudoephedrine combination product, read the information on the package label or ask your doctor or pharmacist for more information.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000721-2" qtype="usage">How should Loratadine be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Loratadine comes as a syrup (liquid), a tablet, and a rapidly disintegrating (dissolving) tablet to take by mouth. It is usually taken once a day with or without food. Follow the directions on the package label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Take loratadine exactly as directed. Do not take more or less of it or take it more often than directed on the package label or recommended by your doctor. If you take more loratadine than directed, you may experience drowsiness. If you are taking the rapidly disintegrating tablet, follow the package directions to remove the tablet from the blister package without breaking the tablet. Do not try to push the tablet through the foil. After you remove the tablet from the blister package, immediately place it on your tongue and close your mouth. The tablet will quickly dissolve and can be swallowed with or without water. Do not use loratadine to treat hives that are bruised or blistered, that are an unusual color, or that do not itch. Call your doctor if you have this type of hives. Stop taking loratadine and call your doctor if your hives do not improve during the first 3 days of your treatment or if your hives last longer than 6 weeks. If you do not know the cause of your hives, call your doctor. If you are taking loratadine to treat hives, and you develop any of the following symptoms, get emergency medical help right away: difficulty swallowing, speaking, or breathing; swelling in and around the mouth or swelling of the tongue; wheezing; drooling; dizziness; or loss of consciousness. These may be symptoms of a life-threatening allergic reaction called anaphylaxis. If your doctor suspects that you may experience anaphylaxis with your hives, he may prescribe an epinephrine injector (EpiPen). Do not use loratadine in place of the epinephrine injector. Do not use this medication if the safety seal is open or torn.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000721-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking loratadine, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to loratadine, any other medications, or any of the ingredients in loratadine preparations. Check the package label for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention medications for colds and allergies., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had asthma or kidney or liver disease., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while taking loratadine, call your doctor., if you have phenylketonuria (PKU, an inherited condition in which a special diet must be followed to prevent damage to your brain that can cause severe intellectual disability), you should know that some brands of the orally disintegrating tablets may contain aspartame that forms phenylalanine., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000721-5" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000721-6" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Take the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not take a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000721-7" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Loratadine may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 headache, dry mouth, nosebleed, sore throat, mouth sores, difficulty falling asleep or staying asleep, nervousness, weakness, stomach pain, diarrhea, red or itchy eyes,  Some side effects may be serious. If you experience any of the following symptoms, stop taking loratadine and call your doctor immediately:
 rash, hives, itching, swelling of the eyes, face, lips, tongue, throat, hands, arms, feet, ankles, or lower legs, hoarseness, difficulty breathing or swallowing, wheezing, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000721-8" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature, away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom)and away from light. Use the orally disintegrating tablets immediately after you remove them from the blister package, and within 6 months after you open the outer foil pouch. Write the date that you open the foil pouch on the product label so that you will know when 6 months have passed. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000721-9" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. Symptoms of overdose may include:
 fast or pounding heartbeat, drowsiness, headache, unusual body movements, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000721-10" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about loratadine. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000721-11" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Agistam &#174; &#182; , Alavert &#174; , Claritin &#174; , Clear-Atadine &#174; &#182; , Dimetapp &#174;  ND, Tavist &#174;  Non-Sedating, Wal-itin &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000721-12" qtype="brand names of combination products">What are the brand names of combination products of Loratadine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Agistam &#174; &#182; , Alavert &#174; , Claritin &#174; , Clear-Atadine &#174; &#182; , Dimetapp &#174;  ND, Tavist &#174;  Non-Sedating, Wal-itin &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>