<Document id="0000659" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607019.html">

<Focus>Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000659-1" qtype="information">What is Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Japanese encephalitis (JE) is a serious infection caused by the Japanese encephalitis virus. It occurs mainly in rural parts of Asia., It is spread through the bite of an infected mosquito. It does not spread from person to person., Risk is very low for most travelers. It is higher for people living in areas where the disease is common, or for people traveling there for long periods of time., Most people infected with JE virus don't have any symptoms. Others might have symptoms as mild as a fever and headache, or as serious as encephalitis (brain infection)., A person with encephalitis can experience fever, neck stiffness, seizures, and coma. About 1 person in 4 with encephalitis dies. Up to half of those who don't die have permanent disability., It is believed that infection in a pregnant woman could harm her unborn baby.,  JE vaccine can help protect travelers from JE disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000659-2" qtype="indication">Who should get Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anyone who has had a severe (life-threatening) allergic reaction to a dose of JE vaccine should not get another dose., Anyone who has a severe (life threatening) allergy to any component of JE vaccine should not get the vaccine. Tell your doctor if you have any severe allergies. , Pregnant women should usually not get JE vaccine. If you are pregnant, check with your doctor. If you will be traveling for fewer than 30 days, especially if you will be staying in urban areas, tell your doctor. You might not need the vaccine., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000659-3" qtype="contraindication">Who should not get Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine and what are its contraindications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anyone who has had a severe (life-threatening) allergic reaction to a dose of JE vaccine should not get another dose., Anyone who has a severe (life threatening) allergy to any component of JE vaccine should not get the vaccine. Tell your doctor if you have any severe allergies. , Pregnant women should usually not get JE vaccine. If you are pregnant, check with your doctor. If you will be traveling for fewer than 30 days, especially if you will be staying in urban areas, tell your doctor. You might not need the vaccine., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000659-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>With a vaccine, like any medicine, there is a chance of side effects. When side effects happen, they are usually mild and go away on their own. Mild problems Pain, tenderness, redness, or swelling where the shot was given (about 1 person in 4)., Fever (mainly in children)., Headache, muscle aches (mainly in adults).,  Moderate or Severe problems Studies have shown that severe reactions to JE vaccine are very rare.,  Problems that can happen after any vaccine Brief fainting spells can happen after any medical procedure, including vaccination. Sitting or lying down for about 15 minutes can help prevent fainting, and injuries caused by a fall. Tell your doctor if you feel dizzy, or have vision changes or ringing in the ears., Lasting shoulder pain and reduced range of motion in the arm where the shot was given can happen, very rarely, after a vaccination., Severe allergic reactions from a vaccine are very rare, estimated at less than 1 in a million doses. If one were to occur, it would usually be within a few minutes to a few hours after the vaccination.,  The safety of vaccines is always being monitored. For more information, visit:  http://www.cdc.gov/vaccinesafety/ .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000659-5" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000659-6" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your doctor., Call your local or state health department., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): Call  1-800-232-4636  ( 1-800-CDC-INFO ), visit the CDC's travelers' health website at  http://www.cdc.gov/travel , or visit CDC's JE website at  http://www.cdc.gov/japaneseencephalitis .,  Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Immunization Program. 01/24/2014.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000659-7" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Japanese Encephalitis Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ixiaro &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>