<Document id="0000754" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607020.html">

<Focus>Meningococcal Vaccines</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000754-1" qtype="information">What is Meningococcal Vaccines ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meningococcal ACWY vaccine can help protect against meningococcal disease caused by serogroups A, C, W, and Y. A different meningococcal vaccine is available that can help protect against serogroup B. Meningococcal disease can cause meningitis (infection of the lining of the brain and spinal cord) and infections of the blood. Even when it is treated, meningococcal disease kills 10 to 15 infected people out of 100. And of those who survive, about 10 to 20 out of every 100 will suffer disabilities such as hearing loss, brain damage, kidney damage, loss of limbs, nervous system problems, or severe scars from skin grafts. Meningococcal disease is rare and has declined in the United States since the 1990s. However, it is a severe disease with a significant risk of death or lasting disabilities in people who get it. Anyone can get meningococcal disease but certain people are at increased risk, including:
 Infants younger than one year old, Adolescents and young adults 16 through 23 years old, People with certain medical conditions that affect the immune system, Microbiologists who routinely work with isolates of  N. meningitidis , the bacteria that cause meningococcal disease, People at risk because of an outbreak in their community, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000754-2" qtype="information">What is Meningococcal Vaccines ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meningococcal ACWY vaccine can help protect against meningococcal disease caused by serogroups A, C, W, and Y. A different meningococcal vaccine is available that can help protect against serogroup B. Meningococcal disease can cause meningitis (infection of the lining of the brain and spinal cord) and infections of the blood. Even when it is treated, meningococcal disease kills 10 to 15 infected people out of 100. And of those who survive, about 10 to 20 out of every 100 will suffer disabilities such as hearing loss, brain damage, kidney damage, loss of limbs, nervous system problems, or severe scars from skin grafts. Meningococcal disease is rare and has declined in the United States since the 1990s. However, it is a severe disease with a significant risk of death or lasting disabilities in people who get it. Anyone can get meningococcal disease but certain people are at increased risk, including:
 Infants younger than one year old, Adolescents and young adults 16 through 23 years old, People with certain medical conditions that affect the immune system, Microbiologists who routinely work with isolates of  N. meningitidis , the bacteria that cause meningococcal disease, People at risk because of an outbreak in their community, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000754-3" qtype="indication">Who should get Meningococcal Vaccines and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000754-4" qtype="contraindication">Who should not get Meningococcal Vaccines and what are its contraindications ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000754-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Meningococcal Vaccines ?</Question>
			<Answer>Redness or soreness where the shot is given can happen after meningococcal ACWY vaccination, A small percentage of people who receive meningococcal ACWY vaccine experience muscle pain, headache, or tiredness.,  People sometimes faint after medical procedures, including vaccination. Tell your provider if you feel dizzy or have vision changes or ringing in the ears. As with any medicine, there is a very remote chance of a vaccine causing a severe allergic reaction, other serious injury, or death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000754-6" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Meningococcal Vaccines ?</Question>
			<Answer>An allergic reaction could occur after the vaccinated person leaves the clinic. If you see signs of a severe allergic reaction (hives, swelling of the face and throat, difficulty breathing, a fast heartbeat, dizziness, or weakness), call 9-1-1 and get the person to the nearest hospital. For other signs that concern you, call your health care provider. Adverse reactions should be reported to the Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS). Your health care provider will usually file this report, or you can do it yourself. Visit the VAERS website at  http://www.vaers.hhs.gov  or call  1-800-822-7967 .  VAERS is only for reporting reactions, and VAERS does not give medical advice.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000754-8" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Meningococcal Vaccines ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your healthcare provider., Call your local or state health department., Visit the website of the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for vaccine package inserts and additional information at  http://www.fda.gov/vaccines-blood-biologics/vaccines ., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): Call  1-800-232-4636  ( 1-800-CDC-INFO ) or visit CDC's website at  http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines ,  Meningococcal Vaccine Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Immunization Program. 8/6/2021.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000754-9" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Meningococcal Vaccines ?</Question>
			<Answer>Menactra &#174; , Menomune &#174; , Menveo &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>