<Document id="0000995" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a610017.html">

<Focus>Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV13)</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000995-1" qtype="why get vaccinated">Why get vaccinated with Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV13) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pneumococcal conjugate vaccine (PCV13, PCV15, and PCV20) can prevent pneumococcal disease. Pneumococcal disease refers to any illness caused by pneumococcal bacteria. These bacteria can cause many types of illnesses, including pneumonia, which is an infection of the lungs. Pneumococcal bacteria are one of the most common causes of pneumonia. Besides pneumonia, pneumococcal bacteria can also cause:
 Ear infections, Sinus infections, Meningitis (infection of the tissue covering the brain and spinal cord), Bacteremia (infection of the blood),  Anyone can get pneumococcal disease, but children under 2 years of age, people with certain medical conditions, and adults 65 years and older are at the highest risk. Most pneumococcal infections are mild. However, some can result in long-term problems, such as brain damage or hearing loss. Meningitis, bacteremia, and pneumonia caused by pneumococcal disease can be fatal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000995-3" qtype="contraindication">Who should not get Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV13) and what are its contraindications ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000995-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV13) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Redness, swelling, pain, or tenderness where the shot is given, and fever, loss of appetite, fussiness (irritability), feeling tired, headache, and chills can happen after pneumococcal conjugate vaccination.,  Young children may be at increased risk for seizures caused by fever after pneumococcal conjugate vaccine if it is administered at the same time as inactivated influenza vaccine. Ask your health care provider for more information. People sometimes faint after medical procedures, including vaccination. Tell your provider if you feel dizzy or have vision changes or ringing in the ears. As with any medicine, there is a very remote chance of a vaccine causing a severe allergic reaction, other serious injury, or death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000995-5" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV13) ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000995-7" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV13) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your healthcare provider. He or she can give you the vaccine package insert or suggest other sources of information., Call your local or state health department., Visit the website of the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for vaccine package inserts and additional information at  http://www.fda.gov/vaccines-blood-biologics/vaccines ., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): call  1-800-232-4636  ( 1-800-CDC-INFO ) or visit CDC's website at  http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines .,  Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV13) Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Immunization Program. 5/12/2023.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000995-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Pneumococcal Conjugate Vaccine (PCV13) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prevnar 15 &#174; &#182; , Prevnar 13 &#174; , Prevnar 20 &#174; , Vaxneuvance &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>