<Document id="0000076" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607013.html">

<Focus>Anthrax Vaccine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000076-1" qtype="information">What is Anthrax Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anthrax vaccine protects against anthrax disease. The vaccine used in the United States does not contain  B. anthracis  cells and it does not cause anthrax. Anthrax vaccine was licensed in 1970 and relicensed in 2008. Based on limited but sound evidence, the vaccine protects against both cutaneous (skin) and inhalational anthrax.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000076-2" qtype="information">What is Anthrax Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anthrax vaccine protects against anthrax disease. The vaccine used in the United States does not contain  B. anthracis  cells and it does not cause anthrax. Anthrax vaccine was licensed in 1970 and relicensed in 2008. Based on limited but sound evidence, the vaccine protects against both cutaneous (skin) and inhalational anthrax.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000076-3" qtype="indication">Who should get Anthrax Vaccine and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anyone who has had a serious allergic reaction to a previous dose of anthrax vaccine should not get another dose., Anyone who has a severe allergy to any vaccine component should not get a dose. Tell your provider if you have any severe allergies, including latex., If you have ever had Guillain Barr syndrome (GBS), your provider might recommend not getting anthrax vaccine., If you have a moderate or severe illness your provider might ask you to wait until you recover to get the vaccine. People with mild illness can usually be vaccinated., Vaccination may be recommended for pregnant women who have been exposed to anthrax and are at risk of developing inhalation disease. Nursing mothers may safely be given anthrax vaccine., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000076-4" qtype="contraindication">Who should not get Anthrax Vaccine and what are its contraindications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anyone who has had a serious allergic reaction to a previous dose of anthrax vaccine should not get another dose., Anyone who has a severe allergy to any vaccine component should not get a dose. Tell your provider if you have any severe allergies, including latex., If you have ever had Guillain Barr syndrome (GBS), your provider might recommend not getting anthrax vaccine., If you have a moderate or severe illness your provider might ask you to wait until you recover to get the vaccine. People with mild illness can usually be vaccinated., Vaccination may be recommended for pregnant women who have been exposed to anthrax and are at risk of developing inhalation disease. Nursing mothers may safely be given anthrax vaccine., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000076-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Anthrax Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Like any medicine, a vaccine could cause a serious problem, such as a severe allergic reaction. Anthrax is a very serious disease, and the risk of serious harm from the vaccine is extremely small. Tenderness on the arm where the shot was given (about 1 person out of 2), Redness on the arm where the shot was given (about 1 out of 7 men and 1 out of 3 women), Itching on the arm where the shot was given (about 1 out of 50 men and 1 out of 20 women), Lump on the arm where the shot was given (about 1 out of 60 men and 1 out of 16 women), Bruise on the arm where the shot was given (about 1 out of 25 men and 1 out of 22 women), Muscle aches or temporary limitation of arm movement (about 1 out of 14 men and 1 out of 10 women), Headaches (about 1 out of 25 men and 1 out of 12 women), Fatigue (about 1 out of 15 men, about 1 out of 8 women),  Serious allergic reaction (very rare - less than once in 100,000 doses).,  As with any vaccine, other severe problems have been reported. But these don't appear to occur any more often among anthrax vaccine recipients than among unvaccinated people. There is no evidence that anthrax vaccine causes long-term health problems. Independent civilian committees have not found anthrax vaccination to be a factor in unexplained illnesses among Gulf War veterans.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000076-6" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Anthrax Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Any unusual condition, such as a severe allergic reaction or a high fever. If a severe allergic reaction occurred, it would be within a few minutes to an hour after the shot. Signs of a serious allergic reaction can include difficulty breathing, weakness, hoarseness or wheezing, a fast heart beat, hives, dizziness, paleness, or swelling of the throat.,  Call a doctor, or get the person to a doctor right away., Tell your doctor what happened, the date and time it happened, and when the vaccination was given., Ask your provider to report the reaction by filing a Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS) form. Or you can file this report through the VAERS website at  https://vaers.hhs.gov/index  or by calling 1-800-822-7967. VAERS does not provide medical advice., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000076-8" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Anthrax Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your doctor or other health care provider. They can give you the vaccine package insert or suggest other sources of information., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): call 1-800-232-4636 (1-800-CDC-INFO) or visit the CDC's website at  http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/anthrax/vaccination/ ., Contact the U.S Department of Defense (DoD): call 1-877-438-8222 or visit the DoD website at  http://www.anthrax.osd.mil .,  Anthrax Vaccine Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Immunization Program. 3/10/2010.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000076-9" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Anthrax Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Biothrax &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>