<Document id="0000017" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a681036.html">

<Focus>Acyclovir Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000017-1" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Acyclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Your doctor may order certain lab tests to check your body's response to acyclovir injection. Do not let anyone else take your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000017-2" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Acyclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before using acyclovir injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to acyclovir, valacyclovir (Valtrex), any other medications, or any of the ingredients in acyclovir injection.  Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., Tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take while receiving acyclovir injection. Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects. , tell your doctor if you have or have ever had problems with your immune system, human immunodeficiency virus infection (HIV), or acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS); or kidney or liver disease. Also tell your doctor if there is a possibility you may be dehydrated from a recent illness or activity., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breastfeeding. If you become pregnant while receiving acyclovir injection, call your doctor., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000017-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Acyclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acyclovir injection may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 redness or swelling at the injection site, nausea, vomiting,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, call your doctor immediately:
 rash, hives, itching, difficulty breathing or swallowing, swelling of the face, throat, tongue, lips, eyes, hoarseness,  Acyclovir injection may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while receiving this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000017-5" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Acyclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000017-6" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Acyclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. Symptoms of overdose may include the following:
 agitation, coma, seizures, tiredness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000017-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Acyclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Zovirax &#174;  Injection &#174; &#182; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>