<Document id="0000006" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a696015.html">

<Focus>Acarbose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000006-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Acarbose and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acarbose is used (with diet only or diet and other medications) to treat type 2 diabetes (condition in which the body does not use insulin normally and therefore cannot control the amount of sugar in the blood) . Acarbose works by slowing the action of certain chemicals that break down food to release glucose (sugar) into your blood. Slowing food digestion helps keep blood glucose from rising very high after meals. Over time, people who have diabetes and high blood sugar can develop serious or life-threatening complications, including heart disease, stroke, kidney problems, nerve damage, and eye problems. Taking medication(s), making lifestyle changes (e.g., diet, exercise, quitting smoking), and regularly checking your blood sugar may help to manage your diabetes and improve your health. This therapy may also decrease your chances of having a heart attack, stroke, or other diabetes-related complications such as kidney failure, nerve damage (numb, cold legs or feet; decreased sexual ability in men and women), eye problems, including changes or loss of vision, or gum disease. Your doctor and other healthcare providers will talk to you about the best way to manage your diabetes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000006-2" qtype="usage">How should Acarbose be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acarbose comes as a tablet to take by mouth. It is usually taken three times a day. It is very important to take each dose with the first bite of each main meal. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Take acarbose exactly as directed. Do not take more or less of it or take it more often than prescribed by your doctor. Continue to take acarbose even if you feel well. Do not stop taking acarbose without talking to your doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000006-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Acarbose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking acarbose, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to acarbose or any other drugs., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications you are taking, especially other medications for diabetes, digoxin (Lanoxin), diuretics ('water pills'), estrogens, isoniazid, medications for high blood pressure or colds, oral contraceptives, pancreatic enzymes, phenytoin (Dilantin), steroids, thyroid medications, and vitamins., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had ketoacidosis, cirrhosis, or intestinal disease such as inflammatory bowel disease or bowel obstruction., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while taking acarbose, call your doctor., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are taking acarbose., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000006-5" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Acarbose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Be sure to follow all exercise and dietary recommendations made by your doctor or dietitian. It is important to eat a healthful diet. Alcohol may cause a decrease in blood sugar. Ask your doctor about the safe use of alcoholic beverages while you are taking acarbose.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000006-6" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Acarbose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Take the missed dose as soon as you remember it. If you will be having a snack soon, take a dose with the snack. If it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not take a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000006-7" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Acarbose ?</Question>
			<Answer>When used in combination with insulin or other medications used to treat diabetes, acarbose may cause excessive lowering of blood sugar levels. If you have any of these symptoms, glucose products (Insta-Glucose or B-D Glucose tablets) should be used and you should call your doctor. Because acarbose blocks the breakdown of table sugar and other complex sugars, fruit juice or other products containing these sugars will not help to increase blood sugar. It is important that you and other members of your household understand this difference between acarbose and other medications used to treat diabetes.
 shakiness, dizziness or lightheadedness, sweating , nervousness or irritability, sudden changes in behavior or mood, headache, numbness or tingling around the mouth, weakness, pale skin , hunger, clumsy or jerky movements,  If hypoglycemia is not treated, severe symptoms may develop. Be sure that your family, friends, and other people who spend time with you know that if you have any of the following symptoms, they should get medical treatment for you immediately.
 confusion, seizures, loss of consciousness,  Call your doctor immediately if you have any of the following symptoms of hyperglycemia (high blood sugar):
 extreme thirst, frequent urination, extreme hunger, weakness, blurred vision,  If high blood sugar is not treated, a serious, life-threatening condition called diabetic ketoacidosis could develop. Call your doctor immediately if you have any of the these symptoms:
 dry mouth, upset stomach and vomiting, shortness of breath, breath that smells fruity, decreased consciousness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000006-8" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Acarbose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000006-9" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Acarbose ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000006-10" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Acarbose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory. Your doctor will order certain lab tests to check your response to acarbose. Your doctor will also tell you how to check your response to this medication by measuring your blood or urine sugar levels at home. Follow these instructions carefully You should always wear a diabetic identification bracelet to be sure you get proper treatment in an emergency. Do not let anyone else take your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000006-11" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Acarbose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prandase &#174; , Precose &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>