<Document id="0001061" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607049.html">

<Focus>Retapamulin</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001061-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Retapamulin and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Retapamulin is used to treat impetigo (a skin infection caused by bacteria) in children and adults. Retapamulin is in a class of medications called antibacterials. It works by killing and stopping the growth of bacteria on the skin. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001061-2" qtype="usage">How should Retapamulin be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Retapamulin comes as an ointment to be applied in a thin layer to the skin.  It is usually used two times a day for 5 days. Apply retapamulin at around the same times every day. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Use retapamulin exactly as directed. Do not use more or less of it or use it more often than prescribed by your doctor.  The infected area of the skin should begin to look better during the first few days of treatment with retapamulin. If your symptoms do not improve after using this medication for 3 to 4 days or get worse, call your doctor. Retapamulin is for use only on the infected area of the skin. Do not let retapamulin ointment get into your eyes, or inside your mouth, or nose, or inside the female genital area. Do not swallow this medication.  Use retapamulin until you finish the prescription, even if the infection looks better. If you stop using retapamulin too soon or skip doses, the infection may not be completely gone and the bacteria could become difficult to treat with another antibiotic. To use the ointment, follow these steps:
 Use a clean cotton swab to spread a thin layer of retapamulin on the skin that is infected. , Cover the treated area with a bandage or clean gauze to protect the area and prevent accidental spread of the ointment to the eyes or other areas, especially in young children., Wash your hands after applying retapamulin if the hands are not to be treated.,  Ask your pharmacist or doctor for a copy of the manufacturer's information for the patient.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001061-3" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Retapamulin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking retapamulin, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to retapamulin, or any other medications. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001061-4" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Retapamulin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001061-5" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Retapamulin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Apply the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not apply extra ointment to make up for a missed dose.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001061-6" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Retapamulin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Retapamulin may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 irritation at the in the place where you applied the ointment, blisters, burning, redness, swelling, oozing from the place where you applied the ointment, itching, diarrhea, headache,  Retapamulin may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while taking this medication.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001061-7" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Retapamulin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001061-8" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Retapamulin ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001061-9" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Retapamulin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Do not let anyone else take your medication. Your prescription is probably not refillable. If you still have symptoms of infection after you finish retapamulin, call your doctor. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0001061-10" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Retapamulin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Altabax &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>