<Document id="0001249" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a682337.html">

<Focus>Triamterene</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001249-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Triamterene and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Triamterene is used alone or with other medications to treat edema (fluid retention; excess fluid held in body tissues) caused by various conditions, including liver and heart disease. Triamterene is in a class of medications called diuretics ('water pills'). It causes the kidneys to eliminate unneeded water and sodium from the body into the urine, but reduces the loss of potassium.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001249-2" qtype="usage">How should Triamterene be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Triamterene comes as a capsule to take by mouth. It usually is taken once a day in the morning after breakfast or twice a day after breakfast and lunch. It is best to take triamterene earlier in the day so that frequent trips to the bathroom do not interfere with nighttime sleep. Take triamterene at around the same time(s) every day. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Take triamterene exactly as directed. Do not take more or less of it or take it more often than prescribed by your doctor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001249-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Triamterene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking triamterene, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to triamterene or any other medications (Dyazide, Maxzide)., do not take triamterene if you are taking amiloride (Midamor), spironolactone (Aldactone), or other medications containing triamterene., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors such as benazepril (Lotensin), captopril (Capoten), enalapril (Vasotec), fosinopril (Monopril), lisinopril (Prinivil, Zestril), moexipril (Univasc), perindopril, (Aceon), quinapril (Accupril), ramipril (Altace), and trandolapril (Mavik); lithium (Eskalith, Lithobid); nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medications (NSAIDS) such as ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin) and naproxen (Aleve, Naprosyn); medications for diabetes, or high blood pressure; other diuretics; and potassium supplements. Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had diabetes, gout, kidney stones, or heart, kidney, or liver disease., tell your doctor if you are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. If you become pregnant while taking triamterene, call your doctor. Do not breastfeed if you are taking triamterene., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are taking triamterene., plan to avoid unnecessary or prolonged exposure to sunlight and to wear protective clothing, sunglasses, and sunscreen. Triamterene may make your skin sensitive to sunlight., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001249-5" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Triamterene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Follow your doctor's directions for your meals, including advice for a reduced salt (sodium) diet and daily exercise program. Avoid potassium-containing salt substitutes while you are taking this medication..Talk with your doctor about the amount of potassium-rich foods (e.g., bananas, prunes, raisins, and orange juice) that you may have in your diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001249-6" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Triamterene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Take the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for your next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not take a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001249-7" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Triamterene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Triamterene may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 vomiting, dizziness, headache,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of the following symptoms, call your doctor immediately:
 muscle weakness or cramps, slow or irregular heartbeat, diarrhea, rash, difficulty breathing or swallowing, upset stomach, extreme tiredness, unusual bleeding or bruising, lack of energy, loss of appetite, pain in the upper right part of the stomach, yellowing of the skin or eyes, flu-like symptoms, sore throat, severe dry mouth, unusual bruising or bleeding,  If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001249-8" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Triamterene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medicine in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001249-9" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Triamterene ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. Symptoms of overdose may include:
 upset stomach, vomiting, weakness or tiredness, dizziness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0001249-10" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Triamterene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory. Your doctor will order certain lab tests to check your body's response to triamterene. Do not let anyone else take your medicine. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0001249-11" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Triamterene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dyrenium &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>