<Document id="0001088" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607024.html">

<Focus>Rotavirus Vaccine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001088-1" qtype="why get vaccinated">Why get vaccinated with Rotavirus Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rotavirus vaccine can prevent rotavirus disease. Rotavirus commonly causes severe, watery diarrhea, mostly in babies and young children. Vomiting and fever are also common in babies with rotavirus. Children may become dehydrated and need to be hospitalized and can even die.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001088-2" qtype="information">What is Rotavirus Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001088-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Rotavirus Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Irritability or mild, temporary diarrhea or vomiting can happen after rotavirus vaccine.,  Intussusception is a type of bowel blockage that is treated in a hospital and could require surgery. It happens naturally in some infants every year in the United States, and usually there is no known reason for it. There is also a small risk of intussusception from rotavirus vaccination, usually within a week after the first or second vaccine dose. This additional risk is estimated to range from about 1 in 20,000 U.S. infants to 1 in 100,000 U.S. infants who get rotavirus vaccine. Your health care provider can give you more information. As with any medicine, there is a very remote chance of a vaccine causing a severe allergic reaction, other serious injury, or death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001088-5" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Rotavirus Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001088-7" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Rotavirus Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your health care provider ., Call your local or state health department., Visit the website of the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) for vaccine package inserts and additional information at  http://www.fda.gov/ vaccines-blood-biologics/vaccines ., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): Call visit CDC's website at  http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines  ( 1-800-CDC-INFO ) or., Visit CDC's website at  http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines ,  ,  Rotavirus Vaccine Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Immunization Program. 10/15/2021.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001088-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Rotavirus Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rotarix &#174; , RotaTeq &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>