<Document id="0001046" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607023.html">

<Focus>Rabies Vaccine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001046-1" qtype="information">What is Rabies Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rabies is a serious disease. It is caused by a virus. Rabies is mainly a disease of animals. Humans get rabies when they are bitten by infected animals. At first there might not be any symptoms. But weeks, or even years after a bite, rabies can cause pain, fatigue, headaches, fever, and irritability. These are followed by seizures, hallucinations, and paralysis. Rabies is almost always fatal. Wild animals, especially bats, are the most common source of human rabies infection in the United States. Skunks, raccoons, dogs, and cats can also transmit the disease. Human rabies is rare in the United States. There have been only 55 cases diagnosed since 1990. However, between 16,000 and 39,000 people are treated each year for possible exposure to rabies after animal bites. Also, rabies is far more common in other parts of the world, with about 40,000 to 70,000 rabies-related deaths each year. Bites from unvaccinated dogs cause most of these cases. Rabies vaccine can prevent rabies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001046-3" qtype="indication">Who should get Rabies Vaccine and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001046-4" qtype="important warning">What important warning or information should I know about Rabies Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001046-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Rabies Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>A vaccine, like any medicine, is capable of causing serious problems, such as severe allergic reactions. The risk of a vaccine causing serious harm, or death, is extremely small. Serious problems from rabies vaccine are very rare. soreness, redness, swelling, or itching where the shot was given (30% to 74%), headache, nausea, abdominal pain, muscle aches, dizziness (5% to 40%),  hives, pain in the joints, fever (about 6% of booster doses),  Other nervous system disorders, such as Guillain-Barr&#233; Syndrome (GBS), have been reported after rabies vaccine, but this happens so rarely that it is not known whether they are related to the vaccine. NOTE: Several brands of rabies vaccine are available in the United States, and reactions may vary between brands. Your provider can give you more information about a particular brand.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001046-6" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Rabies Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Any unusual condition, such as severe allergic reaction or a high fever. If a severe allergic reaction occurred, it would be within a few minutes to an hour after the shot. Signs of a serious allergic reaction can include difficulty breathing, hoarseness or wheezing, swelling of the throat, hives, paleness, weakness, a fast heart beat, or dizziness.,  Call a doctor, or get the person to a doctor right away., Tell your doctor what happened, the date and time it happened, and when the vaccination was given., Ask your provider to report the reaction by filing a Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS) form. Or you can file this report through the VAERS website at  http://vaers.hhs.gov/index , or by calling  1-800-822-7967 . VAERS does not provide medical advice., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001046-7" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Rabies Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your doctor or other health care provider. They can give you the vaccine package insert or suggest other sources of information., Call your local or state health department., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): call  1-800-232-4636  (1-800-CDC-INFO) or visit the CDC's rabies website at  http://www.cdc.gov/rabies/ ,  Rabies Vaccine Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 10/6/2009</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001046-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Rabies Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Imovax &#174; , RabAvert &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>