<Document id="0001261" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607028.html">

<Focus>Typhoid Vaccine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001261-1" qtype="information">What is Typhoid Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Typhoid (typhoid fever) is a serious disease. It is caused by bacteria called  Salmonella  Typhi. Typhoid causes a high fever, fatigue, weakness, stomach pains, headache, loss of appetite, and sometimes a rash. If it is not treated, it can kill up to 30% of people who get it. Some people who get typhoid become ''carriers,'' who can spread the disease to others. Generally, people get typhoid from contaminated food or water. Typhoid is rare in the U.S., and most U.S. citizens who get the disease get it while traveling. Typhoid strikes about 21 million people a year around the world and kills about 200,000.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001261-3" qtype="indication">Who should get Typhoid Vaccine and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Inactivated typhoid vaccine (shot) Should not be given to children younger than 2 years of age., Anyone who has had a severe reaction to a previous dose of this vaccine should not get another dose., Anyone who has a severe allergy to any component of this vaccine should not get it. Tell your doctor if you have any severe allergies., Anyone who is moderately or severely ill at the time the shot is scheduled should usually wait until they recover before getting the vaccine.,  Live typhoid vaccine (oral) Should not be given to children younger than 6 years of age., Anyone who has had a severe reaction to a previous dose of this vaccine should not get another dose., Anyone who has a severe allergy to any component of this vaccine should not get it. Tell your doctor if you have any severe allergies., Anyone who is moderately or severely ill at the time the vaccine is scheduled should usually wait until they recover before getting it. Tell your doctor if you have an illness involving vomiting or diarrhea., Anyone whose immune system is weakened should not get this vaccine. They should get the typhoid shot instead. This includes anyone who: has HIV/AIDS or another disease that affects the immune system, is being treated with drugs that affect the immune system, such as steroids for 2 weeks or longer, has any kind of cancer, or is taking cancer treatment with radiation or drugs., Oral typhoid vaccine should not be given until at least 3 days after taking certain antibiotics.,  Ask your doctor for more information.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001261-4" qtype="contraindication">Who should not get Typhoid Vaccine and what are its contraindications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Inactivated typhoid vaccine (shot) Should not be given to children younger than 2 years of age., Anyone who has had a severe reaction to a previous dose of this vaccine should not get another dose., Anyone who has a severe allergy to any component of this vaccine should not get it. Tell your doctor if you have any severe allergies., Anyone who is moderately or severely ill at the time the shot is scheduled should usually wait until they recover before getting the vaccine.,  Live typhoid vaccine (oral) Should not be given to children younger than 6 years of age., Anyone who has had a severe reaction to a previous dose of this vaccine should not get another dose., Anyone who has a severe allergy to any component of this vaccine should not get it. Tell your doctor if you have any severe allergies., Anyone who is moderately or severely ill at the time the vaccine is scheduled should usually wait until they recover before getting it. Tell your doctor if you have an illness involving vomiting or diarrhea., Anyone whose immune system is weakened should not get this vaccine. They should get the typhoid shot instead. This includes anyone who: has HIV/AIDS or another disease that affects the immune system, is being treated with drugs that affect the immune system, such as steroids for 2 weeks or longer, has any kind of cancer, or is taking cancer treatment with radiation or drugs., Oral typhoid vaccine should not be given until at least 3 days after taking certain antibiotics.,  Ask your doctor for more information.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001261-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Typhoid Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Like any medicine, a vaccine could cause a serious problem, such as a severe allergic reaction. The risk of typhoid vaccine causing serious harm, or death, is extremely small. Serious problems from either typhoid vaccine are very rare. Inactivated typhoid vaccine (shot) Mild reactions Fever (up to about 1 person in 100), Headache (up to about 1 person in 30), Redness or swelling at the site of the injection (up to about 1 person in 15),  Live typhoid vaccine (oral) Mild reactions Fever or headache (up to about 1 person in 20), Stomach pain, nausea, vomiting, rash (rare), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001261-6" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Typhoid Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001261-7" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Typhoid Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your doctor., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC): Call  1-800-232-4636  ( 1-800-CDC-INFO ) or visit CDC's website at  http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/vpd-vac/typhoid/default.htm .,  Typhoid Vaccine Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Immunization Program. 5/29/2012 .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001261-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Typhoid Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vivotif &#174; , Typhim VI &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>