<Document id="0001097" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a693005.html">

<Focus>Sargramostim Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001097-1" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Sargramostim Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory. Your doctor will order certain lab tests to check your body's response to sargramostim. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001097-2" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Sargramostim Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before using sargramostim injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to sargramostim, yeast, any other medications, or any of the ingredients in sargramostim injection. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention betamethasone (Celestone), dexamethasone (Decadron), lithium (Lithobid), methylprednisolone (Medrol), and prednisone. Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you are being treated or if you have ever been treated with radiation therapy or if you have or ever had cancer, edema (swelling of stomach, feet, ankles, or lower legs), any type of heart disease, heart failure, an irregular heartbeat, lung, kidney, or liver disease., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breastfeeding. If you become pregnant while using sargramostim, call your doctor., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are using sargramostim., you should know that sargramostim decreases the risk of infection, but does not prevent all infections that may develop during or after chemotherapy. Call your doctor immediately if you develop signs of infection such as fever, chills, sore throat, or ongoing cough and congestion., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001097-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Sargramostim Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sargramostim may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 redness, swelling, bruising, itching or a lump in the area where the medication was injected, bone, joint, or muscle pain, headache, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, stomach pain, mouth sores, loss of appetite, hair loss,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, call your doctor immediately or get emergency medical treatment:
 shortness of breath or fast breathing, difficulty breathing, wheezing, dizziness, sweating, hives, rash, itching, swelling around the mouth, face, eyes, stomach, feet, ankles, or lower legs, sudden weight gain, chest pain, fast or irregular heartbeat, fainting, unusual bruising or purple markings under the skin, unusual bleeding, nosebleeds, unusual tiredness or weakness, decreased urination,  Sargramostim may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while taking this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001097-5" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Sargramostim Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, away from sunlight, closed, and out of reach of children. Store sargramostim in the refrigerator. Do not freeze or shake sargramostim. Opened sargramostim vials may be refrigerated for up to 20 days. Dispose of opened vials after 20 days. Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001097-6" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Sargramostim Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. Symptoms of overdose may include the following:
 shortness of breath, unusual tiredness or weakness, fever, fast or irregular heartbeat, nausea, headache, rash, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001097-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Sargramostim Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Leukine &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>