<Document id="0000087" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/652.html">

<Focus>Senna</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000087-1" qtype="information">What is Senna ?</Question>
			<Answer>Senna is the fruit (pod) or leaf of the plant Senna alexandrina. It is approved in the US as a laxative for short-term treatment of constipation.  


Senna contains many chemicals called sennosides. Sennosides irritate the lining of the bowel, which causes a laxative effect. 

Senna is an FDA-approved over-the-counter (OTC) laxative. It is used to treat constipation and also to clear the bowel before procedures such as colonoscopy. People also use senna for irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), hemorrhoids, weight loss, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000087-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Senna ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  SENNA  are as follows: Likely effective for... Constipation . Senna is an FDA-approved nonprescription (OTC) drug for adults and children ages 2 years and older. It should be taken at bedtime and tends to work within 6-12 hours. It might cause stomach upset and diarrhea. Senna should not be used for more than 1 week without the supervision of a healthcare provider. ,  Possibly effective for... Emptying the colon before a colonoscopy . Taking senna by mouth might help empty the colon before a colonoscopy. Prior to a colonoscopy, your doctor will recommend a specific regimen to use in order to ensure that your colon is empty prior to the procedure. ,  

There is interest in using senna for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000087-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Senna and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000087-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Senna ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000087-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Senna and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Digoxin (Lanoxin) Senna is a type of laxative called a stimulant laxative. Stimulant laxatives can decrease potassium levels in the body. Low potassium levels can increase the risk of side effects from digoxin. Estrogens Taking senna might decrease the effects of estrogen. Senna can reduce the amount of estrogen in the body and how much estrogen the body absorbs. Warfarin (Coumadin) Senna can work as a laxative. In some people, senna can cause diarrhea. Diarrhea can increase the effects of warfarin and increase the risk of bleeding. If you take warfarin, do not take excessive amounts of senna. Water pills (Diuretic drugs) Senna is a laxative. Some laxatives can cause diarrhea and decrease potassium levels. "Water pills" can also decrease potassium levels. Taking senna along with "water pills" might make potassium levels drop too low.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000087-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Senna and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Horsetail Using senna along with horsetail might cause potassium levels to drop too low. Licorice Using senna along with licorice might cause potassium levels to drop too low. Stimulant laxative herbs Senna is a type of laxative called a stimulant laxative. Stimulant laxatives can cause diarrhea and decrease potassium levels. Taking senna with other supplements with similar effects might cause more diarrhea and very low potassium levels. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, buckthorn, gossypol, and rhubarb.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000087-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Senna and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000087-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Senna ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>