<Document id="0000030" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1040.html">

<Focus>Cod Liver Oil</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000030-1" qtype="information">What is Cod Liver Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cod liver oil can be obtained from eating fresh cod liver or by taking supplements. It is a source of vitamins A and D and a fat called omega-3. 

Cod liver oil contains certain "fatty acids" that prevent the blood from clotting easily. These fatty acids also reduce pain and swelling. 

Cod liver oil is used for heart health, depression, arthritis, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000030-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Cod Liver Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  COD LIVER OIL  are as follows: Possibly ineffective for... 
 Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) . Taking cod liver oil by mouth does not seem to help prevent COVID-19., 
 

There is interest in using cod liver oil for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000030-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Cod Liver Oil and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000030-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Cod Liver Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000030-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Cod Liver Oil and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Cod liver oil might lower blood sugar levels. Taking cod liver oil along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications for high blood pressure (Antihypertensive drugs) Cod liver oil might lower blood pressure. Taking cod liver oil along with medications that lower blood pressure might cause blood pressure to go too low. Monitor your blood pressure closely. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Cod liver oil might slow blood clotting. Taking cod liver oil along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000030-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Cod Liver Oil and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood pressure Cod liver oil might lower blood pressure. Taking it with other supplements that have the same effect might cause blood pressure to drop too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include andrographis, casein peptides, L-arginine, niacin, and stinging nettle. Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Cod liver oil might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Cod liver oil might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000030-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Cod Liver Oil and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000030-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Cod Liver Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>