<Document id="0000019" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1013.html">

<Focus>Blueberry</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000019-1" qtype="information">What is Blueberry ?</Question>
			<Answer>Blueberries are edible fruits from the Vaccinium angustifolium plant. Blueberry is a common food and is also sometimes used as medicine. 

Blueberries are high in fiber, which can help with normal digestion. They also contain vitamin C, other antioxidants, and chemicals that might reduce swelling and destroy cancer cells. 

People use blueberry for aging, memory and thinking skills, high blood pressure, athletic performance, diabetes, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 

Don't confuse blueberry with bilberry. They are related but they are not the same. In countries outside of the US, the name blueberry is used to refer to the plant that is often called bilberry in the US.  

</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000019-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Blueberry ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  BLUEBERRY  are as follows: Possibly ineffective for... 

 High blood pressure . Eating freeze-dried blueberries or taking blueberry powder by mouth doesn't lower blood pressure in people with high blood pressure or other heart disease risk factors.   , 


 

There is interest in using blueberry for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000019-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Blueberry and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000019-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Blueberry ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000019-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Blueberry and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Minor Be watchful with this combination. Buspirone (BuSpar) Blueberry juice might decrease how fast the body gets rid of buspirone. But this is not likely to be a major concern. Flurbiprofen (Ansaid, others) Blueberry juice might decrease how fast the body gets rid of flurbiprofen. But this is not likely to be a major concern. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Blueberry fruit or leaf might lower blood sugar levels. Taking blueberry along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000019-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Blueberry and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Blueberry fruit or leaf might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000019-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Blueberry and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Drinking milk along with blueberries might lower the potential health benefits of blueberries. Consuming blueberries 1-2 hours before or after drinking milk might prevent this interaction.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000019-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Blueberry ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>