<Document id="0000067" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/496.html">

<Focus>Omega-6 Fatty Acids</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000067-1" qtype="information">What is Omega-6 Fatty Acids ?</Question>
			<Answer>Omega-6 fatty acids, such as gamma linolenic acid, are a family of fats found in some plant oils and seeds. They are different from omega-3 fatty acids.  

Omega-6 fatty acids are found everywhere in the body. They help with the function of all cells. But too much omega-6 fatty acids can change the way cells react and have harmful effects on cells in the heart and blood vessels. 

People use omega-6 fatty acids for heart disease, child development, high cholesterol, cancer, diabetes, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 

There are different types of omega-6 fatty acids, such as gamma linolenic acid (GLA). Also, some supplements are used as sources of omega-6 fatty acids, such as evening primrose, borage, and black currant. See separate listings for these topics.
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000067-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Omega-6 Fatty Acids ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  OMEGA-6 FATTY ACIDS  are as follows: Possibly ineffective for... 

 Heart disease . Higher intake of omega-6 fatty acids in the diet doesn't reduce the risk of heart disease., 

 Infant development . Adding the omega-6 fatty acid called arachidonic acid to infant formula, along with an omega-3 fatty acid called docosahexaenoic acid (DHA), doesn't seem to improve brain development, vision, or growth in infants.   , 

 High levels of cholesterol or other fats (lipids) in the blood (hyperlipidemia) . Higher intake of omega-6 fatty acids in the diet doesn't seem to lower cholesterol or triglyceride levels.   , 

 Multiple sclerosis (MS) . Taking omega-6 fatty acids does not seem to prevent the progression of MS., 


 

There is interest in using omega-6 fatty acids for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000067-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Omega-6 Fatty Acids and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000067-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Omega-6 Fatty Acids ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000067-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Omega-6 Fatty Acids and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000067-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Omega-6 Fatty Acids and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000067-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Omega-6 Fatty Acids and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000067-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Omega-6 Fatty Acids ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>