<Document id="0000012" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/313.html">

<Focus>Biotin</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000012-1" qtype="information">What is Biotin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Biotin (vitamin B7) is a vitamin found in foods like eggs, milk, and bananas. Biotin deficiency can cause thinning of the hair and a rash on the face. 

Biotin is an important part of enzymes in the body that break down substances like fats, carbohydrates, and others. There isn't a good test for detecting low biotin levels, so it's usually identified by its symptoms, which include thinning hair and red scaly rash around the eyes, nose, and mouth.  

Biotin is used for biotin deficiency. It is also commonly used for hair loss, brittle nails, and other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. Biotin supplements might interfere with some lab tests. Talk with your doctor if you are taking biotin supplements and need to have any blood tests.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000012-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Biotin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  BIOTIN  are as follows: Likely effective for... Biotin deficiency . Taking biotin by mouth or by a shot can treat and prevent low blood levels of biotin. Up to 10 mg of biotin by mouth daily has been used to treat and prevent deficiency. A biotin shot can only be given by a healthcare provider.,  Possibly ineffective for... 
 Multiple sclerosis (MS) . Taking high-dose biotin by mouth does not reduce disability in people with MS. It also doesn't seem to affect the risk for relapse., 

 Rough, scaly skin on the scalp and face (seborrheic dermatitis) . Taking biotin does not seem to help improve rash in infants.,  

There is interest in using biotin for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000012-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Biotin and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000012-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Biotin ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000012-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Biotin and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000012-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Biotin and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Alpha-lipoic acid Taking alpha-lipoic acid and biotin together can reduce the absorption of both alpha-lipoic acid and biotin into the body. Vitamin B5 (pantothenic acid) Taking biotin and vitamin B5 together can reduce the absorption of both biotin and vitamin B5 into the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000012-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Biotin and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eating 2 or more uncooked egg whites daily for several months can cause biotin deficiency. Raw egg whites bind to biotin in the stomach and prevent the body from absorbing it.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000012-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Biotin ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>