<Document id="0000002" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/19.html">

<Focus>Alfalfa</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000002-1" qtype="information">What is Alfalfa ?</Question>
			<Answer>Alfalfa (Medicago sativa) is an herb that some people consume as a source of calcium, potassium, phosphorous, iron, and vitamins A, C, E, and K. 

Alfalfa is most commonly grown as food for livestock animals. In humans, it's often eaten as a garnish, and seems to prevent cholesterol absorption in the stomach. 

People use alfalfa for high cholesterol, diabetes, indigestion, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000002-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Alfalfa ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using alfalfa for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000002-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Alfalfa and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000002-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Alfalfa ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000002-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Alfalfa and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Warfarin (Coumadin) Alfalfa contains large amounts of vitamin K. Vitamin K is used by the body to help blood clot. By helping the blood clot, alfalfa might decrease the effects of warfarin. Be sure to have your blood checked regularly. The dose of your warfarin might need to be changed. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Birth control pills (Contraceptive drugs) Large amounts of alfalfa might have some of the same effects as estrogen. Taking alfalfa along with birth control pills might decrease the effects of birth control pills. If you take birth control pills along with alfalfa, use an additional form of birth control such as a condom. Estrogens Large amounts of alfalfa might have some of the same effects as estrogen. Taking alfalfa along with estrogen might change the effects of estrogen. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Alfalfa might lower blood sugar levels. Taking alfalfa along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications that decrease the immune system (Immunosuppressants) Alfalfa can increase the activity of the immune system. Some medications, such as those used after a transplant, decrease the activity of the immune system. Taking alfalfa along with these medications might decrease the effects of these medications. Medications that increase sensitivity to sunlight (Photosensitizing drugs) Some medications might make the skin more sensitive to sunlight. Alfalfa might also make the skin more sensitive to sunlight. Using these products together might increase the risk of sunburn, blistering, or rashes when the skin is exposed to sunlight. Be sure to wear sunblock and protective clothing when spending time in the sun.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000002-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Alfalfa and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Alfalfa might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Herbs that might increase sensitivity to sunlight Alfalfa might make the skin more sensitive to sunlight. Using it with other products that also make the skin more sensitive to the sun might increase the risk for sunburn and other side effects. Examples of supplements with this effect include bishop's weed, chlorophyll, khella, and St. John's wort. Iron Taking alfalfa might reduce the amount of iron absorbed by the body. Vitamin E Taking alfalfa might reduce the amount of vitamin E absorbed by the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000002-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Alfalfa and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000002-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Alfalfa ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>