<Document id="0000011" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/891.html">

<Focus>Bifidobacteria</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000011-1" qtype="information">What is Bifidobacteria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis (B. lactis) is a type of probiotic ("good" bacteria) that lives in the intestines. It produces lactic and acetic acid. 

"Good" bacteria such as B. lactis can help break down food, absorb nutrients, and fight off "bad" organisms that might cause diseases. B. lactis is a subspecies of B. animalis. It's found in the human gut and used in probiotic supplements. 

People use B. lactis for excessive crying in infants (colic), constipation, irritable bowel syndrome (IBS), and respiratory tract infections. It is also used for dental cavities, hay fever, diarrhea, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support many of these uses. There is also no good evidence to support using B. lactis for COVID-19. 

Bifidobacterium animalis subsp. lactis is sometimes listed as Bifidobacterium lactis (or B. lactis) on product labels. Don't confuse B. lactis with other probiotics, or with fermented food products such as fermented milk, kefir, or yogurt. These are not the same.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000011-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Bifidobacteria ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  BIFIDOBACTERIUM ANIMALIS SUBSP. LACTIS  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 


 Excessive crying in infants (colic) . Giving infants B. lactis by mouth seems to help reduce crying from colic., 

 Constipation . Taking B. lactis by mouth seems to help relieve constipation., 

 A long-term disorder of the large intestines that causes stomach pain (irritable bowel syndrome or IBS) . Taking B. lactis by mouth seems to help relieve symptoms of IBS. But it's not clear if taking it together with other probiotics helps., 


 Infection of the airways . Taking B. lactis by mouth might help prevent airway infections such as the common cold in otherwise healthy people. But it might not help people who have other serious health issues.,  


 Possibly ineffective for... 
 Cavities . Taking B. lactis by mouth doesn't seem to prevent cavities in young children., 

 

There is interest in using B. lactis for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000011-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Bifidobacteria and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000011-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Bifidobacteria ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000011-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Bifidobacteria and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Antibiotic drugs B. lactis is a type of friendly bacteria. Antibiotics are used to reduce harmful bacteria in the body. Taking antibiotics along with B. lactis might reduce the effects of B. lactis. To avoid this interaction, take B. lactis products at least two hours before or after antibiotics.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000011-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Bifidobacteria and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000011-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Bifidobacteria and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000011-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Bifidobacteria ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>