<Document id="0000076" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/735.html">

<Focus>Phosphate salts</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000076-1" qtype="information">What is Phosphate salts ?</Question>
			<Answer>Phosphorus is an essential mineral found in many foods. In the diet and body, phosphorus usually binds to other minerals in the form of phosphate salts.  

Phosphates are involved in cell structure, energy transport and storage, vitamin function, and many other essential processes in the body. Phosphate salts can act as laxatives by causing more fluid to be drawn into the intestines and making the gut push out its contents faster. 

People use phosphate salts for bowel cleansing, low blood levels of phosphate, constipation, high blood levels of calcium, and heartburn. They are also used for athletic performance, osteoporosis, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these other uses.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000076-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Phosphate salts ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  PHOSPHATE SALTS  are as follows: Effective for... Emptying the colon before a colonoscopy . Taking sodium phosphate products by mouth before a colonoscopy is effective for bowel cleansing. Some sodium phosphate products are approved by the US FDA for this use. But taking sodium phosphate can increase the risk of kidney damage in some people and should be used with caution.,  

 Low levels of phosphate in the blood (hypophosphatemia) . Taking sodium or potassium phosphate by mouth or by IV is effective for preventing or treating low phosphate levels in the blood. IV products can only be given by a healthcare provider.,  Likely effective for... Constipation . Sodium phosphate is an FDA-approved over-the-counter (OTC) ingredient for treating constipation. OTC products are taken by mouth or used as enemas., 

 Indigestion (dyspepsia) . Aluminum phosphate and calcium phosphate are FDA-approved ingredients in OTC antacids.,  

 High levels of calcium in the blood (hypercalcemia) . Taking phosphate salts by mouth is likely effective for treating high levels of calcium in the blood. But calcium phosphate should not be used since it contains calcium and can increase calcium levels.,  
 Possibly effective for... Kidney stones . Taking potassium phosphate by mouth can help prevent calcium kidney stones from forming in people with high urine levels of calcium.,  

There is interest in using phosphate salts for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000076-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Phosphate salts and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000076-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Phosphate salts ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000076-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Phosphate salts and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Erdafitinib (Balversa) Erdafitinib increases the amount of phosphate in the blood. Taking phosphate salts along with erdafitinib can cause very high phosphate levels and serious side effects. Avoid phosphates when using erdafitinib. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Bisphosphonates Bisphosphonate medications and phosphate salts can both lower calcium levels in the body. Taking large amounts of phosphate salts along with bisphosphonate medications might cause calcium levels to become too low.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000076-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Phosphate salts and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Calcium Phosphate can bind with calcium. This reduces the body's ability to absorb phosphate and calcium. To avoid this interaction, phosphate should be taken at least 2 hours before or after taking calcium. Iron Phosphate can bind with iron. This reduces the body's ability to absorb phosphate and iron. To avoid this interaction, phosphate should be taken at least 2 hours before or after taking iron. Magnesium Phosphate can bind with magnesium. This reduces the body's ability to absorb phosphate and magnesium. To avoid this interaction, phosphate should be taken at least 2 hours before or after taking magnesium.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000076-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Phosphate salts and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Taking phosphate with phosphate-containing foods and drinks might increase phosphate levels and increase the risk of side effects, especially in people with kidney problems. Phosphate-containing foods and beverages include cola, wine, beer, whole grain cereals, nuts, dairy products, and some meats.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000076-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Phosphate salts ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>