<Document id="0000051" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/699.html">

<Focus>Horny Goat Weed</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000051-1" qtype="information">What is Horny Goat Weed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Horny goat weed refers to various herb species of the Epimedium genus, and may be known as "yin yang huo." It has limited evidence of health benefits. 

Horny goat weed contains chemicals that might help increase blood flow and improve sexual function. It also contains phytoestrogens, chemicals that act somewhat like the hormone estrogen.  

People use horny goat weed for erectile dysfunction (ED), sexual problems, weak and brittle bones, health problems after menopause, and other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support any of these uses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000051-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Horny Goat Weed ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using horny goat weed for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000051-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Horny Goat Weed and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000051-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Horny Goat Weed ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000051-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Horny Goat Weed and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Estrogens Horny goat weed might have some of the same effects as estrogen and might increase blood levels of estrogen in some people. Taking horny goat weed with estrogen might increase the effects and side effects of estrogen. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 1A2 (CYP1A2) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Horny goat weed might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2B6 (CYP2B6) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Horny goat weed might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications for high blood pressure (Antihypertensive drugs) Horny goat weed might lower blood pressure. Taking horny goat weed along with medications that lower blood pressure might cause blood pressure to go too low. Monitor your blood pressure closely. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Horny goat weed might slow blood clotting. Taking horny goat weed along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000051-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Horny Goat Weed and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Caffeine-containing herbs and supplements Horny goat weed contains an ingredient that might slow down how quickly the body processes caffeine. Taking it with caffeine-containing herbs and supplements might increase the effects and side effects of caffeine. Examples of supplements that contain caffeine include black tea, coffee, green tea, guarana, and yerba mate. Herbs and supplements that might lower blood pressure Horny goat weed might lower blood pressure. Taking it with other supplements that have the same effect might cause blood pressure to drop too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include andrographis, casein peptides, L-arginine, niacin, and stinging nettle. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Horny goat weed might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000051-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Horny Goat Weed and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000051-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Horny Goat Weed ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>