<Document id="0000045" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1264.html">

<Focus>Green Coffee</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000045-1" qtype="information">What is Green Coffee ?</Question>
			<Answer>Green coffee is unroasted coffee beans from Coffea fruits (Coffea arabica, Coffea canephora). It contains more chlorogenic acid than roasted coffee.  

The chlorogenic acid in green coffee is thought to have health benefits. It might affect blood vessels so that blood pressure is reduced. It might also affect how the body handles blood sugar and metabolism. Green coffee also contains caffeine, but in lower amounts than regular coffee. 

People take green coffee for obesity, diabetes, high blood pressure, high cholesterol, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 

Don't confuse green coffee with other caffeine sources, including coffee, black tea, and green tea. These are not the same.
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000045-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Green Coffee ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using green coffee for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000045-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Green Coffee and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000045-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Green Coffee ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000045-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Green Coffee and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Ephedrine Stimulant drugs speed up the nervous system. The caffeine in green coffee and ephedrine are both stimulant drugs. Taking green coffee and ephedrine might cause too much stimulation and sometimes serious side effects and heart problems. Do not take caffeine-containing products and ephedrine at the same time. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Adenosine (Adenocard) Green coffee contains caffeine. The caffeine in green coffee might block the effects of adenosine, which is often used by doctors to do a test called a cardiac stress test. Stop consuming green coffee at least 24 hours before a cardiac stress test. Alendronate (Fosamax) Green coffee might decrease how much alendronate the body absorbs. Taking green coffee and alendronate at the same time might decrease the effects of alendronate. Don't take green coffee within two hours of taking alendronate. Birth control pills (Contraceptive drugs) Green coffee contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Birth control pills can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. This might increase the risk for side effects from caffeine, such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Cimetidine (Tagamet) The body breaks down the caffeine in green coffee to get rid of it. Cimetidine can decrease how quickly your body breaks down caffeine. Taking cimetidine along with green coffee might increase the chance of caffeine side effects including jitteriness, headache, fast heartbeat, and others. Clozapine (Clozaril) The body breaks down clozapine to get rid of it. The caffeine in green coffee might decrease how fast the body breaks down clozapine. Taking green coffee along with clozapine can increase the effects and side effects of clozapine. Dipyridamole (Persantine) The caffeine in green coffee might block the effects of dipyridamole. Dipyridamole is often used by doctors to do a test on the heart called a cardiac stress test. Stop taking green coffee at least 24 hours before a cardiac stress test. Disulfiram (Antabuse) The body breaks down the caffeine in green coffee to get rid of it. Disulfiram can decrease how quickly the body gets rid of caffeine. Taking green coffee along with disulfiram might increase the side effects of caffeine including jitteriness, hyperactivity, irritability, and others. Estrogens The body breaks down the caffeine in green coffee to get rid of it. Estrogens can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking estrogen and green coffee might increase caffeine side effects, including jitteriness, headache, fast heartbeat, and others. If you take estrogen, limit your caffeine intake. Fluvoxamine (Luvox) The body breaks down the caffeine in green coffee to get rid of it. Fluvoxamine can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking caffeine along with fluvoxamine might increase caffeine side effects including nervousness, anxiety, and insomnia. Lithium Green coffee contains caffeine. Caffeine can increase how quickly your body gets rid of lithium. If you take products that contain caffeine and you take lithium, don't stop taking caffeine products all at once. Instead, reduce use slowly. Stopping caffeine too quickly can increase the side effects of lithium. Medications for asthma (Beta-adrenergic agonists) Green coffee contains caffeine. Caffeine can stimulate the heart. Some medications for asthma can also stimulate the heart. Taking caffeine with some medications for asthma might cause too much stimulation and cause heart problems. Medications for depression (MAOIs) Green coffee contains caffeine. There is some concern that caffeine can interact with certain medications, called MAOIs. If caffeine is taken with these medications, it might increase the risk of serious side effects including fast heartbeat and very high blood pressure. 

Some common MAOIs include phenelzine (Nardil), selegiline (Zelapar), and tranylcypromine (Parnate). Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Green coffee might slow blood clotting. Taking green coffee along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Nicotine Green coffee contains caffeine. Taking caffeine along with nicotine might increase rapid heart rate and blood pressure. Pentobarbital (Nembutal) Green coffee contains caffeine. The stimulant effects of caffeine can block the sleep-producing effects of pentobarbital. Phenylpropanolamine The caffeine in green coffee can stimulate the body. Phenylpropanolamine can also stimulate the body. Taking caffeine and phenylpropanolamine together might cause too much stimulation and increase heartbeat, blood pressure, and cause nervousness. Pioglitazone (Actos) Green coffee contains caffeine. Caffeine might increase the amount of pioglitazone that the body absorbs. Taking green coffee might increase the effects and adverse effects of pioglitazone. Riluzole (Rilutek) Green coffee can decrease how quickly the body breaks down riluzole and increase the effects and side effects of riluzole. Stimulant drugs Stimulants, such as amphetamines and cocaine, speed up the nervous system. By speeding up the nervous system, stimulant medications can increase blood pressure and speed up the heartbeat. Green coffee contains caffeine. Caffeine can also speed up the nervous system. Taking green coffee along with stimulant drugs might cause serious problems including increased heart rate and high blood pressure. Theophylline The caffeine in green coffee works similarly to theophylline. Caffeine can also decrease how quickly the body gets rid of theophylline. Taking green coffee and taking theophylline might increase the effects and side effects of theophylline. Verapamil (Calan, others) Verapamil can decrease how quickly the body gets rid of caffeine. Drinking green coffee and taking verapamil can increase the risk of caffeine side effects including jitteriness, headache, and an increased heartbeat. Water pills (Diuretic drugs) The caffeine in green coffee can reduce potassium levels. "Water pills" can also decrease potassium levels in the body. Taking caffeine with water pills might cause potassium levels to drop too low. 

Some "water pills" that can deplete potassium include chlorothiazide (Diuril), chlorthalidone (Thalitone), furosemide (Lasix), hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ, HydroDiuril, Microzide), and others. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Alcohol (Ethanol) The body breaks down the caffeine in green coffee to get rid of it. Alcohol can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking green coffee along with alcohol might increase the risk for caffeine side effects including jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Antibiotics (Quinolone antibiotics) The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Some antibiotics might decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking these antibiotics along with green coffee can increase the risk of caffeine side effects including jitteriness, headache, increased heart rate, and others. Fluconazole (Diflucan) The body breaks down the caffeine in green coffee to get rid of it. Fluconazole might decrease how quickly the body gets rid of caffeine. Taking fluconazole and green coffee might increase caffeine side effects including nervousness, anxiety, and insomnia. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Green coffee might increase or decrease blood sugar levels. Taking green coffee along with diabetes medications might change the effects of these medications. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications for high blood pressure (Antihypertensive drugs) Green coffee might lower blood pressure. Taking green coffee along with medications that lower blood pressure might cause blood pressure to go too low. Monitor your blood pressure closely. Mexiletine (Mexitil) Green coffee contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Mexiletine can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking mexiletine along with green coffee might increase the risk of caffeine side effects. Phenothiazines Green coffee contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Phenothiazines can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking phenothiazines along with green coffee might increase the risk of caffeine side effects. Terbinafine (Lamisil) The body breaks down the caffeine in green coffee to get rid of it. Terbinafine can decrease how fast the body gets rid of caffeine. This might increase the risk of caffeine side effects including jitteriness, headache, increased heartbeat, and others.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000045-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Green Coffee and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bitter orange Green coffee contains caffeine. Bitter orange, used along with caffeine or caffeine-containing herbs such as green coffee, can increase blood pressure and heart rate in otherwise healthy people. This might damage the heart and blood vessels. Caffeine-containing herbs and supplements Green coffee contains caffeine. Taking it along with other products that contain caffeine might increase caffeine side effects. Examples of supplements that contain caffeine include black tea, coffee, green tea, guarana, and yerba mate. Calcium Green coffee contains caffeine. High doses of caffeine can increase the loss of calcium in the urine. Cordyceps Green coffee contains caffeine. Cordyceps might increase how quickly the body gets rid of caffeine. This might decrease the effects of caffeine. Creatine Green coffee contains caffeine. There is some concern that combining caffeine or caffeine-containing beverages and herbs with ephedra and creatine might increase the risk of serious side effects. There is a report of stroke in one athlete who used creatine monohydrate, caffeine, ephedra, and a variety of other supplements daily for 6 weeks. Caffeine might also decrease creatine's possible beneficial effects on athletic performance. Cyclodextrin Cyclodextrin is a dietary fiber. It might bind with a chemical found in green coffee, called chlorogenic acid. This might reduce the blood pressure-lowering effects of green coffee. Echinacea Green coffee contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Echinacea might decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Using echinacea with caffeine might increase caffeine levels. Ephedra (Ma huang) Don't take green coffee with ephedra. Using ephedra with the caffeine in green coffee might increase the risk of serious life-threatening or disabling conditions such as hypertension, heart attack, stroke, seizures, and death. Genistein-containing herbs and supplements Green coffee contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Taking herbs or supplements that contain genistein might decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Using genistein with caffeine might increase caffeine levels. Herbs and supplements that might lower blood pressure Green coffee might lower blood pressure. Taking it with other supplements that have the same effect might cause blood pressure to drop too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include andrographis, casein peptides, L-arginine, niacin, and stinging nettle. Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Green coffee might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Green coffee might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng. Iron Certain components of green coffee might reduce the amount of iron the body absorbs from food. Kudzu Green coffee contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Kudzu seems to decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Using kudzu with caffeine might increase caffeine levels. Magnesium Green coffee contains caffeine. High doses of caffeine can increase how quickly the body releases magnesium in the urine. Melatonin Green coffee contains caffeine. Taking caffeine and melatonin together can increase melatonin levels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000045-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Green Coffee and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000045-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Green Coffee ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>