<Document id="0000075" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/480.html">

<Focus>Pennyroyal</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000075-1" qtype="information">What is Pennyroyal ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pennyroyal (Mentha pulegium) is a plant that grows throughout the world. The leaves, and the oil they contain, are used to make medicine. 

Pennyroyal essential oil contains chemicals that have various toxic effects in the body. 

People use pennyroyal for the common cold, pneumonia, fatigue, ending a pregnancy (abortion), and as an insect repellant, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. It is also unsafe. 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000075-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Pennyroyal ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using pennyroyal for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000075-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Pennyroyal and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000075-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Pennyroyal ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000075-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Pennyroyal and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Acetaminophen (Tylenol, others) Pennyroyal can cause liver damage. Taking pennyroyal with acetaminophen, which causes a similar type of liver damage, might increase the risk for liver damage.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000075-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Pennyroyal and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Iron Pennyroyal might reduce how much iron the body absorbs from supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000075-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Pennyroyal and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pennyroyal might reduce how much iron the body absorbs from food.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000075-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Pennyroyal ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>