<Document id="0000024" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/945.html">

<Focus>Capsicum</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000024-1" qtype="information">What is Capsicum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Capsicum, also known as red pepper or chili pepper, is an herb. Its fruit is commonly applied to the skin for arthritis pain and other conditions. 


The fruit of the capsicum plant contains a chemical called capsaicin. Capsaicin is what seems to help reduce pain and swelling. A particular form of capsicum causes intense eye pain and other unpleasant effects when it comes in contact with the face. This form is used in self-defense pepper sprays.   

Capsicum is commonly used for nerve pain and other painful conditions. It is also used for many other purposes, including digestion problems, conditions of the heart and blood vessels, and many others, but there is no good scientific evidence for many of these uses. 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000024-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Capsicum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  CAPSICUM  are as follows: Likely effective for... 

 Nerve pain in people with diabetes (diabetic neuropathy) . A specific cream containing 0.075% capsaicin (Zostrix-HP, Link Medical Products Pty Ltd.) 4 times daily is approved for treating this condition. Another patch containing 8% capsaicin (Qutenza, NeurogesX, Inc.), which is available by prescription only, is also approved for treating this condition. Creams or gels that contain smaller amounts of capsaicin (less than 0.075%) don't seem to work.  , 

 Chronic pain . Applying creams and lotions containing capsaicin, the active chemical in capsicum, can temporarily relieve chronic pain from several conditions. It's FDA approved for this use., 

 Nerve damage caused by shingles (postherpetic neuralgia) . Applying a patch containing 8% capsaicin (Qutenza, NeurogesX Inc.), the active chemical in capsicum, reduces pain over 24 hours in people with this condition. This capsaicin patch is available by prescription only., 

 

 Possibly effective for... 

 Back pain . Applying capsicum or capsaicin to the skin seems to help reduce back pain., 

 Cluster headache . Applying capsaicin, the active chemical in capsicum, inside the nose can reduce the number and severity of cluster headaches. It's not clear if it helps treat cluster headaches., 

 Runny nose not caused by allergies or infection (nonallergic rhinitis) . Applying capsaicin, the active chemical in capsicum, inside the nose can reduce runny nose in people who do not have allergies or an infection. The benefits might last for 6-9 months., 

 Osteoarthritis . Applying 0.025% capsaicin, the active chemical in capsicum, to the skin can improve symptoms of osteoarthritis.  , 

 Acute pain . Applying capsaicin, the active chemical in capsicum, to the skin can reduce pain from trauma. , 


 Nausea and vomiting after surgery . Applying a plaster containing capsicum to specific points on the hand and forearm reduces nausea and vomiting after surgery., 

 Pain after surgery . Applying a plaster containing capsicum to specific points on the hand and forearm reduces the need for painkillers within the first 24 hours after surgery. , 
 
There is interest in using capsicum for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000024-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Capsicum and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000024-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Capsicum ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000024-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Capsicum and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Aspirin Capsicum might decrease how much aspirin the body can absorb. Taking capsicum along with aspirin might reduce the effects of aspirin. Ciprofloxacin (Cipro) Capsicum might increase how much ciprofloxacin the body can absorb. Taking capsicum along with ciprofloxacin might increase the effects and side effects of ciprofloxacin. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Capsicum might lower blood sugar levels. Taking capsicum along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Capsicum might slow blood clotting. Taking capsicum along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Theophylline Capsicum can increase how much theophylline the body can absorb. Taking capsicum along with theophylline might increase the effects and side effects of theophylline. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Medications for high blood pressure (ACE inhibitors) Some medications for high blood pressure might cause a cough. There is one report of someone whose cough worsened when using a cream with capsicum along with these medications for high blood pressure. But it isn't clear if this interaction is a big concern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000024-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Capsicum and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Capsicum might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Capsicum might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng. Iron There is some concern that using capsicum might reduce how much iron the body can absorb.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000024-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Capsicum and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000024-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Capsicum ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>