<Document id="0000074" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/483.html">

<Focus>Peanut Oil</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000074-1" qtype="information">What is Peanut Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>Peanut oil is the oil from the seed (peanut) of the peanut plant (Arachis hypogaea). Peanut oil is used in cooking and is also used to make medicine. 

Peanut oil is high in monounsaturated "good" fat and low in saturated "bad" fat. This is believed to help prevent heart disease and lower cholesterol. Peanut oil might help to reduce fatty build up in blood vessels.  

People use peanut oil for high levels of cholesterol or other fats in the blood, heart disease, joint pain, dry skin, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 

Peanut is considered a major food allergen in the US. Peanut contents, including peanut oil, must be labeled on packaged food and supplement products.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000074-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Peanut Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using peanut oil for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000074-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Peanut Oil and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000074-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Peanut Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000074-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Peanut Oil and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000074-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Peanut Oil and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000074-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Peanut Oil and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000074-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Peanut Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>