<Document id="0000058" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/754.html">

<Focus>Lutein</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000058-1" qtype="information">What is Lutein ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lutein is a type of organic pigment called a carotenoid. It is related to beta-carotene and vitamin A. Many people think of lutein as "the eye vitamin." 

Lutein is one of two major carotenoids found in the human eye (macula and retina). It is thought to function as a light filter, protecting the eye tissues from sunlight damage. Foods rich in lutein include egg yolks, spinach, kale, corn, orange pepper, kiwi fruit, grapes, zucchini, and squash.  

Lutein is commonly taken by mouth to prevent eye diseases, including cataracts and a disease that leads to vision loss in older adults (age-related macular degeneration or AMD). Lutein is used for many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these other uses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000058-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Lutein ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  LUTEIN  are as follows: Possibly effective for... An eye disease that leads to vision loss in older adults (age-related macular degeneration or AMD) . Taking lutein supplements by mouth for up to 36 months can improve some symptoms of AMD. More benefits might be seen when it's taken for at least 3 months at doses above 5 mg, and when it's combined with other carotenoid vitamins. But lutein doesn't seem to keep AMD from becoming worse over time., 

 Cataracts . Eating higher amounts of lutein in the diet is linked with a lower risk of developing cataracts. But it's not clear if taking lutein supplements by mouth helps people who already have cataracts., 


 Possibly ineffective for... 

 A lung disease that affects newborns (bronchopulmonary dysplasia) . Giving preterm infants lutein and zeaxanthin by mouth doesn't reduce the chance of developing bronchopulmonary dysplasia. , 


 A serious intestinal disease in premature infants (necrotizing enterocolitis or NEC) . Giving preterm infants lutein and zeaxanthin by mouth doesn't prevent NEC., 

 An inherited eye condition that causes poor night vision and loss of side vision (retinitis pigmentosa) . Taking lutein by mouth doesn't improve vision or other symptoms in people with retinitis pigmentosa., 

 An eye disorder in premature infants that can lead to blindness (retinopathy of prematurity) . Giving preterm infants lutein and zeaxanthin by mouth doesn't prevent retinopathy of prematurity., 
 

There is interest in using lutein for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000058-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Lutein and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000058-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Lutein ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000058-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Lutein and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000058-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Lutein and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Beta-carotene Using beta-carotene along with lutein may reduce the amount of lutein or beta-carotene that the body can absorb. Vitamin E Taking lutein supplements might decrease how much vitamin E the body absorbs. Taking lutein and vitamin E together might decrease the effects of vitamin E.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000058-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Lutein and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lutein is better absorbed by the body when it is taken with a high-fat meal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000058-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Lutein ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>