<Document id="0000041" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/807.html">

<Focus>Glucosamine sulfate</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000041-1" qtype="information">What is Glucosamine sulfate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glucosamine is a chemical found in the body. Glucosamine supplements are sold as glucosamine sulfate, glucosamine hydrochloride, and N-acetyl glucosamine. 

Glucosamine is used by the body to make other chemicals that build tendons, ligaments, cartilage, and the fluid that surrounds joints. Joints are cushioned by the fluid and cartilage around them. Taking glucosamine might increase the cartilage and fluid around joints and/or help prevent their breakdown. 

People commonly use glucosamine sulfate and glucosamine hydrochloride for osteoarthritis. Glucosamine is also used for joint pain, rheumatoid arthritis, multiple sclerosis, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these other uses.
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000041-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Glucosamine sulfate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  GLUCOSAMINE  are as follows: Likely effective for... 

 Osteoarthritis . Taking glucosamine sulfate by mouth for at least 4 weeks can provide some pain relief and improve function for people with knee osteoarthritis. Products that contain glucosamine hydrochloride do not seem to work as well unless they are taken in combination with other ingredients. Taking glucosamine sulfate doesn't seem to reduce the risk of getting osteoarthritis.  
  

 ,  

There is interest in using glucosamine for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000041-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Glucosamine sulfate and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000041-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Glucosamine sulfate ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000041-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Glucosamine sulfate and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Warfarin (Coumadin) Warfarin is used to slow blood clotting. Taking glucosamine with or without chondroitin increases the effects of warfarin. This can increase the risk for serious bruising and bleeding. Don't take glucosamine if you are taking warfarin. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications for cancer (Topoisomerase II Inhibitors) Some medications for cancer work by decreasing how fast cancer cells can copy themselves. Glucosamine might block these medications from working. Taking glucosamine along with some medications for cancer might decrease the effectiveness of these medications. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Acetaminophen (Tylenol, others) Taking glucosamine SULFATE and acetaminophen together might affect how well each works. But more information is needed to know if this interaction is a big concern. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Glucosamine might increase blood sugar levels. Taking glucosamine along with diabetes medications might reduce the effects of these medications. Monitor your blood sugar closely.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000041-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Glucosamine sulfate and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chondroitin sulfate Taking chondroitin sulfate together with glucosamine HYDROCHLORIDE might reduce blood levels of glucosamine hydrochloride. But it's not clear if this will change the effects of glucosamine hydrochloride.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000041-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Glucosamine sulfate and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000041-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Glucosamine sulfate ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>