<Document id="0000007" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/78.html">

<Focus>Bee Pollen</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000007-1" qtype="information">What is Bee Pollen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bee pollen is flower pollen that's collected by worker bees, mixed with nectar and bee saliva, and then packed into honeycomb cells in the hive.  

Bee pollen might help stimulate the immune system, but it's not clear how bee pollen causes these effects.  

People take bee pollen for athletic performance, hay fever, eczema, constipation, obesity, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. There is also no good evidence to support using bee pollen for COVID-19. 

Bee pollens come from many different plants, so the contents of bee pollen can vary significantly. Don't confuse bee pollen with beeswax, bee venom, honey, propolis, or royal jelly. These other bee products are not the same.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000007-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Bee Pollen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  BEE POLLEN  are as follows: Possibly ineffective for... Athletic performance . Taking bee pollen by mouth doesn't seem to improve athletic performance.,  

There is interest in using bee pollen for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000007-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Bee Pollen and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000007-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Bee Pollen ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000007-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Bee Pollen and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Warfarin (Coumadin) Bee pollen might increase the effects of warfarin. Taking bee pollen with warfarin might result in an increased chance of bruising or bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000007-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Bee Pollen and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000007-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Bee Pollen and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000007-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Bee Pollen ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>