<Document id="0000099" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/794.html">

<Focus>5-HTP</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000099-1" qtype="information">What is 5-HTP ?</Question>
			<Answer>5-hydroxytryptophan (5-HTP) can be converted to serotonin in the body. It is often used for depression. It has less evidence for insomnia and anxiety.  

5-HTP is a chemical byproduct of the protein building block L-tryptophan. It is produced commercially from the seeds of an African plant known as Griffonia simplicifolia. 5-HTP works in the brain and central nervous system by increasing the production of the chemical serotonin. Serotonin can affect sleep, appetite, temperature, sexual behavior, and pain sensation.  

Since 5-HTP increases serotonin levels, it is used for conditions in which serotonin is believed to play an important role. These include depression, anxiety, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses.
 

</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000099-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is 5-HTP ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  5-HTP  are as follows: Possibly effective for... Depression . Taking 5-HTP by mouth seems to improve symptoms of depression in some people. It might work as well as some prescription antidepressant drugs. , 
 Possibly ineffective for... Down syndrome . Most research shows that taking 5-HTP by mouth does not improve muscle strength or development in children with Down syndrome. , 
 

There is interest in using 5-HTP for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000099-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of 5-HTP and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000099-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about 5-HTP ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000099-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between 5-HTP and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Carbidopa (Lodosyn) 5-HTP can affect the brain. Carbidopa can also affect the brain. Taking 5-HTP along with carbidopa can increase the risk of serious side effects including rapid speech, anxiety, aggressiveness, and others. Sedative medications (CNS depressants) 5-HTP might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Some medications, called sedatives, can also cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking 5-HTP with sedative medications might cause breathing problems and/or too much sleepiness. Serotonergic drugs 5-HTP might increase a brain chemical called serotonin. Some medications also have this effect. Taking 5-HTP along with these medications might increase serotonin too much. This might cause serious side effects including heart problems, seizures, and vomiting.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000099-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between 5-HTP and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements with sedative properties 5-HTP might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking it along with other supplements with similar effects might cause too much sleepiness and/or slowed breathing in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include hops, kava, L-tryptophan, melatonin, and valerian. Herbs and supplements with serotonergic properties 5-HTP increases a brain chemical called serotonin. Taking it along with other supplements that have this effect might cause serious side effects, including heart problems, seizures, and vomiting. Examples of supplements with this effect include black seed, L-tryptophan, SAMe, and St. John's wort.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000099-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between 5-HTP and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000099-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of 5-HTP ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>