<Document id="0000080" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1262.html">

<Focus>Raspberry Ketone</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000080-1" qtype="information">What is Raspberry Ketone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Raspberry ketone is a chemical that is found in red raspberries and other fruits. It's popular for obesity, but it's not clear if it helps. 

It's believed that raspberry ketone might increase metabolism, increase how quickly the body burns fat, and reduce appetite. But evidence in humans is limited. Raspberry ketone is also found in kiwifruit, peaches, grapes, apples, other berries, rhubarb, and the bark of yew, maple, and pine trees. 

People use raspberry ketone for obesity, hair loss, male pattern baldness, and other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000080-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Raspberry Ketone ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using raspberry ketone for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000080-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Raspberry Ketone and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000080-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Raspberry Ketone ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000080-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Raspberry Ketone and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Stimulant drugs Stimulants, such as amphetamines and cocaine, speed up the nervous system. By speeding up the nervous system, stimulant medications can increase blood pressure and speed up the heartbeat. Raspberry ketone might also speed up the nervous system. Taking raspberry ketone along with stimulant drugs might cause serious problems including increased heart rate and high blood pressure.  Warfarin (Coumadin) Warfarin is used to thin the blood and prevent blood clots. Raspberry ketone might reduce the effects of warfarin, which could increase the risk for blood clots. If you take warfarin, talk with your healthcare provider before taking raspberry ketone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000080-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Raspberry Ketone and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements with stimulant properties Raspberry ketone might have stimulant effects. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the chance of side effects, including rapid heartbeat and high blood pressure. Examples of supplements with this effect include 1,3-DMAA, bitter orange, caffeine-containing products, DMHA, and ephedra.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000080-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Raspberry Ketone and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000080-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Raspberry Ketone ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>