<Document id="0000060" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/555.html">

<Focus>Maca</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000060-1" qtype="information">What is Maca ?</Question>
			<Answer>Maca, also called Ginseng Andin, Peruvian Ginseng, Lepidium meyenii, or Lepidium peruvianum, is a relative of radish and smells similar to butterscotch. 

Maca is a plant that grows on the high plateaus of the Andes Mountains. It's been cultivated as a root vegetable for at least 3000 years. The root is also used to make medicine, but there isn't enough reliable information available to know how maca might work. 

People take maca by mouth for male infertility, health problems after menopause, increasing sexual desire in healthy people, and other purposes, but there is no good scientific evidence to support any of these uses.
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000060-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Maca ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using maca for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000060-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Maca and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000060-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Maca ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000060-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Maca and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000060-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Maca and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000060-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Maca and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000060-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Maca ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>