<Document id="0000049" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/738.html">

<Focus>Honey</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000049-1" qtype="information">What is Honey ?</Question>
			<Answer>Honey is a thick, sweet fluid produced by bees from plant nectars. It is commonly used as a sweetener in food, but should be avoided in infants. 

Some chemicals in honey might kill certain bacteria and fungus. When applied to the skin, honey might serve as a barrier to moisture and keep skin from sticking to wound dressings. It might also provide nutrients and chemicals that speed wound healing. But honey can become contaminated with germs during production. Although rare, some infants have gotten botulism from taking honey by mouth.  

People commonly use honey for burns, wound healing, swelling and sores inside the mouth, and cough. It is also used for many other conditions but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these other uses. There is also no good evidence to support using honey for COVID-19.  

Don't confuse honey with bee pollen, bee venom, or royal jelly, which are other types of bee products.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000049-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Honey ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  HONEY  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 
 Burns . Applying honey preparations directly to burns seems to improve healing., 

 Cough . Taking a small amount of honey by mouth at bedtime appears to reduce coughing spells in children aged 2 years and older. Honey appears to be at least as effective as the cough medicine dextromethorphan. But it is not clear if honey reduces cough in adults. , 

 Foot sores in people with diabetes . Applying dressings containing honey to diabetic foot ulcers seems to reduce healing time and prevent the need for antibiotics. , 

 Dry eye . Using specific honey eye drops or eye gel in the eyes (Optimel Manuka plus eye drops or Optimel Antibacterial Manuka Eye Gel) helps to make dry eyes feel better. These products can be used along with regular dry eye treatment such as lubricant drops and warm cloths on the eyes., 

 Cold sores (herpes labialis) . Applying honey to cold sores seems to improve healing time., 

 Sores and ulcers of the mouth and gums caused by herpes virus (herpetic gingivostomatitis) . Rinsing the mouth and then slowly swallowing honey helps these sores and ulcers heal faster in children who are taking a medication called acyclovir., 

 Swelling (inflammation) and sores inside the mouth (oral mucositis) . Rinsing the mouth and then slowly swallowing honey before and after chemotherapy or radiation therapy sessions seems to reduce the risk of developing mouth sores., 

 A skin condition that causes redness on the face (rosacea) . Applying a topical honey product to the skin might improve symptoms of rosacea., 

 Wound healing . Applying honey preparations directly to wounds or using dressings containing honey seems to improve healing. Honey seems to reduce odors and pus, help clean the wound, reduce infection, reduce pain, and decrease time to healing. , 
 Possibly ineffective for... 
 Acne . Applying honey to the face doesn't help treat acne., 

 High levels of cholesterol or other fats (lipids) in the blood (hyperlipidemia) . Taking honey by mouth does not seem to reduce lipid levels in people with high cholesterol., 

 Swelling (inflammation) of the nasal cavity and sinuses (rhinosinusitis) . Using honey in a nasal spray doesn't help improve symptoms in people who have frequent sinus infections., 
 

There is interest in using honey for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000049-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Honey and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000049-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Honey ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000049-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Honey and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Honey might slow blood clotting. Taking honey along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Phenytoin (Dilantin) Honey might increase how much phenytoin the body absorbs. Taking honey along with phenytoin might increase the effects and side effects of phenytoin. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Honey might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000049-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Honey and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Honey might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000049-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Honey and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000049-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Honey ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>