<Document id="0000026" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/744.html">

<Focus>Chondroitin sulfate</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000026-1" qtype="information">What is Chondroitin sulfate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chondroitin sulfate is a chemical found in human and animal cartilage. It is commonly used by mouth with glucosamine or other ingredients for osteoarthritis. 

Chondroitin sulfate is one of the building blocks of cartilage. In osteoarthritis, the cartilage in the joints breaks down. Taking chondroitin sulfate might slow this breakdown. It is usually manufactured from animal sources, such as shark and cow cartilage. It can also be made in a lab. 

Chondroitin sulfate is used for osteoarthritis and cataracts. It is often used together with other ingredients, including manganese ascorbate, hyaluronic acid, collagen peptides, or glucosamine. Chondroitin sulfate is also used for many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000026-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Chondroitin sulfate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  CHONDROITIN SULFATE  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 
 Cataracts . An injectable solution containing chondroitin sulfate and sodium hyaluronate is approved by the FDA to protect the eye during cataract surgery. It is not clear if using it in a different form will help., 

 Osteoarthritis . Taking chondroitin sulfate by mouth seems to provide some relief from osteoarthritis pain and improve function. High quality, pharmaceutical-grade products have shown the most benefit. Chondrosulf (IBSA Institut Biochimique SA), Chondrosan (Bioiberica, S.A.) and Structum (Laboratoires Pierre Fabre) are examples of these products. 
, 

 

There is interest in using chondroitin sulfate for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000026-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Chondroitin sulfate and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000026-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Chondroitin sulfate ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000026-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Chondroitin sulfate and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Warfarin (Coumadin) Warfarin is used to slow blood clotting. There are several reports showing that taking chondroitin with glucosamine increases the effects of warfarin. This can cause bruising and bleeding that can be serious. Don't take chondroitin if you are taking warfarin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000026-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Chondroitin sulfate and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glucosamine Taking chondroitin sulfate together with glucosamine hydrochloride might reduce blood levels of glucosamine. But it's not clear if this will change the effects of glucosamine hydrochloride. It's also not clear if this interaction occurs with other forms of glucosamine, such as glucosamine sulfate.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000026-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Chondroitin sulfate and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000026-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Chondroitin sulfate ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>