<Document id="0000046" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/935.html">

<Focus>Guarana</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000046-1" qtype="information">What is Guarana ?</Question>
			<Answer>Guarana (Paullinia cupana) is a plant native to the Amazon. It is a common ingredient of energy drinks and can be unsafe in large amounts. 

Guarana contains caffeine. Caffeine works by stimulating the central nervous system, heart, and muscles. Guarana also contains theophylline and theobromine, which are chemicals similar to caffeine. 

People take guarana by mouth for obesity, athletic performance, mental performance, to increase energy, and for many other reasons, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. Guarana can also be unsafe when taken long-term in large amounts.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000046-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Guarana ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using guarana for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000046-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Guarana and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000046-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Guarana ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000046-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Guarana and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Ephedrine Stimulant drugs speed up the nervous system. Caffeine (contained in guarana) and ephedrine are both stimulant drugs. Taking guarana along with ephedrine might cause too much stimulation and serious side effects and heart problems. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Adenosine (Adenocard) Guarana contains caffeine. The caffeine in guarana might block the affects of adenosine, which is often used by doctors to do a test called a cardiac stress test. Stop consuming guarana at least 24 hours before a cardiac stress test. Carbamazepine (Tegretol) Carbamazepine is used to treat seizures. The caffeine in guarana might reduce the effects of carbamazepine. In theory, taking guarana with carbamazepine might reduce its effects and increase the risk of seizures in some people. Cimetidine (Tagamet) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Cimetidine can decrease how quickly your body breaks down caffeine. Taking cimetidine along with guarana might increase the chance of caffeine side effects including jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Clozapine (Clozaril) The body breaks down clozapine to get rid of it. The caffeine in guarana seems to decrease how quickly the body breaks down clozapine. Taking guarana along with clozapine can increase the effects and side effects of clozapine. Dipyridamole (Persantine) Guarana contains caffeine. The caffeine in guarana might block the effects of dipyridamole, which is often used by doctors to do a test called a cardiac stress test. Stop consuming guarana at least 24 hours before a cardiac stress test. Disulfiram (Antabuse) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Disulfiram can decrease how quickly the body gets rid of caffeine. Taking guarana along with disulfiram might increase the chance of caffeine side effects, including jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Estrogens Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down the caffeine to get rid of it. Estrogens can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking guarana along with estrogens can increase the risk of caffeine side effects, including jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Ethosuximide Ethosuximide is used to treat seizures. Caffeine in guarana might reduce the effects of ethosuximide. In theory, taking guarana with ethosuximide might reduce its effects and increase the risk of seizures in some people. Felbamate Felbamate is used to treat seizures. Caffeine in guarana might reduce the effects of felbamate. In theory, taking guarana with felbamate might reduce its effects and increase the risk of seizures. Flutamide (Eulexin) The body breaks down flutamide to get rid of it. Caffeine in guarana might decrease how quickly the body breaks down flutamide. In theory, taking guarana along with flutamide might increase the effects and side effects of flutamide. Fluvoxamine (Luvox) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down the caffeine to get rid of it. Fluvoxamine can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking guarana along with fluvoxamine might increase the risk of caffeine side effects, such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Lithium The body naturally gets rid of lithium. The caffeine in guarana can increase how quickly the body gets rid of lithium. If you take products that contain caffeine and you take lithium, don't change your dose of caffeine quickly. Stopping caffeine too quickly can increase the side effects of lithium. If you stop using caffeine, reduce the dose slowly. Medications for asthma (Beta-adrenergic agonists) Guarana contains caffeine. Caffeine can stimulate the heart. Some medications for asthma can also stimulate the heart. Taking caffeine with some medications for asthma might cause too much stimulation and heart problems. Medications for depression (MAOIs) Guarana contains caffeine. There is some concern that caffeine can interact with certain medications, called MAOIs. If caffeine is taken with these medications, it might increase the risk for serious side effects including fast heartbeat and very high blood pressure. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Guarana might slow blood clotting. Taking guarana along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Nicotine Stimulant drugs such as nicotine speed up the nervous system. The caffeine in guarana might also speed up the nervous system. Taking guarana along with stimulant drugs might cause serious problems including increased heart rate and high blood pressure. Pentobarbital (Nembutal) The stimulant effects of the caffeine in guarana can block the sleep-producing effects of pentobarbital. Phenobarbital (Luminal) Phenobarbital is used to treat seizures. Caffeine, in guarana might reduce the effects of phenobarbital. In theory, taking guarana with phenobarbital might reduce its effects and increase the risk of seizures. Phenylpropanolamine The caffeine in guarana can stimulate the body. Phenylpropanolamine can also stimulate the body. Taking guarana along with phenylpropanolamine might cause too much stimulation and increase heartbeat, blood pressure, and cause nervousness. Phenytoin (Dilantin) Phenytoin is used to control some types of seizures. Caffeine in guarana might reduce the effects of phenytoin. In theory, taking guarana with phenytoin might reduce its effects and increase the risk of seizures. Pioglitazone (Actos) The caffeine in guarana might increase the amount of pioglitazone that the body absorbs. Taking guarana might increase the effects and adverse effects of pioglitazone. Riluzole (Rilutek) The body breaks down riluzole to get rid of it. Taking guarana can decrease how fast the body breaks down riluzole and increase the effects and side effects of riluzole. Stimulant drugs Stimulants, such as amphetamines and cocaine, speed up the nervous system. By speeding up the nervous system, stimulant medications can increase blood pressure and speed up the heartbeat. Caffeine in guarana can also speed up the nervous system. Taking guarana along with stimulant drugs might cause serious problems including increased heart rate and high blood pressure. Theophylline Guarana contains caffeine. Caffeine works similarly to theophylline. Caffeine can also decrease how quickly the body gets rid of theophylline. Taking guarana along with theophylline might increase the effects and side effects of theophylline. Valproate Valproate is used to treat seizures. Caffeine in guarana might reduce the effects of valproate. In theory, taking guarana with valproate might reduce its effects and increase the risk of seizures. Verapamil (Calan, others) The body breaks down the caffeine in guarana to get rid of it. Verapamil can decrease how quickly the body gets rid of caffeine. Taking guarana along with verapamil can increase the risk of caffeine side effects including jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Water pills (Diuretic drugs) Guarana contains caffeine. Caffeine can decrease potassium levels. "Water pills" can also decrease potassium levels. Taking guarana along with "water pills" might make potassium levels drop too low. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Alcohol (Ethanol) The body breaks down the caffeine in guarana to get rid of it. Alcohol can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking guarana along with alcohol might increase the risk for caffeine side effects, such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Antibiotics (Quinolone antibiotics) The body breaks down caffeine from guarana to get rid of it. Some drugs can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking these drugs along with guarana might increase the risk of caffeine side effects including jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Birth control pills (Contraceptive drugs) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Birth control pills can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. This might increase the risk for caffeine side effects, such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Fluconazole (Diflucan) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Fluconazole might decrease how quickly the body gets rid of caffeine. Taking guarana along with fluconazole might increase the risk of caffeine side effects such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Guarana might lower blood sugar levels. Taking guarana along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications that decrease the breakdown of other medications by the liver (Cytochrome P450 1A2 (CYP1A2) inhibitors) Guarana is changed and broken down by the liver. Some drugs decrease how quickly the liver changes and breaks down guarana. This could change the effects and side effects of guarana. Metformin (Glucophage) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Metformin can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking metformin along with guarana might increase the risk of caffeine side effects. such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Methoxsalen (Oxsoralen) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Methoxsalen can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking methoxsalen along with guarana might increase the risk of caffeine side effects, such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Mexiletine (Mexitil) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Mexiletine can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking mexiletine along with guarana might increase the risk of caffeine side effects, such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Phenothiazines Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Phenothiazines can decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking phenothiazines along with guarana might increase the risk of caffeine side effects, such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Terbinafine (Lamisil) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Terbinafine can decrease how fast the body gets rid of caffeine and increase the risk of caffeine side effects such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat. Tiagabine (Gabitril) Tiagabine is used to treat seizures. There is some concern that caffeine can reduce the effects of tiagabine. But studies show that tiagabine still works even when taken with caffeine. Ticlopidine (Ticlid) Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Ticlopidine can decrease how fast the body gets rid of caffeine. In theory, taking guarana along with ticlopidine might increase the risk of caffeine side effects, such as jitteriness, headache, and fast heartbeat.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000046-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Guarana and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bitter orange Guarana contains caffeine. Taking bitter orange along with herbs that contain caffeine, such as guarana, can increase blood pressure and heart rate in people who otherwise have normal blood pressure. This might increase the chance of developing problems with the heart and blood vessels. Caffeine-containing herbs and supplements Guarana contains caffeine. Taking it along with other supplements that contain caffeine might increase caffeine side effects. Examples of supplements that contain caffeine include black tea, coffee, green tea, and yerba mate. Calcium High caffeine intake from foods, beverages, and herbs including guarana increases how much calcium the body loses in the urine. This might lower calcium levels. Creatine There is some concern that taking caffeine with creatine might reduce the beneficial effects that creatine has on athletic performance. Danshen Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Danshen might decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Using danshen with guarana might increase the risk of caffeine side effects. Echinachea Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Echinacea might decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Using echinacea with guarana might increase the risk of caffeine side effects. Ephedra Stimulants speed up the nervous system. Caffeine (contained in guarana) and ephedra are both stimulants. Taking guarana along with ephedra might cause too much stimulation and serious side effects and heart problems. Genistein-containing herbs and supplements Guarana contains genistein. Genistein might decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Taking guarana with caffeine might increase caffeine levels and side effects. Examples of supplements that contain genistein include cumin, dyer's broom, kudzu, red clover, and soy. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Guarana might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng. Kudzu Guarana contains caffeine. The body breaks down caffeine to get rid of it. Kudzu might decrease how quickly the body breaks down caffeine. Using kudzu with guarana might increase the risk of caffeine side effects. Magnesium High caffeine intake from foods, beverages, and herbs including guarana increases how much magnesium the body loses in the urine. This might lower magnesium levels. Melatonin Guarana contains caffeine. Taking caffeine along with melatonin can increase melatonin levels. In theory, taking guarana with melatonin might increase melatonin effects and side effects.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000046-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Guarana and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000046-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Guarana ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>