<Document id="0000036" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/700.html">

<Focus>Eucalyptus</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000036-1" qtype="information">What is Eucalyptus ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eucalyptus is a tree. Its leaves and oil have been consumed, chewed, and applied to the skin for many conditions.
 

Eucalyptus contains many different chemicals. These chemicals might have various effects in the body. Also, some research suggests that eucalyptus may have activity against bacteria and fungi. 

People use eucalyptus for many conditions including asthma, bronchitis, flu (influenza), and many others, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000036-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Eucalyptus ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using eucalyptus for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000036-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Eucalyptus and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000036-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Eucalyptus ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000036-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Eucalyptus and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Amphetamines Inhaling eucalyptol, a chemical found in eucalyptus oil, might reduce the levels of amphetamines in the blood. In theory, the effectiveness of amphetamines may be reduced in people who inhale eucalyptol. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 1A2 (CYP1A2) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Eucalyptus might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2C19 (CYP2C19) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Eucalyptus might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2C9 (CYP2C9) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Eucalyptus might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Eucalyptus might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Eucalyptus might lower blood sugar levels. Taking eucalyptus along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Pentobarbital (Nembutal) Inhaling eucalyptol, a chemical found in eucalyptus oil, might reduce the amount of pentobarbital that reaches the brain. In theory, the effectiveness of pentobarbital may be reduced in people who inhale eucalyptol.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000036-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Eucalyptus and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Eucalyptus might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Pyrrolizidine alkaloids (PAs)-containing herbs and supplements Some supplements contain PAs, dangerous chemicals that can harm the liver. Taking eucalyptus along with supplements that contain PAs might increase the chance of developing serious side effects, including liver damage and cancer. Examples of supplements containing PAs include alkanna, butterbur, coltsfoot, comfrey, and groundsel.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000036-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Eucalyptus and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000036-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Eucalyptus ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>