<Document id="0000086" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/332.html">

<Focus>Saccharomyces boulardii</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000086-1" qtype="information">What is Saccharomyces boulardii ?</Question>
			<Answer>Saccharomyces boulardii (S. boulardii) is a type of probiotic ("friendly" organism). It's a yeast that is actually a strain of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. 

"Friendly" organisms such as S. boulardii can help fight off "bad" organisms that might cause diseases. S. boulardii is different from other strains of S. cerevisiae, commonly known as brewer's yeast and baker's yeast. 

People commonly use S. boulardii for treating and preventing diarrhea, including rotaviral diarrhea in children. It's also used for other types of diarrhea, acne, a digestive tract infection that can lead to ulcers, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support many of its other uses. There is also no good evidence to support using S. boulardii for COVID-19. 

Don't confuse S. boulardii with other probiotics, or with fermented food products such as fermented milk, kefir, or yogurt. These are not the same. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000086-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Saccharomyces boulardii ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  SACCHAROMYCES BOULARDII  are as follows: Likely effective for... 

 Diarrhea . Taking S. boulardii by mouth can reduce how long diarrhea lasts in children. It's not clear if it helps children with longer-lasting diarrhea or if it helps adults.,  Possibly effective for... 

 Diarrhea in people taking antibiotics (antibiotic-associated diarrhea) . Taking S. boulardii by mouth can help prevent diarrhea in adults and children being treated with antibiotics.,  

 Infection of the gastrointestinal tract by bacteria called Clostridioides difficile . Taking S. boulardii by mouth seems to help prevent diarrhea from C. difficile infection. Taking it along with antibiotics also seems to help prevent this infection from coming back.,  

 A digestive tract infection that can lead to ulcers (Helicobacter pylori or H. pylori) . Taking S. boulardii by mouth along with standard H. pylori treatment helps prevent side effects such as diarrhea and nausea that occur with standard H. pylori treatment. But it isn't clear if taking S. boulardii helps these standard treatments to work better. ,  

 A serious intestinal disease in premature infants (necrotizing enterocolitis or NEC) . Most research shows that giving S. boulardii by mouth to preterm infants prevents NEC., 

 Diarrhea caused by rotavirus . Taking S. boulardii by mouth seems to reduce how long diarrhea lasts in children with diarrhea caused by rotavirus.,  

 Travelers' diarrhea . Taking S. boulardii by mouth seems to reduce the risk of developing diarrhea while traveling.,  


 
 Possibly ineffective for... 

 Blood infection (sepsis) . Giving S. boulardii to preterm infants by mouth does not prevent sepsis.,  

There is interest in using S. boulardii for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.

</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000086-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Saccharomyces boulardii and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000086-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Saccharomyces boulardii ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000086-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Saccharomyces boulardii and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Minor Be watchful with this combination. Medications for fungal infections (Antifungals) S. boulardii is a fungus. Medications for fungal infections help reduce fungus in and on the body. Taking S. boulardii with medications for fungal infections can reduce the effects of S. boulardii.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000086-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Saccharomyces boulardii and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000086-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Saccharomyces boulardii and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000086-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Saccharomyces boulardii ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>