<Document id="0000386" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007494.htm">
 
<Focus>Back pain - when you see the doctor</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0004604</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000386-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Back pain - when you see the doctor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Questions your provider may ask include: Is your back pain on one side only or both sides?, What does the pain feel like? Is it dull, sharp, throbbing, or burning?, Is this the first time you have had back pain?, When did the pain begin? Did it start suddenly?, Did you have an injury or accident?, What were you doing just before the pain began? For example, were you lifting or bending? Sitting at your computer? Driving a long distance?, If you have had back pain before, is this pain similar or different? In what way is it different?, Do you know what caused your back pain in the past?, How long does each episode of back pain usually last?, Do you feel the pain anywhere else, such as in your hip, thigh, leg or feet?, Do you have any numbness or tingling? Any weakness or loss of function in your leg or elsewhere?, What makes the pain worse? Lifting, twisting, standing, or sitting for long periods?, What makes you feel better? , Does bearing down or straining make your pain worse?,  You will also be asked if you have other symptoms, which may point to a more serious cause. Tell your provider if you have had weight loss, fever, a change in urination or bowel habits, or a history of  cancer . Your provider will perform a physical exam to try to find the exact location of your pain, and determine how it affects your movement. Your back will be pressed on at different spots to find where it hurts. You will also be asked to: Sit, stand, and walk, Walk on your toes and then your heels, Bend forward, backward, and sideways, Lift your legs straight up while lying down, Move your back in certain positions ,  If the pain is worse and goes down your leg when you lift your legs straight up while lying down, you may have sciatica, especially if you also feel numbness or tingling going down the same leg. Your provider will also move your legs into different positions, including bending and straightening your knees. A small rubber hammer is used to check your reflexes and to see if your nerves are working properly. Your provider will touch your skin in many places, using a pin, cotton swab, or feather. This reveals how well you can feel or sense things. Your provider may also scratch the bottom of your feet to see whether you have the right reflexes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000386-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Back pain - when you see the doctor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Questions your provider may ask include: Is your back pain on one side only or both sides?, What does the pain feel like? Is it dull, sharp, throbbing, or burning?, Is this the first time you have had back pain?, When did the pain begin? Did it start suddenly?, Did you have an injury or accident?, What were you doing just before the pain began? For example, were you lifting or bending? Sitting at your computer? Driving a long distance?, If you have had back pain before, is this pain similar or different? In what way is it different?, Do you know what caused your back pain in the past?, How long does each episode of back pain usually last?, Do you feel the pain anywhere else, such as in your hip, thigh, leg or feet?, Do you have any numbness or tingling? Any weakness or loss of function in your leg or elsewhere?, What makes the pain worse? Lifting, twisting, standing, or sitting for long periods?, What makes you feel better? , Does bearing down or straining make your pain worse?,  You will also be asked if you have other symptoms, which may point to a more serious cause. Tell your provider if you have had weight loss, fever, a change in urination or bowel habits, or a history of  cancer . Your provider will perform a physical exam to try to find the exact location of your pain, and determine how it affects your movement. Your back will be pressed on at different spots to find where it hurts. You will also be asked to: Sit, stand, and walk, Walk on your toes and then your heels, Bend forward, backward, and sideways, Lift your legs straight up while lying down, Move your back in certain positions ,  If the pain is worse and goes down your leg when you lift your legs straight up while lying down, you may have sciatica, especially if you also feel numbness or tingling going down the same leg. Your provider will also move your legs into different positions, including bending and straightening your knees. A small rubber hammer is used to check your reflexes and to see if your nerves are working properly. Your provider will touch your skin in many places, using a pin, cotton swab, or feather. This reveals how well you can feel or sense things. Your provider may also scratch the bottom of your feet to see whether you have the right reflexes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>