<Document id="0000906" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003318.htm">
 
<Focus>Coloboma of the iris</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0240063</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T190</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Keyhole pupil</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Iris defect</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000906-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Coloboma of the iris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Coloboma of the iris is a hole or defect of the  iris  of the eye. Most colobomas are present since birth (congenital).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000906-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Coloboma of the iris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Coloboma of the iris can look like a second pupil or a black notch at the edge of the pupil. This gives the pupil an irregular shape. It can also appear as a split in the iris from the pupil to the edge of the iris. A small coloboma (especially if it is not attached to the pupil) may allow a second image to focus on the back of the eye. This may cause:  Blurred vision,  Decreased visual acuity , Double vision, Ghost image ,  If it is congenital, the defect may include the  retina ,  choroid , or optic nerve. Most colobomas are diagnosed at birth or shortly afterward. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000906-3" qtype="causes">What causes Coloboma of the iris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most cases of coloboma have no known cause and are not related to other abnormalities. Some are due to a specific genetic defect. A small number of people with coloboma have other inherited developmental problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000906-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Coloboma of the iris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if: You notice that your child has what appears to be a hole in the iris or an unusual-shaped pupil., Your child's vision becomes blurred or decreased. ,  In addition to your child, you may also need to see an eye specialist (ophthalmologist). </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000906-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Coloboma of the iris ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>