<Document id="0000185" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001578.htm">
 
<Focus>Amelogenesis imperfecta</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002452</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000185-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amelogenesis imperfecta is a tooth development disorder. It causes the tooth enamel to be thin and abnormally formed. Enamel is the outer layer of the coronal, or crown portion of the teeth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000185-2" qtype="causes">What causes Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amelogenesis imperfecta is passed down through families as a  dominant trait . That means you only need to get the abnormal gene from one parent in order to get the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000185-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>The enamel of the tooth is soft and thin. The  teeth appear yellow  and are easily damaged. Both baby teeth and permanent teeth can be affected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000185-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>A dentist can identify and diagnose this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000185-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>The treatment depends on how severe the problem is. Full crowns may be necessary to improve the appearance of the teeth and protect them from further damage. Eating a diet that is low in sugar and practicing very good oral hygiene can reduce the chance of developing cavities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000185-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment is often successful in protecting the teeth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000185-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>The enamel is easily damaged, which affects the appearance of the teeth, especially if left untreated.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000185-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Amelogenesis imperfecta ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your dentist if you have symptoms of this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>