<Document id="0000646" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000886.htm">
 
<Focus>Calorie count - Alcoholic beverages</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Weight loss - calorie count - alcoholic beverages</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Overweight - calorie count - alcoholic beverages</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Obesity - calorie count - alcoholic beverages</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000646-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Calorie count - Alcoholic beverages</Question>
			<Answer>Alcoholic beverages, like many other drinks, contain calories that can add up quickly. Going out for a couple of drinks can add 500 calories, or more, to your daily intake. Most alcoholic drinks have little to no nutritional value. Watching how much you drink can help you lose weight or maintain a healthy weight. Cocktails mixed with soda, juice, cream, or ice cream can have especially high calorie counts. If you find you are having trouble  cutting back on alcohol , talk with your health care provider.  Here is a list of some popular alcoholic beverages, their serving sizes, and the number of calories in each. Calorie count - alcoholic beverages BEVERAGE SERVING SIZE CALORIES Beer 
 
 Beer (light) 12 oz (355 ml)  103 Beer (regular) 12 oz (355 ml)  153 Beer (higher alcohol, craft beers) 12 oz (355 ml)  170 to 350 Distilled Alcohol 
 
 Gin (80 proof) 1.5 oz (45 ml) 97 Gin (94 proof) 1.5 oz (45 ml) 116 Rum (80 proof) 1.5 oz (45 ml) 97 Rum (94 proof) 1.5 oz (45 ml) 116 Vodka (80 proof) 1.5 oz (45 ml) 97 Vodka (94 proof) 1.5 oz (45 ml) 116 Whiskey (80 proof) 1.5 oz (45 ml) 97 Whiskey (94 proof) 1.5 oz (45 ml) 116 Liqueurs 
 
 Coffee liqueur 1.5 oz (45 ml) 160 Coffee liqueur with cream 1.5 oz (45 ml) 154 Cr&#232;me de menthe 1.5 oz (45 ml) 186 Mixed Drinks 
 
 Bloody Mary 4.6 oz (136 ml)  120 Chocolate martini 2.5 oz (74 ml) 418 Cosmopolitan 2.75 oz (81 ml) 146 Daiquiri 2.7 oz (80 ml)  137 Highball 8 oz (235 ml) 110 Hot buttered rum 8 oz (235 ml) 292 Mai Tai 4.9 oz (145 ml) 306 Margarita 4 oz (120 ml) 168 Mimosa 4 oz (120 ml) 75 Mint Julep 4.5 oz (135 ml) 165 Mojito 6 oz (177 ml) 143 Pina colada 6.8 oz (200 ml) 526 Rum and Coke 8 oz (235 ml)  185 Rum and Diet Coke 8 oz (235 ml) 100 Tequila sunrise 6.8 oz (200 ml) 232 Vodka and tonic 7 oz (207 ml) 189 Whiskey sour 3 oz (89 ml) 125 White Russian 8 oz (235 ml) 568 Wine 
 
 White table wine 5 oz (145 ml) 128 Gewurztraminer 5 oz (145 ml) 128 Muscat 5 oz (145 ml) 129 Riesling 5 oz (145 ml) 129 Chenin Blanc 5 oz (145 ml) 129 Chardonnay 5 oz (145 ml) 128 Sauvignon Blanc 5 oz (145 ml) 128 Fume Blanc 5 oz (145 ml) 128 Pinot Grigio 5 oz (145 ml) 128 Dry dessert wine 3.5 oz (90 ml) 157 Red table wine 5 oz (145 ml)  125 Petite Sirah 5 oz (145 ml) 125 Merlot 5 oz (145 ml) 122 Cabernet Sauvignon 5 oz (145 ml) 122 Red Zinfandel 5 oz (145 ml)  129 Burgundy 5 oz (145 ml) 122 Pinot Noir 5 oz (145 ml) 121 Claret 5 oz (145 ml) 122 Syrah 5 oz (145 ml) 122 Red dessert wine 3.5 oz (90 ml) 165</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>