<Document id="0000584" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000001.htm">
 
<Focus>Broken bone</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0016658</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bone - broken</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fracture</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Stress fracture</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bone fracture</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000584-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Broken bone ?</Question>
			<Answer>If more pressure is put on a bone than it can stand, it will split or break. A break of any size is called a fracture. If the broken bone punctures the skin, it is called an open fracture (compound fracture). A stress fracture is a break in the bone that develops because of repeated or prolonged forces against the bone. The repeated stress weakens the bone until it finally breaks.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000584-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Broken bone ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is hard to tell a  dislocated joint  from a broken bone. However, both are emergency situations, and the basic first aid steps are the same.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000584-3" qtype="causes">What causes Broken bone ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following are common causes of broken bones: Fall from a height, Trauma, Motor vehicle accidents, Direct blow,  Child abuse , Repetitive forces, such as those caused by running, can cause stress fractures of the foot, ankle, tibia, or hip , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000584-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Broken bone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of a broken bone include: A visibly out-of-place or misshapen limb or joint, Swelling, bruising, or bleeding, Intense pain, Numbness and tingling, Broken skin with bone protruding, Limited mobility or inability to move a limb or put weight on the leg, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000584-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Broken bone ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is hard to tell a  dislocated joint  from a broken bone. However, both are emergency situations, and the basic first aid steps are the same.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000584-6" qtype="considerations">What to do for Broken bone ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is hard to tell a  dislocated joint  from a broken bone. However, both are emergency situations, and the basic first aid steps are the same.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000584-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Broken bone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911 or the local emergency number if: The person is not responding or is losing consciousness., There is a suspected broken bone in the head, neck, or back., There is a suspected broken bone in the hip, pelvis, or upper leg., You cannot completely immobilize the injury at the scene by yourself., There is severe bleeding., An area below the injured joint is pale, cold, clammy, or blue., There is a bone projecting through the skin. ,  Even though other broken bones may not be medical emergencies, they still deserve medical attention. Contact your health care provider to find out where and when to be seen. If a young child refuses to put weight on an arm or leg after an accident, won't move the arm or leg, or you can clearly see a deformity, assume the child has a broken bone and get medical help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000584-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Broken bone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Take the following steps to reduce your risk of a broken bone: Wear protective gear while skiing, biking, roller blading, and participating in contact sports. This includes using a helmet, elbow pads, knee pads, wrist guards,&#160;and shin pads., Create a safe home for young children. Place a gate at stairways and keep windows closed., Teach children how to be safe and look out for themselves., Supervise children carefully. There is no substitute for supervision, no matter how safe the environment or situation appears to be., Prevent falls by not standing on chairs, counter tops, or other unstable objects. Remove throw rugs and electrical cords from floor surfaces. Use handrails on staircases and non-skid mats in bathtubs. These steps are especially important for older people. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>