<Document id="0000131" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003212.htm">
 
<Focus>Agitation</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085631</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Restlessness</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000131-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Agitation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Agitation is an unpleasant state of extreme arousal. An agitated person may feel stirred up, excited, tense, confused, or irritable.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000131-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Agitation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Agitation can come on suddenly or over time. It can last for a few minutes, for weeks, or even months. Pain, stress, and  fever  can all increase agitation. Agitation by itself may not be a sign of a health problem. But if other symptoms occur, it can be a sign of disease. Agitation with a change in alertness (altered consciousness) can be a sign of  delirium . Delirium has a medical cause and should be checked by a health care provider right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000131-3" qtype="causes">What causes Agitation ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are many causes of agitation. Some of them are: Alcohol intoxication or  withdrawal , Allergic reaction, Caffeine intoxication, Certain forms of heart, lung, liver, or kidney disease, Intoxication or withdrawal from drugs of abuse (such as cocaine, marijuana, hallucinogens, PCP, or opiods), Hospitalization (older adults often have delirium while in the hospital), 
   Overactive thyroid gland ( hyperthyroidism ), Infection (especially in elderly people),  Nicotine withdrawal , Poisoning (for example, carbon monoxide poisoning), Some medicines, including theophylline, amphetamines, and steroids, Trauma,  Vitamin B6  deficiency ,  Agitation can occur with brain and mental health disorders, such as: Anxiety, Dementia (such as  Alzheimer disease ),  Depression , Mania,  Schizophrenia , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000131-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Agitation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Agitation can come on suddenly or over time. It can last for a few minutes, for weeks, or even months. Pain, stress, and  fever  can all increase agitation. Agitation by itself may not be a sign of a health problem. But if other symptoms occur, it can be a sign of disease. Agitation with a change in alertness (altered consciousness) can be a sign of  delirium . Delirium has a medical cause and should be checked by a health care provider right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000131-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Agitation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for agitation that: Lasts a long time, Is very severe, Occurs with thoughts or actions of hurting yourself or others, Occurs with other, unexplained symptoms,  If you are thinking about hurting yourself or others, call or text 988 or chat  988lifeline.org . You can also call 1-800-273-8255 (1-800-273-TALK). The 988 Suicide and Crisis Lifeline provides free and confidential support 24/7, anytime day or night. You can also call 911 or the local emergency number or go to the hospital emergency room. DO NOT delay. If someone you know has attempted suicide, call 911 or the local emergency number right away. DO NOT leave the person alone, even after you have called for help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000131-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Agitation ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>