<Document id="0000005" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001662.htm">
 
<Focus>Aase syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265265</CUI>
			<CUI>C2676137</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Aase-Smith syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hypoplastic anemia - triphalangeal thumbs, Aase-Smith type</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000005-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Aase syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Aase syndrome is a rare disorder that involves  anemia  and certain joint and skeletal deformities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000005-2" qtype="causes">What causes Aase syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many cases of Aase syndrome occur without a known reason and are not passed down through families (inherited). However, some cases (45%) have been shown to be inherited. These are due to a change in 1 of 20 genes important for making protein correctly (the genes make ribosomal proteins). This condition is similar to Diamond-Blackfan anemia, and the two conditions should considered the same. A missing piece on chromosome 19 is found in some people with Diamond-Blackfan anemia. The anemia in Aase syndrome is caused by poor development of the bone marrow, which is where blood cells are formed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000005-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Aase syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Absent or small knuckles,  Cleft palate , Deformed ears, Droopy eyelids, Inability to fully extend the joints from birth, Narrow shoulders,  Pale skin , Triple-jointed thumbs, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000005-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Aase syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical exam. Tests that may be done include: Bone marrow biopsy ,  Complete blood count  (CBC),  Echocardiogram , X-rays, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000005-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Aase syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment may involve blood transfusions in the first year of life to treat anemia.  A steroid medicine called prednisone has also been used to treat anemia associated with Aase syndrome. However, it should only be used after reviewing the benefits and risks with a provider who has experience treating anemias. A  bone marrow transplant  may be necessary if other treatment fails.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000005-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Aase syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The anemia tends to improve with age.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000005-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Aase syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications related to anemia include: Fatigue, Decreased oxygen in the blood, Weakness ,  Heart problems can lead to a variety of complications, depending on the specific defect. Severe cases of Aase syndrome have been associated with  stillbirth  or early death.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000005-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Aase syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling is recommended if you have a family history of this syndrome and wish to become pregnant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>