<Document id="0000322" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001483.htm">
 
<Focus>Asherman syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0156372</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Uterine synechiae, Intrauterine adhesions</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000322-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Asherman syndrome is the formation of scar tissue in the uterine cavity. The problem most often develops after uterine surgery. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000322-2" qtype="causes">What causes Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Asherman syndrome is a rare condition. In most cases, it occurs in women who have had several  dilatation and curettage  (D&amp;C) procedures. A severe pelvic infection unrelated to surgery may also lead to Asherman syndrome. Adhesions in the uterine cavity can also form after infection with tuberculosis or schistosomiasis. These infections are rare in the United States. Uterine complications related to these infections are even less common.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000322-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The adhesions may cause: Amenorrhea  (lack of menstrual periods), Repeated miscarriages, Infertility,  However, such symptoms could be related to several conditions. They are more likely to indicate Asherman syndrome if they occur suddenly after a D&amp;C or other uterine surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000322-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>A pelvic exam does not reveal problems in most cases.  Tests may include: Hysterosalpingography, Hysterosonogram,  Transvaginal ultrasound examination , Blood tests to detect tuberculosis or schistosomiasis, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000322-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment involves surgery to cut and remove the adhesions or scar tissue. This can most often be done with hysteroscopy. This uses small instruments and a camera placed into the uterus through the cervix. After scar tissue is removed, the uterine cavity must be kept open while it heals to prevent adhesions from returning. Your health care provider may place a small balloon inside the uterus for several days. You may also need to take estrogen while the uterine lining heals. You may need to take antibiotics if there is an infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000322-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The stress of illness can often be helped by joining a support group. In such groups, members share common experiences and problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000322-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Asherman syndrome can often be cured with surgery. Sometimes more than one procedure will be necessary. Women who are infertile because of Asherman syndrome may be able to have a baby after treatment. Successful pregnancy depends on the severity of Asherman syndrome and the difficulty of the treatment. Other factors that affect fertility and pregnancy may also be involved.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000322-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications of hysteroscopic surgery are uncommon. When they occur, they may include bleeding, perforation of the uterus, and pelvic infection. In some cases, treatment of Asherman syndrome will not cure infertility.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000322-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if: Your menstrual periods do not return after a gynecologic or obstetrical surgery., You cannot get pregnant after 6 to 12 months of trying (See a specialist for an infertility evaluation). , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000322-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Asherman syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most cases of Asherman syndrome cannot be predicted or prevented.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>