<Document id="0000134" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001664.htm">
 
<Focus>Aicardi syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0175713</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000134-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Aicardi syndrome is a rare disorder. In this condition, the structure that connects the two sides of the brain (called the corpus callosum) is partly or completely missing. Nearly all known cases occur in people with no history of the disorder in their family (sporadic).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000134-2" qtype="causes">What causes Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause of Aicardi syndrome is unknown at this time. In some cases, experts believe it may be a result of a gene defect on the  X chromosome . The disorder affects only girls.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000134-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms most often start when the child is between ages 3 and 5 months. The condition causes jerking (infantile spasms), a type of childhood seizure. Aicardi syndrome may occur with other brain defects. Other symptoms may include: Coloboma  (cat's eye),  Intellectual disability , Smaller-than-normal eyes (microphthalmia) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000134-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children are diagnosed with Aicardi syndrome if they meet the following criteria: Corpus callosum that is partly or completely missing, Female sex,  Seizures  (typically beginning as infantile spasms), Sores on the retina (retinal lesions) or optic nerve ,  In rare cases, one of these features may be missing (especially lack of development of the corpus callosum). Tests to diagnose Aicardi syndrome include: CT scan of the head ,  EEG , Eye exam,  MRI ,  Other procedures and tests may be done, depending on the person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000134-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment is done to help prevent symptoms. It involves managing seizures and any other health concerns. Treatment uses programs to help the family and child cope with delays in development.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000134-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Aicardi Syndrome Foundation --  ouraicardilife.org National Organization for Rare Disorders (NORD) --  rarediseases.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000134-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook depends on how severe the symptoms are and what other health conditions are present. Nearly all children with this syndrome have severe learning difficulties and remain completely dependent on others. However, a few have some language abilities and some can walk on their own or with support. Vision varies from normal to blind.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000134-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications depend on the severity of symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000134-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Aicardi syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if your child has symptoms of Aicardi syndrome. Seek emergency care if the infant is having spasms or a seizure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>