<Document id="0000599" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007213.htm">
 
<Focus>Bruise</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3812660</CUI>
			<CUI>C0009938</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Contusion</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hematoma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000599-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Bruise ?</Question>
			<Answer>A bruise is an area of skin discoloration. A bruise occurs when small blood vessels break and leak their contents into the soft tissue beneath the skin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000599-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Bruise ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are three types of bruises: Subcutaneous -- beneath the skin, Intramuscular -- within the belly of the underlying muscle, Periosteal -- bone bruise,  Bruises can last from days to months. A bone bruise is the most severe and painful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000599-3" qtype="causes">What causes Bruise ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bruises are often caused by falls, sports injuries, car accidents, or blows received from other people or objects. If you take a blood thinner, such as aspirin, warfarin (Coumadin, Jantoven), dabigatran (Pradaxa), rivaroxaban (Xarelto), apixaban (Eliquis), or clopidogrel (Plavix), you are likely to bruise more easily.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000599-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Bruise ?</Question>
			<Answer>Main symptoms are pain, swelling, and skin discoloration. The bruise begins as a pinkish red color that can be very tender to touch. It is often difficult to use the muscle that has been bruised. For example, a deep thigh bruise is painful when you walk or run. Eventually, the bruise changes to a bluish color, then greenish-yellow, and finally returns to the normal skin color as it heals.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000599-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Bruise ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are three types of bruises: Subcutaneous -- beneath the skin, Intramuscular -- within the belly of the underlying muscle, Periosteal -- bone bruise,  Bruises can last from days to months. A bone bruise is the most severe and painful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000599-6" qtype="considerations">What to do for Bruise ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are three types of bruises: Subcutaneous -- beneath the skin, Intramuscular -- within the belly of the underlying muscle, Periosteal -- bone bruise,  Bruises can last from days to months. A bone bruise is the most severe and painful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000599-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Bruise ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider right away if you feel extreme pressure in a bruised part of your body, especially if the area is large or very painful. This may be due to compartment syndrome, and can be life-threatening. You should receive emergency care. Also contact your provider if: You are bruising without any injury, fall, or other reason., There are signs of infection around the bruised area including streaks of redness, pus or other drainage, or fever., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000599-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Bruise ?</Question>
			<Answer>Because bruises are usually the direct result of an injury, the following are important safety recommendations: 
   Teach children how to be safe., Be mindful to avoid falls around the house. For example, be careful when climbing on ladders or other objects. Avoid standing or kneeling on counter tops., Wear seat belts in motor vehicles., Wear proper sports equipment to pad those areas most frequently bruised, such as thigh pads, hip guards, and elbow pads in football and hockey. Wear shin guards and knee pads in soccer and basketball., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>