<Document id="0000656" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001276.htm">
 
<Focus>Cancer - penis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0006826</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Penile cancer</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Squamous cell cancer - penis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000656-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Penile cancer is  cancer  that starts in the  penis , an organ that makes up part of the male reproductive system. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000656-2" qtype="causes">What causes Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cancer of the penis is rare. Its exact cause is unknown. However, certain risk factors include: Uncircumcised men who don't keep the area under the foreskin clean. This leads to buildup of smegma, a cheese-like, foul-smelling substance under the foreskin., History of  genital warts , or human papillomavirus (HPV)., Smoking., Injury to the penis. ,  The cancer usually affects middle age and older men.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000656-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Early symptoms may include: Sore, bump, rash, or swelling at the tip or on the shaft of the penis, Foul-smelling discharge beneath the foreskin,  As the cancer advances, symptoms may include: Pain and bleeding from the penis (may occur with advanced disease), Lumps in the groin area from spread of the cancer to the groin lymph nodes, Weight loss, Difficulty in passing urine, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000656-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask about your health history and symptoms. A  biopsy  of the growth is needed to determine if it is cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000656-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the size and location of the tumor and how much it has spread. Treatment for penile cancer may include: Chemotherapy -- uses medicines to kill cancer cells, Radiation -- uses high-powered x-rays to kill cancer cells, Surgery - cuts out and removes the cancer ,  If the tumor is small or near the tip of the penis, surgery may be done to remove only the cancerous part of the penis where the cancer is found. Depending on the exact location, this is called a glansectomy or partial penectomy. Laser surgery may be used to treat some tumors. For more severe tumors, total removal of the penis (total penectomy) is often needed. A new opening will be created in the groin area to allow urine to exit the body. This procedure is called a urethrostomy. Chemotherapy  may be used along with surgery. &#160; Radiation therapy  may be used along with surgery. A type of radiation therapy called external beam therapy is often used. This method delivers radiation to the penis from outside the body. This therapy is most often performed 5 days a week for 6 to 8 weeks.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000656-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000656-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome can be good with early diagnosis and treatment. Urination and sexual function can often be maintained.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000656-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Untreated, penile cancer can spread to other parts of the body ( metastasize ) early in the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000656-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if symptoms of penile cancer develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000656-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Cancer - penis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Circumcision may decrease the risk. Men who are not circumcised should be taught at an early age the importance of cleaning beneath the foreskin as part of their personal hygiene. Safer sexual practices , such as abstinence, limiting the number of sexual partners, and using condoms to prevent HPV infection, may decrease the risk of developing cancer of the penis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>