<Document id="0000850" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000781.htm">
 
<Focus>Chronic subdural hematoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0749095</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Subdural hemorrhage - chronic</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Subdural hematoma - chronic</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Subdural hygroma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000850-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>A chronic subdural hematoma is an "old" collection of blood and blood breakdown products between the surface of the brain and its outermost covering (the dura). The chronic phase of a  subdural hematoma  begins several weeks after the first bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000850-2" qtype="causes">What causes Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>A subdural hematoma develops when bridging veins tear and leak blood. These are the tiny veins that run between the dura and surface of the brain. This is usually the result of a head injury. A collection of blood then forms over the surface of the brain. In a  chronic  subdural collection, blood leaks from the veins slowly over time, or a fast hemorrhage is left to clear up on its own. A subdural hematoma is more common in older adults because of normal brain shrinkage that occurs with aging. This shrinkage stretches and weakens the bridging veins. These veins are more likely to break in older adults, even after a minor head injury. You or your family may not remember any injury that might have caused a subdural hematoma. Risks include: Long-term heavy alcohol use, Long-term use of aspirin, anti-inflammatory drugs such as ibuprofen, or blood thinning (anticoagulant) medicine such as warfarin, Diseases that lead to reduced blood clotting, Head injury, Old age, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000850-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>In some cases, there may be no symptoms. However, depending on the size of the hematoma and where it presses on the brain, any of the following symptoms may occur:  Confusion or coma , Decreased memory, Problem speaking or swallowing, Trouble walking, Drowsiness, Headache,  Seizures , Weakness or numbness of arms, legs, face , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000850-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will ask about your medical history. The physical exam will include a careful check of your brain and nervous system for problems with: Balance, Coordination, Mental functions, Sensation, Strength, Walking ,  If there is any suspicion of a hematoma, an imaging test, such as a  CT  or  MRI , scan will be done.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000850-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goal of treatment is to control symptoms and reduce or prevent permanent damage to the brain. Medicines may be used to control or prevent seizures. Surgery may be needed. This may include drilling small holes in the skull to relieve pressure and allow blood and fluids to be drained. Large hematomas or solid  blood clots  may need to be removed through a larger opening in the skull ( craniotomy ). Hematomas that do not cause symptoms may not require treatment. Chronic subdural hematomas often come back after being drained. Therefore, it is sometimes better to leave them alone unless they are causing symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000850-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic subdural hematomas that cause symptoms usually do not heal on their own over time. They often require surgery, especially when there are neurologic problems, seizures, or chronic headaches.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000850-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Permanent brain damage, Persistent symptoms, such as  anxiety , confusion, difficulty paying attention,  dizziness ,  headache , and memory loss, Seizures , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000850-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider right away if you or a family member has symptoms of chronic subdural hematoma. For example, if you see symptoms of confusion, weakness, or numbness weeks or months after a head injury in an older adult, contact the provider right away. Take the person to the emergency room or call 911 or the local emergency number if the person: Has  convulsions  (seizures), Is not alert ( loses consciousness ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000850-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Chronic subdural hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Avoid head injuries by using seat belts, bicycle and motorcycle helmets, and hard hats when appropriate.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>