<Document id="0000446" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007309.htm">
 
<Focus>Bilirubin encephalopathy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022610</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bilirubin-induced neurologic dysfunction (BIND)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Kernicterus</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000446-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bilirubin encephalopathy is a rare neurological condition that occurs in some  newborns with severe jaundice .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000446-2" qtype="causes">What causes Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bilirubin encephalopathy (BE) is caused by very high levels of bilirubin. Bilirubin is a yellow pigment that is created as the body gets rid of old red blood cells. High levels of bilirubin in the body can cause the skin to look yellow (jaundice). If the level of bilirubin is very high or a baby is very ill, the substance will move out of the blood and collect in the brain tissue if it is not bound to albumin (protein) in the blood. This can lead to problems such as brain damage and hearing loss. The term "kernicterus" refers to the yellow staining caused by bilirubin. This is seen in parts of the brain on autopsy. This condition most often develops in the first week of life, but may be seen up until the third week. Some newborns with  Rh hemolytic disease  are at high risk for severe jaundice that can lead to this condition. Rarely, BE can develop in seemingly healthy babies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000446-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>The symptoms depend on the stage of BE. Not all babies with kernicterus on autopsy have had definite symptoms. Early stage: Extreme jaundice, Absent startle reflex, Poor feeding or sucking, Extreme sleepiness (lethargy) and low muscle tone (hypotonia),  Middle stage: High-pitched cry, Irritability, May have arched back with neck hyperextended backwards, high muscle tone (hypertonia), Poor feeding,  Late stage: Stupor or coma, No feeding, Shrill cry, Muscle rigidity, markedly arched back with neck hyperextended backwards, Seizures, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000446-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>A blood test will show a high bilirubin level (greater than 20 to 25 mg/dL). However, there is not a direct link between bilirubin level and degree of injury.  Normal value ranges may vary slightly among different laboratories. Talk to your health care provider about the meaning of your specific test results.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000446-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on how old the baby is (in hours) and whether the baby has any risk factors (such as prematurity). It may include: Light therapy (phototherapy), Exchange transfusions (removing the child's blood and replacing it with fresh donor blood or plasma), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000446-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>BE&#160;is a serious condition. Many infants with late-stage nervous system complications die.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000446-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Permanent brain damage, Hearing loss, Death , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000446-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Get medical help right away if your baby has signs of this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000446-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Bilirubin encephalopathy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treating jaundice or conditions that may lead to it can help prevent this problem. Infants with the first signs of jaundice have bilirubin level measured within 24 hours. If the level is high, the infant should be screened for diseases that involve the destruction of red blood cells (hemolysis). All newborns have a follow-up appointment within 2 to 3 days after leaving the hospital. This is very important for late preterm or early term babies (born more than 2 to 3 weeks before their due date).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>