<Document id="0000080" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007656.htm">
 
<Focus>Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0023467</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Acute myelogenous leukemia - children</Synonym>
		<Synonym>AML</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute myeloid leukemia - children</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute granulocytic leukemia - children</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute myeloblastic leukemia - children</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Acute non-lymphocytic leukemia (ANLL) - children</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000080-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acute myeloid leukemia is a cancer of the white blood cells within the blood and bone marrow. Bone marrow is the soft tissue inside bones that generates all blood components including white blood cells. "Acute" means the cancer develops quickly and "myeloid" is the type of white cells that become cancerous. Both  adults  and children can get acute myeloid leukemia (AML). This article is about AML in children.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000080-2" qtype="causes">What causes Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>In children, AML is rare. AML involves cells in the bone marrow that usually become white blood cells. These leukemia cells build up in the bone marrow and blood, leaving no space for healthy red and white blood cells and  platelets  to form. Because there are not enough healthy cells to do their jobs, children with AML are more likely to have: Anemia  (low level of red blood cells), Increased risk for bleeding and bruising, Infections ,  Most of the time, what causes AML is unknown. In children, some things can increase the risk of developing AML: Exposure to alcohol or tobacco smoke before birth, A history of certain diseases, such as  aplastic anemia , Certain genetic disorders, such as  Down syndrome ,&#160; neurofibromatosis , and other rare syndromes, Previous use of certain chemotherapy drugs such as cyclophosphamide, Past treatment with radiation therapy ,  Having one or more risk factor does not mean your child will develop cancer. Most children who develop AML have no known risk factors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000080-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of AML include: Feeling weak or tired, Bone or joint pain, Frequent infections, Easy bleeding or bruising, Fever with or without an infection, Night sweats, Painless lumps in the neck, armpits, stomach, groin, or other parts of the body that may be blue or purple, Pinpoint spots (petechiae) under the skin caused by bleeding, Shortness of breath, Loss of appetite and eating less food, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000080-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform the following exams and tests: Physical exam and health history,  Complete blood count (CBC)  and other blood tests, Blood chemistry study, Chest x-ray, Biopsies of the  bone marrow , or  lymph node , A test to look for changes in the chromosomes in blood or bone marrow,  Other tests may be done to determine the specific type of AML.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000080-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for children with AML may include: Anticancer drugs ( chemotherapy ), Certain types of targeted therapy,  Bone marrow transplant  is used if the leukemia returns after treatment or doesn't respond well to initial therapy with chemotherapy. The process uses high doses of chemotherapy and sometimes radiation therapy and transfusion of bone marrow from a compatible donor. Supportive care includes red blood cell and platelets (cells that help to stop bleeding) transfusions. Your child's treatment team will explain the different options to you. You will want to take notes. Be sure to ask questions if you don't understand something.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000080-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>Having a child with cancer can make you feel very alone. In a cancer support group, you can find people who are going through the same things you are. They can help you cope with your feelings. They can also help you find help or solutions for problems. Ask your health care team or staff at the cancer center to help you find a support group.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000080-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cancer can come back at any time. But for most children, AML doesn't come back after being gone for 5 years. However, there is a wide range in outcomes for different subtypes of AML, and the disease might return.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000080-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>The leukemia cells can affect various organs in the body including: Brain, Kidneys, Lungs, Skin, Intestines,  As a result of the treatment, it's common to experience: Fatigue, Hair loss, Weight loss, Mouth sores, Need for transfusions, Infections requiring hospitalization, Severe organ damage (very rarely), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000080-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment right away if your child develops these symptoms: Persistent fever, Easy bruising, Shortness of breath, Viral infection that doesn't resolve, Prolonged fatigue, Any other symptoms of AML, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000080-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Acute myelogenous leukemia (AML) - children ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many childhood cancers can't be prevented. Most children who develop leukemia have no risk factors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>