<Document id="0000622" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001089.htm">
 
<Focus>Byssinosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0006542</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cotton worker's lung</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cotton bract disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mill fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brown lung disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000622-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Byssinosis is a disease of the lungs. It is caused by breathing in (inhaling) cotton dust or dusts from other vegetable fibers such as flax, hemp, or sisal while at work.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000622-2" qtype="causes">What causes Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Inhaling the dust produced by raw cotton can cause byssinosis. It is most common in people who work in the textile industry. Those who are sensitive to the dust can have an  asthma-like condition  after being exposed. Methods of prevention in the United States have reduced the number of cases. Byssinosis is still common in developing countries. Smoking increases risk&#160;of developing this disease. Being exposed to the dust many times can lead to&#160;long-term (chronic) lung disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000622-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include any of the following: Chest tightness,  Cough ,  Wheezing , Shortness of breath,  Symptoms are worse at the beginning of the work week and improve later in the week. Symptoms are also less severe when the person is away from the workplace.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000622-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will take your medical history. You'll be asked if your symptoms relate to certain exposures or times of exposure. Your provider will also do a physical exam, paying special attention to the lungs. Tests that may be ordered include: Chest x-ray ,  Chest CT scan ,  Lung function tests , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000622-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The most important treatment is to stop being exposed to the dust. Reducing dust levels in the factory (by improving machinery or ventilation) will help prevent byssinosis. Some people may have to change jobs to avoid further exposure. Medicines used for asthma, such as bronchodilators, usually improve symptoms. Corticosteroid medicines may be prescribed in more severe cases. Stopping smoking is very important for people with this condition. Breathing treatments, including  nebulizers , may be prescribed if the condition becomes long-term. Home oxygen therapy may be needed if blood oxygen level is low. People with a long-term (chronic) lung disease can be helped with: Physical exercise programs, Breathing exercises, Patient education programs, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000622-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Stopping exposure to the dust often improves symptoms. Continued exposure can lead to reduced lung function. In the United States, worker's compensation may be available to people with byssinosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000622-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic bronchitis  may develop. This is swelling (inflammation) of the large airways of the lungs with a large amount of phlegm production. Continued exposure can lead to end-stage lung disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000622-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you: Have symptoms of byssinosis and know you have been exposed to cotton or other fibers, Think you have been exposed to cotton or other fiber dust at work and you have breathing problems,  Having byssinosis makes it easier for you to develop lung infections. So if you've been diagnosed with byssinosis, contact your provider right away if you develop: A cough, Shortness of breath, Fever, Other signs of a lung infection, Symptoms of the flu or COVID-19,  Since your lungs are already damaged, it's important to have the infection treated right away. This will prevent breathing problems from becoming severe. It will also prevent further damage to your lungs. Talk to your provider about getting the flu, pneumonia, and other recommended vaccines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000622-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Byssinosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Controlling dust, using face masks, and other measures can reduce the risk. Stop smoking, especially if you work in textile manufacturing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>