<Document id="0000060" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000778.htm">
 
<Focus>Acoustic neuroma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0027859</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Vestibular schwannoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tumor - acoustic</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cerebellopontine angle tumor</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Angle tumor</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000060-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Acoustic neuroma ?</Question>
			<Answer>An acoustic neuroma is a slow-growing tumor of the nerve that connects the ear to the brain. This nerve is called the vestibular cochlear nerve. It is behind the ear, right under the brain. An acoustic neuroma is a benign tumor. This means that it does not spread to other parts of the body. However, it can damage several important nerves as it grows.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000060-2" qtype="causes">What causes Acoustic neuroma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acoustic neuromas have been linked with the genetic disorder  neurofibromatosis type 2  (NF2). Acoustic neuromas are uncommon.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000060-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Acoustic neuroma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The symptoms vary, based on the size and location of the tumor. Because the tumor grows so slowly, symptoms most often start after age 30. Common symptoms include: 
   Abnormal feeling of movement ( vertigo )
   ,  Hearing loss  in the affected ear that makes it hard to hear conversations
   , 
   Ringing ( tinnitus ) in the affected ear
   ,  Less common symptoms include: Difficulty understanding speech,  Dizziness , Headache,  Loss of balance ,  Numbness  in the face or&#160;one ear,  Pain in the face  or one ear, Weakness of the face or facial asymmetry, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000060-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Acoustic neuroma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider may suspect an acoustic neuroma based on your medical history, an exam of your nervous system, or tests. Often, the physical exam is normal when the tumor is diagnosed. Sometimes, the following signs may be present: Decreased feeling on&#160;one side of the face,  Drooping  on&#160;one side of the face,  Unsteady walk ,  The most useful test to identify an acoustic neuroma is an  MRI of the brain . Other tests to diagnose the tumor and tell it apart from other causes of dizziness or vertigo include: Hearing test, Test of equilibrium and balance ( electronystagmography ), Test of hearing and brainstem function (brainstem auditory evoked response), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000060-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Acoustic neuroma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the size and location of the tumor, your age, and your overall health. You and your provider must decide whether to watch the tumor without treatment, use radiation treatment to stop it from growing, or try to remove it. Many acoustic neuromas are small and grow very slowly. Small tumors with few or no symptoms may be watched for changes, especially in older people. Regular MRI scans will be done. If not treated, some acoustic neuromas can: Damage the nerves involved in hearing and balance, Place pressure on nearby brain tissue, Harm the nerves responsible for movement and feeling in the face, Lead to a buildup of fluid ( hydrocephalus ) in the brain (with very large tumors),  Removing an acoustic neuroma is more commonly done for: Larger tumors, Tumors that are causing symptoms, Tumors that are growing quickly, Tumors that are pressing on the brain ,  Surgery or a type of radiation treatment is done to remove the tumor and prevent other nerve damage. Depending on the type of surgery performed, hearing can sometimes be preserved. The surgical technique to remove an acoustic neuroma is called microsurgery. A special microscope and small, precise instruments are used. This technique offers a higher chance of cure.,  Stereotactic radiosurgery  focuses high-powered x-rays on a small area. It is a form of radiation therapy, not a surgical procedure. It may be used to slow down or stop the growth of tumors that are hard to remove with surgery. It may also be done to treat people who are unable to have surgery, such as older adults or people who are very sick.,  Removing an acoustic neuroma can damage nerves. This may cause loss of hearing or weakness in the face muscles. This damage is more likely to occur when the tumor is large.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000060-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Acoustic neuroma ?</Question>
			<Answer>An acoustic neuroma is not cancer. The tumor does not spread to other parts of the body. However, it may continue to grow and press on structures in the skull. People with small, slow-growing tumors may not need treatment. Hearing loss present before treatment is not likely to return after surgery or radiosurgery.&#160;In cases&#160;of&#160;smaller tumors, hearing loss that occurs after surgery may return. Most people with small tumors will have no permanent weakness of the face after surgery. However, people with large tumors are more likely to have some permanent weakness of the face after surgery. Signs of nerve damage such as loss of hearing or weakness of the face may be delayed after radiosurgery.
 In most cases, brain surgery can completely remove the tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000060-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Acoustic neuroma ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000060-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Acoustic neuroma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have: Hearing loss that is sudden or getting worse, Ringing in&#160;one ear, Dizziness (vertigo), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>