<Document id="0000014" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003274.htm">
 
<Focus>Abdominal mass</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0000734</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mass in the abdomen</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000014-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Abdominal mass ?</Question>
			<Answer>An abdominal mass is swelling in one part of the belly area (abdomen).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000014-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Abdominal mass ?</Question>
			<Answer>An abdominal mass is often found during a routine  physical exam . Most of the time, the mass develops slowly. You may not be able to feel the mass. Locating the mass helps your health care provider make a diagnosis. For example, the abdomen can be divided into four areas: Right-upper quadrant, Left-upper quadrant, Right-lower quadrant, Left-lower quadrant,  Other terms used to describe the location of abdominal pain or masses include: Epigastric -- center of the abdomen just below the rib cage, Periumbilical -- area around the belly button ,  The location of the mass and its firmness, texture, and other qualities can provide clues to its cause.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000014-3" qtype="causes">What causes Abdominal mass ?</Question>
			<Answer>Several conditions can cause an abdominal mass: Abdominal aortic aneurysm  can cause a pulsating mass around the navel.,  Bladder distention  (urinary bladder over-filled with fluid) can cause a firm mass in the center of the lower abdomen above the pelvic bones. In extreme cases, it can reach as far up as the navel.,  Cholecystitis  can cause a very tender mass that is felt below the liver in the right-upper quadrant (occasionally).,  Colon cancer  can cause a mass almost anywhere in the abdomen.,  Crohn disease  or bowel obstruction can cause many tender, sausage-shaped masses anywhere in the abdomen.,  Diverticulitis  can cause a mass that is usually located in the left-lower quadrant., Gallbladder tumor can cause a tender, irregularly shaped mass in the right-upper quadrant.,  Hydronephrosis  (fluid-filled kidney) can cause a smooth, spongy-feeling mass in one or both sides or toward the back (flank area).,  Kidney cancer  can sometimes cause a smooth, firm, but not tender mass in the abdomen.,  Liver cancer  can cause a firm, lumpy mass in the right upper quadrant.,  Liver enlargement  (hepatomegaly) can cause a firm, irregular mass below the right rib cage, or on the left side in the stomach area.,  Neuroblastoma , a cancerous tumor often found in the lower abdomen can cause a mass (this cancer mainly occurs in children and infants).,  Ovarian cyst  can cause a smooth, rounded, rubbery mass above the pelvis in the lower abdomen.,  Pancreatic abscess  can cause a mass in the upper abdomen in the epigastric area.,  Pancreatic pseudocyst  can cause a lumpy mass in the upper abdomen in the epigastric area.,  Spleen enlargement  (splenomegaly) can sometimes be felt in the left-upper quadrant.,  Stomach cancer  can cause a mass in the left-upper abdomen in the stomach area (epigastric) if the  cancer  is large., Uterine  leiomyoma  (fibroids) can cause a round, lumpy mass above the pelvis in the lower abdomen (sometimes can be felt if the fibroids are large).,  Volvulus  can cause a mass anywhere in the abdomen.,  Ureteropelvic junction obstruction  can cause a mass in the lower abdomen. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000014-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Abdominal mass ?</Question>
			<Answer>An abdominal mass is often found during a routine  physical exam . Most of the time, the mass develops slowly. You may not be able to feel the mass. Locating the mass helps your health care provider make a diagnosis. For example, the abdomen can be divided into four areas: Right-upper quadrant, Left-upper quadrant, Right-lower quadrant, Left-lower quadrant,  Other terms used to describe the location of abdominal pain or masses include: Epigastric -- center of the abdomen just below the rib cage, Periumbilical -- area around the belly button ,  The location of the mass and its firmness, texture, and other qualities can provide clues to its cause.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000014-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Abdominal mass ?</Question>
			<Answer>Get medical help right away if you have a pulsating lump in your abdomen along with severe  abdominal pain . This could be a sign of a ruptured aortic aneurysm, which is an emergency condition. Contact your provider if you notice any type of abdominal mass.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000014-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Abdominal mass ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>