<Document id="0000791" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003091.htm">
 
<Focus>Chills</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0085593</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Rigors</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Shivering</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000791-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chills ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chills refers to feeling cold after being in a cold environment. The word can also refer to an episode of shivering along with paleness and feeling cold.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000791-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Chills ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chills (shivering) may occur at the start of an infection. They are most often associated with a  fever . Chills are caused by rapid muscle contraction and relaxation. They are the body's way of producing heat when it feels cold. Chills often predict the coming of a fever or an increase in the body's core temperature. Chills are an important symptom with certain diseases such as  malaria . Chills are common in young children. Children tend to develop higher fevers than adults. Even minor illness can produce high fevers in young children. Infants tend not to develop obvious chills. However, call your health care provider about any fever in an infant 6 months or younger. Also call for fevers in infants 6 months to 1 year unless you are sure of the cause. "Goose bumps" are not the same as chills. Goose bumps occur due to cold air. They can also be caused by strong emotions such as shock or fear. With goose bumps, the hair on the body stick up from the skin to form a layer of insulation. When you have chills, you may or may not have goose bumps.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000791-3" qtype="causes">What causes Chills ?</Question>
			<Answer>Causes may include: Exposure to a cold environment, Viral and bacterial infections , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000791-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Chills ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chills (shivering) may occur at the start of an infection. They are most often associated with a  fever . Chills are caused by rapid muscle contraction and relaxation. They are the body's way of producing heat when it feels cold. Chills often predict the coming of a fever or an increase in the body's core temperature. Chills are an important symptom with certain diseases such as  malaria . Chills are common in young children. Children tend to develop higher fevers than adults. Even minor illness can produce high fevers in young children. Infants tend not to develop obvious chills. However, call your health care provider about any fever in an infant 6 months or younger. Also call for fevers in infants 6 months to 1 year unless you are sure of the cause. "Goose bumps" are not the same as chills. Goose bumps occur due to cold air. They can also be caused by strong emotions such as shock or fear. With goose bumps, the hair on the body stick up from the skin to form a layer of insulation. When you have chills, you may or may not have goose bumps.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000791-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Chills ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call the provider if: Symptoms such as stiffness of the neck,  confusion , irritability, or sluggishness are present., Chills are accompanied by a bad cough, shortness of breath, abdominal pain or burning, or frequent urination., A child younger than 3 months has a temperature of 101&#176;F (38.3&#176;C) or more., A child 3 months to 1 year has a fever that lasts more than 24 hours., The fever remains above 103&#176;F (39.4&#176;C) after 1 to 2 hours of home treatment., The fever does not improve after 3 days, or has lasted more than 5 days., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000791-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Chills ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>