<Document id="0000776" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003079.htm">
 
<Focus>Chest pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0008031</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Chest tightness</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chest pressure</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chest discomfort</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000776-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chest pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chest pain is discomfort or pain that you feel anywhere along the front of your body between your neck and upper abdomen.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000776-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Chest pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many people with chest pain fear a  heart attack . However, there are many possible causes of chest pain. Some causes are not dangerous to your health, while other causes are serious and, in some cases, life threatening. Any organ or tissue in your chest can be the source of pain, including your heart, lungs, esophagus, muscles, ribs, tendons, or nerves. Pain may also spread to the chest from the neck, abdomen, and back.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000776-3" qtype="causes">What causes Chest pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Heart or blood vessel problems that can cause chest pain: Angina  or a heart attack. The most common symptom is chest pain that may feel like tightness, heavy pressure, squeezing, or crushing pain. The pain may spread to the arm, shoulder, jaw, or back., A tear in the wall of the aorta, the large blood vessel that takes blood from the heart to the rest of the body ( aortic dissection ) causes sudden, severe pain in the chest and upper back., Swelling (inflammation) in the sac that surrounds the heart ( pericarditis ) causes pain in the center part of the chest. ,  Lung problems that can cause chest pain: A blood clot in the lung ( pulmonary embolism )., Collapse of the lung ( pneumothorax ).,  Pneumonia  causes a sharp chest pain that often gets worse when you take a deep breath or cough., Swelling of the lining around the lung ( pleurisy ) can cause chest pain that usually feels sharp, and often gets worse when you take a deep breath or cough. ,  Other causes of chest pain: Panic attack , which often occurs with fast breathing., Inflammation where the ribs join the breast bone or sternum ( costochondritis ).,  Shingles , which causes sharp, tingling pain on one side that stretches from the chest to the back, and may cause a rash., Strain of the muscles and tendons between the ribs. ,  Chest pain can also be due to the following digestive system problems: Spasms or narrowing of the esophagus (the tube that carries food from the mouth to the stomach),  Gallstones  cause pain that gets worse after a meal (most often a fatty meal)., Heartburn or  gastroesophageal reflux  (GERD),  Stomach ulcer  or gastritis: Burning pain occurs if your stomach is empty and feels better when you eat food ,  In children, most chest pain is not caused by the heart.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000776-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Chest pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many people with chest pain fear a  heart attack . However, there are many possible causes of chest pain. Some causes are not dangerous to your health, while other causes are serious and, in some cases, life threatening. Any organ or tissue in your chest can be the source of pain, including your heart, lungs, esophagus, muscles, ribs, tendons, or nerves. Pain may also spread to the chest from the neck, abdomen, and back.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000776-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Chest pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911 or the local emergency number if: You have sudden crushing, squeezing, tightening, or pressure in your chest., Pain spreads (radiates) to your jaw, left arm, or between your shoulder blades., You have nausea, dizziness, sweating, a racing heart, or shortness of breath., You know you have angina and your chest discomfort is suddenly more intense, brought on by lighter activity, or lasts longer than usual., Your angina symptoms occur while you are at rest., You have sudden, sharp chest pain with shortness of breath, especially after a long trip, a stretch of bedrest (for example, following an operation), or other lack of movement, especially if one leg is swollen or more swollen than the other (this could be a blood clot, part of which has moved to the lungs)., You have been diagnosed with a serious condition, such as heart attack or pulmonary embolism. ,  Your risk of having a heart attack is greater if: You have a family history of  heart disease ., You smoke, use cocaine, or are overweight., You have  high cholesterol ,  high blood pressure , or  diabetes ., You already have heart disease. ,  Call your provider if: You have a fever or a cough that produces yellow-green phlegm., You have chest pain that is severe and does not go away., You are having problems swallowing., Chest pain lasts longer than 3 to 5 days. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000776-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Chest pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>