<Document id="0000475" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003062.htm">
 
<Focus>Bleeding gums</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0017565</CUI>
			<CUI>C2012701</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Gums - bleeding</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000475-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Bleeding gums ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bleeding gums can be a sign that you have or may develop gum disease. Ongoing gum bleeding may be due to plaque buildup on the teeth. It can also be a sign of a serious medical condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000475-2" qtype="causes">What causes Bleeding gums ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main cause of bleeding gums is the buildup of plaque at the gum line. This will lead to a condition called  gingivitis , or inflamed gums. Plaque that is not removed will harden into tartar. This will lead to increased bleeding and a more advanced form of gum and jaw bone disease known as  periodontitis . Other causes of bleeding gums include: Any bleeding disorders, Brushing too hard, Hormonal changes during pregnancy, Ill-fitting dentures or other dental appliances, Improper flossing, Infection, which can be either in a tooth or the gum,  Leukemia , a type of blood cancer,  Scurvy , a vitamin C deficiency, Use of blood thinners,  Vitamin K  deficiency , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000475-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Bleeding gums ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000475-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Bleeding gums ?</Question>
			<Answer>Consult your provider if: The bleeding is severe or long-term (chronic), Your gums continue to bleed even after treatment, You have other unexplained symptoms with the bleeding, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000475-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Bleeding gums ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>