<Document id="0000838" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001239.htm">
 
<Focus>Chronic granulomatous disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0018203</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>CGD</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fatal granulomatosis of childhood</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic granulomatous disease of childhood</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Progressive septic granulomatosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000838-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic granulomatous disease (CGD) is an inherited disorder in which certain immune system cells do not function properly. This leads to repeated and severe infections.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000838-2" qtype="causes">What causes Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>In CGD, immune system cells called phagocytes are unable to kill some types of bacteria and fungi. This disorder leads to long-term ( chronic ) and repeated (recurrent) infections. The condition is often discovered very early in childhood. Milder forms may be diagnosed during the teenage years, or even in adulthood. Risk factors include a family history of recurrent or chronic infections. About half of CGD cases are passed down through families as a  sex-linked recessive trait . This means that boys are more likely to get the disorder than girls. The defective gene is carried on the X chromosome. Boys have 1 X chromosome and 1 Y chromosome. If a boy has an X chromosome with the defective gene, he may inherit this condition. Girls have 2 X chromosomes. If a girl has 1 X chromosome with the defective gene, the other X chromosome may have a working gene to make up for it. A girl must inherit the defective X gene from each parent in order to have the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000838-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>CGD can cause many types of skin infections that are hard to treat, including: Blisters or sores on the face (impetigo),  Eczema , Growths filled with pus (abscesses), Pus-filled lumps in the skin (boils),  CGD can also cause: Persistent diarrhea,  Swollen lymph nodes  in the neck, Lung infections, such as pneumonia or lung  abscess , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000838-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will do an examination and may find: Liver swelling, Spleen swelling, Swollen lymph nodes,  There may be signs of a bone infection, which may affect many bones. Tests that may be done include: Bone scan ,  Chest x-ray ,  Complete blood count  (CBC), Flow cytometry tests to help confirm the disease, Genetic testing to confirm the diagnosis, Test of white blood cell function, Tissue  biopsy , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000838-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Antibiotics are used to treat infections caused by this condition. Chronic use of antibiotics may prevent infections. A medicine called interferon-gamma may also help reduce the number of severe infections. Surgery may be needed to treat some abscesses. The only cure for CGD is a bone marrow or stem cell transplant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000838-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Long-term antibiotic treatments may help reduce infections, but early death can occur from repeated lung infections.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000838-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>CGD may cause these complications:  Bone damage and infections, Chronic infections in the nose, Pneumonia that keeps coming back and is hard to cure, Lung damage, Skin damage, Swollen lymph nodes that stay swollen, occur often, or form abscesses that need surgery to drain them, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000838-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you or your child has this condition and you suspect pneumonia or another infection, contact your provider right away. Tell your provider if a lung, skin, or other infection does not respond to treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000838-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Chronic granulomatous disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling  is recommended if you are planning to have children and you have a family history of this disease. Advances in genetic screening and increasing use of  chorionic villus sampling  (a test that may be done during a woman's 10th to 12th week of pregnancy) have made early detection of CGD possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>