<Document id="0000885" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002495.htm">
 
<Focus>Cobalt poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0274927</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Cobalt chloride</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cobalt oxide</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cobalt sulfate</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000885-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cobalt poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cobalt is a naturally occurring element in the earth's crust. It is a very small part of our environment. Cobalt is a component of vitamin B12, which supports the production of red blood cells. Very small amounts are needed for animals and humans to stay healthy. Cobalt poisoning can occur when you are exposed to large amounts of it. There are three ways that cobalt can cause poisoning. You can swallow it, breathe it into your lungs, or have it come in prolonged contact with your skin. Cobalt poisoning can also occur from the wear and tear of some cobalt/chromium metal-on-metal hip implants. This type of implant is an artificial hip socket that is created by fitting a metal ball into a metal cup. Sometimes, metal particles (cobalt) are released as the metal ball grinds against the metal cup when you walk. These metal particles (ions) can get released into the hip socket and sometimes the bloodstream, causing cobalt toxicity. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000885-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Cobalt poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Usually you have to be exposed to high levels of cobalt for weeks to months to have symptoms. However, it is possible to have some symptoms if you swallow a large amount of cobalt at one time. The most worrisome form of cobalt poisoning occurs when you breathe it into your lungs. This usually will only happen in industrial settings where large amounts of drilling, polishing, or other processes release fine particles containing cobalt into the air. Breathing in this cobalt dust can lead to chronic lung problems. If you breathe in this substance for long periods, you will likely develop breathing problems that are similar to asthma or pulmonary fibrosis, such as shortness of breath and decreased exercise tolerance. Cobalt poisoning that occurs from prolonged constant with your skin will likely cause irritation and rashes that go away slowly. Swallowing a large amount of absorbable cobalt at one time is very rare and is likely not very dangerous. It may cause nausea and vomiting. However, absorbing a large amount of cobalt over longer periods of time can lead to serious health problems, such as: Cardiomyopathy (a problem where your heart becomes big and floppy and has problems pumping blood), Deafness, Nerve problems, Ringing in the ears (tinnitus), Thickening of the blood, Thyroid problems, Vision problems, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000885-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Cobalt poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000885-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Cobalt poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>People who get sick from being exposed to large amounts of cobalt on one single occasion usually recover and have no long-term complications. The symptoms and problems associated with long-term cobalt poisoning are rarely reversible. People who have such poisoning will likely have to take medicine for the rest of their life to control the symptoms. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000885-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Cobalt poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>People who get sick from being exposed to large amounts of cobalt on one single occasion usually recover and have no long-term complications. The symptoms and problems associated with long-term cobalt poisoning are rarely reversible. People who have such poisoning will likely have to take medicine for the rest of their life to control the symptoms. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>