<Document id="0000528" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001395.htm">
 
<Focus>Brachial plexus injury in newborns</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0161446</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Klumpke paralysis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Erb-Duchenne paralysis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Erb's palsy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brachial palsy</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000528-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>The brachial plexus is a group of nerves around the shoulder. A loss of movement or weakness of the arm may occur if these nerves are damaged. This injury is called neonatal brachial plexus palsy (NBPP).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000528-2" qtype="causes">What causes Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>The nerves of the brachial plexus can be affected by compression inside the mother's womb or during a difficult delivery. Injury may be caused by: The infant's head and neck pulling toward the side as the shoulders pass through the birth canal, The infant's shoulders stretching during a head-first delivery, Pressure on the baby's raised arms during a breech (feet-first) delivery,  There are different forms of NBPP. The type depends on the amount of arm paralysis: Brachial plexus palsy most often affects only the upper arm. It is also called Duchenne-Erb or Erb-Duchenne paralysis., Klumpke paralysis affects the lower arm and hand. This is less common.,  The following factors increase the risk of NBPP: Breech delivery, Maternal obesity, Larger-than-average newborn (such as an  infant of a diabetic mother ), Difficulty delivering the baby's shoulder after the head has already come out (called shoulder dystocia),  NBPP is less common than in the past. Cesarean delivery is used more often when there are concerns about a difficult delivery. Although a C-section reduces the risk of injury, it does not prevent it. A C-section also carries other risks. NBPP may be confused with a condition called  pseudoparalysis . This is seen when the infant has a fracture and is not moving the arm because of pain, but there is no nerve damage.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000528-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms can be seen right away or soon after birth. They may include: No movement in the newborn's upper or lower arm or hand, Absent  Moro reflex  on the affected side, Arm extended (straight) at elbow and held against body, Decreased grip on the affected side (depending on the site of injury), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000528-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam most often shows that the infant is not moving the upper or lower arm or hand. The affected arm may flop when the infant is rolled from side to side. The Moro reflex is absent on the side of injury. The health care provider will examine the clavicle (collarbone) to look for a fracture. The infant may need to have an x-ray taken.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000528-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>In mild cases, the provider will suggest: Gentle massage of the arm, Range-of-motion exercises,  Pediatric physical therapists can help with these. The infant may need to be seen by specialists if the damage is severe or the condition does not improve in the first few weeks.  Surgery may be considered if strength does not improve by 3 to 9 months of age. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000528-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most babies will fully recover within 3 to 4 months. Those who do not recover during this time have a poor outlook for full recovery. In these cases, there may be a separation of the nerve root from the spinal cord (avulsion). It is not clear whether surgery to fix the nerve problem can help. Surgery may involve nerve grafts or nerve transfers. It may take many years for healing to occur. In cases of pseudoparalysis, the child will begin to use the affected arm as the fracture heals. Fractures in infants heal quickly and easily in most cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000528-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications include: Abnormal muscle contractions (contractures) or tightening of the muscles. These may be permanent., Permanent, partial, or total loss of function of the affected nerves, causing paralysis of the arm or arm weakness., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000528-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if your newborn is not moving an arm.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000528-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Brachial plexus injury in newborns ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is difficult to prevent NBPP. Taking steps to avoid a difficult delivery, whenever possible, reduces the risk.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>