<Document id="0000209" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000352.htm">
 
<Focus>Anaplastic thyroid cancer</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238461</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Anaplastic carcinoma of the thyroid</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000209-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anaplastic thyroid carcinoma is a rare and aggressive form of cancer of the thyroid gland.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000209-2" qtype="causes">What causes Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anaplastic thyroid cancer is an invasive type of  thyroid cancer  that grows very rapidly. It occurs most often in people over age 60. It is more common in females than in males. The cause is unknown. Anaplastic cancer accounts for only about less than 1% of all thyroid cancers in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000209-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Cough, Coughing up blood, Difficulty swallowing, Hoarseness or changing voice, Loud breathing, Lower neck lump, which often grows quickly , Pain, Vocal cord paralysis, Overactive thyroid ( hyperthyroidism ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000209-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam almost always shows a growth in the neck region. Other exams include: An MRI or CT scan of the neck may show a tumor growing from the thyroid gland., A thyroid biopsy makes the diagnosis. The tumor tissue can be checked for genetic markers that may suggest targets for treatment, preferably within a clinical trial., An examination of the airway with a fiberoptic scope (laryngoscopy) may show a paralyzed vocal cord., A  thyroid scan  shows this growth to be "cold," meaning it does not absorb a radioactive substance. ,  Thyroid function blood tests are normal in most cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000209-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>This type of cancer cannot be cured by surgery. Complete removal of the thyroid gland does not prolong the lives of people who have this type of cancer. Surgery combined with radiation therapy and chemotherapy may have a significant benefit. Surgery to place a tube in the throat to help with breathing (tracheostomy) or in the stomach to help with eating (gastrostomy) may be needed during treatment. For some people, enrolling in a clinical trial of new thyroid cancer treatments based on the genetic changes in the tumor may be an option.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000209-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can often ease the stress of illness by joining a support group of people sharing common experiences and problems. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000209-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook with this disease is poor. Most people do not survive longer than 6 months because the disease is aggressive and there is a lack of effective treatment options.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000209-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer> Complications may include: Spread of tumor within the neck
  ,  Metastasis  (spread) of cancer to other body tissues or organs, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000209-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Anaplastic thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you notice: A persistent lump or mass in the neck, Hoarseness or changes in your voice, Cough or coughing up blood, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>