<Document id="0000810" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000051.htm">
 
<Focus>Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0041657</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year</Synonym>
		<Synonym>First aid- choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year</Synonym>
		<Synonym>CPR - choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000810-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year ?</Question>
			<Answer>Choking is when someone cannot breathe because food, a toy, or other object is blocking the throat or windpipe (airway). A choking person's airway may be blocked so that not enough oxygen reaches the lungs. Without oxygen, brain damage can occur in as little as 4 minutes. Rapid first aid for choking can save a person's life. 
  This article discusses choking in adults or children over age 1 year who have lost alertness (are unconscious).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000810-2" qtype="causes">What causes Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year ?</Question>
			<Answer>Choking may be caused by: Eating too fast, not chewing food well, or eating with dentures that do not fit well, Foods such as food chunks, hot dogs, popcorn, peanut butter, sticky or gooey food (marshmallows, gummy bears, dough) , Drinking alcohol (even a small amount of alcohol affects awareness), Being unconscious and breathing in vomit, Breathing in or swallowing small objects (young children), Injury to the head and face (for example, swelling, bleeding, or a deformity can cause choking), Swallowing problems caused by a stroke or other brain disorders, Enlarged tonsils or tumors of the neck and throat, Problems with the esophagus (food pipe or swallowing tube), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000810-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of choking when a person is unconscious include: Bluish color to the lips and nails (cyanosis), Inability to breathe, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000810-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000810-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000810-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year ?</Question>
			<Answer>Seek medical help right away if someone is found unconscious. In the days following a choking episode, contact a doctor right away if the person develops: A cough that doesn't go away, Fever, Difficulty swallowing or speaking, Shortness of breath, Wheezing,  The above signs may indicate: The object entered the lung instead of being expelled, Injury to the voice box (larynx), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000810-7" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Choking - unconscious adult or child over 1 year ?</Question>
			<Answer>To prevent choking: Eat slowly and chew food completely., Cut large pieces of food into easily chewable sizes. , Do not drink too much alcohol before or during eating., Keep small objects away from young children., Make sure dentures fit properly., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>