<Document id="0000096" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001663.htm">
 
<Focus>Adrenocortical carcinoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0206686</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tumor - adrenal</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000096-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Adrenocortical carcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Adrenocortical carcinoma (ACC) is a cancer of the  adrenal glands . The adrenal glands are two triangle-shaped glands. One gland is located on top of each kidney.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000096-2" qtype="causes">What causes Adrenocortical carcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>ACC is most common in children younger than 5 years old&#160;and adults in their 40s and 50s. The condition may be linked to a cancer syndrome that is passed down through families (inherited). Both men and women can develop this tumor. ACC can produce the hormones cortisol, aldosterone, estrogen, or testosterone, as well as other hormones. In women the tumor often releases these hormones, which can lead to male characteristics. ACC is very rare. The cause is unknown.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000096-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Adrenocortical carcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of increased cortisol or other adrenal gland hormones may include: Fatty, rounded hump high on the back just below the neck ( buffalo hump ), Flushed, rounded face with pudgy cheeks ( moon face ), Obesity, Stunted growth ( short stature ),  Virilization  -- the appearance of male characteristics, including increased body hair (especially on the face), pubic hair, acne, deepening of the voice, and enlarged clitoris (females) ,  Symptoms of increased aldosterone are the same as symptoms of low potassium, and include: Muscle cramps, Weakness, Pain in the abdomen, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000096-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Adrenocortical carcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask about your symptoms. Blood tests will be done to check hormone levels: ACTH  level will be low.,  Aldosterone  level will be high.,  Cortisol  level will be high.,  Potassium  level will be low., Male or female hormones may be abnormally high. ,  Imaging tests of the abdomen may include: Ultrasound, CT scan, MRI, PET scan , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000096-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Adrenocortical carcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Primary treatment is surgery to remove the tumor. ACC may not improve with  chemotherapy . Medicines may be given to reduce production of cortisol, which causes many of the symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000096-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Adrenocortical carcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome depends on how early the diagnosis is made and whether the tumor has spread (metastasized). Tumors that have spread usually lead to death within 1 to 3 years.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000096-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Adrenocortical carcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The tumor can spread to the liver, bone, lung, or other areas.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000096-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Adrenocortical carcinoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you or your child has symptoms of ACC,&#160; Cushing syndrome , or failure to grow.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>