<Document id="0000676" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001587.htm">
 
<Focus>Caput succedaneum</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0270090</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Caput</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000676-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Caput succedaneum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Caput succedaneum is  swelling  of the scalp in a newborn. It is most often brought on by pressure from the uterus or vaginal wall during a head-first (vertex) delivery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000676-2" qtype="causes">What causes Caput succedaneum ?</Question>
			<Answer>A caput succedaneum is more likely to form during a long or hard delivery. It is more common after the membranes have broken. This is because the fluid in the amniotic sac is no longer providing a cushion for the baby's head. Vacuum extraction done during a difficult birth can also increase the chances of a caput succedaneum. A caput succedaneum may be detected by prenatal ultrasound, even before labor or delivery begins. It has been found as early as 31 weeks of pregnancy. Very often, this is due to an early rupture of the membranes or too little amniotic fluid. It is less likely that a caput will form if the membranes stay intact.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000676-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Caput succedaneum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Soft, puffy swelling on the scalp of a  newborn infant , Possible  bruising  or color change on the scalp swelling area, Swelling that may extend to both sides of the scalp, Swelling that is most often seen on the portion of the head which presented first , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000676-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Caput succedaneum ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will look at the swelling to confirm that it is a caput succedaneum. No other testing is needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000676-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Caput succedaneum ?</Question>
			<Answer>No treatment is needed. The problem most often goes away on its own within a few days.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000676-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Caput succedaneum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complete recovery can be expected. The scalp will go back to a normal shape.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000676-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Caput succedaneum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include a yellow color to the skin ( jaundice ) if bruising is involved. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000676-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Caput succedaneum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of the time, the problem is noticed right after birth. You do not need to contact your provider unless you have other questions.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>