<Document id="0000269" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002522.htm">
 
<Focus>Antidiarrheal drug overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0029944</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000269-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Antidiarrheal drug overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Antidiarrheal drugs are used to treat loose, watery, and frequent stools. This article discusses  overdose  of antidiarrheal drugs containing diphenoxylate and atropine. Both ingredients help slow intestinal movement. In addition, atropine helps decrease the body's production of fluids. Other antidiarrheal drugs on the market contain different ingredients, such as loperamide. This article focuses on antidiarrheal drugs containing diphenoxylate and atropine specifically. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with overdoses, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000269-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Antidiarrheal drug overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Someone who has overdosed on this medicine may have some of these symptoms: Apathy (loss of desire to do anything), Slow breathing, or breathing stops,  Pounding or racing heartbeat  (palpitations), Slowdown or stoppage of the bowels,  Coma  (decreased level of consciousness, lack of responsiveness),  Constipation , Seizures (convulsions),  Drowsiness , Dry mucous membranes in the mouth, Eye changes in pupil size (may be small, normal-sized, or large),  Eyes move quickly from side to side , Flushed skin, Hallucinations (seeing or hearing things that aren't there), Restlessness, Urination difficulty, Vomiting,  Note:  Symptoms may take up to 12 hours to appear.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000269-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Antidiarrheal drug overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000269-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Antidiarrheal drug overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people will recover with treatment and are monitored for 24 hours. However, deaths may occur in young children. Children under age 6 should be admitted to the hospital and closely watched for 24 hours because signs of lung problems may be delayed and severe. Keep all medicines in child-proof containers and out of reach of children. Read all medicine labels and take only medicines that have been prescribed for you.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000269-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Antidiarrheal drug overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people will recover with treatment and are monitored for 24 hours. However, deaths may occur in young children. Children under age 6 should be admitted to the hospital and closely watched for 24 hours because signs of lung problems may be delayed and severe. Keep all medicines in child-proof containers and out of reach of children. Read all medicine labels and take only medicines that have been prescribed for you.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>