<Document id="0000723" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002033.htm">
 
<Focus>Cellulite</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0424624</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000723-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Cellulite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Everyone has layers of fat under the skin, so even thin people can have cellulite. Collagen fibers that connect fat to the skin may stretch, break down, or pull tight. This allows fat cells to bulge out. Your genes may play a part in whether or not you have cellulite. Other factors may include: Sex and race/ethnicity, How your body burns energy, Hormone changes, Dehydration,  Cellulite is not harmful to your health. Most health care providers consider cellulite a normal condition for many women and some men. Many people seek treatment for cellulite because they are bothered by how it looks. Talk to your provider about treatment options. These include: Laser treatment, which uses laser energy to break up the tough bands that pull on the skin resulting in the dimpled skin of cellulite., Subcision, which uses a tiny blade to also break up the tough bands., Fillers that stimulate collagen to soften appearance of dimpled areas., Other treatments, such as carbon dioxide, radiofrequency, ultrasound, creams and lotions, and deep massage devices.,  Be sure you understand the risks and benefits of any treatment for cellulite. Tips for avoiding cellulite include: Eating a healthy diet rich in fruits, vegetables, and fiber, Staying hydrated by drinking plenty of fluids, Exercising regularly to keep muscles toned and bones strong, Maintaining a healthy weight (no yo-yo dieting), Not smoking, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000723-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Cellulite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Everyone has layers of fat under the skin, so even thin people can have cellulite. Collagen fibers that connect fat to the skin may stretch, break down, or pull tight. This allows fat cells to bulge out. Your genes may play a part in whether or not you have cellulite. Other factors may include: Sex and race/ethnicity, How your body burns energy, Hormone changes, Dehydration,  Cellulite is not harmful to your health. Most health care providers consider cellulite a normal condition for many women and some men. Many people seek treatment for cellulite because they are bothered by how it looks. Talk to your provider about treatment options. These include: Laser treatment, which uses laser energy to break up the tough bands that pull on the skin resulting in the dimpled skin of cellulite., Subcision, which uses a tiny blade to also break up the tough bands., Fillers that stimulate collagen to soften appearance of dimpled areas., Other treatments, such as carbon dioxide, radiofrequency, ultrasound, creams and lotions, and deep massage devices.,  Be sure you understand the risks and benefits of any treatment for cellulite. Tips for avoiding cellulite include: Eating a healthy diet rich in fruits, vegetables, and fiber, Staying hydrated by drinking plenty of fluids, Exercising regularly to keep muscles toned and bones strong, Maintaining a healthy weight (no yo-yo dieting), Not smoking, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>