<Document id="0001931" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000243.htm">
 
<Focus>Hepatic hemangioma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238246</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Liver hemangioma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemangioma of the liver</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cavernous hepatic hemangioma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Infantile hemangioendothelioma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multinodular hepatic hemangiomatosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001931-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hepatic hemangioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>A hepatic hemangioma is a liver mass made of widened (dilated) blood vessels. It is not cancerous.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001931-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hepatic hemangioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>A hepatic hemangioma is the most common type of liver mass that is not caused by cancer. It may be a birth defect. Hepatic hemangiomas can occur at any time. They are most common in people in their 30s to 50s. Women get these masses more often than men. The masses are often bigger in size. Babies may develop a type of hepatic hemangioma called benign infantile hemangioendothelioma. This is also known as multinodular hepatic hemangiomatosis. This is a rare, noncancerous  tumor  that has been linked to high rates of heart failure and death in infants. Infants are most often diagnosed by the time they are 6 months old.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001931-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hepatic hemangioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some hemangiomas may cause bleeding or interfere with organ function. Most do not produce symptoms. In rare cases, the hemangioma may rupture.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001931-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hepatic hemangioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, the condition is not found until liver images are taken for some other reason. If the hemangioma ruptures, the only sign may be an enlarged liver. Babies with benign infantile hemangioendothelioma may have:  A growth in the abdomen,  Anemia , Signs of  heart failure ,  The following tests may be performed: Blood tests,  CT scan of the liver , Hepatic angiogram
   ,  MRI , Single-photon emission computed tomography (SPECT),  Ultrasound of the abdomen , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001931-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hepatic hemangioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of these tumors are treated only if there is ongoing pain. Treatment for infantile hemangioendothelioma depends on the child's growth and development. The following treatments may be needed: Inserting a material in a blood vessel of the liver to block it (embolization), Tying off (ligating) a liver artery, Medicines for heart failure, Surgery to remove the tumor , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001931-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hepatic hemangioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Surgery can cure a tumor in an infant if it is only in one lobe of the liver. This can be done even if the child has heart failure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001931-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hepatic hemangioma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pregnancy and estrogen-based medicines can cause these tumors to grow. The tumor may rupture in rare cases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>