<Document id="0001841" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000727.htm">
 
<Focus>Healthy food trends -- chia seeds</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Healthy food trends -- sage</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Healthy food trends -- salvia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001841-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Healthy food trends -- chia seeds</Question>
			<Answer>WHY THEY ARE GOOD FOR YOU Chia seeds are rich in fiber, healthy fats, and antioxidants that help prevent cell damage. Chia seeds are a good source of  insoluble fiber . The seeds expand quite a bit and form a gel when they come into contact with water. This gel adds bulk to your stool, which keeps bowel movements regular and helps prevent constipation. The added bulk also may help you feel fuller so you eat less. Just 1 tablespoon of chia seeds will give you 20% of your recommended daily fiber. Chia seeds are also rich in the essential fatty acids: omega-3 and omega-6. Essential fatty acids are fatty substances that your body needs to function. They are not made in the body, and you must get them from foods. Researchers are looking at the benefits of chia, in particular whether consuming more of the fatty acids found in chia seeds can improve blood pressure, heart health, and blood sugar. HOW THEY ARE PREPARED Chia seeds can be added or sprinkled on almost anything. There is no preparation needed -- unlike flax seed, chia seeds do not need to be ground for maximal benefit. To add chia seeds to your diet: Use them instead of breadcrumbs., Sprinkle them on salads., Use them in drinks, smoothies, yogurt, or oatmeal., Add them to soups or any cooked dishes., Mix them in the batter of pancakes and French toast.,  Chia seeds can be ground into a paste and added to your dough or other mixes before cooking or baking. WHERE TO FIND CHIA SEEDS Chia seeds may be purchased at any health food store, or online. Major grocery stores may also carry chia seeds in the natural or organic food aisle. Simply buy a bag of chia seeds, milled or whole. RECIPE There are many delicious recipes you can make with chia seeds. Here is one to try. Chia Pudding Ingredients Two tablespoons of chia seeds, Half cup unsweetened vanilla flavored almond milk (or another nondairy milk of your choice), Half cup of strawberries, washed and chopped small,  Instructions Put chia seeds and the non-dairy milk of your choice in a mason jar. Make sure the lid is closed tightly. Shake to mix and leave in the refrigerator for at least four hours. The chia seeds will absorb the liquid and swell to a pudding-like consistency., Remove the chia pudding from the refrigerator, add the diced strawberries and enjoy., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>