<Document id="0001657" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002844.htm">
 
<Focus>Funnel-web spider bite</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0242188</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001657-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Funnel-web spider bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>This article describes the effects of a bite from the funnel-web spider. Male funnel-web spider bites are more toxic than bites by females. The class of insects to which the funnel-web spider belongs, contains the largest number of venomous species known. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage a bite from this type of spider. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001657-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Funnel-web spider bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Funnel-web spider bites are very painful and dangerous. They have been known to cause these symptoms in different parts of the body: EYES, EARS, NOSE, AND THROAT Drooling, Drooping eyelids, Double vision, Swallowing difficulty, Tingling or numbness in the mouth or lips within 10 to 15 minutes ,  HEART AND BLOOD Collapse ( shock ), Rapid heart rate ,  LUNGS Difficulty breathing ,  MUSCLES AND JOINTS Joint pain, Severe muscle spasms, usually in the legs and belly area ,  NERVOUS SYSTEM Agitation, Confusion, Coma (lack of responsiveness), Headache, Numbness of mouth and lips, Tremors (shaking), Shivering (chills) ,  SKIN Heavy sweating, Redness around the site of the bite ,  STOMACH AND INTESTINES Diarrhea, Nausea and vomiting , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001657-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Funnel-web spider bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001657-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Funnel-web spider bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Funnel-web spider bites can be life threatening, especially in children. They must be treated quickly with antivenin by an experienced provider. Even with appropriate and quick treatment, symptoms may last for several days to weeks. The original bite may be small and may progress to a blood blister and look like a bull's eye. (This is similar to the appearance of a brown recluse spider bite.) The area affected by the bite may become deeper. Additional symptoms such as fever, chills, and other signs of additional organ system involvement may develop. Deep scarring may occur and surgery may be needed to improve appearance of the scar.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001657-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Funnel-web spider bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Funnel-web spider bites can be life threatening, especially in children. They must be treated quickly with antivenin by an experienced provider. Even with appropriate and quick treatment, symptoms may last for several days to weeks. The original bite may be small and may progress to a blood blister and look like a bull's eye. (This is similar to the appearance of a brown recluse spider bite.) The area affected by the bite may become deeper. Additional symptoms such as fever, chills, and other signs of additional organ system involvement may develop. Deep scarring may occur and surgery may be needed to improve appearance of the scar.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>