<Document id="0001736" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001305.htm">
 
<Focus>Glanzmann disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040015</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Glanzmann's diasease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Thrombasthenia - Glanzmann</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001736-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glanzmann thrombasthenia is a rare disorder of blood platelets. Platelets are particles in the blood that aid in blood clotting.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001736-2" qtype="causes">What causes Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glanzmann thrombasthenia is caused by the lack of a protein that is normally on the surface of platelets. This substance is needed for platelets to clump together to plug up bleeding spots and begin forming a clot. The condition is congenital, which means it is present from birth. There are several genetic abnormalities that can cause the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001736-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include any of the following: Heavy bleeding during and after surgery, Bleeding gums, Bruising easily or pinpoint red spots on the skin, Heavy menstrual bleeding, Nosebleeds that do not stop easily, Prolonged bleeding with minor injuries , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001736-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following tests may be used to diagnose this condition: Complete blood count  (CBC),  Platelet aggregation test , Platelet function analysis (PFA),  Prothrombin time  (PT) and  partial thromboplastin time  (PTT) ,  Other tests may be needed. Family members may also need to be tested.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001736-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no specific treatment for this disorder. Platelet transfusions may be given to people who are having severe bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001736-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glanzmann thrombasthenia is a lifelong condition, and there is no cure. You should take special steps to try to avoid bleeding if you have this condition.  Anyone with a bleeding disorder should avoid taking aspirin and other nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) such as ibuprofen and naproxen. These drugs can prolong bleeding times by preventing platelets from clumping.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001736-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Severe bleeding,  Iron deficiency anemia  in menstruating women due to abnormally heavy bleeding , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001736-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if: You have bleeding or bruising of an unknown cause, Bleeding does not stop after usual treatments , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001736-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Glanzmann disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Glanzmann thrombasthenia is an inherited condition. There is no known prevention.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>