<Document id="0001771" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003100.htm">
 
<Focus>Groin lump</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0240007</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Lump in the groin</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Inguinal lymphadenopathy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Localized lymphadenopathy - groin</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bubo</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lymphadenopathy - groin</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001771-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Groin lump ?</Question>
			<Answer>A groin lump is swelling in the groin area. This is where the upper leg meets the lower abdomen.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001771-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Groin lump ?</Question>
			<Answer>A groin lump may be firm or soft, tender, or not painful at all. Your health care provider should examine any groin lumps.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001771-3" qtype="causes">What causes Groin lump ?</Question>
			<Answer>The most common cause of a groin lump is swollen lymph nodes. These may be caused by: Cancer, most often lymphoma (cancer of the lymph system), Infection in the legs, Body-wide infections, often caused by viruses, Infections spread through sexual contact such as genital herpes, chlamydia, or gonorrhea,  Other causes include any of the following: Allergic reaction, Drug reaction, Harmless (benign) cyst,  Hernia  (a soft, large bulge in the groin on one or both sides), Injury to the groin area, Lipomas (harmless fatty growths), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001771-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Groin lump ?</Question>
			<Answer>A groin lump may be firm or soft, tender, or not painful at all. Your health care provider should examine any groin lumps.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001771-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Groin lump ?</Question>
			<Answer>Small lymph nodes that can be felt in the groin are common, especially in men, and usually result from prior leg infection. Make an appointment to see your provider if you have an unexplained groin lump.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001771-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Groin lump ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>