<Document id="0001688" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001134.htm">
 
<Focus>Gastroesophageal reflux in infants</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0017168</CUI>
			<CUI>C3813607</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Reflux - infants</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001688-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Gastroesophageal reflux in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gastroesophageal reflux occurs when stomach contents leak backward from the stomach into the esophagus. This causes " spitting up " in infants.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001688-2" qtype="causes">What causes Gastroesophageal reflux in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>When a person eats, food passes from the throat to the stomach through the esophagus. The esophagus is called the food pipe or swallowing tube. A ring of muscle fibers prevents food at the top of the stomach from moving up into the esophagus. These muscle fibers are called the lower esophageal sphincter, or LES. If this muscle does not close well, food can leak back into the esophagus. This is called gastroesophageal reflux. A small amount of gastroesophageal reflux is normal in young infants. However, ongoing reflux with frequent vomiting can irritate the esophagus and make the infant fussy. Severe reflux that causes weight loss or breathing problems is not normal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001688-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Gastroesophageal reflux in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Cough, especially after eating,  Excessive crying  as if in pain, Excessive vomiting during the first few weeks of life; worse after eating, Extremely forceful vomiting, Not feeding well, Refusing to eat, Slow growth, Weight loss, Wheezing or other breathing problems , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001688-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Gastroesophageal reflux in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider can often diagnose the problem by asking about the infant's symptoms and doing a physical exam. Infants who have severe symptoms or are not growing well may need more testing to find the best treatment.  Tests that may be done include: Esophageal pH monitoring of stomach contents entering the esophagus, X-ray of the esophagus, X-ray of the upper gastrointestinal system after the baby has been given a special liquid, called contrast, to drink , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001688-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Gastroesophageal reflux in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>Often, no feeding changes are needed for infants who spit up but are growing well and seem otherwise content.  Your provider may suggest simple changes to help the symptoms such as:  Burp the baby after drinking 1 to 2 ounces (30 to 60 milliliters) of formula, or after feeding on each side if breastfeeding., Add 1 tablespoon (2.5 grams) of rice cereal to 2 ounces (60 milliliters) of formula, milk, or expressed breast milk. If needed, change the nipple size or cut a small x in the nipple., Hold the baby upright for 20 to 30 minutes after feeding., Raise the head of the crib. However, your infant should still sleep on the back, unless your provider suggests otherwise. ,  When the infant begins to eat solid food, feeding thickened foods may help. Medicines can be used to reduce acid or increase the movement of the intestines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001688-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Gastroesophageal reflux in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most infants outgrow this condition. Rarely, reflux continues into childhood and causes esophageal damage.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001688-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Gastroesophageal reflux in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Aspiration pneumonia caused by stomach contents passing into the lungs, Irritation and swelling of the esophagus, Scarring and narrowing of the esophagus , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001688-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Gastroesophageal reflux in infants ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if your baby: Is vomiting forcefully and often, Has other symptoms of reflux, Has problems breathing after vomiting, Is refusing food and losing or not gaining weight, Is crying often, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>