<Document id="0001892" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003181.htm">
 
<Focus>Heel pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0231780</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pain - heel</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001892-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Heel pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Heel pain is most often the result of overuse. However, it may be caused by an injury. Your heel may become tender or swollen from: Shoes with poor support or shock absorption, Running on hard surfaces, like concrete, Running too often, Tightness in your calf muscle or the Achilles tendon, Sudden inward or outward turning of your heel, Landing hard or awkwardly on the heel ,  Conditions that may cause heel pain include: Swelling and pain in the  Achilles tendon , Swelling of the  fluid-filled sac  (bursa) at the back of the heel bone under the Achilles tendon (bursitis), Bone spurs in the heel, Swelling of the thick band of tissue on the bottom of your foot (plantar fasciitis), Fracture of the heel bone that is related to landing very hard on your heel from a fall (calcaneus fracture) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001892-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Heel pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001892-3" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Heel pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if your heel pain does not get better after 2 to 3 weeks of home treatment. Also call if: Your pain is getting worse despite home treatment., Your pain is sudden and severe., You have redness or swelling of your heel., You cannot put weight on your foot, even after resting., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001892-4" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Heel pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001892-5" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Heel pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>