<Document id="0001440" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000618.htm">
 
<Focus>Erysipelas</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0014733</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001440-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Erysipelas is a type of skin infection.&#160;It affects the outermost layer of the skin and the local lymph nodes.&#160;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001440-2" qtype="causes">What causes Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Erysipelas is usually caused by group A streptococcus bacteria. The condition may affect both children and adults. Some conditions that can lead to erysipelas are: A cut in the skin, Problems with drainage through the veins or lymph system, Skin sores (ulcers) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001440-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>The infection occurs on the legs or arms most of the time. It may also occur on the face and trunk. Symptoms of erysipelas may include: Fever and chills&#160;, Skin sore with a sharp raised border. As the infection spreads, the skin is painful, very red, swollen, and warm.  Blisters  on the skin can form. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001440-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Erysipelas is diagnosed based on how the skin looks. A  biopsy of the skin  is usually not needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001440-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Antibiotics are used to get rid of the infection. If the infection is severe, antibiotics may need to be given through an intravenous 
(IV) line. People who have repeated episodes of erysipelas may need long-term antibiotics.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001440-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>With treatment, the outcome is good. It may take a few weeks for the skin to return to normal. Peeling is common as the skin heals. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001440-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sometimes the bacteria that cause erysipelas may travel to the blood. This results in a condition called bacteremia. When this happens, the infection may spread to the heart valves, joints, and bones. Other complications include: Return of infection,  Septic shock  (a dangerous body-wide infection) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001440-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have a skin sore or other symptoms of erysipelas.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001440-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Erysipelas ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep your skin healthy by avoiding dry skin and preventing cuts and scrapes. This may reduce the risk for erysipelas.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>