<Document id="0001790" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002702.htm">
 
<Focus>Hair bleach poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0520897</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hair lightener poisoning</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001790-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hair bleach poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hair  bleach  poisoning occurs when someone swallows hair bleach or splashes it on their skin or in their eyes. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001790-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hair bleach poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of hair bleach poisoning can include: Abdominal pain , Blurred vision, Breathing difficulty, Mild lung irritation when vapors from household strength hydrogen peroxide (3%) are inhaled, Severe lung irritation when vapors from industrial strength solutions (higher than 10%) are inhaled, Burning pain in the throat, Burns to the eye, redness, and tearing,  Collapse ,  Coma  (decreased level of consciousness and lack of responsiveness),  Diarrhea  (watery, bloody),  Low blood pressure ,  Inability to walk normally ,  No urine output , Rash, Slurred speech,  Stupor ,  Vomiting , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001790-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Hair bleach poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001790-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hair bleach poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on how severe the poisoning is and how quickly they receive treatment. The faster medical help is given, the better the chance for recovery.  Extensive damage to the mouth, throat, and stomach is possible. The outcome depends on how much of this damage there is. Damage to the esophagus and stomach can continue to occur for several weeks after the product is swallowed. A hole can develop in these organs, and that can lead to bleeding and severe infection. Surgery may be needed to treat these and other complications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001790-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hair bleach poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on how severe the poisoning is and how quickly they receive treatment. The faster medical help is given, the better the chance for recovery.  Extensive damage to the mouth, throat, and stomach is possible. The outcome depends on how much of this damage there is. Damage to the esophagus and stomach can continue to occur for several weeks after the product is swallowed. A hole can develop in these organs, and that can lead to bleeding and severe infection. Surgery may be needed to treat these and other complications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>