<Document id="0001574" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000911.htm">
 
<Focus>Fetal alcohol syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1542327</CUI>
			<CUI>C0015923</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Alcohol in pregnancy</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Alcohol-related birth defects</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fetal alcohol effects</Synonym>
		<Synonym>FAS</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001574-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fetal alcohol syndrome (FAS) is a collection of growth, mental, and physical problems that may occur in a baby when a mother drinks alcohol during pregnancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001574-2" qtype="causes">What causes Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Using alcohol during pregnancy can cause the same risks as using alcohol in general. But it poses extra risks to the unborn baby. When a pregnant woman drinks alcohol, it easily passes across the placenta to the fetus. Because of this, drinking alcohol can harm the unborn baby. There is no "safe" level of alcohol use during pregnancy. Larger amounts of alcohol appear to increase the problems. Binge drinking is more harmful than drinking small amounts of alcohol. Timing of alcohol use during pregnancy is also important. Drinking alcohol is likely most harmful during the first 3 months of pregnancy. But drinking alcohol any time during pregnancy can be harmful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001574-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>A baby with FAS may have the following symptoms: Poor growth while the baby is in the womb and after birth, Decreased muscle tone and poor coordination, Delayed  developmental milestones , Vision difficulties, such as nearsightedness (myopia), Hyperactivity, Anxiety, Extreme nervousness, Short attention span, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001574-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam of the baby may show a  heart murmur  or other heart problems. A common defect is a hole in the wall that separates the right and left lower chambers (ventricles) of the heart. There also may be problems with the face and bones. These may include: Narrow and small eyes, Small head and upper jaw, Smooth groove in the upper lip, smooth and thin upper lip, Deformed ears, Flat, short, and upturned nose, Ptosis (drooping of upper eyelids),  Tests that may be done include: Blood alcohol level in pregnant women who show signs of being drunk (intoxicated), Brain imaging studies (CT or MRI) after the child is born,  Pregnancy ultrasound , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001574-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Women who are pregnant or who are trying to get pregnant should not drink any amount of alcohol. Pregnant women with alcohol use disorder should join a rehabilitation program and be checked closely by a health care provider throughout pregnancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001574-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001574-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome for infants with FAS varies. Almost none of these babies have normal brain development. Infants and children with FAS have many different problems, which can be difficult to manage. Children do best if they are diagnosed early and referred to a team of providers who can work on educational and behavioral strategies that fit the child's needs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001574-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if you are drinking alcohol regularly or heavily, and are finding it difficult to cut back or stop. Also contact your provider if you are drinking alcohol in any amount while you are pregnant or trying to get pregnant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001574-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Fetal alcohol syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Avoiding alcohol during pregnancy prevents FAS. Counseling can help women who have already had a child with FAS. Sexually active women who drink heavily should use birth control and control their drinking behaviors, or stop using alcohol before trying to get pregnant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>