<Document id="0001675" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003124.htm">
 
<Focus>Gas - flatulence</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0016204</CUI>
			<CUI>C0596601</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Flatulence</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Flatus</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001675-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Gas - flatulence ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gas is air in the intestine that is passed through the rectum. Air that moves from the digestive tract through the mouth is called  belching . Gas is also called flatus or flatulence.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001675-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Gas - flatulence ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gas is normally formed in the intestines as your body digests food.  Gas can make you feel bloated. It can cause crampy or colicky pains in your belly. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001675-3" qtype="causes">What causes Gas - flatulence ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gas can be caused by certain foods you eat. You may have gas if you: Eat foods that are hard to digest, such as fiber. Sometimes, adding more fiber into your diet can cause temporary gas. Your body may adjust and stop producing gas over time., Eat or drink something your body cannot tolerate. For example, some people have  lactose intolerance  and cannot eat or drink dairy products. ,  Other common causes of gas are: Antibiotics,  Irritable bowel syndrome , Inability to absorb nutrients properly ( malabsorption ), Inability to digest nutrients properly (maldigestion), Swallowing air while eating , Chewing gum, Smoking cigarettes, Drinking carbonated beverages, Talking while eating and eating too rapidly, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001675-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Gas - flatulence ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gas is normally formed in the intestines as your body digests food.  Gas can make you feel bloated. It can cause crampy or colicky pains in your belly. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001675-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Gas - flatulence ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have: Gas and other symptoms such as stomach pain, rectal pain, heartburn, nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, constipation, fever, or weight loss, Oily, foul-smelling, or bloody stools , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001675-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Gas - flatulence ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>