<Document id="0001654" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002895.htm">
 
<Focus>Fuel oil poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032343</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001654-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Fuel oil poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fuel oil poisoning occurs when someone swallows, breathes in (inhales), or touches fuel oil. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001654-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fuel oil poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Below are symptoms of fuel oil poisoning in different parts of the body. EYES, EARS, NOSE, AND THROAT Loss of vision, Pain in the throat, Pain or burning in the nose, eyes, ears, lips, or tongue,  STOMACH AND INTESTINES Abdominal pain ,  Blood in the stool ,  Diarrhea , Nausea, Vomiting (may contain blood),  HEART AND BLOOD Collapse,  Low blood pressure  that develops rapidly,  LUNGS Breathing difficulty  (from breathing the fumes), Throat swelling (which may also cause breathing difficulty),  NERVOUS SYSTEM Depression , Difficulty concentrating, Dizziness, Drowsiness, Feeling of being drunk (euphoria),  Headaches , Lightheadedness, Loss of alertness (unconsciousness),  Seizures  (convulsions), Staggering, Weakness,  SKIN Blisters, Burn, Irritation, Peeling of the skin, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001654-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Fuel oil poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001654-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Fuel oil poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on how much fuel oil was swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster medical help is given, the better the chance for recovery. Swallowing such poisons can have severe effects on many parts of the body. Burns in the airway or gastrointestinal tract can lead to tissue necrosis, resulting in infection, shock, and death, even several months after the substance is first swallowed. Scars may form in these tissues leading to long-term difficulties with breathing, swallowing, and digestion. If fuel oil gets into the lungs (aspiration), serious and possibly permanent lung damage can occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001654-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Fuel oil poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on how much fuel oil was swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster medical help is given, the better the chance for recovery. Swallowing such poisons can have severe effects on many parts of the body. Burns in the airway or gastrointestinal tract can lead to tissue necrosis, resulting in infection, shock, and death, even several months after the substance is first swallowed. Scars may form in these tissues leading to long-term difficulties with breathing, swallowing, and digestion. If fuel oil gets into the lungs (aspiration), serious and possibly permanent lung damage can occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>