<Document id="0001637" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003104.htm">
 
<Focus>Foot, leg, and ankle swelling</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0235439</CUI>
			<CUI>C0576177</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Swelling of the ankles - feet - legs</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ankle swelling</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Foot swelling</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leg swelling</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Edema - peripheral</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Peripheral edema</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001637-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Foot, leg, and ankle swelling ?</Question>
			<Answer>Painless swelling of the feet and ankles is a common problem, especially among older people. Abnormal buildup of fluid in the ankles, feet, and legs can cause swelling. This fluid buildup and swelling is called edema.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001637-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Foot, leg, and ankle swelling ?</Question>
			<Answer>Painless swelling may affect both legs and may include the calves or even the thighs. The effect of gravity makes the swelling most noticeable in the lower part of your body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001637-3" qtype="causes">What causes Foot, leg, and ankle swelling ?</Question>
			<Answer>Foot, leg, and ankle swelling is common when the person also: Is overweight, Has a  blood clot in the leg , Is older, Has a leg infection, Has  veins in the legs that cannot properly pump blood  back to the heart (called venous insufficiency, most often due to varicose veins),  Injury or surgery involving the leg, ankle, or foot can also cause swelling. Swelling may also occur after pelvic surgery, especially for cancer. Long airplane flights or car rides, as well as standing for long periods of time, often lead to some swelling in the feet and ankles. Swelling may occur in women who take estrogen, or during parts of the menstrual cycle. Most women have some swelling during pregnancy. More severe swelling during pregnancy may be a sign of  preeclampsia , a serious condition that includes high blood pressure and significant swelling.  Swollen legs may be a sign of  heart failure ,  kidney failure , or  liver failure . In these conditions, there is too much fluid in the body, and it collects in the legs. Certain medicines may also cause your legs to swell. Some of these are: Antidepressants, including MAO inhibitors and tricyclics, Blood pressure medicines called calcium channel blockers, Hormones, such as estrogen (in birth control pills or hormone replacement therapy) and testosterone, Steroids , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001637-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Foot, leg, and ankle swelling ?</Question>
			<Answer>Painless swelling may affect both legs and may include the calves or even the thighs. The effect of gravity makes the swelling most noticeable in the lower part of your body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001637-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Foot, leg, and ankle swelling ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911&#160;or the local emergency number if: You feel short of breath., You have  chest pain , especially if it feels like pressure or tightness. ,  Contact your provider right away if: You have  heart disease  or kidney disease and the swelling gets worse., You have a history of  liver disease  and now have swelling in your legs or abdomen., Your swollen foot or leg is red or warm to the touch., You have a  fever ., You are pregnant and have more than just mild swelling or have a sudden increase in swelling., You have new or worsened swelling in only one leg.,  Also contact your provider if self-care measures do not help or swelling gets worse.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001637-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Foot, leg, and ankle swelling ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>