<Document id="0001842" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000728.htm">
 
<Focus>Healthy food trends -- flaxseeds</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Healthy food trends -- flax meal</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Healthy food trends -- flax seeds</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Healthy food trends -- linseeds</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001842-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Healthy food trends -- flaxseeds</Question>
			<Answer>WHY THEY ARE GOOD FOR YOU Flaxseeds contain fiber, vitamins, minerals, protein, healthy plant-based fats, and antioxidants that help prevent cell damage. Flaxseeds are a good source of  soluble and insoluble fiber  which help keep your bowel movements regular and prevent constipation. Flaxseeds are also a good source of: Vitamins  B1 ,  Copper ,  Phosphorus ,  Magnesium , Manganese ,  These vitamins and minerals help support your energy, immune system, nervous system, bones, blood, heartbeat, and many other bodily processes. Flaxseeds are rich in omega-3s and omega-6s, which are essential fatty acids. These are substances that your body needs to function but cannot make on its own. You must get them from foods like seafood and flaxseeds. Oils, such as canola and soybean oil, contain the same fatty acids as flax oil. But flax oil contains more. Next to seafood, flax oil is one of the best sources of omega-3 fatty acids. Eating flaxseeds can help boost your omega-3s. However, the main type of omega-3 found in flaxseeds is less usable than the types found in seafood. Half of flaxseed calories come from fat. But this is healthy fat that helps boost your "good cholesterol." Small amounts will not prevent weight control. Consuming flaxseeds has been shown to reduce the blood cholesterol level. Researchers are looking at whether consuming more of the essential fatty acids found in flaxseeds will improve blood pressure, blood sugar, heart health, and other areas. If you plan to consume flaxseeds or flax oil on a regular basis, talk with your doctor. It may affect how certain medicines work. HOW THEY ARE PREPARED Flaxseeds can be added to or sprinkled on almost any food. Some cereals, such as Raisin Bran, now come with flaxseeds already mixed in. Grinding whole seeds will help you get the most nutrients. To add flaxseeds to your diet, add ground flax to: Pancakes, French toast, or other baking mixes, Smoothies, yogurt, or cereals, Soups, salads, or pasta dishes, Also use in place of breadcrumbs,  WHERE TO FIND FLAXSEEDS Flaxseeds may be purchased online or at any health food store. Many major grocery stores also carry flaxseeds in their natural or organic food sections. Simply buy a bag or container of flaxseeds in whole, crushed, or milled form, depending on the texture you like. You can also buy flaxseed oil.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>