<Document id="0001641" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000036.htm">
 
<Focus>Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0016542</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Obstructed airway</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Blocked airway</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001641-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you swallow a foreign object, it can get stuck in the gastrointestinal (GI) tract from the esophagus (swallowing tube) to the colon (large intestine). This can lead to a blockage or tear in the GI tract.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001641-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed ?</Question>
			<Answer> Children ages 6 months to 3 years are the age group most likely to swallow a foreign object. These items may include coins, marbles, pins, pencil erasers, buttons, beads, or other small items or foods. Adults can also swallow foreign objects due to intoxication, mental illness, or dementia. Older adults who have swallowing problems may accidentally swallow their dentures. Construction workers often swallow nails or screws, and tailors and dressmakers often swallow pins or buttons.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001641-3" qtype="causes">What causes Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed ?</Question>
			<Answer> Young children like to explore things with their mouths and may swallow an object on purpose or by accident. If the object passes through the food pipe and into the stomach without getting stuck, it will probably pass through the entire GI tract. Sharp, pointed, or caustic objects such as batteries can cause serious problems. Objects will often pass through the GI tract within a week. In most cases, the object passes through without harming the person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001641-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed ?</Question>
			<Answer> Symptoms include: Choking , Coughing,  Wheezing ,  Noisy breathing , No breathing or breathing trouble (respiratory distress), Chest, throat, or neck pain, Turning blue, red, or white in the face, Difficulty swallowing saliva,  Sometimes, only minor symptoms are seen at first. The object may be forgotten until symptoms such as inflammation or infection develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001641-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed ?</Question>
			<Answer> Children ages 6 months to 3 years are the age group most likely to swallow a foreign object. These items may include coins, marbles, pins, pencil erasers, buttons, beads, or other small items or foods. Adults can also swallow foreign objects due to intoxication, mental illness, or dementia. Older adults who have swallowing problems may accidentally swallow their dentures. Construction workers often swallow nails or screws, and tailors and dressmakers often swallow pins or buttons.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001641-6" qtype="considerations">What to do for Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed ?</Question>
			<Answer> Children ages 6 months to 3 years are the age group most likely to swallow a foreign object. These items may include coins, marbles, pins, pencil erasers, buttons, beads, or other small items or foods. Adults can also swallow foreign objects due to intoxication, mental illness, or dementia. Older adults who have swallowing problems may accidentally swallow their dentures. Construction workers often swallow nails or screws, and tailors and dressmakers often swallow pins or buttons.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001641-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider, or call 911 or the local emergency number if you think a child has swallowed a foreign object.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001641-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Foreign object - inhaled or swallowed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Preventive measures include: Cut food into small pieces for young children. Teach them how to chew well. , Discourage talking, laughing, or playing while food is in the mouth., Do not give potentially dangerous foods such as hot dogs, whole grapes, nuts, popcorn, food with bones, or hard candy to children under age 3 years., Keep small objects out of the reach of young children., Teach children to avoid placing foreign objects into their noses and other body openings., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>