<Document id="0001244" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000993.htm">
 
<Focus>Diskitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0012624</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Disk inflammation</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001244-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Diskitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diskitis is swelling (inflammation) and irritation of the space between the bones of the spine (intervertebral disk space).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001244-2" qtype="causes">What causes Diskitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diskitis is an uncommon condition. It is usually seen in children younger than 10 years and in adults around 50 years of age. Men are more affected than women. Diskitis can be caused by an infection from bacteria or a virus. It can also be caused by inflammation, such as from autoimmune diseases. Autoimmune diseases are conditions in which the immune system mistakenly attacks certain cells in the body. Disks in the neck and low back are most commonly affected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001244-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Diskitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include any of the following: Abdominal pain , Back pain, Difficulty getting up and standing, Fever (typically 102&#176;F or 38.9&#176;C or lower), Increased  curvature of the back , Irritability, Neck pain, Sweating at night , Recent flu-like symptoms, Refusal to sit up, stand, or walk (younger child), Stiffness in back , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001244-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Diskitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask about the symptoms. Tests that may be ordered include any of the following: Bone scan , 
   Complete blood count ( CBC ),  ESR &#160;or&#160; C-reactive protein  to measure inflammation,  MRI  of the spine,  X-ray  of the spine , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001244-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Diskitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goal is to treat the cause of the inflammation or infection and reduce pain. Treatment may involve any of the following: Antibiotics if the infection is caused by bacteria, Anti-inflammatory medicines if the cause is an autoimmune disease, Pain medicines such as NSAIDs, Bed rest or a brace to keep the back from moving, Surgery if other methods don't work, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001244-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Diskitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children with an infection should fully recover after treatment. In rare cases, chronic back pain persists. In cases of autoimmune disease, the outcome depends on the underlying condition. These are often chronic illnesses that need long-term medical care.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001244-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Diskitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Persistent back pain (rare), Side effects of medicines, Worsening pain with numbness and weakness in your limbs, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001244-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Diskitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you or your child has back pain that does not go away, or problems with standing and walking that seem unusual for the child's age.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>