<Document id="0001634" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003183.htm">
 
<Focus>Foot pain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0016512</CUI>
			<CUI>C2016948</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pain - foot</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001634-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Foot pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pain or discomfort can be felt anywhere in the foot. You may have pain in the  heel , toes, arch, instep, or bottom of foot (sole).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001634-2" qtype="causes">What causes Foot pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Foot pain may be due to: Aging, Being on your feet for long periods of time, Being  overweight , A foot deformity that you were born with or develops later, Injury, Shoes that fit poorly or do not have much cushioning, Too much walking or other sports activity, Trauma ,  The following can cause foot pain: Arthritis  and  gout  -- Common in the big toe, which becomes red, swollen, and very tender.,  Broken bones .,  Bunions  -- A bump at the base of the big toe from wearing narrow-toed shoes or from abnormal bone alignment.,  Calluses and corns  -- Thickened skin from rubbing or pressure. Calluses are on the balls of the feet or heels. Corns appear on the top of your toes.,  Hammer toes  -- Toes that curl downward into a claw-like position.,  Fallen arches  -- Also called flat feet.,  Morton neuroma  -- A thickening of nerve tissue between the toes., Nerve damage from diabetes.,  Plantar fasciitis ., Plantar warts -- Sores on the soles of your feet due to pressure.,  Sprains ., Stress fracture., Nerve problems., Heel spurs or Achilles tendinitis. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001634-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Foot pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001634-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Foot pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You have sudden, severe foot pain., Your foot pain began following an injury, especially if your foot is bleeding or bruising, or you cannot put weight on it., You have redness or swelling of the joint, an open sore or ulcer on your foot, or a fever., You have pain in your foot and have  diabetes  or a disease that affects blood flow., Your foot does not feel better after using at-home treatments for 1 to 2 weeks., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001634-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Foot pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001634-6" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Foot pain ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>