<Document id="0001996" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001531.htm">
 
<Focus>Histrionic personality disorder</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019681</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001996-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Histrionic personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Histrionic personality disorder is a mental condition in which people act in a very emotional and dramatic way that draws attention to themselves.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001996-2" qtype="causes">What causes Histrionic personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Causes of histrionic personality disorder are unknown. Genes and early childhood events may be responsible. It is diagnosed more often in women than in men. Doctors believe that more men may have the disorder than are diagnosed. Histrionic personality disorder usually begins by late teens or early 20s.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001996-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Histrionic personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with this disorder are usually able to function at a high level and can be successful socially and at work. Symptoms include: Acting or looking overly seductive, Being easily influenced by other people, Being overly concerned with their looks, Being overly dramatic and emotional, Being overly sensitive to criticism or disapproval, Believing that relationships are more intimate than they actually are, Blaming failure or disappointment on others, Constantly seeking reassurance or approval, Having a low tolerance for frustration or delayed gratification, Needing to be the center of attention ( self-centeredness ), Quickly changing emotions, which may seem shallow to others, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001996-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Histrionic personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Histrionic personality disorder is diagnosed based on a psychological evaluation. The health care provider will consider how long and how severe the person's symptoms have been. The provider can diagnose histrionic personality disorder by looking at the person's: Behavior, Overall appearance, Psychological evaluation , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001996-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Histrionic personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with this condition often seek treatment when they have depression or anxiety from failed romantic relationships or other conflicts with people. Medicine may help the symptoms. Talk therapy is the best treatment for the condition itself.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001996-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Histrionic personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Histrionic personality disorder can improve with talk therapy and sometimes medicines. Left untreated, it can cause problems in people's personal lives and prevent them from doing their best at work.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001996-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Histrionic personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Histrionic personality disorder may affect a person's social or romantic relationships. The person may be unable to cope with losses or failures. The person may change jobs often because of boredom and not being able to deal with frustration. They may crave new things and excitement, which leads to risky situations. All of these factors may lead to a higher chance of  depression &#160;or suicidal thoughts.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001996-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Histrionic personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>See your provider or mental health professional if you or someone you know has symptoms of histrionic personality disorder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>