<Document id="0001900" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000646.htm">
 
<Focus>Helping your teen with depression</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0349217</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011570</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011581</CUI>
			<CUI>C0344315</CUI>
			<CUI>C1579931</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001900-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Helping your teen with depression ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your  teen's depression  may be treated with talk therapy, antidepressant medicines, or a combination of these. Learn about what is available and what you can do at home to help your teen.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001900-2" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Helping your teen with depression ?</Question>
			<Answer>You, your teen, and your teen's health care provider should discuss what might help your teen the most. The most effective treatments for depression are: Talk therapy, Antidepressant medicines ,  If your teen has a problem with drugs or alcohol, discuss this with the provider. If your teen has severe depression or is at risk for suicide, your teen may need to stay in the hospital for treatment. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001900-4" qtype="information">What is (are) Helping your teen with depression ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your  teen's depression  may be treated with talk therapy, antidepressant medicines, or a combination of these. Learn about what is available and what you can do at home to help your teen.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001900-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Helping your teen with depression ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you or someone you know is thinking about suicide, call or text 988 or chat  988lifeline.org . You can also call 1-800-273-8255 (1-800-273-TALK). The 988 Suicide and Crisis Lifeline provides free and confidential support 24/7, anytime day or night. You can also call 911 or the local emergency number or go to the hospital emergency room. DO NOT delay. If someone you know has attempted suicide, call 911 or the local emergency number right away. DO NOT leave the person alone, even after you have called for help. Warning signs of suicide  include: Giving possessions away, Personality change, Risk-taking behavior, Threat of suicide or plans to hurt oneself, Withdrawal, urge to be alone, isolation , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>