<Document id="0001897" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000814.htm">
 
<Focus>Help your teen cope with stress</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0038435</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Adolescents - stress</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001897-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Help your teen cope with stress ?</Question>
			<Answer>Teenagers face a variety of stresses. For some, it is trying to balance a part-time job with mountains of homework. Others may have to help out at home or deal with bullying or peer pressure. Whatever the cause, starting down the road to adulthood has its own special challenges. You can help your teen by learning to recognize the signs of stress and teaching your child healthy ways to deal with it.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001897-2" qtype="causes">What causes Help your teen cope with stress ?</Question>
			<Answer>Common sources of stress in teens include: Worrying about schoolwork or grades, Juggling responsibilities, such as school and work or sports, Having problems with friends, bullying, or peer group pressures, Becoming sexually active or feeling pressure to do so, Changing schools, moving, or dealing with housing problems or homelessness, Having negative thoughts about themselves, Going through body changes, in both  boys  and  girls , Seeing their parents go through a divorce or separation, Having financial problems in the family, Living in an unsafe home or neighborhood, Figuring out what to do after high school, Getting into college , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001897-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Help your teen cope with stress ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>