<Document id="0001598" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001375.htm">
 
<Focus>Fish tapeworm infection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0012561</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Diphyllobothriasis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001598-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fish tapeworm infection is an intestinal infection with a parasite found in fish.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001598-2" qtype="causes">What causes Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>The fish tapeworm ( Diphyllobothrium latum ) is the largest parasite that infects humans. Humans become infected when they eat raw or undercooked freshwater fish that contain fish tapeworm cysts. The infection is seen in many areas where humans eat uncooked or undercooked freshwater fish from rivers or lakes, including: 
 Africa
 , 
 Eastern Europe
 , 
 North and South America
 , 
 Scandinavia
 , 
 Some Asian countries
 ,  After a person has eaten infected fish, the worm larva begins to grow in the intestine. Larvae are fully grown in 3 to 6 weeks. The adult worm, which is segmented, attaches to the wall of the intestine. The tapeworm may reach a length of 30 feet (9 meters). Eggs are formed in each segment of the worm and are passed in the stool. Sometimes, parts of the worm may also be passed in the stool. The tapeworm absorbs the nutrition from food that the infected person eats. This may lead to  vitamin B12  deficiency and anemia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001598-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people who are infected have no symptoms. If symptoms do occur, they may include: Abdominal discomfort or pain, Diarrhea, Weakness, Weight loss, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001598-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>People who are infected sometimes pass segments of worm in their stools. These segments can be seen in the stool. Tests may include: Complete blood count , including  differential , Blood tests to determine the cause of anemia, if present, Vitamin B12 level,  Stool exam  for worm eggs and parasites , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001598-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>You will receive medicines to fight the parasites. You take these medicines by mouth, usually in a single dose. The drug of choice for tapeworm infections is praziquantel. Niclosamide can also be used. If needed, your health care provider will prescribe vitamin B12 injections or supplements to treat vitamin B12 deficiency and anemia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001598-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fish tapeworms can be treated with a single treatment dose. There are no lasting effects.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001598-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Untreated, fish tapeworm infection may cause the following: Anemia caused by vitamin B12 deficiency (megaloblastic anemia),  Intestinal blockage  (rare), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001598-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You have noticed a worm or segments of a worm in your stool, You have symptoms of anemia, Any family members are diagnosed with a fish tapeworm infection, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001598-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Fish tapeworm infection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Measures you can take to prevent tapeworm infection include: Do not eat raw or undercooked fish., Cook fish at 145&#176;F (63&#176;C) for at least 4 minutes. Use a food thermometer to measure the thickest part of the fish., Freeze fish at -4&#176;F (-20&#176;C) or below for 7 days, or at -31&#176;F (-35&#176;C) or below for 15 hours., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>