<Document id="0001844" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000730.htm">
 
<Focus>Healthy food trends -- microgreens</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001844-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Healthy food trends -- microgreens</Question>
			<Answer>WHY THEY ARE GOOD FOR YOU Microgreens are packed with nutrition. Many of the tiny microgreens are 4 to 6 times higher in vitamins and antioxidants than their adult forms. Antioxidants are substances that help to prevent cell damage. The following microgreens have higher amounts of certain vitamins than their adult forms: Red cabbage --  Vitamin C , Green daikon radish --  Vitamin E , Cilantro -- Carotenoids (antioxidants that can turn into  vitamin A ), Garnet amaranth --  Vitamin K ,  Eating lots of fruits and vegetables in any form is good for you and including microgreens in your diet can give you a nutrient boost in just a few calories. A healthy diet rich in fruits and vegetables may help reduce the risk for cancer and other chronic diseases. If you take blood-thinning medicine, such as the anticoagulant warfarin, you may need to limit vitamin K foods. Vitamin K can affect how this medicine works. HOW THEY ARE PREPARED Microgreens can be eaten in several simple ways. Be sure to rinse them thoroughly first. Eat them raw. Add them to salads and drizzle with a little lemon juice or dressing. They are also tasty on their own., Garnish meals with raw microgreens. Add them to your breakfast plate. Top your fish, chicken, or baked potato with microgreens., Use them in sandwiches or wraps., Toss them in soups, stir fries, and pasta dishes., Add them to a fruit drink or cocktail.,  If you grow your own microgreens or purchase them in soil, snip the healthy stems and leaves above the soil when they are 7 to 14 days old. Eat them fresh or store them in the refrigerator. WHERE TO FIND MICROGREENS Microgreens are available at your local health food store or natural foods market. Look near the lettuce for packages of greens with tiny stems and leaves (just a couple inches, or 5 cm, in length). Check your local farmers' market as well. Microgreen growing kits can be ordered online or found in some kitchen stores. The selections may change from time to time so keep an eye out for your favorites. They are a bit pricey, so you may want to try growing them in your kitchen window. Once cut, they can last in the refrigerator for 5 to 7 days, sometimes longer depending on the type.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>