<Document id="0001845" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000731.htm">
 
<Focus>Healthy food trends -- quinoa</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Healthy food trends -- goosefoot</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001845-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Healthy food trends -- quinoa</Question>
			<Answer>WHY IT IS GOOD FOR YOU Quinoa is rich in  protein . It has almost twice the amount of protein found in brown rice, as well as a bit more  fiber  and  iron . Quinoa is a complete protein. This means that it contains all nine essential amino acids (the building blocks of proteins) that your body needs but cannot make on its own. You need protein in your diet to help your body repair cells and make new ones. Protein is also important for growth and development during childhood, adolescence, and pregnancy. Quinoa's protein content makes it a good option in place of rice and other grains, which are generally higher in carbohydrates and lower in protein, especially for people with diabetes. Quinoa is a good source of magnesium, which you need for muscle function and many other bodily functions. It offers many other vitamins and minerals as well. Quinoa has several antioxidants, like those found in berries. Antioxidants help prevent cell damage. This is important for healing, as well as prevention of disease and aging. If you have celiac disease, or follow a gluten-free diet, quinoa is a great option since it does not contain gluten. Quinoa contains heart-healthy fats that can help boost your "good cholesterol." It is filling and packs a nutritious punch in a small amount. HOW IT IS PREPARED Quinoa can be cooked and eaten in many ways. You will need to simmer it in water like rice. Add 1 part quinoa to 2 parts water or stock and simmer uncovered until the water has been absorbed, for about 15 minutes. When quinoa is finished cooking, you will see curly threads around each grain. Remove from the stove, cover the pot, and let your quinoa rest for five minutes before serving. To add quinoa to your diet: Sprinkle cooked quinoa on salad, soups, or pasta dishes., Make it a side dish. Think of quinoa as your new rice. Combine cooked quinoa with herbs, beans, vegetables, and seasonings and serve with your meal. Add a healthy protein like chicken or fish., Use quinoa flour instead of wheat flour in your muffins, pancakes, cookies, or any time you bake.,  Quinoa reheats well. Cook a big batch and store it in the refrigerator for up to a week. You will have a nutritious side dish ready for several meals as you need it. WHERE TO FIND QUINOA Most grocery stores carry bags of quinoa in their rice section or in their natural or organic food sections. You can also purchase quinoa flour, pasta, and cereal products. Quinoa may also be purchased online or at any health food store. There are over many varieties of quinoa. You will most likely see yellow/ivory, red, or black quinoa in stores. You can store uncooked quinoa in your pantry for several months. Use an airtight container or bag for storage. RECIPE There are many delicious recipes using quinoa. Here is one you can try. Quinoa-Stuffed Tomatoes (Yields 4 servings. Serving size: 1 tomato, &#190; cup (180 milliliters, mL) stuffing Ingredients 4 medium (2&#189; inches, or 6 centimeters) tomatoes, rinsed, 1 tablespoon (tbsp), or 15 mL, olive oil, 2 tbsp (30 mL) red onions, peeled and chopped, 1 cup (240 mL) cooked mixed vegetables -- such as peppers, corn, carrots, or peas (leftover friendly), 1 cup (240 mL) quinoa, rinsed, 1 cup (240 mL) low-sodium chicken broth, &#189; ripe avocado, peeled and diced (see tip), &#188; teaspoon (tsp) or 1 mL ground black pepper, 1 tbsp (15 mL) fresh parsley, rinsed, dried, and chopped (or 1 tsp, or 5 mL, dried),  Instructions Preheat oven to 350&#186;F (176.6&#186;C)., Cut off the tops of the tomatoes and hollow out the insides. (The pulp can be saved for use in tomato soup or sauce, or salsa.) Set tomatoes aside., Heat oil in a saucepan over medium-high heat. Add onions, and cook until they begin to soften, for about 1 to 2 minutes., Add cooked vegetables, and heat through, about another 1 to 2 minutes., Add quinoa, and cook gently until it smells good, about 2 minutes., Add chicken broth and bring to a boil. Reduce the heat and cover the pan. Cook until the quinoa has absorbed all the liquid and is fully cooked, about 7 to 10 minutes., When the quinoa is cooked, remove the lid, and gently fluff quinoa with a fork. Stir in avocado, pepper, and parsley., Carefully stuff about &#190; cup of quinoa into each tomato., Place tomatoes on a baking sheet, and bake for about 15 to 20 minutes, or until tomatoes are hot throughout (tomatoes may be stuffed in advance and baked later)., Serve immediately.,  Nutrition facts Calories: 299, Total fat: 10 g, Saturated fat: 1 g, Sodium: 64 mg, Total fiber: 8 g, Protein: 10 g, Carbohydrates: 46 g,  Source:  National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute. Deliciously healthy family meals .  healthyeating.nhlbi.nih.gov/pdfs/KTB_Family_Cookbook_2010.pdf</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>