<Document id="0001157" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001533.htm">
 
<Focus>Developmental coordination disorder</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011757</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001157-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Developmental coordination disorder is a childhood disorder. It leads to poor coordination and clumsiness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001157-2" qtype="causes">What causes Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>A small number of school-age children have some kind of developmental coordination disorder. Children with this disorder may: Have trouble holding objects, Have an unsteady walk, Run into other children, Trip over their own feet ,  Developmental coordination disorder may occur alone or with  attention deficit hyperactivity disorder &#160;(ADHD). It may also occur with other learning disorders, such as communication disorders or  disorder of written expression .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001157-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children with developmental coordination disorder have problems with motor coordination compared to other children the same age. Some common symptoms include: Clumsiness , Delays in sitting up, crawling, and walking, Problems with sucking and swallowing during first year of life, Problems with gross motor coordination (for example, jumping, hopping, or standing on&#160;one foot), Problems with visual or fine motor coordination (for example, writing, using scissors, tying shoelaces, or tapping&#160;one finger to another), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001157-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Physical causes and other types of learning disabilities must be ruled out before the diagnosis can be confirmed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001157-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Physical education and perceptual motor training (combining movement with tasks that require thinking, like math or reading) are the best ways to treat coordination disorder. Using a computer to take notes may help children who have trouble writing. Children with developmental coordination disorder are more likely to be overweight than other children their age. Encouraging physical activity is important to prevent obesity.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001157-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a child does depends on the severity of the disorder. The disorder does not get worse over time. It most often&#160;continues into adulthood.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001157-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Developmental coordination disorder can lead to: Learning problems, Low self-esteem resulting from poor ability at sports and teasing by other children, Repeated injuries, Weight gain as a result of not wanting to participate in physical activities, such as sports , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001157-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you are concerned about your child's development.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001157-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Developmental coordination disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Families who are affected by this condition should try to recognize problems early and have them treated. Early treatment will lead to future success.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>