<Document id="0001289" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000578.htm">
 
<Focus>Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1096070</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Immune hemolytic anemia secondary to drugs</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Anemia - immune hemolytic - secondary to drugs</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001289-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Drug-induced immune  hemolytic anemia  is a blood disorder that occurs when a medicine triggers the body's defense (immune) system to attack its own red blood cells. This causes red blood cells to break down earlier than normal, a process called hemolysis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001289-2" qtype="causes">What causes Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anemia is a condition in which the body does not have enough healthy red blood cells. Red blood cells provide oxygen to body tissues. Normally, red blood cells last for about 120 days in the body. In people with hemolytic anemia, red blood cells in the blood are destroyed earlier than normal. In some cases, a drug can cause the immune system to mistake your own red blood cells for foreign substances. The body responds by making antibodies to attack the body's own red blood cells. The antibodies attach to red blood cells and cause them to break down too early. Drugs that can cause this type of hemolytic anemia include: Cephalosporins (a class of antibiotics), most common cause, Dapsone, Levodopa, Levofloxacin, Methyldopa, Nitrofurantoin, Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), Penicillin and its derivatives, Phenazopyridine (Pyridium), Quinidine ,  Drug-induced hemolytic anemia is rare in children.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001289-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include any of the following:  Dark urine , Fatigue, Pale skin color, Rapid heart rate, Shortness of breath, Yellow skin and whites of the eyes ( jaundice ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001289-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam may show an enlarged spleen. You may have blood and urine tests to help diagnose this condition. Tests may include: Absolute  reticulocyte count  to determine if red blood cells are being created in the bone marrow at an appropriate rate,  Direct or indirect Coombs test  to check if there are antibodies against red blood cells that are causing red blood cells to die too early,  Indirect bilirubin  levels to check for jaundice,  Red blood cell count ,  Serum haptoglobin  to check if red blood cells are being destroyed too early,  Lactate dehydrogenase  level, which increases with red cell destruction,  Urine hemoglobin  to check for hemolysis, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001289-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Stopping the drug that is causing the problem may relieve or control the symptoms. You may need to take a medicine called prednisone to suppress the immune response against the red blood cells. Special blood transfusions may be needed to treat severe symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001289-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome is good for most people if they stop taking the drug that is causing the problem.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001289-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Death caused by severe anemia is rare.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001289-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>See your health care provider if you have symptoms of this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0001289-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Drug-induced immune hemolytic anemia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Avoid the drug that caused this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>