<Document id="0001492" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003974.htm">
 
<Focus>External incontinence devices</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0021167</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Condom catheter</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Incontinence devices</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fecal collection devices</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001492-1" qtype="information">What is (are) External incontinence devices ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are several products available. The features of these different products are listed below. FECAL INCONTINENCE DEVICES There are many types of products for managing long-term  diarrhea  or  fecal incontinence . These devices have a drainable pouch attached to an adhesive wafer. This wafer has a hole cut through the center that fits over the anal opening (rectum). If put on properly, a fecal incontinence device may stay in place for 24 hours. It is important to remove the pouch if any stool has leaked. Liquid stool can irritate the skin. Always clean the skin and apply a new pouch if any leakage has occurred. The device should be applied to clean, dry skin: Your health care provider may prescribe a protective skin barrier. This barrier is usually a paste. You apply the barrier to the skin before attaching the device. You can put the paste in the skin folds of the buttocks to prevent liquid stool from leaking through this area., Spread the buttocks apart, exposing the anus, and apply the wafer and pouch. It may help to have someone help you. The device should cover the skin with no gaps or creases., You may need to trim the hair around the anus to help the wafer stick better to the skin. ,  An enterostomal therapy nurse or skin care nurse can provide you with a list of products that are available in your area. URINARY INCONTINENCE DEVICES Urine collection devices are mainly used by men with  urinary incontinence . Women are generally treated with medicines and disposable undergarments. The systems for men most often consist of a pouch or condom-like device. This device is securely placed around the  penis . This is often called a condom catheter. A drainage tube is attached at the tip of the device to remove urine. This tube empties into a storage bag, which can be emptied directly into the toilet. Condom catheters are most effective when applied to a clean, dry penis. You may need to trim the hair around the pubic area for better grip of the device. You must change the device at least every other day to protect the skin and prevent  urinary tract infections . Make sure the condom device fits snugly, but not too tightly. Skin damage may occur if it is too tight.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0001492-2" qtype="information">What is (are) External incontinence devices ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are several products available. The features of these different products are listed below. FECAL INCONTINENCE DEVICES There are many types of products for managing long-term  diarrhea  or  fecal incontinence . These devices have a drainable pouch attached to an adhesive wafer. This wafer has a hole cut through the center that fits over the anal opening (rectum). If put on properly, a fecal incontinence device may stay in place for 24 hours. It is important to remove the pouch if any stool has leaked. Liquid stool can irritate the skin. Always clean the skin and apply a new pouch if any leakage has occurred. The device should be applied to clean, dry skin: Your health care provider may prescribe a protective skin barrier. This barrier is usually a paste. You apply the barrier to the skin before attaching the device. You can put the paste in the skin folds of the buttocks to prevent liquid stool from leaking through this area., Spread the buttocks apart, exposing the anus, and apply the wafer and pouch. It may help to have someone help you. The device should cover the skin with no gaps or creases., You may need to trim the hair around the anus to help the wafer stick better to the skin. ,  An enterostomal therapy nurse or skin care nurse can provide you with a list of products that are available in your area. URINARY INCONTINENCE DEVICES Urine collection devices are mainly used by men with  urinary incontinence . Women are generally treated with medicines and disposable undergarments. The systems for men most often consist of a pouch or condom-like device. This device is securely placed around the  penis . This is often called a condom catheter. A drainage tube is attached at the tip of the device to remove urine. This tube empties into a storage bag, which can be emptied directly into the toilet. Condom catheters are most effective when applied to a clean, dry penis. You may need to trim the hair around the pubic area for better grip of the device. You must change the device at least every other day to protect the skin and prevent  urinary tract infections . Make sure the condom device fits snugly, but not too tightly. Skin damage may occur if it is too tight.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>