<Document id="0001838" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007463.htm">
 
<Focus>Health screening - women - over age 65</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Health maintenance visit - women - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Physical exam - women - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Yearly exam - women - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Checkup - women - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Women's health - over age 65</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Preventive care exam - women - over age 65</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001838-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Health screening - women - over age 65</Question>
			<Answer>Even if you feel fine, you should still see your provider for regular checkups. These visits can help you avoid problems in the future. For example, the only way to find out if you have  high blood pressure  is to have it checked regularly. High blood sugar and  high cholesterol  levels also may not have any symptoms in the early stages. A simple blood test can check for these conditions. There are specific times when you should see your provider or receive specific health screenings. The US Preventive Services Task Force publishes a list of recommended screenings. Below are screening guidelines for women age 65 and older. BLOOD PRESSURE SCREENING Have your  blood pressure  checked at least once every year. Watch for blood pressure screenings in your area. Ask your provider if you can stop in to have your blood pressure checked. You can also check your blood pressure using the automated machines at local grocery stores and pharmacies. Ask your provider if you need your blood pressure checked more often if: You have diabetes,  heart disease ,  kidney problems , or are overweight or have certain other health conditions, You have a first-degree relative with high blood pressure, You are Black, Your blood pressure top number is from 120 to 129 mm Hg, or the bottom number is from 70 to 79 mm Hg,  BREAST CANCER SCREENING Women may do a monthly breast self-exam. However, experts do not agree about the benefits of breast self-exams in finding  breast cancer  or saving lives. Talk to your provider about what is best for you., Your provider may do a clinical breast exam during your preventive exam. Experts do not agree on the benefit of a breast examination., Women up to age 75 should have a  mammogram  every 1 to 2 years, depending on their risk factors, to check for breast cancer., Experts do not agree on the benefits of having a mammogram for women age 75 and older. Some do not recommend having mammograms after this age. Others recommend mammography for women in good health. Talk to your provider about what is best for you.,  CERVICAL CANCER SCREENING After age 65, most women who have not been diagnosed with cervical cancer or precancer can stop having screening tests, as long as: They have had 3 consecutive negative Pap test results or 2 consecutive negative PAP and HPV tests results within 10 years, The most recent test occurred within 5 years,  CHOLESTEROL SCREENING If your cholesterol level is normal, have it rechecked at least every 5 years. You should have repeat testing sooner if: Changes occur in your lifestyle (including weight gain and diet), You have high cholesterol, diabetes, heart disease, kidney problems, or certain other health conditions,  COLORECTAL CANCER SCREENING Until age 75, you should have  screening for colorectal cancer  on a regular basis. If you are age 76 or older, you should ask your doctor if you should receive screening. Several tests are available for colorectal cancer screening: A stool-based fecal occult blood (gFOBT) or fecal immunochemical test ( FIT ) every year, A stool sDNA-FIT test every 1 to 3 years,  Flexible sigmoidoscopy  every 5 years or every 10 years with stool testing with FIT done every year, CT colonography ( virtual colonoscopy ) every 5 years,  Colonoscopy  every 10 years ,  You may need a colonoscopy more often if you have risk factors for colon cancer, including: Ulcerative colitis , A personal or family history of  colorectal cancer , A history of growths in your colon called  adenomatous polyps ,  DENTAL EXAM  Go to the dentist once or twice every year for an exam and cleaning. Your dentist will evaluate if you have a need for more frequent visits. ,  DIABETES SCREENING You should be screened for  diabetes  every 3 years. You may be tested more often if you have other risk factors for diabetes, such as: A first degree relative with diabetes, You are overweight or have obesity, high blood pressure, prediabetes, or a history of heart disease,  EYE EXAM  Have an eye exam every 1 to 2 years. Your provider may recommend more frequent eye exams if you have vision problems or glaucoma risk., Have an eye exam that includes an examination of your retina (back of your eye) at least every year if you have diabetes.,  HEARING TEST  Have your hearing tested if you have symptoms of  hearing loss . ,  IMMUNIZATIONS Commonly needed vaccines include: Flu  shot : get one every year,  COVID-19 vaccine:  ask your doctor what is best for you,  Pneumococcal vaccines : you should receive this vaccine,  Shingles (herpes zoster) vaccine:  at or after age 50,  Tetanus-diphtheria and acellular pertussis (Tdap) vaccine : have as one of your tetanus-diphtheria vaccines if you did not receive it as an adolescent,  Tetanus-diphtheria : have a booster (or Tdap) every 10 years,  INFECTIOUS DISEASE SCREENING Screening for hepatitis C:  All adults ages 18 to 79 should get a one-time test for  hepatitis C .,  Screening for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV):  All people ages 15 to 65 should get a one-time test for  HIV ,  Depending on your lifestyle and medical history, you may need to be screened for infections such as syphilis, chlamydia, and other infections. LUNG CANCER SCREENING You should have an annual screening for  lung cancer  with low-dose computed tomography (LDCT) if: You are age 50 to 80 years AND, You have a 20 pack-year smoking history AND, You currently smoke or have quit within the past 15 years,  OSTEOPOROSIS SCREENING All women age 65 or older should have a  bone density test  (DEXA scan)., Ask your provider which exercises or other interventions can help prevent  osteoporosis  or bone fractures.,  PHYSICAL EXAMS All adults should visit their provider from time to time, even if they are healthy. The purpose of these visits is to: Screen for diseases, Assess risk of future medical problems, Encourage a healthy lifestyle, Update vaccinations and other preventive care services, Maintain a relationship with a provider in case of an illness,  In addition: Your blood pressure should be checked at least every year., Your height, weight, and body mass index (BMI) should be checked at every exam.,  During the exam, your provider will ask questions about: Depression  and anxiety, Diet and exercise including exercises to improve your balance and reduce your risk of falling, Alcohol and tobacco use, Safety, such as use of seat belts and smoke detectors and intimate partner violence, Whether you have had any falls or are afraid of falling, Whether you have symptoms of urinary incontinence, Your medicines and risk for interactions,  SKIN EXAM Your provider may check your skin for signs of  skin cancer , especially if you're at high risk., People at high risk include those who have had skin cancer before, have close relatives with skin cancer, or have a weakened immune system., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>