<Document id="0002784" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001613.htm">
 
<Focus>Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS)</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0027877</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Lipofuscinoses</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Batten disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Jansky-Bielschowsky</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Kufs' disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spielmeyer-Vogt</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002784-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCL) refers to a group of rare disorders of the nerve cells. NCL is passed down through families (inherited). These are the three main types of NCL: Adult (Kufs or Parry disease), Juvenile (Batten disease), Late infantile (Jansky-Bielschowsky disease), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002784-2" qtype="causes">What causes Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>NCL involves the buildup of an abnormal material called lipofuscin in the brain. NCL is thought to be caused by problems with the brain's ability to remove and recycle proteins. Lipofuscinoses are inherited as  autosomal recessive  traits. This means each parent passes on a nonworking copy of the gene for the child to develop the condition. Only one adult subtype of NCL is inherited as autosomal dominant trait.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002784-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of NCL include: Abnormally increased muscle tone or spasm, Blindness or vision problems, Dementia, Lack of muscle coordination, Intellectual disability, Movement disorder, Loss of speech , Seizures, Unsteady walk, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002784-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>The disorder may be seen at birth, but it is usually diagnosed much later in childhood. Tests include: Autofluorescence (a light technique), EEG (measures electrical activity in the brain), Electron microscopy of a skin biopsy, Electroretinogram (an eye test), Genetic testing, MRI or CT scans of the brain, Tissue biopsy
   , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002784-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no cure for NCL disorders. Treatment depends on the type of NCL and extent of symptoms. Your health care provider may prescribe muscle relaxants to control irritability and sleep disturbances. Medicines may also be prescribed to control seizures and anxiety. A person with NCL may need lifelong assistance and care.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002784-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>More information and support for people with NCL condition and their families can be found at: Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center --  rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/10973/adult-neuronal-ceroid-lipofuscinosis , Batten Disease Support and Research Association --  bdsrafoundation.org , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002784-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>The younger the person is when the disease appears, the greater the risk for disability and early death. Those who develop the disease early can have vision problems that progress to blindness and problems with mental function that get worse. If the disease starts in the first year of life, death by age 10 is likely. If the disease occurs in adulthood, symptoms will be milder, with no vision loss and a normal life expectancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002784-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>These complications can occur: Vision impairment or blindness (with the early-onset forms of the disease), Mental impairment, ranging from severe developmental delays at birth to  dementia  later in life, Rigid muscles (due to severe problems with the nerves that control muscle tone) ,  The person may become totally dependent on others for help with daily activities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002784-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if your child shows symptoms of blindness or intellectual disability.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0002784-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Neuronal ceroid lipofuscinoses (NCLS) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling is recommended if your family has a known history of NCL. Prenatal tests, or a test called preimplantation genetic diagnosis (PGD), may be available, depending on the specific type of disease. In PGD, an embryo is tested for abnormalities before it is implanted in the woman's womb.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>