<Document id="0002725" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001424.htm">
 
<Focus>Myotonia congenita</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2936781</CUI>
			<CUI>C0027127</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Thomsen's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Becker's disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002725-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>Myotonia congenita is an inherited condition that affects muscle relaxation. It is congenital, meaning that it is present from birth. It occurs more frequently in northern Scandinavia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002725-2" qtype="causes">What causes Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>Myotonia congenita is caused by a genetic change (mutation). It is passed down from either one or both parents to their children (inherited). Myotonia congenita is caused by a problem in the part of the muscle cells that are needed for muscles to relax. Abnormal repeated electrical signals occur in the muscles, causing a stiffness called myotonia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002725-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>The hallmark of this condition is myotonia. This means the muscles are unable to quickly relax after contracting. For example, after a handshake, the person is only very slowly able to open and pull away their hand. Early symptoms may include: 
  Difficulty swallowing
  , 
  Gagging
  , 
  Stiff movements that improve when they are repeated
  , Shortness of breath or tightening of the chest at the beginning of exercise, Frequent falls, Difficulty opening eyes after forcing them closed or crying,  Children with myotonia congenita often look muscular and well-developed. They may not have symptoms of myotonia congenita until age 2 or 3.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002725-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider may ask if there is a family history of myotonia congenita. Tests include: Electromyography  (EMG, a test of the electrical activity of the muscles) and nerve conduction studies (NCS), Genetic testing,  Muscle biopsy , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002725-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mexiletine is a medicine that treats symptoms of myotonia congenita. Other treatments include: Phenytoin, Procainamide, Quinine (rarely used now, due to side effects), Tocainide, Carbamazepine, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002725-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with this condition can do well. Symptoms only occur when a movement is first started. After a few repetitions, the muscle relaxes and the movement becomes normal.  Some people experience the opposite effect (paradoxical myotonia) and get worse with movement. Their symptoms may improve later in life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002725-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Aspiration pneumonia  caused by swallowing difficulties, Frequent choking, gagging, or trouble swallowing in an infant, Long-term (chronic) joint problems, Weakness of the abdominal muscles , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002725-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if your child has symptoms of myotonia congenita.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002725-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Myotonia congenita ?</Question>
			<Answer>Couples who want to have children and who have a family history of myotonia congenita should consider genetic counseling.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>