<Document id="0002244" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000742.htm">
 
<Focus>Ischemic ulcers - self-care</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0265000</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Arterial ulcers - self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Arterial insufficiency ulcer self-care</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ischemic wounds - self-care</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002244-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ischemic ulcers - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ischemic ulcers (wounds) can occur when there is  poor blood flow in your legs . Ischemic means reduced blood flow to an area of the body. Poor blood flow causes cells to die and damages tissue. Most ischemic ulcers occur on the feet and legs. These types of wounds can be slow to heal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002244-2" qtype="causes">What causes Ischemic ulcers - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Narrowed arteries ( atherosclerosis ) are the most common cause of ischemic ulcers. Narrowed arteries prevent a healthy supply of blood from flowing to the legs. This means that the tissues in your legs do not get enough nutrients and oxygen., The lack of nutrients causes cells to die, damaging the tissue., Damaged tissue that does not get enough blood flow also tends to heal more slowly. ,  Conditions in which the skin becomes inflamed and fluid builds up in the legs can also cause ischemic ulcers. People with poor blood flow often also have  nerve damage  or  foot ulcers from diabetes . Nerve damage makes it harder to feel an area in the shoe that rubs and causes a sore. Once a sore forms, poor blood flow makes it harder for the sore to heal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002244-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ischemic ulcers - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of ischemic ulcers include: Wounds may appear on legs, ankles, toes, and between toes., Dark red, yellow, gray, or black sores., Raised edges around the wound (looks punched out)., No bleeding., Deep wound through which tendons may show through., Wound may or may not be painful., Skin on the leg appears shiny, tight, dry, and hairless., Dangling the leg down off the side of a bed or chair causes the leg to turn red., When you raise the leg, it turns pale and cool to touch., Aching pain in the foot or leg, often at night. Pain may go away when the leg is dangled down., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002244-4" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Ischemic ulcers - self-care? ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002244-6" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Ischemic ulcers - self-care ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you are at risk for ischemic ulcers, taking these steps may help prevent problems: Check your feet and legs every day. Check the tops and bottoms, ankles, heels, and between your toes. Look for changes in color and red or sore areas., Wear shoes that fit properly and do not rub or put pressure on your feet. Wear socks that fit. Socks that are too big can bunch up in your shoes and cause rubbing of the skin, which can lead to a sore., Try not to sit or stand too long in one position., Protect your feet from the cold., Do not walk barefoot. Protect your feet from injury., Do not wear compression stockings or wraps unless told to by your provider. These may restrict blood flow., Do not soak your feet in hot water.,  Certain lifestyle changes can help prevent ischemic ulcers. If you have a wound, taking these steps can improve blood flow and aid healing. Quit smoking. Smoking can lead to narrowed arteries., If you have diabetes, keep your blood sugar level under control. This will help you heal faster., Exercise as much as you can. Staying active can help with blood flow., Eat healthy foods and get plenty of sleep at night., Lose weight if you are overweight., Manage your blood pressure and cholesterol levels., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>