<Document id="0002947" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001281.htm">
 
<Focus>Paraphimosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0030483</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002947-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Paraphimosis occurs when the foreskin of an uncircumcised male cannot be pulled back over the head of the penis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002947-2" qtype="causes">What causes Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Causes of paraphimosis include: Injury to the penis., Failure to return the foreskin to its normal location after urination or washing. This is more common in hospitals and nursing homes., Infection, which may be due to not washing the area well.,  Men who have not been circumcised and those who may not have been correctly circumcised are at risk. Paraphimosis occurs most often in&#160;boys and older men.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002947-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The foreskin is pulled back (retracted) behind the rounded tip of the penis (glans) and stays there. The retracted foreskin and glans become swollen. This makes it difficult to return the foreskin to its extended position. Symptoms include: Inability to pull the retracted foreskin forward over the head of the penis , Painful swelling at the end of the penis,  Pain in the penis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002947-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam confirms the diagnosis. The health care provider will usually find a "doughnut" around the shaft near the head of the penis (glans).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002947-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pressing on the head of the penis while pushing the foreskin forward may reduce the swelling. If this fails, prompt surgical  circumcision  or other surgery to relieve swelling will be needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002947-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome is likely to be excellent if the condition is diagnosed and treated quickly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002947-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>If paraphimosis is left untreated, it can disrupt blood flow to the tip of the penis. In extreme (and rare) cases, this may lead to: Damage to the penis tip ,  Gangrene ,  Loss of the penis tip , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002947-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Go to your local emergency room if this occurs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002947-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Paraphimosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Returning the foreskin to its normal position after pulling it back may help prevent this condition.  Circumcision, when done correctly, prevents this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>