<Document id="0002830" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001934.htm">
 
<Focus>Nurse practitioner (NP)</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002830-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Nurse practitioner (NP)</Question>
			<Answer>The NP is allowed to provide a broad range of health care services, which may include: Taking the person's history, performing a physical exam, and ordering laboratory tests and procedures, Diagnosing, treating, and managing diseases, Prescribing medicines and writing prescriptions, Coordinating referrals, Providing education on disease prevention and healthy lifestyles, Performing certain procedures, such as a  bone marrow biopsy  or  lumbar puncture ,  Nurse practitioners work in a variety of specialties, including: Cardiology, Emergency, Family practice, Geriatrics, Neonatology, Nephrology, Oncology, Pediatrics, Primary care, Psychiatry, School health, Women's health ,  Their range of health care services (scope of practice) and privileges (authority granted to a provider) depends on laws in the state in which they work. Some nurse practitioners may work independently in clinics or hospitals without doctor supervision. Others work together with doctors as a joint health care team.  Like many other professions, nurse practitioners are regulated at two different levels. They are licensed through a process that takes place at the state level under state laws. They are also certified through national organizations, with consistent professional practice standards across all states. LICENSURE The laws on NP licensure vary greatly from state to state. Today, more states are requiring NPs to have a master's or doctorate degree and national certification. In some states, NP practice is completely independent. Other states require that NPs work with an MD for prescriptive practice privileges or to get licensed.  CERTIFICATION National certification is offered through various nursing organizations (such as the American Nurses' Credentialing Center, Pediatric Nursing Certification Board, and others). Most of these organizations require that NPs complete an approved master's or doctorate-level NP program before taking the certification exam. The exams are offered in specialty areas, such as: Acute care, Adult health, Family health, Geriatric health, Neonatal health, Pediatric/child health, Psychiatric/mental health, Women's health ,  To be recertified, NPs need to show proof of continuing education. Only certified nurse practitioners may use a "C" either in front of or behind their other credentials (for example, Certified Pediatric Nurse Practitioner, FNP-C, Certified Family Nurse Practitioner). Some nurse practitioners may use the credential ARNP, which means advanced registered nurse practitioner. They may also use the credential APRN, which means advanced practice nurse practitioner. This is a broader category that includes clinical nurse specialists, certified nurse midwives, and nurse anesthetists.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>