<Document id="0002744" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001292.htm">
 
<Focus>Nasal septal hematoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0339842</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002744-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>A nasal septal hematoma is a collection of blood within the septum of the nose. The septum is the part of the nose between the nostrils. An injury disrupts the blood vessels so that fluid and blood may collect under the lining.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002744-2" qtype="causes">What causes Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>A septal hematoma can be caused by: A broken nose , Injury to the soft tissue of the area, Surgery, Taking blood-thinning medicines,  The problem is more common in children because their septums are thicker and have a more flexible lining. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002744-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Blockage in breathing, Nasal congestion, Painful swelling of the nasal septum, Change in the shape of the nose, Fever, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002744-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will look into your nose to see if there is swelling of the tissue between the nostrils. The provider will touch the area with an applicator or a cotton swab. If there is a hematoma, the area will be soft and able to be pressed down. The nasal septum is normally thin and rigid.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002744-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider will make a small cut to drain the blood. Gauze or cotton will be placed inside the nose after the blood is removed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002744-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>You should heal fully if the injury is treated quickly. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002744-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you have had the hematoma for a long time, it may become infected and will be painful. You may develop a septal  abscess  and fever. An untreated septal hematoma may lead to a hole in the area separating the nostrils, called a septal perforation. This can cause nasal congestion. Or, the area may collapse, leading to a deformity of the outer nose called a saddle nose deformity.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002744-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for any nasal injury resulting in nasal congestion or pain. You may be referred to an ear, nose, and throat (ENT) specialist. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002744-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Nasal septal hematoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recognizing and treating the problem early can prevent complications and allow the septum to heal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>