<Document id="0002377" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001376.htm">
 
<Focus>Leptospirosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0023364</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Weil disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Icterohemorrhagic fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Swineherd's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Rice-field fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cane-cutter fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Swamp fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mud fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hemorrhagic jaundice</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Stuttgart disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Canicola fever</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002377-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Leptospirosis is an infection caused by leptospira bacteria.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002377-2" qtype="causes">What causes Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>These bacteria can be found in fresh water that has been soiled by animal urine. You may get infected if you consume or come in contact with contaminated water or soil. The infection occurs in warmer climates. Leptospirosis is not spread from person to person, except in very rare cases. Risk factors include: Occupational exposure -- farmers, ranchers, slaughterhouse workers, trappers, veterinarians, loggers, sewer workers, rice field workers, and military personnel, Recreational activities -- fresh water swimming, canoeing, kayaking, and trail biking in warm areas, Household exposure -- pet dogs, domesticated livestock, rainwater catchment systems, and infected rodents ,  Weil disease, a severe form of leptospirosis, is rare in the continental United States. Hawaii has the highest number of cases in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002377-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms can take 2&#160;to 30 days (average 10 days) to develop, and may include: Dry cough, Fever, Headache, Muscle pain, Nausea, vomiting, and diarrhea, Shaking chills,  Less common symptoms include: Abdominal pain, Abnormal lung sounds, Bone pain,  Conjunctival (surface of the whites of the eyes) redness without fluid , Enlarged lymph glands,  Enlarged spleen  or liver, Joint aches, Muscle rigidity, Muscle tenderness, Skin rash, Sore throat, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002377-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The blood is tested for antibodies to the bacteria. During some phases of the illness, the bacteria themselves can be detected using polymerase chain reaction (PCR) testing. Other tests that may be done: Complete blood count  (CBC)
   ,  Creatine kinase ,  Liver enzymes ,  Urinalysis , Blood cultures, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002377-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medicines to treat leptospirosis include: Ampicillin, Azithromycin, Ceftriaxone, Doxycycline, Penicillin,  Complicated or serious cases may need supportive care. You may need treatment in a hospital intensive care unit (ICU).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002377-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook is generally good. However, a complicated case can be fatal if it is not treated promptly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002377-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Jarisch-Herxheimer reaction when penicillin is given,  Meningitis , Severe bleeding, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002377-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have any symptoms of, or risk factors for, leptospirosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002377-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Leptospirosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Avoid areas of stagnant water or floodwater, especially in tropical climates. If you are exposed to a high risk area, take precaution to avoid infection. Wear protective clothing, shoes, or boots when near water or soil contaminated with animal urine. You can take doxycycline to decrease the risk.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>