<Document id="0002673" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001317.htm">
 
<Focus>Mosaicism</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0392053</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T049</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Chromosomal mosaicism</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gonadal mosaicism</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002673-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mosaicism is a condition in which cells within the same person have a different genetic makeup. This condition can affect any type of cell, including: Blood cells ,  Egg and sperm cells  ,  Skin cells , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002673-2" qtype="causes">What causes Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mosaicism is caused by an error in cell division very early in the development of the unborn baby. Examples of mosaicism include: Mosaic  Down syndrome , Mosaic  Klinefelter syndrome , Mosaic  Turner syndrome , Mosaic neurofibromatosis, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002673-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms vary and are very difficult to predict. Symptoms may not be as severe if you have both normal and abnormal cells.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002673-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic testing can diagnose mosaicism. Tests will likely need to be repeated to confirm the results, and to help determine the type and severity of the disorder. Sometimes two different body tissues may need to be tested, such as blood and skin, or skin from two different areas of the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002673-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment will depend on the type and severity of the disorder.&#160;You&#160;may need less intense treatment if only some of the cells are abnormal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002673-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well you do depends on which organs and tissues are affected (for example, the brain or heart). It is difficult to predict the effects of having two different cell lines in one person. In general, people with a high number of abnormal cells have the same outlook as people with the typical form of the disease (those who have all abnormal cells). The typical form is also called non-mosaic. People with a low number of abnormal cells may be only mildly affected. They may not discover that they have mosaicism until they give birth to a child who has the non-mosaic form of the disease. Sometimes a child born with the non-mosaic form will not survive, but a child born with mosaicism will.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002673-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications depend on how many cells are affected by the genetic change.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002673-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>A diagnosis of mosaicism may cause confusion and uncertainty. A genetic counselor may help  answer any questions  about diagnosis and testing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002673-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Mosaicism ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is currently no known way to prevent mosaicism.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>