<Document id="0002566" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001621.htm">
 
<Focus>Meibomianitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0549398</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Meibomian gland dysfunction</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002566-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Meibomianitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meibomianitis is inflammation of the meibomian glands, a group of oil-releasing (sebaceous) glands in the eyelids. These glands have tiny openings to release oils onto the surface of the cornea.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002566-2" qtype="causes">What causes Meibomianitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Any condition that increases the oily secretions of the meibomian glands will allow excess oils to&#160;build up&#160;on the edges of the eyelids. This allows for&#160;the excess growth of bacteria that are normally present on the skin. These problems can be caused by allergies,&#160;hormone changes&#160;during adolescence, or skin conditions such as  rosacea  and acne. Meibomianitis is often associated with  blepharitis , which can cause&#160;a buildup of a&#160;dandruff-like substance at the base of the eyelashes. In some people with meibomianitis, the glands will be plugged so that there is less oil being made for the normal tear film. These people often have symptoms of dry eyes.&#160;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002566-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Meibomianitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Swelling and redness of eyelid edges, Symptoms of dry eye, Slight blurring of vision due to excess oil in tears -- most often cleared by blinking, Frequent  styes , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002566-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Meibomianitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meibomianitis can be diagnosed by an eye exam. Special tests are not required.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002566-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Meibomianitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Standard treatment involves: Carefully cleansing the edges of the lids, Applying moist heat to the affected eye ,  These treatments will usually reduce symptoms in most cases. Your health care provider may prescribe an antibiotic ointment to apply&#160;to the lid's edge. Other treatments may include: Having an eye doctor perform meibomian gland expression to help clear the glands of secretions., Inserting a small tube (cannula) into each gland opening to wash out thickened oil., Taking&#160;tetracycline antibiotics for several weeks., Using LipiFlow, a device that automatically warms the eyelid and helps clear the glands., Taking fish oil to improve the flow of oil from the glands., Using a medicine containing hypochlorous acid, that is sprayed onto the eyelids. This may be particularly useful in people who have rosacea.,  You may also need treatment for general skin conditions such as acne or rosacea.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002566-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Meibomianitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meibomianitis is not a vision-threatening condition. However, it may be a long-term (chronic) and recurring cause of eye irritation. Many people find the treatments frustrating because results are not often immediate. Treatment, however, will often help reduce symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002566-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Meibomianitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if treatment does not lead to improvement or if styes develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002566-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Meibomianitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keeping your eyelids clean&#160;and treating associated skin conditions will help prevent meibomianitis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>