<Document id="0002303" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001070.htm">
 
<Focus>Kneecap dislocation</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0012691</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Dislocation - kneecap</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Patellar dislocation or instability</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002303-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Kneecap dislocation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kneecap dislocation occurs when the round-shaped bone covering the knee (patella) moves or slides out of place. The dislocation often occurs toward the outside of the leg.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002303-2" qtype="causes">What causes Kneecap dislocation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kneecap dislocation often occurs after a sudden change in direction when your leg is planted. This puts your kneecap under stress. This can occur when playing certain sports, such as basketball. Dislocation may also occur as result of direct trauma. When the kneecap is dislocated, it can slip sideways to the outside of the knee.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002303-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Kneecap dislocation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of kneecap dislocation include: Knee appears to be deformed, Knee is bent and cannot be straightened out, Kneecap (patella) dislocates to the outside of the knee,  Knee pain  and tenderness,  Knee swelling , "Sloppy" kneecap -- you can move the kneecap too much from right to left (hypermobile patella),  The first few times this occurs, you will feel pain and may be unable to walk. If you continue to have dislocations, your knee may not hurt as much and you may not be as disabled. This is not a reason to avoid treatment. Kneecap dislocation damages your knee joint. It can lead to cartilage injuries and increase the risk of developing osteoarthritis at a younger age. Repeat dislocations will make the condition worse and harder to treat.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002303-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Kneecap dislocation ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002303-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Kneecap dislocation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you injure your knee and have symptoms of dislocation. Contact your provider if you are being treated for a dislocated knee and you notice: Increased instability in your knee ,  Pain or  swelling  return after they went away , Your injury does not appear to be getting better with time,  Also contact your provider if you re-injure your knee.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002303-6" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Kneecap dislocation ?</Question>
			<Answer>Use proper techniques when exercising or playing sports. Keep your knees strong and flexible. Some cases of knee dislocation may not be preventable, especially if physical factors make you more likely to dislocate your knee.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>