<Document id="0002649" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000907.htm">
 
<Focus>Miscarriage - threatened</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0000786</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Threatened miscarriage</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Threatened spontaneous abortion</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Abortion - threatened</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Threatened abortion</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002649-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>A threatened miscarriage is a condition that indicates the potential for a miscarriage or early pregnancy loss. It might take place before the 20th week of pregnancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002649-2" qtype="causes">What causes Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some pregnant women have some  vaginal bleeding &#160;during the first 3 months of pregnancy. Bleeding may occur&#160;with or without abdominal cramps. When the symptoms indicate a miscarriage is possible, the condition is called a "threatened abortion." (This refers to a natural event that is not due to a medical or surgical abortion.) Miscarriage  is common. Small falls, injuries or stress during the first trimester of pregnancy can cause threatened miscarriage. It occurs in almost one half of all pregnancies. The chance of miscarriage is higher in older women. About one half of women who have bleeding in the first trimester will have a miscarriage.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002649-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of a threatened miscarriage include: Vaginal bleeding during the first 20 weeks of pregnancy (last menstrual period was less than 20 weeks ago). Vaginal bleeding occurs in almost all threatened miscarriages., Abdominal cramps may also occur. If abdominal cramps occur in the absence of significant bleeding, consult your health care provider to check for other problems besides threatened miscarriage.,  Note: During a miscarriage, low back pain or abdominal pain (dull to sharp, constant to intermittent) can occur. Tissue or clot-like material may pass from the  vagina .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002649-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider may perform an abdominal or vaginal ultrasound to check the baby's development and heartbeat, and the amount of bleeding. A pelvic exam may also be done to check your cervix. Blood tests done may include: Beta HCG (quantitative) test  (pregnancy test)  over a period of days or weeks to confirm whether the pregnancy is continuing,  Complete blood count  (CBC) to determine the presence of anemia, Progesterone level,  White blood count  (WBC) with  differential  to check for infection, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002649-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>Apart from controlling the blood loss, you may not need any particular treatment. If you are  Rh Negative , then you may be given immune globulin. You may be told to avoid or restrict some activities. Not having sexual intercourse is often recommended until the warning signs have disappeared.&#160;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002649-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most women with a threatened miscarriage go on to have a normal pregnancy.  Women who have had two or more miscarriages in a row may be more likely than other women to miscarry again. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002649-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Anemia  from moderate to heavy blood loss, which may require a blood transfusion., Infection., Miscarriage., The provider will want to ensure that the symptoms are not due to an ectopic pregnancy. This is a potentially life-threatening complication., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002649-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you know you are (or are likely to be) pregnant and you have any symptoms of threatened miscarriage, contact your prenatal provider right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002649-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Miscarriage - threatened ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most miscarriages cannot be prevented. The most common cause of a miscarriage is a random genetic abnormality in the developing pregnancy. If you have two or more repeated miscarriages, you should consult a specialist to look for an underlying condition that is causing the problem. Women who get prenatal care have better pregnancy outcomes for themselves and their babies.&#160; A healthy pregnancy is more likely when you avoid things that are harmful to your pregnancy, such as: Alcohol, Infectious diseases, High caffeine intake, Recreational drugs, X-rays,  Taking a prenatal vitamin or folic acid supplement before becoming pregnant and throughout your pregnancy can lower your chance of miscarriage and improve the chance of delivering a healthy baby. It is better to treat health problems before you get pregnant than to wait until you are already pregnant. Miscarriages caused by diseases that affect your whole body, such as high blood pressure, are rare. But you can prevent these miscarriages by detecting and treating the disease before becoming pregnant. Other factors that can increase your risk for miscarriage include: Obesity , Thyroid problems, Uncontrolled diabetes, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>