<Document id="0002319" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000391.htm">
 
<Focus>Lactic acidosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0001125</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002319-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lactic acidosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lactic acidosis refers to  lactic acid  build up in the bloodstream. Lactic acid is produced when oxygen levels become low in cells within the areas of the body where metabolism takes place or in response to sympathetic overactivity related to epinephrine-type substances or exercise.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002319-2" qtype="causes">What causes Lactic acidosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The most common cause of lactic acidosis is severe medical illness in which blood pressure is low and too little oxygen is reaching the body's tissues. Intense exercise or convulsions can cause temporary lactic acidosis. Certain diseases can also cause the condition, including:  AIDS , Alcoholism, Cancer, Cirrhosis, Cyanide poisoning, Kidney failure,  Respiratory failure ,  Sepsis  (severe infection),  Some medicines can rarely cause lactic acidosis: Beta adrenergic agonist inhalers used to treat asthma or COPD (albuterol and salmeterol), Epinephrine, Linezolid, Metformin, used to treat diabetes (most often when overdosed), Nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors used to treat HIV infection, Propofol, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002319-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Lactic acidosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Nausea, Vomiting, Weakness , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002319-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Lactic acidosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests may include a blood test to check lactate and electrolyte levels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002319-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Lactic acidosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main treatment for lactic acidosis is to correct the medical problem that causes the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>