<Document id="0002698" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002596.htm">
 
<Focus>Multiple vitamin overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0573812</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002698-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Multiple vitamin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multiple vitamin overdose occurs when someone takes more than the normal or recommended amount of multivitamin supplements. This can be by accident or on purpose. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with has an overdose, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002698-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Multiple vitamin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Iron overdose may include vomiting, diarrhea (which may be bloody or dark), or weakness. People with severe overdoses may develop coma, low blood pressure, liver failure, lung injury, and death. Calcium overdose can impair the functioning of the kidneys, increase the pH of the blood, and can cause nausea and vomiting, confusion or changes in thinking or mentation, itching, and in extreme cases irregular heartbeat. Vitamin D overdose can contribute to high levels of calcium in the blood. Vitamin A overdose can cause nausea and vomiting, dizziness, blurry vision. Additional symptoms of a multivitamin overdose in different parts of the body may include: BLADDER AND KIDNEYS Cloudy urine, Frequent urination, Increased urine amount ,  EYES, EARS, NOSE, MOUTH, AND THROAT Dry, cracking lips (from chronic overdose), Eye irritation, Increased sensitivity of the eyes to light ,  HEART AND BLOOD Irregular heartbeat , Rapid heartbeat ,  MUSCLES AND JOINTS Bone pain , Joint pain, Muscle pain, Muscle weakness ,  NERVOUS SYSTEM Confusion, mood changes,  Convulsions  (seizures), Fainting, Fatigue, Headache, Mental changes, Irritability ,  SKIN AND HAIR Flushing  (reddened skin) from niacin (vitamin B3), Dry, cracking skin,  Itching , burning skin, or rash, Yellow-orange areas of skin, Sensitivity to sun (more likely to sunburn), Hair loss (from long-term overdose) ,  STOMACH AND INTESTINES Intestinal bleeding (from iron), Appetite loss, Constipation (from iron or calcium), Diarrhea, possibly bloody, Nausea and vomiting, Stomach pain, Weight loss (from long-term overdose) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002698-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Multiple vitamin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002698-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Multiple vitamin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>If medical treatment is quickly received, people who have iron and calcium overdoses usually recover. Overdoses of iron that cause coma or low blood pressure can sometimes be fatal. Iron overdoses can have long-term consequences to the intestines and liver, including intestinal scarring and liver failure. Niacin flush (vitamin B3) is uncomfortable, but lasts only 2 to 8 hours. Vitamins A and D may cause symptoms when large doses are taken each day, but a one large dose of these vitamins is rarely harmful. B vitamins usually do not cause symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002698-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Multiple vitamin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>If medical treatment is quickly received, people who have iron and calcium overdoses usually recover. Overdoses of iron that cause coma or low blood pressure can sometimes be fatal. Iron overdoses can have long-term consequences to the intestines and liver, including intestinal scarring and liver failure. Niacin flush (vitamin B3) is uncomfortable, but lasts only 2 to 8 hours. Vitamins A and D may cause symptoms when large doses are taken each day, but a one large dose of these vitamins is rarely harmful. B vitamins usually do not cause symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>