<Document id="0002498" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000933.htm">
 
<Focus>Major depression with psychotic features</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1269683</CUI>
			<CUI>C0033975</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Psychotic depression</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Delusional depression</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002498-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Major depression with psychotic features ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major depression with psychotic features is a mental disorder in which a person has depression along with loss of touch with reality (psychosis).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002498-2" qtype="causes">What causes Major depression with psychotic features ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause is unknown. A family or personal history of depression or psychotic illness makes you more likely to develop this condition. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002498-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Major depression with psychotic features ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with psychotic depression have  symptoms of depression &#160;and  psychosis . Psychosis is a loss of contact with reality. It usually includes: Delusions: False beliefs about what is taking place or who one is, Hallucinations: Seeing or hearing things that aren't there ,  The types of delusions and hallucinations are often related to your depressed feelings. For example, some people may hear voices criticizing them, or telling them that they don't deserve to live. The person may develop false beliefs about their body, such as believing that they have cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002498-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Major depression with psychotic features ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask questions about your medical history and symptoms. Your answers and certain questionnaires can help your provider diagnose this condition and determine how severe it may be. Blood and urine tests, and possibly a brain scan may be done to rule out other medical conditions with similar symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002498-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Major depression with psychotic features ?</Question>
			<Answer>Psychotic depression requires immediate medical care and treatment.  Treatment usually involves antidepressant and antipsychotic medicine. You may only need antipsychotic medicine for a short period of time. Electroconvulsive therapy  can help treat depression with psychotic symptoms. However, medicine is usually tried first.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002498-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Major depression with psychotic features ?</Question>
			<Answer>This is a serious condition. You will need immediate treatment and close monitoring by a provider.  You may need to take medicine for a long time to prevent the depression from coming back. Depression symptoms are more likely to return than psychotic symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002498-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Major depression with psychotic features ?</Question>
			<Answer>The risk for suicide is much higher in people with depression with psychotic symptoms than in those without psychosis. You may need to stay in the hospital if you have thoughts of suicide. The safety of other people&#160;must also be considered.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002498-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Major depression with psychotic features ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider right away if: You hear voices that are not there., You have frequent crying spells with little or no reason., Your depression is disrupting work, school, or family life., You think that your current medicines are not working or are causing side effects. Never change or stop any medicines without first talking to your provider.,  If you or someone you know is thinking about suicide, call or text 988 or chat 988lifeline.org. You can also call 1-800-273-8255 (1-800-273-TALK). The 988 Suicide and Crisis Lifeline provides free and confidential support 24/7, anytime day or night. You can also call 911 or the local emergency number or go to the hospital emergency room. DO NOT delay. If someone you know has attempted suicide, call 911 or the local emergency number right away. DO NOT leave the person alone, even after you have called for help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>