<Document id="0002247" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002660.htm">
 
<Focus>Isopropanol overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0745426</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Rubbing alcohol overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Isopropyl alcohol overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002247-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Isopropanol overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Isopropanol is a type of alcohol used in some household products, medicines, and cosmetics. It is not meant to be swallowed. Isopropanol poisoning occurs when someone swallows this substance. This can be by accident or on purpose. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002247-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Isopropanol overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of an isopropanol poisoning include: Acting or feeling drunk, Slurred speech, Stupor,  Uncoordinated movement ,  Coma  (decreased level of consciousness and lack of responsiveness), Unconsciousness, Unpaired movements of the eyes, Throat pain,  Abdominal pain , Burns and damage to the clear covering of the front of the eye (cornea),  Dizziness , Headache,  Low body temperature ,  Low blood pressure ,  Low blood sugar ,  Nausea  and  vomiting  (may contain blood), Rapid heart rate, Skin redness and pain,  Slowed breathing , Urination problems (too much or too little urine), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002247-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Isopropanol overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002247-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Isopropanol overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on the amount of poison swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster someone gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Drinking isopropanol will most likely make you very drunk. Recovery is very likely if a person does not swallow a large amount. However, drinking large amounts can lead to: Coma and possibly brain damage, Internal bleeding, Breathing difficulty, Kidney failure,  It is dangerous to give a child a sponge bath with isopropanol to reduce a fever. Isopropanol is absorbed through the skin, so it can make children very sick.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002247-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Isopropanol overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well someone does depends on the amount of poison swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster someone gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Drinking isopropanol will most likely make you very drunk. Recovery is very likely if a person does not swallow a large amount. However, drinking large amounts can lead to: Coma and possibly brain damage, Internal bleeding, Breathing difficulty, Kidney failure,  It is dangerous to give a child a sponge bath with isopropanol to reduce a fever. Isopropanol is absorbed through the skin, so it can make children very sick.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>