<Document id="0002848" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000758.htm">
 
<Focus>Olivopontocerebellar atrophy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0028968</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>OPCA</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Olivopontocerebellar degeneration</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Multiple system atrophy  cerebellar predominance</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MSA-C</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002848-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Olivopontocerebellar atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Multiple system atrophy - cerebellar subtype (MSA-C) is a rare disease that causes areas deep in the brain, just above the spinal cord, to shrink (atrophy). MSA-C used to be known as olivopontocerebellar atrophy (OPCA).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002848-2" qtype="causes">What causes Olivopontocerebellar atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>MSA-C can be passed down through families (inherited form). It can also affect people without a known family history (sporadic form). Researchers have identified certain genes that are involved in the inherited form of this condition. The cause of MSA-C in people with the sporadic form is not known. The disease slowly gets worse (is progressive). MSA-C is slightly more common in men than in women. The average age of onset is 54 years old.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002848-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Olivopontocerebellar atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of MSA-C&#160;tend to start at a younger age in people with the inherited form. The main symptom is clumsiness ( ataxia ) that slowly gets worse. There may also be problems with balance, slurring of speech, and difficulty walking. Other symptoms may include: Abnormal eye movements, Abnormal movements, Abnormal sweating, Bowel or bladder problems, Difficulty swallowing, Cold hands and feet, Lightheadedness when standing, Headache while standing that is relieved by lying down , Muscle stiffness or rigidity, spasms, tremor, Nerve damage (neuropathy), Problems in speaking and sleeping due to  spasms of the vocal cords , Sexual function problems, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002848-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Olivopontocerebellar atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>A thorough medical and nervous system examination, as well as a symptom review and family history are needed to make the diagnosis. There are genetic tests to look for the causes of some forms of the disorder. But, no specific test is available in many cases. An  MRI of the brain  may show changes in the size of affected brain structures, especially as the disease gets worse. But it is possible to have the disorder and have a normal MRI. Other tests such as  positron emission tomography (PET)  may be done to rule out other conditions. These may include swallowing studies to see if a person can safely swallow food and liquid.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002848-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Olivopontocerebellar atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no specific treatment or cure for MSA-C. The aim is to treat the symptoms and prevent complications. This may include: Tremor medicines, such as those for Parkinson disease, Speech, occupational and physical therapy, Ways to prevent choking, Walking aids to help with balance and prevent falls, Devices to treat sleep apnea (such as CPAP), Treatment for low blood pressure, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002848-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Olivopontocerebellar atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>MSA-C slowly gets worse, and there is no cure. The outlook is generally poor. But, it may be years before someone is very disabled.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002848-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Olivopontocerebellar atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications of MSA-C include: Choking, Infection from inhaling food into the lungs ( aspiration pneumonia ), Injury from falls, Nutrition problems due to difficulty swallowing, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002848-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Olivopontocerebellar atrophy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have any symptoms of MSA-C. You will need to be seen by a neurologist. This is a doctor who treats nervous system problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>