<Document id="0002125" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001451.htm">
 
<Focus>Ichthyosis vulgaris</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0079584</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Common ichthyosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fish scale disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002125-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ichthyosis vulgaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ichthyosis vulgaris is a skin disorder passed down through families that leads to dry, scaly skin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002125-2" qtype="causes">What causes Ichthyosis vulgaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ichthyosis vulgaris is one of the most common inherited skin disorders. It may begin in early childhood. The condition is inherited in an  autosomal dominant  pattern. That means if you have the condition, your child has a 50% chance of getting the gene from you. The condition is often more noticeable in the winter. It may occur along with other skin problems including  atopic dermatitis , asthma, keratosis pilaris (small bumps on the back of the arms and legs), or other skin disorders.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002125-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Ichthyosis vulgaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include any of the following: Dry skin , severe, Scaly skin ( scales ), Possible skin thickening, Mild itching of the skin ,  The dry, scaly skin is usually most severe on the legs. But it can also involve the arms, hands, and middle of the body. People with this condition may also have many fine lines on their palms. In infants, the skin changes usually appear in the first year of life. Early on, the skin is only slightly rough, but by the time a baby is about 3 months old, they begin appearing on the shins and back of the arms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002125-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Ichthyosis vulgaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can usually diagnose this condition by looking at your skin. Tests may be done to check for other possible causes of dry, scaly skin. Your provider will ask if you have a family history of similar skin dryness. A  skin biopsy  may be performed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002125-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ichthyosis vulgaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider may ask you to use heavy-duty moisturizers. Creams and ointments work better than lotions. Apply these to moist skin immediately after bathing. You should use mild, non-drying soaps.  Your provider may tell you to use hydrating-moisturizing creams that contain keratolytic chemicals such as lactic acid, salicylic acid, and urea. These chemicals help skin shed normally while retaining moisture.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002125-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Ichthyosis vulgaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ichthyosis vulgaris can be bothersome, but it rarely affects your overall health. The condition usually disappears during adulthood but may return years later as people age.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002125-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Ichthyosis vulgaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>A bacterial skin infection may develop if scratching causes openings in the skin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002125-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Ichthyosis vulgaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call for an appointment with your provider if: Symptoms continue despite treatment, Symptoms get worse, Skin lesions spread, New symptoms develop , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>