<Document id="0002860" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001537.htm">
 
<Focus>Oppositional defiant disorder</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0029121</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002860-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oppositional defiant disorder is a pattern of disobedient, hostile, and defiant behavior toward authority figures.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002860-2" qtype="causes">What causes Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>This disorder is more common in boys than in girls. Some studies have shown that it affects 20% of school-age children. However, most experts believe this figure is high due to changing definitions of normal childhood behavior. It may also possibly have racial, cultural, and gender biases. This behavior typically starts by age 8. However, it may start as early as the preschool years. This disorder is thought to be caused by a combination of biological, psychological, and social factors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002860-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Actively does not follow adults' requests, Angry and resentful of others, Argues with adults, Blames others for own mistakes, Has few or no friends or has lost friends, Is often in trouble in school, Loses temper, Is spiteful or seeks revenge, Is touchy or easily annoyed,  To fit this diagnosis, the pattern must last for at least 6 months and must be more than normal childhood misbehavior. The pattern of behaviors must be different from those of other children around the same age and developmental level. The behavior must lead to significant problems in school or social activities.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002860-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children with symptoms of this disorder should be evaluated by a psychiatrist or psychologist. In children and adolescents, the following conditions can cause similar behavior problems and should be considered as possibilities: Anxiety disorders,  Attention-deficit/hyperactivity disorder  (ADHD),  Bipolar disorder , Depression, Learning disorders, Substance abuse disorders , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002860-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>The best treatment for the child is to talk with a mental health professional in individual and possibly family therapy. The parents should also learn how to manage the child's behavior. Medicines may also be helpful, especially if the behaviors occur as part of another condition (such as depression, childhood  psychosis , or ADHD).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002860-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some children respond well to treatment, while others do not.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002860-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>In many cases, children with oppositional defiant disorder grow up to have  conduct disorder  as teenagers or adults. In some cases, children may grow up to have  antisocial personality disorder .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002860-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have concerns about your child's development or behavior.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002860-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Oppositional defiant disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Be consistent about rules and consequences at home. Don't make punishments too harsh or inconsistent. Model the right behaviors for your child. Abuse and neglect increase the chances that this condition will occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>