<Document id="0002085" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000109.htm">
 
<Focus>Hypersensitivity pneumonitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0002390</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Extrinsic allergic alveolitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Farmer's lung</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Mushroom picker's disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Humidifier or air-conditioner lung</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Bird breeder's or bird fancier's lung</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002085-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypersensitivity pneumonitis is inflammation of the lungs due to breathing in dust, fungus, molds, or other substances.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002085-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypersensitivity pneumonitis usually occurs in people who work in places where there are high levels of dust, fungus, or molds. Long-term exposure can lead to lung inflammation and acute  lung disease . Over time, the acute condition turns into long-lasting (chronic) lung disease. Hypersensitivity pneumonitis may also be caused by: Fungi or bacteria in humidifiers, heating systems, and air conditioners found in homes and offices, Exposure to certain chemicals, such as isocyanates or acid anhydrides,  Examples of hypersensitivity pneumonitis include: Bird fancier's lung  is caused by exposure to proteins found in the feathers or droppings of many species of birds. This is the most common type of hypersensitivity pneumonitis. Farmer's lung  is caused by exposure to dust from moldy hay, straw, and grain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002085-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms often occur 4 to 8 hours after you have left the area where the triggering substance is found. This makes it hard to figure out what has caused the disease. Your symptoms may get better before you go back to the area where you were exposed to the substance. In the chronic phase of the condition, the symptoms are more constant and less affected by exposure to the substance. Symptoms after acute exposure may include: Chills,  Cough ,  Fever ,  Malaise  (feeling ill),  Shortness of breath ,  Symptoms of chronic hypersensitivity pneumonitis may include: Breathlessness, especially with activity, Cough, often dry,  Loss of appetite , Unintentional weight loss, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002085-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical examination and ask about your symptoms. Your provider may hear abnormal lung sounds called crackles (rales) when listening to your chest with a stethoscope. Lung changes due to chronic hypersensitivity pneumonitis may be seen on a  chest x-ray . Other tests may include: Aspergillosis precipitin blood test  to check if you've been exposed to the aspergillus fungus,  Bronchoscopy  with washings, biopsy, and bronchoalveolar lavage, 
   Complete blood count ( CBC ),  CT scan of the chest , Hypersensitivity pneumonitis  antibody  panel blood test, Krebs von den Lungen-6 assay (KL-6) blood test,  Lung function tests , Surgical lung biopsy, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002085-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>First, the offending substance must be identified. Treatment involves avoiding this substance in the future. Some people may need to change jobs if they cannot avoid the substance at work. If you have a chronic form of this disease, your provider may recommend that you take glucocorticoids (anti-inflammatory medicines). Sometimes, treatments used for asthma can help people with hypersensitivity pneumonitis. Sometimes medicines that suppress the immune system are needed to control the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002085-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most symptoms go away when you avoid or limit your exposure to the material that caused the problem. The outlook is good if you prevent exposure during the acute stage. When it reaches the chronic stage, the disease might continue to progress, even if the offending substance is avoided.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002085-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The chronic form of this disease may lead to  pulmonary fibrosis . This is scarring of the lung tissue that often is not reversible. Eventually, end-stage lung disease and respiratory failure can occur. Some people might need lung transplantation at the end-stage of the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002085-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you develop symptoms of hypersensitivity pneumonitis, especially if you have been exposed to potentially harmful agents that can cause the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002085-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Hypersensitivity pneumonitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The chronic form can be prevented by avoiding the material that causes the lung inflammation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>