<Document id="0002792" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001452.htm">
 
<Focus>Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0007097</CUI>
			<CUI>C0004779</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>NBCC syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Gorlin syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002792-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome is a group of defects passed down through families. The disorder involves the skin, nervous system, eyes,  endocrine  glands, urinary and reproductive systems, and bones. It causes an unusual facial appearance and a higher risk for skin cancers and noncancerous tumors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002792-2" qtype="causes">What causes Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nevoid basal cell carcinoma nevus syndrome is a rare genetic condition. The main gene linked to the syndrome is known as PTCH ("patched"). A second gene, called SUFU, has also been associated with this condition. Abnormalities in these genes are most commonly passed down through families as an  autosomal dominant  trait. This means you&#160;develop the syndrome if either parent passes the gene to you. If either of your parents has this syndrome, you have a 50 percent chance of having it. It is also possible to develop this gene defect with no family history.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002792-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Main symptoms of this disorder are: A type of skin cancer called  basal cell carcinoma  that develops around the time of puberty, A noncancerous tumor of the jaw, called kerotocystic odontogenic tumor that also develops during puberty,  Other symptoms include: Broad nose,  Cleft palate , Heavy, protruding brow, Jaw that sticks out (in some cases), Wide-set eyes , Pitting on palms and soles,  The condition may affect the nervous system and lead to: Eye problems, Deafness,  Intellectual disability ,  Seizures , Tumors of the brain,  The condition also leads to bone defects, including: Curvature of the back ( scoliosis) , Severe curvature of the back ( kyphosis ) , Abnormal ribs, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002792-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>There may be a family history of this disorder and a past history of basal cell skin cancers. Tests may reveal: Brain tumors , Cysts in the jaw, which can lead to abnormal tooth development or jaw fractures, Defects in the colored part (iris) or lens of the eye, Head swelling due to fluid on the brain ( hydrocephalus) , Rib abnormalities,  Tests that may be done include: Echocardiogram  of the heart, Genetic testing (in some patients),  MRI of the brain ,  Skin biopsy  of tumors, X-rays of the bones, teeth, and skull, Ultrasound to check for ovarian tumors, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002792-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is important to get examined by a skin doctor (dermatologist) often, so that skin cancers may be treated while they are still small. People with this disorder may also be seen and treated by other specialists, depending on which part of the body is affected. For example, a cancer specialist (oncologist) may treat tumors in the body, and an orthopedic surgeon may help treat bone problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002792-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Frequent follow-up with a variety of specialist doctors is important for having a good outcome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002792-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with this condition may develop: Blindness, Brain tumor, Deafness, Fractures, Ovarian tumors, Cardiac fibromas, Skin damage and severe scarring due to skin cancers , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002792-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider for an appointment if: You or any family members have nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome, especially if you are planning to have a child., You have a child who has symptoms of this disorder., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002792-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Couples with a family history of this syndrome might consider  genetic counseling  before becoming pregnant. Staying out of the sun and using sunscreen can help prevent new basal cell skin cancers. Avoid radiation such as x-rays. People with this condition are very sensitive to radiation. Exposure to radiation can lead to skin cancers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>