<Document id="0002385" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001046.htm">
 
<Focus>Leukoplakia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0023531</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hairy leukoplakia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Smoker's keratosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002385-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Leukoplakia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Leukoplakia are white patches on the tongue, in the mouth, or on the inside of the cheek. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002385-2" qtype="causes">What causes Leukoplakia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Leukoplakia affects the mucous membranes of the mouth. The exact cause is not known. It may be due to irritation such as:  Rough teeth, Rough places on dentures, fillings, and crowns, Smoking or other tobacco use (smoker's keratosis), especially pipes, Holding chewing tobacco or snuff in the mouth for a long period of time, Drinking a lot of alcohol ,  The disorder is more common in older adults. A type of leukoplakia of the mouth, called oral hairy leukoplakia, is caused by the Epstein-Barr virus. It is seen mostly in people with  HIV/AIDS . It may be one of the first signs of HIV infection. Oral hairy leukoplakia can also appear in other people whose immune system is not working well, such as after a  bone marrow transplant .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002385-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Leukoplakia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Patches in the mouth usually develop on the tongue (sides of the tongue with oral hairy leukoplakia) and on the insides of the cheeks. Leukoplakia patches are: Most often white or gray, Uneven in shape, Fuzzy (oral hairy leukoplakia), Slightly raised, with a hard surface, Unable to be scraped off, Painful when the mouth patches come into contact with acidic or spicy food , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002385-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Leukoplakia ?</Question>
			<Answer>A  biopsy  of the lesion confirms the diagnosis. Examination of the biopsy may find changes that indicate  oral cancer .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002385-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Leukoplakia ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goal of treatment is to get rid of the leukoplakia patch. Removing the source of irritation may cause the patch to disappear. Treat dental causes such as rough teeth, irregular denture surface, or fillings as soon as possible., Stop smoking or using other tobacco products., Do not drink alcohol. ,  If removing the source of the irritation does not work, your health care provider may suggest applying medicine to the patch or using surgery to remove it. For oral hairy leukoplakia, taking antiviral medicine usually causes the patch to disappear. Your provider may also suggest applying medicine to the patch. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002385-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Leukoplakia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Leukoplakia is usually harmless. Patches in the mouth often clear up in a few weeks or months after the source of irritation is removed. In some cases, the patches may be an early sign of cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002385-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Leukoplakia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if you have any patches that look like leukoplakia or hairy leukoplakia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002385-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Leukoplakia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Stop smoking and do not use other tobacco products. Do not drink alcohol, or reduce the number of drinks you have that contain alcohol. Have rough teeth treated and dental appliances repaired.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>