<Document id="0002222" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001500.htm">
 
<Focus>Intrauterine growth restriction</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0015934</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Intrauterine growth retardation</Synonym>
		<Synonym>IUGR</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002222-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Intrauterine growth restriction (IUGR) refers to the poor growth of a baby while in the mother's womb during pregnancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002222-2" qtype="causes">What causes Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many different things can lead to IUGR. An unborn baby may not get enough oxygen and nutrition from the placenta during pregnancy because of: Mother living at high altitude, Multiple pregnancy, such as twins or triplets, Placenta problems,  Preeclampsia  or  eclampsia ,  Problems at birth (congenital abnormalities)&#160;or chromosome problems are often associated with below-normal weight. Infections during pregnancy can also affect the weight of the developing baby. These include: Cytomegalovirus ,  Rubella ,  Syphilis ,  Toxoplasmosis ,  Risk factors in the mother that may contribute to IUGR include: Alcohol abuse, Smoking, Drug addiction, Clotting disorders, High blood pressure or heart disease, Diabetes, Kidney disease, Poor nutrition, Thyroid disease, Anemia, Uterine malformations, Multiple gestation, Other chronic disease,  If the mother is small, it may be normal for her baby to be small, and this is not due to IUGR. Depending on the cause of IUGR, the developing baby may be small all over. Or, the baby's head may be normal size while the rest of the body is small. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002222-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>A pregnant woman may feel that her baby is not as big as it should be. The measurement from the mother's pubic bone to the top of the uterus will be smaller than expected for the baby's gestational age. This measurement is called the uterine fundal height.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002222-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>IUGR may be suspected if the size of the pregnant woman's uterus is small. The condition is most often confirmed by  ultrasound . More tests may be needed to screen for infection or genetic problems if IUGR is suspected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002222-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>IUGR increases the risk that the baby will die inside the womb before birth. If your health care provider thinks you might have IUGR, you will be monitored closely. This will include regular pregnancy ultrasounds to measure the baby's growth, movements, blood flow, and fluid around the baby. Nonstress testing will also be done. This involves listening to the baby's heart rate for a period of 20 to 30 minutes. Depending on the results of these tests, your baby may need to be delivered early.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002222-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>After delivery, the newborn's growth and development depends on the severity and cause of IUGR. Discuss the baby's outlook with your providers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002222-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>IUGR increases the risk of pregnancy and newborn complications, depending on the cause. Babies whose growth is restricted often become more stressed during labor or  C-section delivery . </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002222-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider right away if you are pregnant and notice that your baby is moving less than usual. After giving birth, call your provider if your infant or child does not seem to be growing or developing normally.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002222-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Intrauterine growth restriction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Following these guidelines will help prevent IUGR: Do not&#160;drink alcohol, smoke, or use recreational drugs., Eat healthy foods., Get regular prenatal care., If you have a chronic medical condition or you take prescribed medicines regularly, see your provider before you get pregnant. This can help reduce risks to your pregnancy and the baby. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>