<Document id="0002086" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000874.htm">
 
<Focus>Hypersensitivity vasculitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0151436</CUI>
			<CUI>C2973529</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Allergic vasculitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Leukocytoclastic vasculitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cutaneous vasculitis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002086-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypersensitivity vasculitis is an extreme reaction to a drug, infection, or foreign substance. It leads to inflammation and damage to blood vessels, mainly in the skin. The term is not used much currently because more specific names are considered more precise.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002086-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypersensitivity vasculitis, or cutaneous small vessel vasculitis, is caused by: An  allergic reaction  to a drug or other foreign substance, A reaction to an infection,  It usually affects people older than age 16. Often, the cause of the problem cannot be found even with a careful study of the person's medical history. Hypersensitivity vasculitis may look like systemic,  necrotizing vasculitis , which can affect blood vessels throughout the body and not just in the skin. In children, it can look like Henoch-Schonlein purpura.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002086-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: New rash with tender, purple or brownish-red spots&#160;over large areas, Skin sores mostly located on the legs, buttocks, or trunk,  Blisters  on the skin, Hives ( urticaria ), may last longer than 24 hours, Open sores with dead tissue (necrotic  ulcers ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002086-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will base the diagnosis on symptoms. The provider will review any medicines or drugs you have taken and recent infections. You will be asked about cough, fever, or chest pain. A complete physical exam will be done. Blood and urine tests may be done to look for systemic disorders such systemic lupus erythematosus, dermatomyositis, or hepatitis C. The blood tests may include: Complete blood count with differential, C-reactive protein, Erythrocyte sedimentation rate, Chemistry panel with liver enzymes and creatinine, Antinuclear antibody (ANA), Rheumatoid factor, Antineutrophil cytoplasmic antibodies (ANCA), Complement levels, Cryoglobulins, Hepatitis B and C tests, HIV test, Urinalysis,  Skin biopsy  shows inflammation of the small blood vessels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002086-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goal of treatment is to reduce inflammation. Your provider may prescribe aspirin, nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), or corticosteroids to reduce inflammation of the blood vessels. (Do not give aspirin to children except as advised by your provider). Your provider will tell you to stop taking medicines that could be causing this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002086-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypersensitivity vasculitis most often goes away over time. The condition may come back in some people. People with ongoing vasculitis should be checked for systemic vasculitis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002086-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Lasting damage to the blood vessels or skin with scarring, Inflamed blood vessels affecting the internal organs , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002086-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have symptoms of hypersensitivity vasculitis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002086-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Hypersensitivity vasculitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Do not take medicines that have caused an allergic reaction in the past.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>