<Document id="0002606" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001161.htm">
 
<Focus>Metabolic neuropathies</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0442874</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Neuropathy - metabolic</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002606-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>Metabolic neuropathies are nerve disorders that occur with diseases that disrupt the chemical processes in the body</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002606-2" qtype="causes">What causes Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nerve damage can be caused by many different things. Metabolic neuropathy may be caused by: A problem with the body's ability to use energy, often due to a lack of enough nutrients (nutritional deficiency), Dangerous substances (toxins) that build up in the body ,  Diabetes is one of the most common causes of metabolic neuropathies. People who are at the highest risk for nerve damage ( diabetic neuropathy ) from diabetes include those who have: Damage to the kidneys or eyes, Poorly controlled blood sugar ,  Other common causes of metabolic neuropathies include: Alcohol use disorder  ( alcoholic neuropathy ), Low blood sugar ( hypoglycemia ), Kidney failure, 
  Inherited conditions, such as&#160; porphyria , Severe infection throughout the body ( sepsis ), Thyroid disease, Liver disease, Vitamin deficiencies (including vitamins  B12 ,  B6 ,&#160; E , and  B1 ) ,  Some metabolic disorders are passed down through families (inherited), while others develop due to various diseases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002606-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>These symptoms occur because nerves cannot send proper signals to and from your brain: Difficulty feeling in any area of the body, Difficulty using the arms or hands, Difficulty using the legs or feet, Difficulty walking, Pain, burning feeling, a pins and needles feeling or shooting pains in any area of the body (nerve pain), Weakness in the face, arms, legs, or other areas of the body, Dysautonomia, which affects the autonomic (involuntary) nervous system, resulting in symptoms such as rapid heart rate, exercise intolerance, low blood pressure when standing, abnormal sweat patterns, stomach problems, abnormal functioning of the pupils of the eye, and poor erection,  These symptoms often start in the toes and feet and move up the legs, eventually affecting the hands and arms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002606-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will examine you and ask about your symptoms. Tests that may be ordered include: Blood tests, Electrical test of the muscles ( electromyography or EMG ), Electrical test of  nerve conduction ,  Nerve tissue biopsy , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002606-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>For most metabolic neuropathies, the best treatment is to correct the metabolic problem. Vitamin deficiencies are treated with diet or with vitamins by mouth or by injection. Abnormal blood sugar level or thyroid function may need medicines to correct the problem. For alcoholic neuropathy, the best treatment is to stop drinking. In some cases, pain is treated with medicines that reduce abnormal pain signals from the nerves. In some cases, lotions, creams, or medicated patches can provide relief. Weakness is often treated with physical therapy. You may need to learn how to use a cane or walker if your balance is affected. You may need special ankle braces to help you walk better.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002606-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>These groups can provide more information on neuropathy: Neuropathy Action Foundation --  www.neuropathyaction.org , The Foundation for Peripheral Neuropathy --  www.foundationforpn.org , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002606-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook mainly depends on the cause of the disorder. In some cases, the problem can easily be treated. In other cases, the metabolic problem cannot be controlled, and nerves may continue to become damaged.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002606-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications that may result include: Deformity, Injury to feet, Numbness or weakness, Pain, Trouble walking and falls, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002606-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Metabolic neuropathies ?</Question>
			<Answer>Maintaining a healthy lifestyle can reduce the risk for neuropathy. Avoid excess alcohol use., Eat a balanced diet., Quit smoking., Visit&#160;your provider regularly to find metabolic disorders before neuropathy develops. ,  If you have neuropathy in your feet, a foot doctor&#160;(podiatrist) can teach you how to inspect your feet for signs of injury and infection. Proper fitting shoes can lessen the chance of skin breakdown in sensitive areas of the feet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>