<Document id="0002564" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000374.htm">
 
<Focus>Medullary carcinoma of thyroid</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0238462</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Thyroid - medullary carcinoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cancer - thyroid (medullary carcinoma)</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MTC</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002564-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medullary carcinoma of the thyroid is cancer of the thyroid gland that starts in cells that release a hormone called calcitonin. These cells are called "C" cells. The thyroid gland is located inside the front of your lower neck.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002564-2" qtype="causes">What causes Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause of medullary carcinoma of the thyroid (MTC) is unknown. MTC is very rare. It can occur in children and adults. Unlike other types of thyroid cancer, MTC is less likely to be caused by radiation therapy to the neck given to treat other cancers during childhood. There are two forms of MTC: 
 Sporadic MTC, which does not run in families. Most MTCs are sporadic. This form mainly affects older adults.
 , Hereditary MTC, which runs in families.
 ,  You have an increased risk for this type of cancer if you have: 
 A family history of MTC
 , 
 A family history of  multiple endocrine neoplasia (MEN) , A prior history of  pheochromocytoma , mucosal neuromas,  hyperparathyroidism  or pancreatic endocrine tumors,  Other types of thyroid cancer include: Anaplastic carcinoma of the thyroid ,  Follicular tumor of the thyroid ,  Papillary carcinoma of the thyroid , 
 Thyroid  lymphoma , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002564-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>MTC often begins as a small lump (nodule) in the thyroid gland. There also may be  lymph node swelling  in the neck. As a result, symptoms may include: Swelling of the neck, Hoarseness, Breathing problems due to narrowing of airways, Cough,  Cough with blood , Diarrhea due to high calcitonin level, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002564-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask about your symptoms and medical history. Tests that may be used to diagnose MTC include: Calcitonin  blood test,  CEA  blood test, Genetic testing,  Thyroid biopsy ,  Ultrasound of the thyroid &#160;and the lymph nodes of the neck,  PET scan ,  People with MTC should be checked for certain other tumors, especially pheochromocytoma and parathyroid tumors and parathyroid tumors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002564-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment involves surgery to remove the thyroid gland and surrounding lymph nodes. Because this is an uncommon tumor, surgery should be performed by a surgeon who is familiar with this type of cancer and experienced with the operation required. Further treatment will depend on your calcitonin levels. A rise in calcitonin levels again may indicate new growth of the cancer. Chemotherapy and radiation do not work very well for this type of cancer., Radiation is used in some people after surgery., Newer  targeted therapies  may reduce tumor growth also. Your provider can tell you more about these, if needed.,  Near relatives of persons diagnosed with hereditary forms of MTC are at increased risk of this cancer and should discuss with their providers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002564-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most people with MTC live at least 5 years after diagnosis, depending upon the stage of the cancer. The 10-year survival rate is 65%.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002564-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: 
Cancer spreads to other areas of the body
  , 
Parathyroid glands are accidentally removed during surgery
  , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002564-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have symptoms of MTC.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002564-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Medullary carcinoma of thyroid ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prevention may not be possible. But, being aware of your risk factors, especially your family history, may allow for early diagnosis and treatment. For people who have a very strong family history of MTC, the option to remove the thyroid gland may be recommended. You should carefully discuss this option with a doctor who is very familiar with the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>