<Document id="0002268" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000661.htm">
 
<Focus>Kaposi sarcoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0036220</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Kaposi's sarcoma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002268-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Kaposi sarcoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kaposi sarcoma (KS) is a cancerous  tumor  of the connective tissue.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002268-2" qtype="causes">What causes Kaposi sarcoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>KS is the result of infection with a gamma herpesvirus known as Kaposi sarcoma-associated herpesvirus (KSHV), or human herpesvirus 8 (HHV8). It is in the same family as the Epstein-Barr virus, which causes  mononucleosis . KSHV is transmitted mainly through saliva. It can also be spread through sexual contact, blood transfusion, or transplants. After it enters the body, the virus can infect different kinds of cells, especially cells that line blood vessels and lymphatic vessels. Like all herpesviruses, KSHV remains in your body for the rest of your life. If your immune system becomes weakened in the future, this virus may have the chance to reactivate, causing symptoms. There are four types of KS based on the groups of people who are infected: Classic KS: Mainly affects older men of Eastern European, Middle Eastern, and Mediterranean descent. The disease usually develops slowly., Epidemic (AIDS-related) KS: Occurs most often in people who have  HIV infection  and have developed AIDS., Endemic (African) KS: Mainly affects people of all ages in Africa., Immunosuppression-associated, or transplantation-associated, KS: Occurs in people who have had an organ transplant and take medicines that suppress their immune system. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002268-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Kaposi sarcoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The tumors (lesions) most often appear as bluish-red or purple bumps on the skin. They are reddish-purple because they are rich in blood vessels. The lesions may first appear on any part of the body. They also can appear inside the body. Lesions inside the body may bleed. Lesions in the lungs can cause  bloody sputum  or  shortness of breath .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002268-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Kaposi sarcoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam, focusing on the lesions. The following tests may be performed to diagnose KS and associated conditions: Bronchoscopy ,  CT scan ,  Endoscopy ,  Skin biopsy , HIV test, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002268-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Kaposi sarcoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>How KS is treated depends on: How much the immune system is suppressed ( immunosuppression ), Number and location of the tumors, Symptoms ,  Treatments include: Antiviral therapy against&#160;HIV, since there is no specific therapy for HHV-8, Combination  chemotherapy , Freezing the lesions,  Radiation therapy ,  Lesions may return after treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002268-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Kaposi sarcoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treating KS does not improve the chances of survival from HIV/AIDS itself. The outlook depends on the person's immune status and how much of the HIV virus is in their blood (viral load).&#160;If the HIV is controlled with medicine, the lesions will often shrink away on their own.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002268-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Kaposi sarcoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications can include: Cough (possibly bloody) and shortness of breath if the disease is in the lungs, Leg swelling that may be painful or cause infections if the disease is in the lymph nodes of the legs ,  The tumors can return even after treatment. KS can be deadly for a person with AIDS. An aggressive form of endemic KS can spread quickly to the bones. Another form found in African children does not affect the skin. Instead, it spreads through the lymph nodes and vital organs, and can quickly become deadly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002268-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Kaposi sarcoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Safer sexual practices  can prevent HIV infection. This prevents HIV/AIDS and its complications, including KS. KS almost never occurs in people with HIV/AIDS whose disease is well controlled.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>