<Document id="0002346" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000499.htm">
 
<Focus>Latex allergies - for hospital patients</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0239966</CUI>
			<CUI>C0577628</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002346-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Latex allergies - for hospital patients ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you have a latex allergy, your skin or mucous membranes (eyes, mouth, nose, or other moist areas) react when latex touches them. A severe latex allergy can affect breathing and cause other serious problems. Latex is made from the sap of rubber trees. It is very strong and stretchy. For this reason, it is used in a lot of medical equipment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002346-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Latex allergies - for hospital patients ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you have a latex allergy, your skin or mucous membranes (eyes, mouth, nose, or other moist areas) react when latex touches them. A severe latex allergy can affect breathing and cause other serious problems. Latex is made from the sap of rubber trees. It is very strong and stretchy. For this reason, it is used in a lot of medical equipment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002346-4" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Latex allergies - for hospital patients? ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002346-5" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Latex allergies - for hospital patients ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002346-6" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Latex allergies - for hospital patients ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can have a reaction to latex if your skin, mucous membranes (eyes, mouth, or other moist areas), or bloodstream (during surgery) come into contact with latex. Breathing in the powder on latex gloves can also cause reactions. Symptoms of latex allergy include: Dry, itchy skin,  Hives , Skin redness and swelling, Watery, itchy eyes, Runny nose, Scratchy throat, Wheezing or coughing ,  Signs of a severe allergic reaction often involve more than one body part. Some of the symptoms are: Having a hard time breathing or swallowing, Dizziness or fainting, Confusion, Vomiting, diarrhea, or stomach cramps, Pale or red skin, Symptoms of shock, such as shallow breathing, cold and clammy skin, or weakness ,  A severe allergic reaction is an emergency. You must be treated right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>