<Document id="0002589" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001160.htm">
 
<Focus>Menkes syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022716</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Steely hair disease</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Menkes kinky hair syndrome</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Kinky hair disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002589-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Menkes disease is a genetic disorder in which the body has a problem absorbing and distributing copper to bodily organs. The disease affects development, both mental and physical.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002589-2" qtype="causes">What causes Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Menkes disease is caused by a defect in the  ATP7A  gene. The defect makes it hard for the body to properly distribute (transport) copper throughout the body. As a result, the brain and other parts of the body do not get enough copper, while it builds up in the small intestine and kidneys. A low copper level can affect the structure of bone, skin, hair, and blood vessels, and interfere with nerve function. Menkes syndrome is usually inherited, which means it runs in families. The gene is on the X-chromosome, so if a mother carries the defective gene, each of her sons has a 50% (1 in 2) chance of developing the disease, and 50% of her daughters will be a carrier of the disease. This kind of gene inheritance is called  X-linked recessive . In some people, the disease is not inherited from their parents. Instead, the gene defect occurs at the time the baby is conceived.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002589-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Common symptoms of Menkes disease in infants are: Brittle, kinky, steely, sparse, or tangled hair, Pudgy, rosy cheeks, sagging facial skin, Feeding difficulties, Irritability, Decreased muscle tone (hypotonia), floppiness,  Low body temperature , Intellectual disability and developmental delay,  Seizures , Skeletal changes, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002589-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Once Menkes disease is suspected, tests that may be done include: Ceruloplasmin blood test  (substance that transports copper in the blood), Copper  blood test , Skin cell culture, X-ray of the skeleton or x-ray of the skull, Gene testing to check for defect of the  ATP7A  gene , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002589-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment usually only helps when started very early in the course of the disease. Injections of copper into a vein or under the skin have been used with mixed results and depend on whether the  ATP7A  gene still has some activity.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002589-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most children with this disease die within the first few years of life.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002589-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002589-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Talk to your provider if you have a family history of Menkes syndrome and you plan to have children. A baby with this condition will often show symptoms early in infancy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002589-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Menkes syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>See a genetic counselor if you want to have children and you have a family history of Menkes syndrome. Maternal relatives (relatives on the mother's side of the family) of a boy with this syndrome could be seen by a geneticist to find out if they are carriers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>