<Document id="0002485" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000634.htm">
 
<Focus>Lymphogranuloma venereum</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0024286</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>LGV</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lymphogranuloma inguinale</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lymphopathia venereum</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002485-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lymphogranuloma venereum (LGV) is a sexually transmitted infection (STI).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002485-2" qtype="causes">What causes Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>LGV is a long-term (chronic) infection of the lymphatic system. It is caused by certain strains of the bacteria  Chlamydia trachomatis . The bacteria are spread by sexual contact. The infection is not caused by the same strain of bacteria that causes genital  chlamydia . LGV is more common in Central and South America than in North America.  LGV is more common in men than women. The main risk factor is being HIV-positive.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002485-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of LGV can begin a few days to a month after coming in contact with the bacteria. Symptoms include: Drainage through the skin from lymph nodes in the groin,  Painful bowel movements , Small painless sore on the male genitals or in the female genital tract, Swelling and redness of the skin in the groin area, Swelling of the labia (in women), Swollen groin lymph nodes on one or both sides; it may also affect lymph nodes around the rectum in people who have anal intercourse, Blood or pus from the rectum ( blood in the stools ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002485-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will examine you. You will be asked about your medical and sexual history. Tell your provider if you had sexual contact with someone you think has had symptoms of LGV. A physical exam may show: An oozing, abnormal connection (fistula) in the rectal area, A sore on the genitals, Drainage through the skin from lymph nodes in the groin, Swelling of the vulva or labia in women, Swollen lymph nodes in the groin,  Tests may include: Biopsy  of the lymph node, Blood test for the bacteria that causes LGV, Laboratory test to detect chlamydia from genital lesions, pharyngeal, rectal and lymph node specimens, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002485-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>LGV is treated with antibiotics,&#160;including doxycycline and erythromycin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002485-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>With treatment, the outlook is good and complete recovery can be expected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002485-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health problems that may result from LGV infection include: Abnormal connections between the rectum and vagina ( fistula ), Brain inflammation ( encephalitis  - very rare), Infections in the joints, eyes, heart, or liver, Long-term inflammation and swelling of the genitals, Scarring and narrowing of the rectum,  Complications can occur many years after you are first infected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002485-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You have been in contact with someone who may have an STI, including LGV, You develop symptoms of LGV, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002485-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Lymphogranuloma venereum ?</Question>
			<Answer>Not having any sexual activity is the only way to prevent an STI.  Safer sex behaviors  may reduce the risk. The proper use of condoms, either the  male  or  female  type, greatly decreases the risk of catching an STI. You need to wear the condom from the beginning to the end of each sexual activity.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>