<Document id="0002114" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003298.htm">
 
<Focus>Hypotonia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026827</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Decreased muscle tone</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Floppy infant</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002114-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypotonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypotonia means decreased muscle tone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002114-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Hypotonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypotonia is often a sign of a worrisome problem. The condition can affect children or adults. Infants with this problem seem floppy and feel like a "rag doll" when held. They rest with their elbows and knees loosely extended. Infants with normal tone tend to have flexed elbows and knees. They may have poor head control. The head may fall to the side, backward, or forward. Infants with normal tone can be lifted with the adult's hands placed under the armpits. Hypotonic infants tend to slip between the hands.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002114-3" qtype="causes">What causes Hypotonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Muscle tone and movement involve the brain, spinal cord, nerves, and muscles. Hypotonia may be a sign of a problem anywhere along the pathway that controls muscle movement. Causes may include: Brain damage, due to lack of oxygen before or right after birth, or problems with brain formation, Disorders of the muscles, such as  muscular dystrophy , Disorders that affect the nerves that supply muscles, Disorders that affect the ability of nerves to send messages to the muscles, Infections ,  Genetic or chromosomal disorders, or defects that may cause brain and nerve damage include: Down syndrome ,  Spinal muscular atrophy ,  Prader-Willi syndrome ,  Tay-Sachs disease ,  Trisomy 13 ,  Other disorders that can lead to the condition include: Achondroplasia ,  Being born with hypothyroidism , Poisons or toxins, Spinal cord injuries that occur around the time of birth, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002114-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Hypotonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypotonia is often a sign of a worrisome problem. The condition can affect children or adults. Infants with this problem seem floppy and feel like a "rag doll" when held. They rest with their elbows and knees loosely extended. Infants with normal tone tend to have flexed elbows and knees. They may have poor head control. The head may fall to the side, backward, or forward. Infants with normal tone can be lifted with the adult's hands placed under the armpits. Hypotonic infants tend to slip between the hands.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002114-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hypotonia ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>