<Document id="0002865" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002588.htm">
 
<Focus>Oral hypoglycemics overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0029944</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Diabetes pill overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sulfonylurea overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002865-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Oral hypoglycemics overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oral hypoglycemic pills are medicines to control diabetes. Oral means "taken by mouth." There are many different types of oral hypoglycemics. This article focuses on a type called sulfonylureas. An  overdose  occurs when someone takes more than the normal or recommended amount of this medicine. The result is a drop in blood sugar level that affects normal function of the body's organs. An overdose may occur by accident or on purpose. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with overdoses, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002865-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Oral hypoglycemics overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of an overdose of this medicine include: Agitation, sometimes violent, Nervousness, anxiety, Tremor, shaking, Apathy (lack of desire to do anything), Coma (decreased level of consciousness and lack of responsiveness),  Confusion ,  Convulsions  (seizures, especially in infants and children),  Increased appetite ,  Nausea ,  Rapid heartbeat ,  Stupor  (decreased level of consciousness plus confusion), Sweating,  Tingling  of tongue and lips ,  People who have had a stroke in the past may appear to be having another stroke if their blood sugar drops too low.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002865-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Oral hypoglycemics overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some oral hypoglycemics may stay in the body for a long time, so the person may need to stay in the hospital for 24 hours or more. Permanent brain damage and death are possible, especially if  blood glucose level  does not return to normal in a timely manner. Infants, children, and older people are most likely to develop more serious and long-term complications from low blood sugar levels that are not corrected rapidly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002865-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Oral hypoglycemics overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some oral hypoglycemics may stay in the body for a long time, so the person may need to stay in the hospital for 24 hours or more. Permanent brain damage and death are possible, especially if  blood glucose level  does not return to normal in a timely manner. Infants, children, and older people are most likely to develop more serious and long-term complications from low blood sugar levels that are not corrected rapidly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>