<Document id="0002810" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002478.htm">
 
<Focus>Nitric acid poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0161695</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002810-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nitric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nitric acid is a poisonous clear-to-yellow liquid. It is a chemical known as a caustic. If it contacts tissues, it can cause severe damage, such as burning, on contact. This article discusses poisoning from swallowing or breathing in nitric acid. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002810-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nitric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms from swallowing nitric acid may include: Abdominal pain  - severe, Burns to skin or mouth, Drooling, Fever, Mouth pain - severe, Rapid drop in blood pressure (shock), Throat swelling, which leads to breathing difficulty, Throat pain - severe, Vomiting, bloody ,  Symptoms from breathing in (inhaling) nitric acid may include: Bluish-colored lips and fingernails &#160;(cyanosis), Chest tightness, Choking, Coughing, Coughing up blood, Dizziness, Low blood pressure, Rapid pulse, Shortness of breath, Weakness ,  If the poison touches your skin or eyes, you may have: Blisters, Burns, Pain, Vision loss , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002810-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Nitric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002810-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Nitric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on the amount of poison swallowed, how concentrated the poison is, and how quickly treatment was received. The faster a person gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Cancer of the esophagus is a high risk in people who survive after ingesting nitric acid.&#160; Perforation may lead to potentially serious infection and shock, which may be fatal. Permanent injury and disability may occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002810-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Nitric acid poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does depends on the amount of poison swallowed, how concentrated the poison is, and how quickly treatment was received. The faster a person gets medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Cancer of the esophagus is a high risk in people who survive after ingesting nitric acid.&#160; Perforation may lead to potentially serious infection and shock, which may be fatal. Permanent injury and disability may occur.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>