<Document id="0002620" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007480.htm">
 
<Focus>Methamphetamine overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Other</Category>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Intoxication - amphetamines</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intoxication - uppers</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Amphetamine intoxication</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Uppers overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Overdose - methamphetamine</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Crank overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Meth overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Crystal meth overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Speed overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ice overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>MDMA overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002620-1" qtype="information">Do you have information about Methamphetamine overdose</Question>
			<Answer>Methamphetamine is a stimulant drug. A strong form of the drug is illegally sold on the streets. A much weaker form of the drug is used to treat narcolepsy and attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). This weaker form is sold as a prescription. Medicines that are legally used to treat cold symptoms, such as decongestants, can be made into methamphetamines. Other related compounds include MDMA, ('ecstasy,' 'Molly,' 'E'), MDEA, ('Eve'), and MDA, ('Sally,' 'sass'). This article focuses on the illegal street drug. The street drug is usually a white crystal-like powder, called "crystal meth." This powder can be snorted up the nose, smoked, swallowed, or dissolved and injected into a vein. A methamphetamine  overdose  may be acute (sudden) or chronic (long-term). An acute methamphetamine overdose occurs when someone takes this drug by accident or on purpose and has side effects. These side effects can be life threatening., A chronic methamphetamine overdose refers to the health effects in someone who uses the drug on a regular basis. ,  Injuries during illegal methamphetamine production or police raids include exposure to dangerous chemicals, as well as burns and explosions. All of these can cause serious, life threatening injuries and conditions. This is for information only and not for use in the treatment or management of an actual overdose. If you have an overdose, you should call your local emergency number (such as 911) or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>