<Document id="0002750" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003117.htm">
 
<Focus>Nausea and vomiting - adults</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0027498</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Emesis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Vomiting</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Stomach upset</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Upset stomach</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Queasiness</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002750-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nausea and vomiting - adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nausea is feeling an urge to vomit. It is often called "being sick to your stomach." Vomiting or throwing-up forces the contents of the stomach up through the food pipe (esophagus) and out of the mouth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002750-2" qtype="causes">What causes Nausea and vomiting - adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>Common problems that may cause nausea and vomiting include: Food allergies , Infections of the stomach or bowels, such as the "stomach flu" or  food poisoning , Leaking of stomach contents (food or liquid) upward (also called  gastroesophageal reflux  or GERD), Medicines or medical treatments, such as cancer  chemotherapy  or radiation treatment,  Migraine headaches ,  Morning sickness  during pregnancy, Seasickness or motion sickness, Severe pain, such as with kidney stones, Excessive use of marijuana ,  Nausea and vomiting may also be early warning signs of more serious medical problems, such as: Appendicitis ,  Blockage in the intestines , Cancer or a tumor, Ingesting a drug or poison, especially by children,  Ulcers in the lining of the stomach or small intestine , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002750-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Nausea and vomiting - adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002750-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Nausea and vomiting - adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911 or the local emergency number or go to an emergency room if you: Think the vomiting is from poisoning, Notice blood or dark, coffee-colored material in the vomit,  Call a provider right away or seek medical care if you or another person has: Been vomiting for longer than 24 hours, Been unable to keep any fluids down for 12 hours or more, Headache or stiff neck, Not urinated for 8 or more hours, Severe stomach or belly pain, Vomited 3 or more times in 1 day,  Signs of  dehydration  include: Crying without tears, Dry mouth, Increased thirst, Eyes that appear sunken, Skin changes: For example, if you touch or squeeze the skin, it doesn't bounce back the way it usually does, Urinating less often or having dark yellow urine, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002750-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Nausea and vomiting - adults ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>