<Document id="0002538" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001534.htm">
 
<Focus>Mathematics disorder</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1411876</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Developmental dyscalculia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002538-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mathematics disorder is a condition in which a child's math ability is far below normal for their age, intelligence, and education.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002538-2" qtype="causes">What causes Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children who have mathematics disorder have trouble with simple mathematical activities, such as counting and adding. Mathematical disorder may appear with: Developmental coordination disorder ,  Developmental reading disorder ,  Mixed receptive-expressive language disorder , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002538-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>The child may have trouble with math, as well as low scores in math classes and on tests. Problems the child may have are: Trouble with reading, writing, and copying numbers, Problems counting and adding numbers, often making simple mistakes, A hard time telling the difference between adding and subtracting, Problems understanding math symbols and word problems, Can't line up numbers properly to add, subtract, or multiply, Can't arrange numbers from smallest to largest, or the opposite, Can't understand graphs , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002538-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Standardized tests can assess the child's math ability. Grades and class performance can also help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002538-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>The best treatment is special (remedial) education. Computer-based programs may also help.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002538-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Early intervention improves the chances of a better outcome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002538-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>The child may have problems in school, including behavior problems and loss of self-esteem. Some children with mathematics disorder become anxious or afraid when given math problems, making the problem even worse.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002538-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call for an appointment with your health care provider if you have any concerns about your child's development.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002538-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Mathematics disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recognizing the problem early is important.&#160;Treatment may begin as early as kindergarten or elementary school.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>