<Document id="0002101" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001461.htm">
 
<Focus>Hypomelanosis of Ito</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022283</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Incontinentia pigmenti achromians</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002101-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Hypomelanosis of Ito ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hypomelanosis of Ito (HMI) is a very rare birth defect that causes unusual patches of light-colored ( hypopigmented ) skin and may be associated with eye, nervous system, and skeletal problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002101-2" qtype="causes">What causes Hypomelanosis of Ito ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health care providers do not know the exact cause of HMI, but they believe it may involve a genetic condition called mosaicism. It is twice as common in girls as in boys.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002101-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Hypomelanosis of Ito ?</Question>
			<Answer>Skin symptoms are most often visible by the time a child is about 2 years old. Other symptoms develop as the child grows, and may include: Crossed eyes  (strabismus), Hearing problems, Increased body hair ( hirsutism ),  Scoliosis ,  Seizures , Streaked, whorled or mottled patches of skin on the arms, legs, and middle of the body, Intellectual disability, including  autism spectrum disorder  and learning disability, Mouth or tooth problems , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002101-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Hypomelanosis of Ito ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ultraviolet light ( Wood lamp ) examination of the skin lesions may help confirm the diagnosis. Tests that may be done include any of the following: CT  or  MRI  scan of the head for a child with seizures and nervous system symptoms, X-rays for a child with skeletal problems,  EEG  to measure the electrical activity of the brain in a child with seizures, Genetic testing, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002101-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Hypomelanosis of Ito ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no treatment for the skin patches. Cosmetics or clothing may be used to cover the patches. Seizures, scoliosis, and other problems are treated as needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002101-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Hypomelanosis of Ito ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook depends on the type and severity of symptoms that develop. In most cases, skin color eventually turns to normal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002101-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Hypomelanosis of Ito ?</Question>
			<Answer>Problems that may result from HMI include: Discomfort and walking problems due to scoliosis, Emotional distress, related to the physical appearance,  Intellectual disability , Injury from seizures, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002101-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Hypomelanosis of Ito ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if your child has an unusual pattern of the color of the skin.&#160;However, any unusual patterns are likely to have another cause than HMI.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>