<Document id="0002334" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001385.htm">
 
<Focus>Laryngitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0023067</CUI>
			<CUI>C0001327</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hoarseness</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002334-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Laryngitis is swelling and irritation (inflammation) of the voice box (larynx). The problem is most often associated with  hoarseness  or loss of voice.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002334-2" qtype="causes">What causes Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The voice box (larynx) is located at the top of the airway to the lungs (trachea). The larynx contains the vocal cords. When the vocal cords become inflamed or infected, they swell. This can cause hoarseness. Sometimes, the airway can get blocked. The most common form of laryngitis is an infection caused by a virus. It may also be caused by: Allergies , Bacterial infection,  Bronchitis , Gastroesophageal reflux disease (GERD), Injury, Irritants and chemicals,  Laryngitis often occurs with an  upper respiratory infection , which is typically caused by a virus. Several forms of laryngitis occur in children that can lead to a dangerous or fatal respiratory blockage. These forms include: Croup ,  Epiglottitis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002334-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Fever, Hoarseness, Swollen lymph nodes or glands in the neck , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002334-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam can find whether hoarseness is caused by a respiratory tract infection. People with hoarseness that lasts more than a month (especially smokers) should see an ear, nose, and throat doctor (otolaryngologist). An exam of the throat and upper airway will be done.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002334-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Laryngitis is often caused by a virus, so antibiotics likely will not help. Your health care provider will make this decision. Resting your voice helps to reduce inflammation of the vocal cords. A humidifier may soothe the scratchy feeling that comes with laryngitis. Decongestants and pain medicines may relieve the symptoms of an upper respiratory infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002334-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Laryngitis that is not caused by a serious condition often gets better on its own.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002334-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>In rare cases, severe respiratory distress develops. This requires immediate medical attention.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002334-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: A small child who is not teething has difficulty breathing, swallowing, or is  drooling , A child less than 3 months old has hoarseness, Hoarseness has lasted for more than 1 week in a child, or 2 weeks in an adult, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002334-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Laryngitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>To prevent getting laryngitis: Try to avoid people who have upper respiratory infections during cold and flu season., Wash your hands often., Do not strain your voice., Stop smoking. This can help prevent tumors of the head and neck or lungs, which can lead to hoarseness. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>