<Document id="0002290" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003005.htm">
 
<Focus>Kidney transplant</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0677491</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Renal transplant</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Transplant - kidney</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002290-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Kidney transplant ?</Question>
			<Answer>A kidney transplant is surgery to place a healthy kidney into a person with  kidney failure .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002290-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Kidney transplant ?</Question>
			<Answer>A kidney transplant is surgery to place a healthy kidney into a person with  kidney failure .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002290-4" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Kidney transplant? ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002290-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Kidney transplant ?</Question>
			<Answer>Almost everyone feels that they have a better quality of life after the transplant. Those who receive a kidney from a living related donor do better than those who receive a kidney from a donor who has died. If you donate a kidney, you can most often live safely without complications with your one remaining kidney. People who receive a transplanted kidney may reject the new organ. This means that their immune system sees the new kidney as a foreign substance and tries to destroy it. In order to avoid rejection, almost all kidney transplant recipients must take medicines that suppress their immune response for the rest of their life. This is called immunosuppressive therapy. Although the treatment helps prevent organ rejection, it also puts patients at a higher risk for infection and cancer. If you take this type of medicine, you need to be screened for cancer. The medicines may also cause high blood pressure and high cholesterol and increase the risk for diabetes. A successful kidney transplant requires close follow-up with your doctor and you must always take your medicine as directed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>