<Document id="0002020" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000845.htm">
 
<Focus>How childhood cancers are different from adult cancers</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0006826</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002020-1" qtype="information">What is (are) How childhood cancers are different from adult cancers ?</Question>
			<Answer>Childhood cancers are not the same as adult cancers. The type of cancer, how far it spreads, and how it is treated is often different from adult cancers. Children's bodies and the way they respond to treatments are unique as well.  Keep this in mind when reading about cancer. Some cancer research is based on adults only. Your child's cancer care team can help you understand your child's cancer and the best options for treatment. One big difference is that the chance of recovery is high in children. Most children with cancer can be cured.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002020-2" qtype="information">What is (are) How childhood cancers are different from adult cancers ?</Question>
			<Answer>Childhood cancers are not the same as adult cancers. The type of cancer, how far it spreads, and how it is treated is often different from adult cancers. Children's bodies and the way they respond to treatments are unique as well.  Keep this in mind when reading about cancer. Some cancer research is based on adults only. Your child's cancer care team can help you understand your child's cancer and the best options for treatment. One big difference is that the chance of recovery is high in children. Most children with cancer can be cured.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002020-3" qtype="causes">What causes How childhood cancers are different from adult cancers ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of the time the cause of a childhood cancer is not known. Some cancers are linked to changes in certain genes (mutations) passed from parent to child. In some children, gene changes that occur during early growth in the womb increase the risk of leukemia. However, not all children with the mutation get cancer. Children born with Down syndrome are also more likely to develop leukemia.  Unlike adult cancers, childhood cancers do not occur due to lifestyle choices, like diet and smoking.  It is hard to study childhood cancer because it is rare. Scientists have looked at other risk factors including chemicals, toxins, and factors from the mother and father. The results of these studies show few clear links to childhood cancers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002020-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose How childhood cancers are different from adult cancers ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002020-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for How childhood cancers are different from adult cancers ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment for childhood cancer is similar to treatment for adult cancer. It may include: Chemotherapy ,  Radiation therapy , Medicines,  Immune therapy ,  Stem cell transplants , Surgery ,  For children, the amount of therapy, type of medicine, or need for surgery may differ from adults. In many cases, the cancer cells in children respond better to treatments compared to adults. Children can often handle higher doses of chemo drugs in shorter periods before side effects occur. Children seem to bounce back sooner from treatments compared to adults.  Some treatments or medicines given to adults are not safe for children. Your health care team will help you to understand what is right for your child depending on their age. Children with cancer are best treated in  children's cancer centers  attached to major children's hospitals or universities. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>