<Document id="0002728" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001514.htm">
 
<Focus>Nabothian cyst</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0027269</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002728-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>A nabothian cyst is a lump filled with mucus on the surface of the cervix or cervical canal. The cervix is located at the lower end of the womb (uterus) at the top of the vagina. It is about 1 inch (2.5 centimeters) long.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002728-2" qtype="causes">What causes Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cervix is lined with glands and cells that release mucus. The glands can become covered by a type of skin cells called squamous epithelium. When this happens, the secretions build up in the plugged glands. They form a smooth, rounded bump on the  cervix . The bump is called a nabothian cyst.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002728-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>Each nabothian cyst appears as a small, white raised bump. There can be more than one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002728-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>During a pelvic exam, your health care provider will see a small, smooth, rounded lump (or collection of lumps) on the surface of the cervix. Rarely, magnifying the area (colposcopy) may be needed to tell these cysts from other bumps that can occur. Most women have small nabothian cysts. These can be detected by vaginal ultrasound. If you're told you have a nabothian cyst during a vaginal ultrasound exam, don't be concerned, as their presence is normal. Sometimes the cyst is opened to confirm the diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002728-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>No treatment is necessary. Nabothian cysts do not cause any problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002728-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nabothian cysts do not cause any harm. They are a  benign  condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002728-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>The presence of many cysts or cysts that are large and blocked can make it hard for the provider to do a  Pap test . This is rare.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002728-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of the time, this condition is found during a routine pelvic exam.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002728-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Nabothian cyst ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known prevention. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>