<Document id="0002918" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003150.htm">
 
<Focus>Painful menstrual periods</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013390</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Menstruation - painful</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dysmenorrhea</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Periods - painful</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cramps - menstrual</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Menstrual cramps</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002918-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Painful menstrual periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Painful menstrual periods are periods in which a woman has crampy lower abdominal pain, which can be sharp or aching and come and go. Back pain and/or leg pain may also be present. Some pain during your period is normal, but a large amount of pain is not. The medical term for painful menstrual periods is dysmenorrhea.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002918-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Painful menstrual periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many women have painful periods. Sometimes, the pain makes it hard to do normal household, job, or school-related activities for a few days during each menstrual cycle. Painful menstruation is the leading cause of lost time from school and work among women in their teens and 20s.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002918-3" qtype="causes">What causes Painful menstrual periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Painful menstrual periods fall into two groups, depending on the cause: Primary dysmenorrhea, Secondary dysmenorrhea ,  Primary dysmenorrhea is menstrual pain that occurs around the time that menstrual periods first begin in otherwise healthy young women. In most cases, this pain is not related to a specific problem with the uterus or other pelvic organs. Increased activity of the hormone prostaglandin, which is produced in the uterus, is thought to play a role in this condition. Secondary dysmenorrhea is menstrual pain that develops later in women who have had normal periods. It is often related to problems in the uterus or other pelvic organs, such as: Endometriosis ,  Fibroids ,  Intrauterine device  (IUD) made of copper,  Pelvic inflammatory  disease
   ,  Premenstrual syndrome  (PMS), Sexually transmitted infection, Stress and anxiety , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002918-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Painful menstrual periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Many women have painful periods. Sometimes, the pain makes it hard to do normal household, job, or school-related activities for a few days during each menstrual cycle. Painful menstruation is the leading cause of lost time from school and work among women in their teens and 20s.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002918-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Painful menstrual periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider right away if you have: Increased or foul-smelling vaginal discharge, Fever and pelvic pain, Sudden or severe pain, especially if your period is more than 1 week late and you have been sexually active. ,  Also call if: Treatments do not relieve your pain after 3 months., You have pain and had an IUD placed more than 3 months ago., You pass blood clots or have other symptoms with the pain., Your pain occurs at times other than menstruation, begins more than 5 days before your period, or continues after your period is over. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002918-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Painful menstrual periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>