<Document id="0002529" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000373.htm">
 
<Focus>Maple syrup urine disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0024776</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MSUD</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0002529-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Maple syrup urine disease (MSUD) is a disorder in which the body cannot break down certain parts of proteins. The urine of people with this condition can smell like maple syrup.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0002529-2" qtype="causes">What causes Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Maple syrup urine disease (MSUD) is inherited, which means it is passed down through families. It is caused by a defect in 1 of 3 genes. People with this condition cannot break down the  amino acids  leucine, isoleucine, and valine. This leads to a buildup of these chemicals in the blood. In the most severe form, MSUD can damage the brain during times of physical stress (such as infection, fever, or not eating for a long time). Some types of MSUD are mild or come and go. Even in the mildest form, repeated periods of physical stress can cause  intellectual&#160;disability  and high levels of leucine to build up.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0002529-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of this disorder include: Coma, Feeding difficulties,  Lethargy ,  Seizures , Urine that smells like maple syrup, Vomiting , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0002529-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>These tests may be done to check for this disorder: Plasma amino acid test ,  Urine organic acid test , Genetic testing,  There will be signs of  ketosis  (buildup of ketones, a by-product of burning fat for energy) and excess acid in the blood (acidosis).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0002529-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>When the condition is diagnosed, and during episodes, treatment involves eating a protein-free diet. Fluids, sugars, and sometimes fats are given through a vein (IV). Dialysis through your belly or a vein can be done to reduce the level of abnormal substances in your blood. Long-term treatment requires a special diet. For infants, the diet includes a formula with low levels of the amino acids leucine, isoleucine, and valine. People with this condition must remain on a diet low in these amino acids for life. It is very important to always follow this diet to prevent nervous system (neurological) damage. This requires frequent blood tests and close supervision by a registered dietitian and physician, as well as cooperation by parents of children with the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0002529-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>This disease can be life threatening if untreated. Even with dietary treatment, stressful situations and illness can still cause high levels of certain amino acids. Death may occur during these episodes. With strict dietary treatment, children have grown into adulthood and can remain healthy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0002529-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>These complications can occur: Neurological damage, Coma, Death, Intellectual disability, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0002529-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have a family history of MSUD and are planning to start a family. Also call your provider right away if you have a newborn who has symptoms of maple syrup urine disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0002529-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Maple syrup urine disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling is suggested for people who want to have children and who have a family history of maple syrup urine disease. Many states now screen all newborns with blood testing for MSUD. If a screening test shows that your baby may have MSUD, a follow-up blood test for amino acid levels should be done right away to confirm the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>