<Document id="0003669" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003204.htm">
 
<Focus>Speech impairment (adult)</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0233715</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Language impairment</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Impairment of speech</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Inability to speak</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Aphasia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dysarthria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Slurred speech</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dysphonia voice disorders</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003669-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Speech impairment (adult) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Speech and language impairment may be any of several problems that make it difficult to communicate.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003669-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Speech impairment (adult) ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following are common speech and language disorders. APHASIA Aphasia is loss of the ability to understand or express spoken or written language. It commonly occurs after strokes or traumatic brain injuries. It can also occur in people with brain tumors or degenerative diseases that affect the language areas of the brain. This term does not apply to children who have never developed communication skills. There are many different types of aphasia. In some cases of aphasia, the problem eventually corrects itself, but in others, it doesn't get better.
 DYSARTHRIA With  dysarthria , the person has problems expressing certain sounds or words. They have poorly pronounced speech (such as slurring) and the rhythm or speed of speech is changed. Usually, a nerve or brain disorder has made it difficult to control the tongue, lips, larynx, or vocal cords, which make speech. Dysarthria, which is difficulty pronouncing words, is sometimes confused with aphasia, which is difficulty producing language. They have different causes. People with dysarthria may also have problems swallowing. VOICE DISTURBANCES Anything that changes the shape of the vocal cords or the way they work will cause a voice disturbance. Lump-like growths such as nodules, polyps, cysts, papillomas, granulomas, and cancers can be to blame. These changes cause the voice to sound different from the way it normally sounds.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003669-3" qtype="causes">What causes Speech impairment (adult) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some of these disorders develop gradually, but anyone can develop a speech and language impairment suddenly, usually due to a stroke or trauma. APHASIA Alzheimer disease , Brain tumor (more common in aphasia than dysarthria), Dementia, Head trauma, Stroke, Transient ischemic attack (TIA) ,  DYSARTHRIA Alcohol intoxication, Dementia, Diseases that affect nerves and muscles (neuromuscular diseases), such as  amyotrophic lateral sclerosis  (ALS or Lou Gehrig disease), cerebral palsy, myasthenia gravis, or  multiple sclerosis  (MS), Facial trauma, Facial weakness, such as  Bell's palsy  or tongue weakness,  Head trauma , Head and neck cancer surgery, Nervous system (neurological) disorders that affect the brain, such as  Parkinson disease  or  Huntington disease  (more common in dysarthria than aphasia), Poorly fitting dentures, Side effects of medicines that act on the central nervous system, such as narcotics, phenytoin, or carbamazepine,  Stroke ,  Transient ischemic attack (TIA) ,  VOICE DISTURBANCES Growths or nodules on the vocal cords, People who use their voice heavily (teachers, coaches, vocal performers) are more likely to develop voice disorders. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003669-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Speech impairment (adult) ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following are common speech and language disorders. APHASIA Aphasia is loss of the ability to understand or express spoken or written language. It commonly occurs after strokes or traumatic brain injuries. It can also occur in people with brain tumors or degenerative diseases that affect the language areas of the brain. This term does not apply to children who have never developed communication skills. There are many different types of aphasia. In some cases of aphasia, the problem eventually corrects itself, but in others, it doesn't get better.
 DYSARTHRIA With  dysarthria , the person has problems expressing certain sounds or words. They have poorly pronounced speech (such as slurring) and the rhythm or speed of speech is changed. Usually, a nerve or brain disorder has made it difficult to control the tongue, lips, larynx, or vocal cords, which make speech. Dysarthria, which is difficulty pronouncing words, is sometimes confused with aphasia, which is difficulty producing language. They have different causes. People with dysarthria may also have problems swallowing. VOICE DISTURBANCES Anything that changes the shape of the vocal cords or the way they work will cause a voice disturbance. Lump-like growths such as nodules, polyps, cysts, papillomas, granulomas, and cancers can be to blame. These changes cause the voice to sound different from the way it normally sounds.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003669-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Speech impairment (adult) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact the provider if: Impairment or loss of communication comes on suddenly, There is any unexplained impairment of speech or written language, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003669-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Speech impairment (adult) ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>