<Document id="0003635" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001151.htm">
 
<Focus>Small intestinal ischemia and infarction</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0021308</CUI>
			<CUI>C0156149</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Intestinal necrosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ischemic bowel</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dead bowel</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dead gut</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003635-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Intestinal ischemia and infarction occurs when there is a narrowing or blockage of one or more of the arteries that supply the small intestine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003635-2" qtype="causes">What causes Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are several possible causes of intestinal ischemia and infarction. Hernia  -- If the intestine moves into the wrong place or becomes tangled, it can cut off the blood flow. ,  Adhesions  -- The intestine may become trapped in scar tissue (adhesions) from past surgery. This can lead to loss of blood flow if left untreated., Embolus --  Blood clots  can block one of the arteries supplying the intestine. People who have had a heart attack or who have  arrhythmias , such as  atrial fibrillation , are at risk for this problem., Narrowing of the arteries -- The arteries that supply blood to the bowel may become narrowed or blocked from cholesterol buildup. When this happens in the arteries to the heart, it causes a heart attack. When it happens in the arteries to the intestine, it causes intestinal ischemia., Narrowing of the veins -- The veins carrying blood away from the intestine may become blocked by blood clots. This blocks blood flow in the intestine. This is more common in people with liver disease, cancer, or blood clotting disorders., Low blood pressure -- Very low blood pressure in people who already have narrowing of the intestinal arteries may also cause loss of blood flow to the intestine. This often occurs in people with other serious medical problems. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003635-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main symptom of intestinal ischemia is pain in abdomen. The pain is severe, even though the area is not very tender when touched. Other symptoms include: Diarrhea, Fever, Vomiting, Blood in the stool, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003635-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Laboratory tests may show a high  white blood cell (WBC) count  (a marker of infection). There may be bleeding in the GI tract.  Some tests to detect the extent of damage include: Increased acid in the bloodstream (lactic acidosis),  Angiogram ,  CT scan  of the abdomen,  Doppler ultrasound  of the abdomen ,  These tests do not always detect the problem. Sometimes, the only way to detect intestinal ischemia is with a surgical procedure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003635-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>In most cases, the condition needs to be treated with surgery. The section of intestine that has died is removed. The healthy remaining ends of the bowel are reconnected. In some cases, a  colostomy  or  ileostomy  is needed. The blockage of arteries to the intestine is corrected, if possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003635-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Damage or death of the bowel tissue is a serious condition. This can result in death if not treated right away. The outlook depends on the cause. Prompt treatment can lead to a good outcome.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003635-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Damage or death of the bowel tissue may require a colostomy or ileostomy. This may be short-term or permanent.  Peritonitis  is common in these cases. People who have a large amount of tissue death in the intestine can have problems absorbing nutrients. They can become dependent on getting nutrition through their veins.  Some people may become severely ill with fever and a bloodstream infection ( sepsis ).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003635-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have any severe abdominal pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003635-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Small intestinal ischemia and infarction ?</Question>
			<Answer>Preventive measures include: Controlling risk factors, such as irregular heartbeat, high blood pressure, and high cholesterol, Not smoking , Eating a nutritious diet, Quickly treating hernias, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>