<Document id="0003954" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002558.htm">
 
<Focus>Tolmetin overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0572201</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tolectin overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003954-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tolmetin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tolmetin is an NSAID (nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug). It is used to help relieve pain, tenderness, swelling, and stiffness due to certain types of arthritis or other conditions that cause inflammation, such as sprains or strains. In the United States, Tolmetin has been discontinued and is no longer available, but it is still used internationally. Tolmetin  overdose  occurs when someone takes more than the normal or recommended amount of this medicine, either by accident or on purpose. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with overdoses, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003954-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tolmetin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Below are symptoms of an overdose of tolmetin in different parts of the body. AIRWAYS AND LUNGS Rapid breathing, Slow breathing, Wheezing ,  EYES, EARS, NOSE, AND THROAT Blurred vision ,  Ringing in the ears ,  KIDNEYS AND BLADDER Kidney failure,  NERVOUS SYSTEM Coma ,  Confusion ,  Convulsions , Dizziness,  Drowsiness , Incoherence (not understandable),  Unsteadiness ,  STOMACH AND INTESTINAL TRACT Abdominal pain, Bleeding in the stomach and intestines, Diarrhea, Heartburn, Nausea and vomiting (sometimes bloody),  SKIN Rash, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003954-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Tolmetin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003954-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tolmetin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recovery is very likely. However, gastrointestinal bleeding may be severe and require blood transfusion. Kidney damage may be permanent. Some people may need endoscopy, placing a tube through the mouth to the stomach, to stop the bleeding. Some may need to use a kidney machine (dialysis) if their kidney function does not return to normal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003954-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tolmetin overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recovery is very likely. However, gastrointestinal bleeding may be severe and require blood transfusion. Kidney damage may be permanent. Some people may need endoscopy, placing a tube through the mouth to the stomach, to stop the bleeding. Some may need to use a kidney machine (dialysis) if their kidney function does not return to normal.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>