<Document id="0003975" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000749.htm">
 
<Focus>Torticollis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040485</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Spasmodic torticollis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Wry neck</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Loxia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cervical dystonia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003975-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Torticollis is a condition in which the neck muscles cause the head to tilt, turn or rotate to the side.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003975-2" qtype="causes">What causes Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Torticollis may be: Due to changes in genes, often passed down in the family, Due to problems in the nervous system, upper spine, or muscles,  The condition may also occur without a known cause. With torticollis present at birth, it may occur if: The baby's head was in the wrong position while growing in the womb, The muscles or blood supply to the neck were injured, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003975-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of torticollis include: Limited movement  of the head,  Headache , Head tremor, Neck pain, Shoulder that is higher than the other, Stiffness of the neck muscles, Swelling of the neck muscles (possibly present at birth) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003975-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam. The exam may show: The head is rotated, tilted, or leaning forward or backward. In severe cases, the entire head is pulled and turned to one side., Shortened or larger neck muscles.,  Tests that may be done include: X-ray of the neck,  CT scan  of the head and neck,  Electromyogram  (EMG) to see which muscles are most affected,  MRI of the head and neck , Blood tests to look for medical conditions that are linked to torticollis, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003975-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treating torticollis that is present at birth involves stretching the shortened neck muscle. Passive stretching and positioning are used in infants and small children. In passive stretching, a device such as strap, a person, or something else is used to hold the body part in a certain position. These treatments are often successful, especially if they are started within 3 months of birth. Surgery to correct the neck muscle may be done in the preschool years, if other treatment methods fail. Torticollis that is caused by damage to the nervous system, spine, or muscles is treated by finding the cause of the disorder and treating it. Depending on the cause, treatment may include: Physical therapy (applying heat,  traction  to the neck, and massage to help relieve head and neck pain)., Stretching exercises and neck braces to help with muscle spasms., Taking medicines such as baclofen to reduce neck muscle contractions., Injecting botulinum toxin., Trigger point injections to relieve pain at a particular point., Surgery of the spine might be needed when the torticollis is due to dislocated vertebrae. In some cases, surgery involves destroying some of the nerves in the neck muscles, or using brain stimulation., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003975-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The condition may be easier to treat in infants and children. If torticollis becomes  chronic , numbness and tingling may develop due to pressure on the nerve roots in the neck.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003975-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications in children may include: Flat head syndrome, Deformity of the face due to lack of sternomastoid muscle movement,  Complications in adults may include: Muscle swelling due to constant tension, Nervous system symptoms due to pressure on nerve roots, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003975-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if symptoms do not improve with treatment, or if new symptoms develop. Torticollis that occurs after an injury or with illness may be serious. Seek medical help right away if this occurs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003975-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Torticollis ?</Question>
			<Answer>While there is no known way to prevent this condition, early treatment may prevent it from getting worse.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>