<Document id="0003477" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001525.htm">
 
<Focus>Schizotypal personality disorder</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0036363</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003477-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Schizotypal personality disorder (SPD) is a mental condition in which a person has trouble with relationships and disturbances in thought patterns, appearance, and behavior.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003477-2" qtype="causes">What causes Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of SPD is unknown. Many factors may be involved: Genetic -- SPD seems to be more common among relatives of people with SPD . Studies have found that some gene defects are found more often in people with SPD., Psychological -- A person's personality, ability to deal with stress, and handle relationships with others may contribute to SPD., Environmental -- Emotional trauma as a child and chronic stress may also play roles in developing SPD., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003477-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>SPD should not be confused with  schizophrenia . People with SPD can have odd beliefs and behaviors, but unlike people with schizophrenia, they are not disconnected from reality and usually do not&#160; hallucinate . They also do not have delusions. People with SPD may be very disturbed. They may also have unusual preoccupations and fears, such as fear of being monitored by government agencies. More commonly, people with this disorder behave oddly and have unusual beliefs (such as aliens). They cling to these beliefs so strongly that they have difficulty forming and keeping close relationships. People with SPD may also have depression. A second personality disorder, such as  borderline personality disorder , is also common. Mood, anxiety, and substance use disorders are also common among people with SPD. Common signs of SPD include: Discomfort in social situations, Inappropriate displays of feelings, No close friends, Odd behavior or appearance, Odd beliefs, fantasies, or preoccupations, Odd speech, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003477-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>SPD is diagnosed based on a psychological evaluation. The health care provider will consider how long and how severe the person's symptoms have been.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003477-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Talk therapy is an important part of treatment. Social skills training can help some people cope with social situations. Medicines may also be a helpful addition if mood or anxiety disorders are also present.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003477-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>SPD is usually a long-term (chronic) illness. Outcome of treatment varies based on the severity of the disorder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003477-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Poor social skills, Lack of interpersonal relationships , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003477-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>See your provider or a mental health professional if you or someone you know has symptoms of SPD.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003477-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Schizotypal personality disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known prevention. Awareness of risk, such as a family history of schizophrenia, may allow early diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>