<Document id="0003925" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001213.htm">
 
<Focus>Thyroid cancer</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0549473</CUI>
			<CUI>C0007115</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tumor - thyroid</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cancer - thyroid</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003925-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Thyroid cancer is a cancer that starts in the thyroid gland. The thyroid gland is located inside the front of your lower neck.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003925-2" qtype="causes">What causes Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Thyroid cancer can occur in people of any age. Radiation increases the risk of developing thyroid cancer. Exposure may occur from: Radiation therapy  to the neck (especially in childhood), Radiation exposure from nuclear plant disasters ,  Other risk factors are a family history of thyroid cancer and chronic  goiter  (enlarged thyroid). Being overweight or having obesity may be a risk factor for papillary carcinoma of the thyroid. There are several types of thyroid cancer: Anaplastic carcinoma  (also called giant and spindle cell cancer) is the most dangerous form of thyroid cancer. It is rare, and spreads quickly., Follicular tumor is more likely to come back and spread.,  Medullary carcinoma  is a cancer of non-thyroid hormone-producing cells that are normally present in the thyroid gland. This form of thyroid cancer tends to occur in families.,  Papillary carcinoma  is the most common type, and it usually affects women of childbearing age. It spreads slowly and is the least dangerous type of thyroid cancer. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003925-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms vary depending on the type of thyroid cancer, but may include: Cough, Difficulty swallowing, Enlargement of the thyroid gland, Hoarseness or changing voice, Neck swelling, Thyroid lump (nodule), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003925-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical exam. This may reveal a lump in the thyroid or swollen lymph nodes in the neck. The following tests may be done: Calcitonin  blood test to check for medullary thyroid cancer, Laryngoscopy (looking inside the throat using a mirror or flexible tube called a laryngoscope placed through the mouth) ;to assess vocal cord function, Thyroid biopsy, which may include genetic testing of the cells obtained in the biopsy,  Thyroid scan ,  TSH , free  T4  (blood tests for thyroid function),  Ultrasound of the thyroid  and the lymph nodes of the neck, CT scan of the neck (to determine the extent of the cancerous mass),  PET scan , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003925-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the type of thyroid cancer. Treatment of most thyroid cancer types is effective if diagnosed early. Surgery is most often done. All or part of the thyroid gland may be  removed . If your provider suspects that the cancer has spread to lymph nodes in the neck, these will also be removed. If some of your thyroid gland remains, you will need follow-up ultrasound and possibly other studies to detect any regrowth of thyroid cancer. Radiation therapy may be done with or without surgery. It may be performed by: Taking radioactive iodine by mouth, Aiming external beam (x-ray) radiation at the thyroid,  After treatment for thyroid cancer, you must take thyroid hormone pills for the rest of your life. The dosage is usually slightly higher than what your body needs. This helps keep the cancer from coming back. The pills also replace the thyroid hormone your body needs to function normally. If the cancer does not respond to surgery or radiation, and has spread to other parts of the body,  chemotherapy  or  targeted therapy  may be used. These are only needed by a small number of people.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003925-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can ease the stress of illness by joining a  cancer support group . Sharing with others who have common experiences and problems can help you not feel alone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003925-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications of thyroid cancer may include: Injury to the voice box and hoarseness after thyroid surgery, Low calcium level from accidental removal of the parathyroid glands during surgery, Spread of the cancer to the lungs, bones, or other parts of the body , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003925-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if you notice a lump in your neck.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003925-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Thyroid cancer ?</Question>
			<Answer>Awareness of risk (such as previous radiation therapy to the neck) can allow earlier diagnosis and treatment. Sometimes, people with family histories and genetic mutations related to medullary thyroid cancer will have their thyroid gland removed to prevent cancer.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>