<Document id="0003931" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002592.htm">
 
<Focus>Thyroid preparation overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0029944</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003931-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Thyroid preparation overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Thyroid preparations are medicines used to treat thyroid gland disorders. Overdose occurs when someone takes more than the normal or recommended amount of this medicine. This can be by accident or on purpose. Symptoms of thyroid preparation overdose can be the same as symptoms of stimulant medicines. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual overdose. If you or someone you are with has an overdose, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003931-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Thyroid preparation overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of poisoning with this type of medicine include: Anxiety, nervousness,  Tremor , shaking,  Insomnia ,  Seizures , Confusion, Muscle aches or cramps, Irregular heartbeat,  Palpitations , Chest pain or discomfort, Changes in menstrual pattern, Dilated pupils,  Excessive sweating , skin flushing, Nausea, vomiting, Diarrhea, Weight loss,  Shock  (extremely low blood pressure and collapse), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003931-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Thyroid preparation overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003931-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Thyroid preparation overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>People who receive quick treatment make a good recovery. But heart-related complications can lead to death.  Symptoms may not appear until a week after the overdose or may build up over time. They may be treated successfully with several medicines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003931-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Thyroid preparation overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>People who receive quick treatment make a good recovery. But heart-related complications can lead to death.  Symptoms may not appear until a week after the overdose or may build up over time. They may be treated successfully with several medicines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>