<Document id="0003460" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001210.htm">
 
<Focus>Sanfilippo syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0026706</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>MPS III</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003460-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mucopolysaccharidosis type III (MPS III) is a rare disease in which the body is missing or does not have enough of certain  enzymes  needed to break down long chains of sugar molecules. These chains of molecules are called glycosaminoglycans (formerly called mucopolysaccharides). As a result, the molecules build up in different parts of the body and cause various health problems. The condition belongs to a group of diseases called  mucopolysaccharidoses  (MPSs). MPS III is also known as Sanfilippo syndrome. There are several other types of MPSs, including: MPS I  (Hurler syndrome; Hurler-Scheie syndrome; Scheie syndrome),  MPS II  (Hunter syndrome),  MPS IV  (Morquio syndrome), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003460-2" qtype="causes">What causes Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>MPS III is an inherited disorder. This means it is typically passed down through families. If both parents carry a nonworking copy of a gene related to this condition, each of their children has a 25% (1 in 4) chance of developing the disease. This is called an  autosomal recessive  trait. MPS III occurs when the enzymes needed to break down the heparan sulfate sugar chain are missing or defective. There are four main types of MPS III. The type a person has depends on which enzyme is affected. Type A is caused by a defect in the  SGSH  gene and is the most severe form. People with this type do not have a normal form of the enzyme called heparan  N -sulfatase., Type B is caused by a defect in the  NAGLU  gene. People with this type are missing or do not produce enough alpha- N -acetylglucosaminidase., Type C is caused by a defect in the  HGSNAT  gene. People with this type are missing or do not produce enough acetyl-CoA:alpha-glucosaminide N-acetyltransferase., Type D is caused by a defect in the  GNS  gene. People with this type are missing or do not produce enough  N -acetylglucosamine 6-sulfatase. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003460-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms often appear after the first year of life. A decline in learning ability typically occurs between ages 2 and 6. The child may have normal growth during the first few years, but final height is below average. Delayed development is followed by worsening mental status. Other symptoms may include: Behavioral problems, including  hyperactivity , Coarse facial features with heavy eyebrows that meet in the middle of the face above the nose, Chronic diarrhea,  Enlarged liver  and  spleen , Sleep difficulties, Stiff joints that may not extend fully, Vision problems and hearing loss, Walking problems , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003460-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will perform a physical exam. Urine tests will be done. People with MPS III have a large amount of a mucopolysaccharide called heparan sulfate in the urine. Other tests may include: Blood enzyme level,  Echocardiogram , Genetic testing,  Slit lamp eye exam , Skin fibroblast culture, X-rays of the bones , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003460-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment of MPS III is aimed at managing the symptoms. There is no specific treatment for this disease. New research is under development for gene therapy and enzyme replacement.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003460-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>More information and support for people with MPS III and their families can be found at: National MPS Society --  mpssociety.org/ , National Organization for Rare Disorders --  rarediseases.org/rare-diseases/mucopolysaccharidosis-type-iii/ , NIH Genetic and Rare Diseases Information Center --  rarediseases.info.nih.gov/diseases/3807/mucopolysaccharidosis-type-iii , Team Sanfilippo Foundation --  teamsanfilippo.org/ , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003460-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>MPS III causes significant nervous system symptoms, including severe intellectual disability. Most people with MPS III live into their teenage years. Some live longer, while others with severe forms die at an earlier age. Symptoms are most severe in people with type A.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003460-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>These complications can occur: Blindness, Inability to care for self, Intellectual disability, Nerve damage that slowly gets worse and eventually requires wheelchair use, Seizures , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003460-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your child's provider if your child does not seem to be growing or developing normally. See your provider if you plan to have children and you have a family history of MPS III.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0003460-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Sanfilippo syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling  is recommended for couples who want to have children and who have a family history of MPS III. Prenatal testing is available.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>