<Document id="0003612" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000865.htm">
 
<Focus>Skin lesion of blastomycosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0005716</CUI>
			<CUI>C0037284</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003612-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Skin lesion of blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>A skin lesion of blastomycosis is a symptom of an infection with the fungus  Blastomyces dermatitidis.  The skin becomes infected as the fungus spreads throughout the body. Another form of blastomycosis is only on the skin and usually gets better on its own with time. This article deals with the more widespread form of the infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003612-2" qtype="causes">What causes Skin lesion of blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Blastomycosis  is a rare fungal infection. It is most&#160;often found&#160;in: Africa, Canada, around the Great Lakes, South central and north central&#160;United States, India, Israel, Saudi Arabia ,  A person gets infected by breathing in particles of the fungus that are found in moist soil, especially where there is rotting vegetation. People with immune system disorders are at higher risk for this infection, though healthy people can also develop this disease. The fungus enters the body through the lungs and infects them. In some people, the fungus then spreads (disseminates) to other areas of the body. The infection may affect the skin, bones and joints,&#160;genitals and urinary&#160;tract, and other systems. Skin symptoms are a sign of widespread (disseminated) blastomycosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003612-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Skin lesion of blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>In many people, skin symptoms develop when the infection spreads beyond their lungs. Papules ,  pustules , or  nodules  are most frequently found on exposed body areas. They may look like warts or ulcers., They are usually painless., They may vary from gray to violet in color.,  The pustules may: Form ulcers, Bleed easily, Occur in the nose or mouth,  Over time, these skin lesions can lead to scarring and loss of skin color (pigment).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003612-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Skin lesion of blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will examine your skin and ask about symptoms. The infection is diagnosed by identifying the fungus in a culture taken from a skin lesion. This usually requires a  skin biopsy .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003612-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Skin lesion of blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>This infection is treated with antifungal drugs such as amphotericin B, itraconazole, voriconazole, or fluconazole. Either oral or intravenous (directly in the vein) drugs are used, depending on the drug and stage of the disease.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003612-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Skin lesion of blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well you do depends on the form of blastomycosis and on your immune system. People with a suppressed immune system may need long-term treatment to prevent symptoms from coming back.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003612-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Skin lesion of blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Abscesses (pockets of pus), Another (secondary) skin infection caused by bacteria, Complications related to medicines (for instance, amphotericin B can have severe side effects), Spontaneously draining nodules , Severe body-wide infection and death , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003612-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Skin lesion of blastomycosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some of the skin problems caused by blastomycosis can be similar to skin problems caused by other illnesses. Tell your provider if you develop any worrisome skin problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>