<Document id="0003071" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001541.htm">
 
<Focus>Phonological disorder</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0003910</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Articulation disorder</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Developmental articulation disorder</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Speech distortion</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Sound distortion</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003071-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Phonological disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Phonological disorder is a type of speech sound disorder. Speech sound disorders are the inability to correctly form the sounds of words.  Speech sound disorders  also include articulation disorder, disfluency, and voice disorders.  Children with phonological disorder do not use some or all of the speech sounds to form words as expected for a child their age.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003071-2" qtype="causes">What causes Phonological disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>This disorder is more common in boys. The cause of phonological disorders in children is often unknown. Close relatives may have had speech and language problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003071-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Phonological disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>In a child developing normal speech patterns: By age 3, at least one half of what a child says should be understood by a stranger., The child should make most sounds correctly by age 4 or 5, except for a few sounds such as  l ,  s ,  r ,  v ,  z ,  ch ,  sh,  and  th ., Harder sounds may not be completely correct until age 7 or 8.,  It is normal for young children to make speech errors as their language develops. Children with a phonological disorder keep using incorrect speech patterns past the age they should have stopped using them. Incorrect speech rules or patterns include dropping the first or last sound of each word or replacing certain sounds for others. Children may leave out a sound even though they are able to pronounce the same sound when it occurs in other words or in nonsensical syllables. For example, a child who drops last consonants may say "boo" for "book" and "pi" for "pig", but may have no problem saying words like "key" or "go". These errors may make it hard for other people to understand the child. Only family members may be able to understand a child who has a more severe phonological speech disorder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003071-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Phonological disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>A speech language pathologist can diagnose a phonological disorder. They may ask the child to say certain words and then use a test such as the Arizona-4 (Arizona Articulation and Phonology Scale, 4th revision). Children should be examined to help rule out disorders not linked with phonological disorders. These include: Cognitive problems (such as  intellectual disability ), Hearing impairment, Neurological conditions (such as  cerebral palsy ), Physical problems (such as cleft palate),  The health care provider should ask questions, such as&#160;if more than one language or a certain dialect is spoken at home.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003071-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Phonological disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Milder forms of this disorder may go away on their own by around age 6. Speech therapy may help more severe symptoms or speech problems that don't get better. Therapy may help the child create the sound. For example, a therapist can show where to place the tongue or how to form the lips when making a sound.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003071-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Phonological disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome depends on the age the disorder started and how severe it is. Many children&#160;will go on to&#160;develop almost normal speech.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003071-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Phonological disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>In severe cases, the child may have problems being understood even by family members. In milder forms, the child may have trouble being understood by people outside the family. Social and academic problems (reading or writing disability) may occur as a result.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003071-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Phonological disorder ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if your child is: Still difficult to understand by age 4, Still unable to make certain sounds by age 6, Leaving out, changing, or substituting certain sounds at age 7, Having speech problems that cause embarrassment, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>