<Document id="0003620" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000060.htm">
 
<Focus>Skull fracture</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0037304</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Basilar skull fracture</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Depressed skull fracture</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Linear skull fracture</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003620-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Skull fracture ?</Question>
			<Answer>A skull  fracture  is a fracture or break in the skull (cranial) bones.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003620-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Skull fracture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Skull fractures may occur with  head injuries . The skull provides good protection for the brain. However, a severe impact or blow can cause the skull to break. It may be accompanied by a&#160; concussion  or other injury to the brain. The brain can be affected directly by damage to the nervous system tissue and bleeding. The brain can also be affected by bleeding under the skull. This can compress the underlying brain tissue. A simple fracture is a break in the bone without damage to the skin. A linear skull fracture is a break in a cranial bone resembling a thin line, without splintering, depression, or distortion of bone. A depressed skull fracture is a break in a cranial bone (or "crushed" portion of skull) with depression of the bone in toward the brain. A compound fracture involves a break in, or loss of, skin and splintering of the bone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003620-3" qtype="causes">What causes Skull fracture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Causes of skull fracture can include: Head trauma, Falls, automobile accidents, physical assault, and sports , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003620-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Skull fracture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Bleeding from wound, ears, nose, or around eyes,  Bruising  behind the ears or under the eyes, Changes in pupils ( sizes unequal , not reactive to light),  Confusion , Convulsions ( seizures ), Difficulties with balance, Drainage of clear or bloody fluid from ears or nose,  Drowsiness ,  Headache , Loss of consciousness (unresponsiveness),  Nausea and vomiting ,  Restlessness , irritability,  Slurred speech ,  Stiff neck ,  Swelling , Visual disturbances ,  In some cases, the only symptom may be a bump on the head. A bump or bruise may take up to 24 hours to develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003620-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Skull fracture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Skull fractures may occur with  head injuries . The skull provides good protection for the brain. However, a severe impact or blow can cause the skull to break. It may be accompanied by a&#160; concussion  or other injury to the brain. The brain can be affected directly by damage to the nervous system tissue and bleeding. The brain can also be affected by bleeding under the skull. This can compress the underlying brain tissue. A simple fracture is a break in the bone without damage to the skin. A linear skull fracture is a break in a cranial bone resembling a thin line, without splintering, depression, or distortion of bone. A depressed skull fracture is a break in a cranial bone (or "crushed" portion of skull) with depression of the bone in toward the brain. A compound fracture involves a break in, or loss of, skin and splintering of the bone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003620-6" qtype="considerations">What to do for Skull fracture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Skull fractures may occur with  head injuries . The skull provides good protection for the brain. However, a severe impact or blow can cause the skull to break. It may be accompanied by a&#160; concussion  or other injury to the brain. The brain can be affected directly by damage to the nervous system tissue and bleeding. The brain can also be affected by bleeding under the skull. This can compress the underlying brain tissue. A simple fracture is a break in the bone without damage to the skin. A linear skull fracture is a break in a cranial bone resembling a thin line, without splintering, depression, or distortion of bone. A depressed skull fracture is a break in a cranial bone (or "crushed" portion of skull) with depression of the bone in toward the brain. A compound fracture involves a break in, or loss of, skin and splintering of the bone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003620-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Skull fracture ?</Question>
			<Answer>The provider will perform a physical exam. The person's nervous system will be checked. There may be changes in the person's pupil size, thinking ability, coordination, and reflexes. Get medical help right away if: There are problems with breathing or circulation., Direct pressure does not stop bleeding from the nose, ears, or wound., There is drainage of clear fluid from the nose or ears., There is facial swelling, bleeding, or bruising., There is an object protruding from the skull., The person is unconscious, is experiencing convulsions, has multiple injuries, appears to be in any distress, or cannot think clearly.,  Tests that may be done include: Blood and urine tests,  Brain wave test  [electroencephalogram (EEG)] may be needed if seizures are present,  Head CT scan ,  MRI of the brain ,  X-rays , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003620-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Skull fracture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Not all head injuries can be prevented. The following  simple steps  can help keep you and your child safe:  Always use safety equipment during activities that could cause a head injury. These include seat belts, bicycle or motorcycle helmets, and hard hats., Learn and follow bicycle safety recommendations., Do not drink and drive. Do not allow yourself to be driven by someone who may have been drinking alcohol or is otherwise impaired., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>