<Document id="0003908" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001119.htm">
 
<Focus>Thoracic aortic aneurysm</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0162872</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Aortic aneurysm - thoracic</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Syphilitic aneurysm</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Aneurysm - thoracic aortic</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003908-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>An aneurysm is an abnormal widening or ballooning of a portion of an artery due to weakness in the wall of the blood vessel. A thoracic aortic aneurysm occurs in the part of the body's largest artery (the aorta) that passes through the chest.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003908-2" qtype="causes">What causes Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>The most common cause of a thoracic aortic aneurysm is  hardening of the arteries  (atherosclerosis). This condition is more common in people with high cholesterol, long-term high blood pressure, or who smoke. Other risk factors for a thoracic aneurysm include: Changes caused by age, Connective tissue disorders such as  Marfan  or Ehlers-Danlos syndrome, Inflammation of the aorta, Injury from falls or motor vehicle accidents, Syphilis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003908-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>Aneurysms develop slowly over many years. Most people have no symptoms until the aneurysm begins to leak or expand.  Symptoms often begin suddenly when: The aneurysm grows quickly., The aneurysm tears open (called a rupture)., Blood leaks along the wall of the aorta (aortic dissection).,  If the aneurysm presses on nearby structures, the following symptoms may occur: Hoarseness, Swallowing problems, High-pitched breathing (stridor), Swelling in the neck,  Other symptoms may include: Chest or upper back pain, Clammy skin, Nausea and vomiting, Rapid heart rate, Sense of impending doom, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003908-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>The physical exam is often normal unless a rupture or leak has occurred.  Most thoracic aortic aneurysms are detected on imaging tests performed for other reasons. These tests include chest x-ray, echocardiogram, or  chest CT scan  or MRI. A chest CT scan shows the size of the aorta and the exact location of the aneurysm. An aortogram (a special set of x-ray images made when dye is injected into the aorta) can identify the aneurysm and any branches of the aorta that may be involved.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003908-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is a risk that the aneurysm may open up (rupture) if you do not have surgery to repair it. The treatment depends on the location of the aneurysm. The aorta is made of three parts: The first part moves upward toward the head. It is called the ascending aorta., The middle part is curved. It is called the aortic arch., The last part moves downward, toward the feet. It is called the descending aorta.,  For people with aneurysms of the ascending aorta or aortic arch: Surgery to replace the aorta is recommended if an aneurysm is larger than 5 to 6 centimeters (approximately 2 inches)., A cut is made in the middle of the breast bone (sternum)., The aorta is replaced with a plastic or fabric graft., This is major surgery that requires a heart-lung machine.,  For people with aneurysms of the descending thoracic aorta: Major surgery is done to replace the aorta with a fabric graft if the aneurysm is larger than 6 centimeters (2.3 inches)., This surgery is done through a cut on the left side of the chest, which may reach to the abdomen., Endovascular stenting is a less invasive option. A  stent  is a tiny metal or plastic tube that is used to hold an artery open. Stents can be placed into the body without cutting the chest. However, not all people with descending thoracic aneurysms are candidates for stenting., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003908-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>The long-term outlook for people with thoracic aortic aneurysm depends on other medical problems, such as heart disease, high blood pressure, and diabetes. These problems may have caused or contributed to the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003908-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>Serious complications after aortic surgery can include: Bleeding, Graft infection, Heart attack, Irregular heartbeat, Kidney damage, Paralysis, Stroke,  Death soon after the operation occurs in 5% to 10% of people. Complications after aneurysm stenting include damage to the blood vessels supplying the leg, which may require another operation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003908-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have: A family history of connective tissue disorders (such as Marfan or Ehlers-Danlos syndrome), Chest or back discomfort , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003908-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Thoracic aortic aneurysm ?</Question>
			<Answer>To prevent atherosclerosis: Control your blood pressure and blood lipid levels., DO NOT smoke., Eat a healthy diet., Exercise regularly. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>