<Document id="0003543" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000820.htm">
 
<Focus>Serum sickness</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0036830</CUI>
			<CUI>C1963234</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003543-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Serum sickness is a reaction that is similar to an  allergy . The  immune system reacts  to medicines that contain proteins used to treat immune conditions. It can also react to antiserum, the liquid part of blood that contains  antibodies  given to a person to help protect them against germs or poisonous substances.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003543-2" qtype="causes">What causes Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Plasma is the clear fluid portion of blood. It does not contain blood cells. But it does contain many proteins, including antibodies, which are formed as part of the immune response to protect against infection. Antiserum is produced from the plasma of a person or animal that has immunity against an infection or poisonous substance. Antiserum may be used to protect a person who has been exposed to a germ or toxin. For example, you may receive a certain type of antiserum injection: If you have been exposed to  tetanus  or  rabies &#160;and have never been vaccinated against these germs. This is called passive immunization., If you have been bitten by a snake that produces a dangerous toxin.,  During serum sickness, the immune system falsely identifies a protein in antiserum as a harmful substance ( antigen ). The result is an immune system response that attacks the antiserum. Immune system elements and the antiserum combine to form immune complexes, which cause the symptoms of serum sickness. Certain medicines (such as penicillin, cefaclor, and sulfa) can cause a similar reaction. Injected proteins such as antithymocyte globulin (used to treat organ transplant rejection) and rituximab (used to treat immune disorders and cancers) can cause serum sickness reactions. Blood products may also cause serum sickness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003543-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unlike other  drug allergies , which occur very soon after receiving the medicine, serum sickness develops 7 to 21 days after the first exposure to a medicine. Some people develop symptoms in 1 to 3 days if they have already been exposed to the medicine. Symptoms of serum sickness can include: Fever, General ill feeling,  Hives , Itching, Joint pain, Rash, Swollen lymph nodes , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003543-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform an exam to look for lymph nodes that are enlarged and tender to the touch. Tests that may be done include: Urine test, Blood test, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003543-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Medicines, such as corticosteroids, applied to the skin may relieve discomfort from itching and a rash. Antihistamines may shorten the length of the illness and help ease a rash and itching. Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), such as ibuprofen or naproxen, may relieve joint pain. Corticosteroids taken by mouth may be prescribed for severe cases. The medicine that caused the problem should be stopped. Avoid using that medicine or antiserum in the future.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003543-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>The symptoms usually go away within a few days.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003543-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>If you use the drug or antiserum that caused serum sickness again in the future, your risk of having another similar reaction is high. Complications include: Inflammation of the blood vessels, Swelling of the face, arms, and legs ( angioedema ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003543-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you received medicine or antiserum in the last 4 weeks and have symptoms of serum sickness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003543-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Serum sickness ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known way to prevent the development of serum sickness.  People who have had serum sickness or drug allergy should avoid future use of the antiserum or drug.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>