<Document id="0003473" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001321.htm">
 
<Focus>Schistosomiasis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0036323</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bilharzia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Katayama fever</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Swimmer's itch</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Blood fluke</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003473-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Schistosomiasis is an infection with a type of blood fluke parasite called schistosomes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003473-2" qtype="causes">What causes Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can get a schistosoma infection through contact with contaminated water. This parasite swims freely in open bodies of fresh water. When the parasite comes into contact with humans, it burrows into the skin and matures into another stage. Then, it travels to the lungs and liver, where it grows into the adult form of the worm. The adult worm then travels to its preferred body part, depending on its species. These areas include the: Bladder, Rectum, Intestines, Liver, Veins that carry blood from the intestines to the liver, Spleen, Lungs,  Schistosomiasis is not usually seen in the United States except for returning travelers or people from other countries who have the infection and are now living in the United States. It is common in many tropical and subtropical areas worldwide.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003473-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms vary with the species of worm and the phase of infection. Many parasites may cause fever, chills, swollen lymph nodes, and swollen&#160;liver and spleen., When the worm first gets into the skin, it&#160;may cause itching and a rash (swimmer's itch). In this condition, the schistosome is destroyed within the skin., Intestinal symptoms include abdominal pain and diarrhea (which may be bloody)., Urinary symptoms may include frequent urination, painful urination, and blood in the urine. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003473-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will examine you. Tests that may be done include: Antibody test to check for signs of infection,  Biopsy  of tissue,  Complete blood count (CBC)  to check for signs of anemia, Eosinophil count to measure the number of eosinophils, a type of white blood cell, Kidney function tests, Liver function tests, Stool examination to look for parasite eggs,  Urinalysis  to look for parasite eggs , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003473-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>This infection is usually treated with the drug praziquantel or oxamniquine. This is usually given along with corticosteroids. If the infection is severe or involves the brain, corticosteroids may be given first.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003473-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment before significant damage or severe complications occur usually produces good results.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003473-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>These complications may occur: Bladder cancer,  Chronic kidney failure , Chronic liver damage and an enlarged spleen, Colon (large intestine) inflammation, Kidney and bladder blockage, 
   High blood pressure in the arteries of the lungs ( pulmonary hypertension ), Repeated blood infections, if bacteria enter the bloodstream through an irritated colon, Right-sided heart failure,  Seizures , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003473-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you develop symptoms of schistosomiasis, especially if you have: Traveled to a tropical or subtropical area where the disease is known to exist, Been exposed to contaminated or possibly contaminated bodies of water, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003473-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Schistosomiasis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Follow these steps to avoid getting this infection: Avoid swimming or bathing in contaminated or potentially contaminated water., Avoid bodies of water if you do not know whether they are safe.,  Snails can host this parasite and are part of its normal life cycle. Getting rid of snails in bodies of water used by humans may help prevent infection.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>