<Document id="0003108" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002044.htm">
 
<Focus>Plaque and tartar on teeth</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0011330</CUI>
			<CUI>C0241148</CUI>
			<CUI>C0333463</CUI>
			<CUI>C0332461</CUI>
			<CUI>C0011389</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T020</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tartar and plaque on teeth</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Calculus</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003108-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Plaque and tartar on teeth ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your dentist or hygienist should show you the correct way to brush and floss. Prevention is key to  oral health . Brush at least twice a day for at least two minutes each time. The brush head should have medium to soft, rounded bristles and not be too large for your mouth, letting you reach every surface in your mouth easily. The toothpaste should contain fluoride, and not be too abrasive. Electric toothbrushes have been shown to clean teeth better than manual brushes . Some have timers to tell you when two minutes have passed. Other tips for preventing and removing tartar or plaque on your teeth include: Floss gently at least once a day, following the technique provided by your dental professional. This is important to prevent gum disease., Using water irrigation systems helps to flush out debris from between your teeth, and under your gums, which may help control bacteria around your teeth and below the gum line., See your dentist or dental hygienist at least every 6 months for a thorough teeth cleaning and oral exam. Some people who have periodontal disease may require more frequent cleanings., Swishing a solution or chewing a special tablet in your mouth may help identify areas of plaque buildup., Well-balanced meals will help keep your teeth and gums healthy. Avoid snacking between meals, especially on sticky or sugary foods as well as food high in carbohydrates, such as potato chips. If you do snack in the evening, you need to brush afterward. No more eating or drinking (water is allowed) after the bedtime brushing., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>