<Document id="0003860" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001417.htm">
 
<Focus>Tay-Sachs disease</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039373</CUI>
			<CUI>C0012634</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003860-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tay-Sachs disease is a life-threatening disease of the nervous system passed down through families.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003860-2" qtype="causes">What causes Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tay-Sachs disease occurs when the body lacks hexosaminidase A. This is a protein that helps break down a group of chemicals found in nerve tissue called gangliosides. Without this protein, gangliosides, particularly ganglioside GM2, build up in cells, often nerve cells in the brain. Tay-Sachs disease is caused by a defective gene on  chromosome  15. When both parents carry the defective Tay-Sachs gene, a child has a 25% chance of developing the disease. The child must receive two copies of the defective gene, one from each parent, in order to become sick. If only one parent passes the defective gene to the child, the child is called a carrier. They will not be sick, but may pass the disease to their own children. Anyone can be a carrier of the Tay-Sachs gene. But, the disease is most common among people with Ashkenazi Jewish ancestry, where 1 in every 27 people carries the Tay-Sachs gene. Tay-Sachs is divided into infantile, juvenile, and adult forms, depending on the symptoms and when they first appear. Most people with Tay-Sachs have the infantile form. In this form, the nerve damage usually begins while the baby is still in the womb. Symptoms usually appear when the child is 3 to 6 months old. The disease tends to get worse very quickly, and the child usually dies by age 4 or 5. Late-onset Tay-Sachs disease, which affects adults, is very rare.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003860-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include any of the following: Deafness , Decreased eye contact,  blindness ,  Decreased muscle tone  (loss of muscle strength), loss of motor skills, paralysis, Slow growth and delayed mental and social skills,  Dementia  (loss of brain function), Increased startle reaction, Irritability, Listlessness,  Seizures , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003860-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will examine your baby and ask about your family history. Tests that may be done are: Enzyme  exam of blood or body tissue for hexosaminidase levels, Eye exam (reveals a cherry-red spot in the  macula ) , Genetic testing, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003860-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no treatment for Tay-Sachs disease itself, only ways to make the person more comfortable.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003860-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>The stress of illness may be eased by joining  support groups  whose members share common experiences and problems. The following groups can provide more information on Tay-Sachs disease: National Organization for Rare Disorders --  rarediseases.org/rare-diseases/tay-sachs-disease , National Tay-Sachs and Allied Diseases Association --  www.ntsad.org , NLM Genetics Home Reference --  ghr.nlm.nih.gov/condition/tay-sachs-disease , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003860-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children with this disease have symptoms that get worse over time. They usually die by age 4 or 5.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003860-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms appear during the first 3 to 10 months of life and progress to  spasticity , seizures, and loss of all voluntary movements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003860-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>Go to the emergency room or call 911 or the local emergency number if:  Your child has a seizure of unknown cause, The seizure is different from previous seizures, The child has  difficulty breathing , The seizure lasts longer than 2 to 3 minutes ,  Contact your provider for an appointment if your child has other noticeable behavioral changes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0003860-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Tay-Sachs disease ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known way to prevent this disorder once someone is born. Genetic testing can detect if you are a carrier of the gene for this disorder. If you or your partner is from an at-risk population, you may wish to seek  genetic counseling  before starting a family. If you are already pregnant,  testing the amniotic fluid  can diagnose Tay-Sachs disease in the womb.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>