<Document id="0003368" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000488.htm">
 
<Focus>Renal papillary necrosis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0022667</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Necrosis - renal papillae</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Renal medullary necrosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003368-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Renal papillary necrosis is a disorder of the kidneys in which all or part of the renal papillae die. The renal papillae are the areas where the openings of the collecting ducts enter the kidney and where urine flows into the ureters.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003368-2" qtype="causes">What causes Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Renal papillary necrosis often occurs with  analgesic nephropathy . This is damage to one or both kidneys caused by overexposure to pain medicines. But, other conditions can also cause renal papillary necrosis, including: Diabetic nephropathy , Kidney infection (pyelonephritis), Kidney transplant rejection,  Sickle cell anemia , a common cause of renal papillary necrosis in children, Urinary tract blockage, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003368-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of renal papillary necrosis may include: Back pain or  flank pain ,  Bloody, cloudy, or dark urine , Tissue pieces in the urine,  Other symptoms that may occur with this disease: Fever and chills,  Painful urination , Needing to urinate more often than usual (frequent urination) or a sudden, strong urge to urinate (urgency), Difficulty starting or maintaining a urine stream ( urinary hesitancy ),  Urinary incontinence , Urinating large amounts, Urinating often at night, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003368-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The area over the affected kidney (in the flank) may feel tender during an exam. There may be a history of urinary tract infections. There may be signs of  blocked urine flow  or kidney failure. Tests that may be done include: Urine test, Blood tests, Ultrasound, CT, or other imaging tests of the kidneys, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003368-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no specific treatment for renal papillary necrosis. Treatment depends on the cause. For example, if analgesic nephropathy is the cause, your health care provider will recommend that you stop using the medicine that is causing it. This may allow the kidney to heal over time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003368-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well a person does, depends on what is causing the condition. If the cause can be controlled, the condition may go away on its own. Sometimes, people with this condition develop kidney failure and will need  dialysis  or a  kidney transplant .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003368-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health problems that may result from renal papillary necrosis include: Kidney infection, Kidney stones, Kidney cancer, especially in people who take a lot of pain medicines, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003368-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if: You have  bloody urine , You develop other symptoms of renal papillary necrosis, especially after taking over-the-counter pain medicines, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003368-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Renal papillary necrosis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Controlling diabetes or sickle cell anemia may reduce your risk. To prevent renal papillary necrosis from analgesic nephropathy,&#160;follow your provider's instructions when using medicines, including over-the-counter pain relievers. Do not take more than the recommended dose without asking your provider.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>