<Document id="0003352" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001132.htm">
 
<Focus>Rectal prolapse</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0034888</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Procidentia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003352-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Rectal prolapse ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rectal prolapse occurs when the rectum sags and comes through the anal opening.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003352-2" qtype="causes">What causes Rectal prolapse ?</Question>
			<Answer>The exact cause of rectal prolapse is unclear. Possible causes may include any of the following: An enlarged opening due to relaxed muscles in the pelvic floor, which is formed of muscles around the rectum, Loose muscles of the anal sphincter, An abnormally long colon, Downward movement of the abdominal cavity between the rectum and uterus, Prolapse of the small intestine,  Constipation , Diarrhea, Chronic coughing and sneezing,  A prolapse can be partial or complete: With a partial prolapse, the inner lining of the rectum bulges partly from the anus., With a complete prolapse, the entire rectum bulges through the anus.,  Rectal prolapse occurs most often in children under age 6. Health problems that may lead to prolapse include: Cystic fibrosis , Intestinal worm infections, Long-term diarrhea, Other health problems present at birth,  In adults, it is usually found with constipation, or with a muscle or nerve problem in the pelvic or genital area.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003352-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Rectal prolapse ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main symptom is a reddish-colored mass that sticks out from the opening of the anus, especially after a bowel movement. This reddish mass is actually the inner lining of the rectum. It may bleed slightly and can be uncomfortable and painful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003352-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Rectal prolapse ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam, which will include a  rectal exam . To check for prolapse, the provider may ask the person to bear down while sitting on a toilet. Tests that may be done include: Colonoscopy  to confirm the diagnosis,  Blood test  to check for anemia if there is bleeding from the rectum, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003352-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Rectal prolapse ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if a rectal prolapse occurs. In some cases, the prolapse can be treated at home. Follow your provider's instructions on how to do this. The rectum must be pushed back inside manually. A soft, warm, wet cloth is used to apply gentle pressure to the mass to push it back through the anal opening. The person should lie on one side in a knee-chest position before applying pressure. This position allows gravity to help put the rectum back into position. Immediate surgery is rarely needed. In children, treating the cause often solves the problem. For example, if the cause is straining because of dry stools, laxatives may help. If the prolapse continues, surgery may be needed. In adults, the only cure for rectal prolapse is a  procedure  that repairs the weakened anal sphincter and pelvic muscles.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003352-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Rectal prolapse ?</Question>
			<Answer>In children, treating the cause cures rectal prolapse. In adults, surgery usually cures the prolapse. When rectal prolapse is not treated, constipation and loss of bowel control may develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003352-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Rectal prolapse ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider right away if there is a rectal prolapse.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003352-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Rectal prolapse ?</Question>
			<Answer>In children, treating the cause usually prevents rectal prolapse from happening again. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>