<Document id="0003623" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000800.htm">
 
<Focus>Sleep disorders - overview</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0851578</CUI>
			<CUI>C0037317</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003623-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sleep disorders - overview ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sleep disorders are problems with sleeping. These include trouble falling or staying asleep, falling asleep at the wrong times, too much sleep, and abnormal behaviors during sleep.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003623-2" qtype="causes">What causes Sleep disorders - overview ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are more than 100 different sleeping and waking disorders. They can be grouped into four main categories: Problems falling and staying asleep (insomnia), Problems staying awake (excessive daytime sleepiness), Problems sticking to a regular sleep schedule (sleep rhythm problem), Unusual behaviors during sleep (sleep-disruptive behaviors) ,  PROBLEMS FALLING AND STAYING ASLEEP  Insomnia  includes trouble falling asleep or staying asleep. Episodes may come and go, last up to 3 weeks (be short-term), or be long-lasting (chronic). PROBLEMS STAYING AWAKE  Hypersomnia  is a condition in which people have excessive daytime sleepiness. This means they feel tired during the day. Hypersomnia can also include situations in which a person needs to sleep a lot. This may be due to other medical conditions, but can also be due to a problem in the brain. Causes of this problem include: Medical conditions, such as  fibromyalgia  and low thyroid function, Medicines that are sedating,  Mononucleosis  or other viral illnesses,  Narcolepsy  and other sleep disorders, Obesity, especially if it causes  obstructive sleep apnea ,  When no cause for the sleepiness can be found, it is called  idiopathic hypersomnia . PROBLEMS STICKING TO A REGULAR SLEEP SCHEDULE  Problems may also occur when you do not stick to a regular sleep and wake schedule. This occurs when people travel between time zones. It can also occur with shift workers who are on changing schedules, especially nighttime workers. Disorders that involve a disrupted sleep schedule include: Irregular sleep-wake syndrome  ,  Jet lag syndrome , Shift work sleep disorder, Delayed sleep phase, as in teenagers who go to sleep very late at night and then sleep until noon, Advanced sleep phase, as in older adults who go to sleep early in the evening and wake up very early ,  SLEEP-DISRUPTIVE BEHAVIORS  Abnormal behaviors during sleep are called parasomnias. They are fairly common in children and include: Sleep terrors ,  Sleepwalking , REM sleep-behavior disorder (a person moves during REM sleep and may act out dreams) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>