<Document id="0003420" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000344.htm">
 
<Focus>Rickets</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0035579</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Osteomalacia in children</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Vitamin D deficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Renal rickets</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hepatic rickets</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003420-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>Rickets is a disorder caused by a lack of vitamin D, calcium, or phosphate. It leads to softening and weakening of the bones.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003420-2" qtype="causes">What causes Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vitamin D  helps the body control calcium and phosphate levels. If the blood levels of these minerals become too low, the body may produce hormones that cause calcium and phosphate to be released from the bones. This leads to weak and soft bones. Vitamin D is absorbed from food or produced by the skin when exposed to sunlight. Lack of vitamin D production by the skin may occur in people who: Live in climates with little exposure to sunlight, Must stay indoors, Work indoors during the daylight hours,  You may not get enough vitamin D from your diet if you: Are  lactose intolerant  (have trouble digesting milk products), DO NOT drink milk products, Follow a vegetarian diet,  Infants who are breastfed only may develop vitamin D deficiency. Human breast milk does not supply the proper amount of vitamin D. This can be a particular problem for darker-skinned children in winter months. This is because there are lower levels of sunlight during these months. Not getting enough calcium and phosphorous in your diet can also lead to rickets. Rickets caused by a lack of these minerals in the diet is rare in developed countries. Calcium and phosphorous are found in milk and green vegetables. Your genes may increase your risk for rickets. Hereditary rickets is a form of the disease that is passed down through families. It occurs when the kidneys are unable to hold onto the mineral phosphate. Rickets may also be caused by kidney disorders that involve  renal tubular acidosis . Disorders that reduce the digestion or absorption of fats will make it more difficult for vitamin D to be absorbed into the body. Sometimes, rickets may occur in children who have disorders of the liver. These children cannot convert vitamin D to its active form. Rickets is rare in the United States. It is most likely to occur in children during periods of rapid growth. This is the age when the body needs high levels of calcium and phosphate. Rickets may also be seen in children ages 6 to 24 months. It is uncommon in newborns.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003420-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of rickets include: Bone pain or tenderness  in the arms, legs, pelvis, and spine,  Decreased muscle tone  (loss of muscle strength) and  weakness  that gets worse, Dental deformities, including delayed tooth formation, defects in the tooth structure, holes in the enamel, and increased cavities ( dental caries ),  Impaired growth , Increased bone fractures,  Muscle cramps ,  Short stature  (adults less than 5 feet or 1.52 meters tall),  Skeletal deformities  such as an odd-shaped skull,  bowlegs , bumps in the ribcage (rachitic rosary), breastbone that is pushed forward (pigeon chest), pelvic deformities, and spine deformities (spine that curves abnormally, including  scoliosis  or  kyphosis ), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003420-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam reveals tenderness or pain in the bones, but not in the joints or muscles. The following tests may help diagnose rickets: Arterial blood gases , Blood tests ( serum calcium ),  Bone biopsy  (rarely done),  Bone x-rays ,  Serum alkaline phosphatase  (ALP),  Serum phosphorus ,  Other tests and procedures include the following: ALP isoenzyme ,  Calcium (ionized) , Parathyroid hormone ( PTH ),  Urine calcium , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003420-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>The goals of treatment are to relieve symptoms and correct the cause of the condition. The cause must be treated to prevent the disease from returning. Replacing calcium, phosphorus, or vitamin D that is lacking will eliminate most symptoms of rickets. Dietary sources of vitamin D include fish liver and processed milk. Exposure to moderate amounts of sunlight is encouraged. If rickets is caused by a metabolic problem, a prescription for vitamin D supplements may be needed. Positioning or bracing may be used to reduce or prevent deformities. Some skeletal deformities may require surgery to correct them.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003420-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>The disorder may be corrected by replacing vitamin D and minerals. Laboratory values and x-rays usually improve after about 1 week. Some cases may require large doses of minerals and vitamin D. If rickets is not corrected while the child is still growing, skeletal deformities and short stature may be permanent. If it is corrected while the child is young, skeletal deformities often improve or disappear with time.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003420-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>Possible complications are: 
   Long-term ( chronic ) skeletal pain
   , Skeletal deformities
   , Skeletal fractures, may occur without cause, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003420-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your child's health care provider if you notice symptoms of rickets.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003420-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Rickets ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can prevent rickets by making sure that your child gets enough calcium, phosphorus, and vitamin D in their diet. Children who have digestive or other disorders may need to take supplements prescribed by the child's provider. Kidney (renal) diseases that may cause poor vitamin D absorption should be treated right away. If you have&#160; renal disorders , monitor calcium and phosphorus levels regularly. Genetic counseling may help people who have a family history of inherited disorders that can cause rickets.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>