<Document id="0003312" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001197.htm">
 
<Focus>Pyruvate kinase deficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0340968</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003312-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pyruvate kinase deficiency is an inherited lack of the  enzyme  pyruvate kinase, which is used by red blood cells. Without this enzyme, red blood cells break down too easily, resulting in a low level of these cells ( hemolytic anemia ).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003312-2" qtype="causes">What causes Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pyruvate kinase deficiency (PKD) is passed down as an  autosomal recessive  trait. This means that a child must receive a non-working gene from each parent to develop the disorder. There are many different types of enzyme-related defects of the red blood cell that can cause hemolytic anemia. PKD is the second most common cause, after glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase  (G6PD) deficiency . PKD is found in people of all ethnic backgrounds. But, certain populations, such as the Amish, are more likely to develop the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003312-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of PKD include: Low count of healthy red blood cells ( anemia ), Swelling of the spleen ( splenomegaly ), Yellow color of the skin, mucous membranes, or white part of the eyes ( jaundice ), Neurologic condition, called  kernicterus , that affects the brain, Fatigue, lethargy, Pale skin ( pallor ), In infants, not gaining weight and growing as expected ( failure to thrive ), Gallstones, usually in the teens and older , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003312-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will perform a physical exam and ask about and check for symptoms such as an  enlarged spleen . If PKD is suspected, tests that will likely be ordered include: Bilirubin  in the blood,  CBC , Genetic testing for mutation in the pyruvate kinase gene,  Haptoglobin blood test ,  Osmotic fragility ,  Pyruvate kinase  activity, Stool urobilinogen , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003312-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>People with severe anemia may need blood transfusions. Removing the spleen ( splenectomy ) may help reduce the destruction of red blood cells. But, this does not help in all cases. In newborns with a dangerous level of jaundice, the provider may recommend an  exchange transfusion . This procedure involves slowly removing the infant's blood and replacing it with fresh donor blood or plasma. Someone who had a splenectomy should receive the  pneumococcal vaccine  at recommended intervals. They also should receive preventive antibiotics until age 5.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003312-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome varies. Some people have few or no symptoms. Others have severe symptoms. Treatment can usually make symptoms less severe.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003312-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gallstones are a common problem. They are made of too much bilirubin, which is produced during hemolytic anemia. Severe pneumococcal disease is a possible complication after splenectomy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003312-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>See your provider if: You have jaundice or anemia., You have a family history of this disorder and are planning to have children.  Genetic counseling  can help you know how likely it will be that your child would have PKD. You can also learn about tests that check for genetic disorders, such as PKD, so that you can decide if you'd like to have these tests. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003312-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Pyruvate kinase deficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>