<Document id="0003043" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007232.htm">
 
<Focus>Periventricular leukomalacia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0023529</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>PVL</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brain injury - infants</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003043-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Periventricular leukomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Periventricular leukomalacia (PVL) is a type of brain injury that affects  premature  infants. The condition involves the death of small areas of brain tissue around fluid-filled areas called ventricles. The damage creates "holes" in the brain. "Leuko" refers to the brain's white matter. "Periventricular" refers to the area around the ventricles.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003043-2" qtype="causes">What causes Periventricular leukomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>PVL is much more common in premature infants than in full-term infants. A major cause is thought to be changes in blood flow to the area around the ventricles of the brain. This area is fragile and prone to injury, especially before 32 weeks of gestation. Infection around the time of delivery may also play a role in causing PVL. The risk for PVL is higher for babies who are more premature and more unstable at birth. Premature babies who have  intraventricular hemorrhage (IVH)  are also at increased risk for developing this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003043-3" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Periventricular leukomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tests used to diagnose PVL include ultrasound and MRI of the head.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003043-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Periventricular leukomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no treatment for PVL. Premature babies' heart, lung, intestine, and kidney functions are watched closely and treated in the newborn intensive care unit (NICU). This helps reduce the risk of developing PVL. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003043-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Periventricular leukomalacia ?</Question>
			<Answer>PVL often leads to nervous system and developmental problems in growing babies. These problems most often occur during the first to second year of life. It may cause  cerebral palsy (CP) , especially tightness or increased muscle tone (spasticity) in the legs. Babies with PVL are at risk for major nervous system problems. These are likely to include movements such as sitting, crawling, walking, and moving the arms. These babies will need physical therapy. Extremely premature babies may have more problems with learning and behavior than with movement. A baby who is diagnosed with PVL should be monitored by a developmental pediatrician or a pediatric neurologist. The child should see the regular pediatrician for scheduled exams.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>