<Document id="0003055" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000244.htm">
 
<Focus>Peutz-Jeghers syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0031269</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>PJS</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003055-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Peutz-Jeghers syndrome (PJS) is a rare disorder in which growths called polyps form in the intestines. A person with PJS has a high risk for developing certain cancers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003055-2" qtype="causes">What causes Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is unknown how many people are affected by PJS. However, the National Institutes of Health estimates that it affects about 1 in 25,000 to 300,000 births. PJS is caused by a mutation in the gene called STK11 (previously known as LKB1). There are two ways that PJS can occur: Familial PJS is inherited through families as an  autosomal dominant  trait. That means if one of your parents has this type of PJS, you have a 50% chance of inheriting the gene and having the disease., Spontaneous PJS is not inherited from a parent. The gene mutation occurs on its own. Once someone carries the genetic change, their children have a 50% chance of inheriting it., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003055-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of PJS are: Brownish or bluish-gray spots on the lips, gums, inner lining of the mouth, and skin,  Clubbed fingers or toes , Cramping pain in the belly area, Dark freckles on and around the lips of a child,  Blood in the stool  that can be seen with the naked eye (sometimes), Vomiting, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003055-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The polyps develop mainly in the small intestine, but also in the large intestine (colon). An exam of the colon called a colonoscopy will show colon polyps. The small intestine is evaluated in two ways. One is a barium x-ray (small bowel series). The other is a capsule endoscopy, in which a small camera is swallowed and then takes many pictures as it travels through the small intestine. Additional exams may show: 
  Part of the intestine folded in on itself ( intussusception ), Benign (noncancerous) tumors in the nose, airways, ureters, or bladder,  Laboratory tests may include: Complete blood count (CBC) -- may reveal  anemia , Genetic testing,  Stool guaiac , to look for blood in stool,  Total iron-binding capacity  (TIBC) -- may be linked with iron-deficiency anemia, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003055-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Surgery may be needed to remove polyps that cause long-term problems. Iron supplements help counteract blood loss. People with this condition should be monitored by a health care provider and checked regularly for cancerous polyp changes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003055-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>There may be a high risk for these polyps becoming cancerous. Some studies link PJS with cancers of the gastrointestinal tract, lung, breast, uterus, and ovaries.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003055-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Intussusception, Polyps that lead to cancer,  Ovarian cysts , A type of ovarian tumors called sex cord tumors, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003055-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider for an appointment if you or your child has symptoms of this condition. Severe abdominal pain may be a sign of an emergency condition such as intussusception.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003055-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Peutz-Jeghers syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling is recommended if you are planning to have children and have a family history of this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>