<Document id="0003506" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002544.htm">
 
<Focus>Secobarbital overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0572929</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Meballymal overdose</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Quinalbarbitone sodium overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003506-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Secobarbital overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Secobarbital is a drug used to treat insomnia (difficulty falling or staying asleep). It is in a class of medicines called barbiturates. It may also be given before surgery to relieve anxiety. Secobarbital overdose occurs when someone takes too much of this medicine. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual  overdose . If you or someone you are with overdoses, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003506-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Secobarbital overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of a secobarbital overdose may include: Blurred or double vision, rapid side-to-side movement of eyes (nystagmus),  Coma  (decreased level of consciousness and lack of responsiveness),  Confusion , Dizziness, Drowsiness, tiredness, fainting, Muscle and skin damage (discoloration, blisters, ulcers) from lying on a hard surface while stuporous or in a coma, Nausea, Rash or blisters, Shock (extremely low blood pressure), Slowed or absent breathing, Stupor (decreased level of alertness), Slurred speech, Weakness, uncoordinated movement, staggering gait (ataxia, seen commonly in children), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003506-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Secobarbital overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well the person does depends on the severity of the overdose and how quickly treatment is received. With proper treatment, people can recover in 1 to 5 days.&#160; People who are in a prolonged coma or who have respiratory complications, or those who develop shock may have permanent disability.&#160;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003506-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Secobarbital overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well the person does depends on the severity of the overdose and how quickly treatment is received. With proper treatment, people can recover in 1 to 5 days.&#160; People who are in a prolonged coma or who have respiratory complications, or those who develop shock may have permanent disability.&#160;</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>