<Document id="0003100" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001471.htm">
 
<Focus>Pityriasis rubra pilaris</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032027</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003100-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pityriasis rubra pilaris (PRP) is a rare skin disorder that causes inflammation and  scaling  (exfoliation) of the skin.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003100-2" qtype="causes">What causes Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are several subtypes of PRP. The cause is unknown, although genetic factors and an abnormal immune response may be involved. One subtype is associated with  HIV/AIDS .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003100-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>PRP is a chronic skin condition in which orange or salmon-colored scaly patches with thick skin develop on the hands and feet. The scaly areas may cover much of the body. Small islands of normal skin (called islands of sparing) are seen within the areas of the scaly skin. The scaly areas may be itchy. There may be changes in the nails. PRP can be severe. Although it's not life threatening, PRP can greatly reduce quality of life and limit activities of daily living.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003100-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will examine your skin. The diagnosis is usually made by the presence of the unique skin lesions. (A lesion is an abnormal area on the skin). Your provider may take samples ( biopsies ) of the affected skin to confirm the diagnosis and rule out conditions that may look like PRP.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003100-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Topical creams containing urea, lactic acid, retinoids, and steroids may help. More commonly, treatment includes pills taken by mouth such as isotretinoin, acitretin, or methotrexate. Exposure to ultraviolet light (light therapy) may also help. Medicines that affect the body's immune system are currently being studied and may be effective for PRP.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003100-6" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Pityriasis rubra pilaris ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you develop symptoms of PRP. Also contact your provider if you have the disorder and symptoms worsen.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>