<Document id="0003086" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003253.htm">
 
<Focus>Pilonidal dimple</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0426848</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pilonidal abscess</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pilonidal sinus</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pilonidal cyst</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pilonidal disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003086-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pilonidal dimple ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pilonidal sinus disease is an inflammatory condition involving the hair follicles that can occur anywhere along the crease between the buttocks, which runs from the bone at the bottom of the spine (sacrum) to the anus. The disease is benign and has no association with cancer. Pilonidal dimple may appear as: A pilonidal  abscess , in which the hair follicle becomes infected and pus collects in the fat tissue, A pilonidal cyst, in which a cyst or hole forms if there has been an abscess for a long time, A pilonidal sinus, in which a tract grows under the skin or deeper from the hair follicle, A small pit or pore in the skin that contains dark spots or hair , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003086-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Pilonidal dimple ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Pus draining to a small pit in the skin, Tenderness over the area after you are active or sit for a period of time, Warm, tender, swollen area near the tailbone, Fever (rare) ,  There may be no symptoms other than a small dent (pit) in the skin in the crease between the buttocks.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003086-3" qtype="causes">What causes Pilonidal dimple ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause of pilonidal disease is not clear. It is thought to be caused by hair growing into the skin in the crease between the buttocks. This problem is more likely to occur in people who: Are obese, Experience trauma or irritation in the area, Have excess body hair, particularly coarse, curly hair , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003086-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Pilonidal dimple ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Pus draining to a small pit in the skin, Tenderness over the area after you are active or sit for a period of time, Warm, tender, swollen area near the tailbone, Fever (rare) ,  There may be no symptoms other than a small dent (pit) in the skin in the crease between the buttocks.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003086-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Pilonidal dimple ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your health care provider if you notice any of the following around the pilonidal cyst: Drainage of pus ,  Redness ,  Swelling ,  Tenderness  , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003086-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Pilonidal dimple ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>