<Document id="0003423" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001387.htm">
 
<Focus>Riley-Day syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0013364</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Familial dysautonomia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathy - type III (HSAN III)</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003423-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Familial dysautonomia (FD) is an inherited disorder that affects nerves throughout the body.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003423-2" qtype="causes">What causes Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>FD is passed down through families (inherited). A person must inherit a copy of the defective gene from each parent to develop the condition. FD occurs most often in people of Eastern European Jewish ancestry (Ashkenazi Jews). It is caused by a change (mutation) to a gene. It is rare in the general population.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003423-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>FD affects the nerves in the autonomic (involuntary) nervous system. These nerves manage daily body functions such as blood pressure, heart rate, sweating, bowel and bladder emptying, digestion, and the senses. Symptoms of FD are present at birth and may grow worse over time. Symptoms vary, and may include: Swallowing problems in infants, resulting in  aspiration pneumonia  or poor growth, Breath-holding spells, resulting in fainting, Constipation or diarrhea, Inability to feel pain and changes in temperature (can lead to injuries), Dry eyes and lack of tears when crying, Poor coordination and unsteady walk,  Seizures , Unusually smooth, pale tongue surface and lack of taste buds and decrease in sense of taste,  After age 3, most children develop autonomic crises. These are episodes of vomiting with very high blood pressure, racing heart, fever, and sweating.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003423-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will do a physical exam to look for: Absent or decreased deep tendon reflexes, Lack of a response after receiving a histamine injection (usually redness and swelling would occur), Lack of tears with crying, Low muscle tone, most often in babies, Severe curving of the spine ( scoliosis ), Tiny pupils after receiving certain eye drops ,  Blood tests are available to check for the gene mutation that causes FD.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003423-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>FD can't be cured. Treatment is aimed at managing the symptoms and may include: Medicines to help prevent seizures, Feeding in an upright position and giving textured formula to prevent  gastroesophageal reflux  (stomach acid and food coming back up, also called GERD), Measures to prevent low blood pressure when standing, such as increasing intake of fluid, salt, and caffeine, and wearing elastic stockings, Medicines to control vomiting, Medicines to prevent dry eyes, Physical therapy of the chest, Measures to protect against injury, Providing enough nutrition and fluids, Surgery or  spinal fusion  to treat spine problems, Treating aspiration pneumonia
   , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003423-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Advances in diagnosis and treatment are increasing the survival rate. About one half of babies born with FD will live to age 30.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003423-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003423-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if symptoms change or get worse. A genetic counselor can help teach you about the condition and direct you to support groups in your area.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003423-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Riley-Day syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic DNA testing is very accurate for FD. It may be used for diagnosing people with the condition or those who carry the gene. It can also be used for prenatal diagnosis. People of Eastern European Jewish background and families with a history of FD may wish to seek  genetic counseling  if they are thinking of having children.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>