<Document id="0003238" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002537.htm">
 
<Focus>Propoxyphene overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0572050</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Propoxyphene hydrochloride</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Dextropropoxyphene</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003238-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Propoxyphene overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Propoxyphene is medicine used to relieve pain. It is one of a number of chemicals called opioids or opiates, which were originally derived from the poppy plant and used for pain relief or their calming effects Propoxyphene overdose occurs when someone takes too much of this medicine. The US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) took this drug off the market in December 2010 because of the potential to cause deadly heart disturbances. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual  overdose . If you or someone you are with overdoses, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003238-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Propoxyphene overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Eyes, ears, nose, and throat: Hearing loss, Pinpoint pupils ,  Heart and blood vessels: Heart rhythm disturbances, Low blood pressure, Weak pulse ,  Lungs: Breathing slow, labored,  or shallow, No breathing ,  Muscles: Muscle spasticity , Muscle damage from being immobile while in a coma ,  Nervous system: Coma  (lack of responsiveness), Confusion, Drowsiness,  Seizures ,  Skin: Cyanosis  (blue fingernails or lips),  Jaundice (turning yellow) , Rash ,  Stomach and intestines: Nausea, vomiting, Spasms of the stomach or intestines ( abdominal cramps ),  Propoxyphene is a weak opioid. It may cause opioid withdrawal symptoms in people who use it as a substitute for stronger formulations. Symptoms of withdrawal may include: Anxiety and restlessness, Diarrhea, Goose bumps, Rapid heart rate, Vomiting, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003238-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Propoxyphene overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003238-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Propoxyphene overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well the person does depends on the severity of the overdose and how quickly treatment is received. If the proper narcotic antagonist (drug to counteract the effects of narcotics) can be given, recovery from an  acute  overdose occurs within 24 to 48 hours. However, if there has been prolonged coma and shock (damage to multiple internal organs), a more serious outcome is possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003238-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Propoxyphene overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well the person does depends on the severity of the overdose and how quickly treatment is received. If the proper narcotic antagonist (drug to counteract the effects of narcotics) can be given, recovery from an  acute  overdose occurs within 24 to 48 hours. However, if there has been prolonged coma and shock (damage to multiple internal organs), a more serious outcome is possible.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>