<Document id="0003176" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002875.htm">
 
<Focus>Potato plant poisoning - green tubers and sprouts</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032087</CUI>
			<CUI>C3812802</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Solanum tuberosum poisoning</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003176-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Potato plant poisoning - green tubers and sprouts ?</Question>
			<Answer>Potato plant poisoning occurs when someone eats the green tubers or new sprouts of the potato plant. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call your local emergency number (such as 911), or your local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003176-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Potato plant poisoning - green tubers and sprouts ?</Question>
			<Answer>Effects are mostly gastrointestinal. They are often delayed 8 to 10 hours. Central nervous system effects may occur in large ingestions. These poisonings can be very dangerous. Symptoms may include: Abdominal or stomach pain ,  Delirium  (agitation and confusion), Diarrhea, Dilated (wide) pupils, Fever,  Hallucinations , Headache,  Loss of sensation ,  Lower than normal body temperature  (hypothermia), Nausea and vomiting,  Paralysis ,  Shock ,  Slow pulse , Slowed breathing, Vision changes, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003176-5" qtype="considerations">What to do for Potato plant poisoning - green tubers and sprouts ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003176-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Potato plant poisoning - green tubers and sprouts ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well you do depends on the amount of poison swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster you get medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Symptoms may last for 1 to 3 days, and hospitalization may be necessary. Death has been reported, but is rare. DO NOT touch or eat any plant with which you are not familiar. Wash your hands after working in the garden or walking in the woods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003176-9" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Potato plant poisoning - green tubers and sprouts ?</Question>
			<Answer>How well you do depends on the amount of poison swallowed and how quickly treatment is received. The faster you get medical help, the better the chance for recovery. Symptoms may last for 1 to 3 days, and hospitalization may be necessary. Death has been reported, but is rare. DO NOT touch or eat any plant with which you are not familiar. Wash your hands after working in the garden or walking in the woods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>