<Document id="0003150" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003267.htm">
 
<Focus>Polyhydramnios</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0020224</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003150-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Polyhydramnios ?</Question>
			<Answer>Polyhydramnios occurs when too much amniotic fluid builds up during pregnancy. It is also called amniotic fluid disorder, or hydramnios.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003150-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Polyhydramnios ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amniotic fluid is the liquid that surrounds the baby in the womb (uterus). It comes from the baby's kidneys and developing urinary system, and then it goes into the uterus from the baby's urine. The fluid is absorbed when the baby swallows it and through breathing motions. While in the womb, the baby floats in the amniotic fluid. It surrounds and cushions the infant during pregnancy. The amount of amniotic fluid is greatest at 34 to 36 weeks of pregnancy. Then the amount slowly decreases until the baby is born. The amniotic fluid: Allows the baby to move in the womb, promoting muscle and bone growth, Helps the baby's lungs to develop, Protects the baby from heat loss by keeping the temperature constant, Cushions and protects the baby from sudden blows from outside the womb, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003150-3" qtype="causes">What causes Polyhydramnios ?</Question>
			<Answer>Polyhydramnios can occur if the baby does not swallow and absorb amniotic fluid in normal amounts. This can happen if the baby has certain health problems, including: Gastrointestinal disorders, such as  duodenal atresia ,  esophageal atresia ,  gastroschisis , and  diaphragmatic hernia , Brain and nervous system problems, such as  anencephaly  and myotonic dystrophy,  Achondroplasia ,  Beckwith-Wiedemann syndrome ,  It can also happen if the mother has poorly controlled diabetes. Polyhydramnios also may occur if too much fluid is produced. This may be due to: Certain lung disorders in the baby, Multiple pregnancy (for example, twins or triplets),  Hydrops fetalis  in the baby,  Sometimes, no specific cause is found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003150-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Polyhydramnios ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you are pregnant and notice that your belly is getting large very quickly.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003150-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Polyhydramnios ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>