<Document id="0003737" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001388.htm">
 
<Focus>Stork bite</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0235752</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Salmon patch</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Nevus flammeus</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003737-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Stork bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>A stork bite is a common type of birthmark seen in a newborn. It is most often temporary. The medical term for a stork bite is nevus simplex. A stork bite is also called a salmon patch.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003737-2" qtype="causes">What causes Stork bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Stork bites occur in about one third of all newborns. A stork bite is due to a stretching (dilation) of certain blood vessels. It may become darker when the child cries or the temperature changes. It may fade when pressure is put on it.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003737-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Stork bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>A stork bite usually looks pink and flat. A baby may be born with a stork bite. It may also appear in the first months of life. Stork bites may be found on the forehead, eyelids, nose, upper lip, or back of the neck. Stork bites are purely cosmetic and do not cause any symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003737-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Stork bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can diagnose a stork bite simply by looking at it. No tests are needed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003737-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Stork bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>No treatment is needed. If a stork bite lasts longer than 3 years, it may be removed with a laser to improve the person's appearance.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003737-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Stork bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most stork bites on the face go away completely in about 18 months. Stork bites on the back of the neck usually do not go away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003737-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Stork bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider should look at all birthmarks during a routine  well-baby exam . </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003737-8" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Stork bite ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known prevention. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>