<Document id="0003225" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000734.htm">
 
<Focus>Primary lymphoma of the brain</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0240803</CUI>
			<CUI>C0024299</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Brain lymphoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cerebral lymphoma</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Primary lymphoma of the central nervous system</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Lymphoma - brain</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003225-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Primary lymphoma of the brain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Primary lymphoma of the brain is cancer of white blood cells that starts in the brain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003225-2" qtype="causes">What causes Primary lymphoma of the brain ?</Question>
			<Answer>The cause of primary brain lymphoma is not known.  People with a weakened immune system are at high risk for primary lymphoma of the brain. Common causes of a weakened immune system include HIV/AIDS and having had an organ transplant (especially heart transplant). Primary lymphoma of the brain may be linked to Epstein-Barr Virus (EBV), especially in people with HIV/AIDS. EBV is the virus that causes  mononucleosis . Primary brain lymphoma is more common in people ages 45 to 70. The rate of primary brain lymphoma is rising. Almost 1,500 new patients are diagnosed with primary brain lymphoma every year in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003225-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Primary lymphoma of the brain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of primary brain lymphoma may include any of the following: Changes in speech or vision, Confusion or  hallucinations ,  Seizures ,  Headaches , nausea, or vomiting, Leaning to one side when walking, Weakness in hands or loss of coordination,  Numbness  to hot, cold, and pain, Personality changes, Weight loss , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003225-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Primary lymphoma of the brain ?</Question>
			<Answer>The following tests may be done to help diagnose a primary lymphoma of the brain: Biopsy  of the brain tumor,  Head CT scan , PET scan or  MRI ,  Spinal tap  (lumbar puncture), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003225-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Primary lymphoma of the brain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Primary lymphoma of the brain is often first treated with corticosteroids. These medicines are used to control swelling and improve symptoms. The main treatment is with  chemotherapy . Younger people may receive high-dose chemotherapy, possibly followed by an  autologous stem cell transplant . Radiation therapy  of the whole brain may be done after chemotherapy. Boosting the immune system, such as in those with HIV/AIDS, may also be tried.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003225-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Primary lymphoma of the brain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Without treatment, people with primary brain lymphoma survive for less than 6 months. When treated with chemotherapy, half of the patients will be in remission 10 years after being diagnosed. Survival may improve with autologous stem cell transplant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003225-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Primary lymphoma of the brain ?</Question>
			<Answer>Possible complications include: Chemotherapy side effects, including low blood counts, Radiation side effects, including confusion, headaches, nervous system (neurologic) problems, and tissue death, Return (recurrence) of the lymphoma, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>