<Document id="0003305" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003232.htm">
 
<Focus>Purpura</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0034150</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Blood spots</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Skin hemorrhages</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003305-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Purpura ?</Question>
			<Answer>Purpura is purple-colored spots and patches that occur on the skin, and in mucus membranes, including the lining of the mouth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003305-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Purpura ?</Question>
			<Answer>Purpura occurs when small blood vessels leak blood under the skin. Purpura measure between 4 and 10 mm (millimeters) in diameter. When purpura spots are less than 4 mm in diameter, they are called  petechiae . Purpura spots larger than 1 cm (centimeter) are called ecchymoses. Platelets help the blood clot. A person with purpura may have a normal platelet count (non-thrombocytopenic purpuras) or a low platelet counts ( thrombocytopenic  purpuras).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003305-3" qtype="causes">What causes Purpura ?</Question>
			<Answer>Non-thrombocytopenic purpuras may be due to: Amyloidosis  (disorder in which abnormal proteins build up in tissues and organs), Blood clotting disorders,  Congenital cytomegalovirus  (condition in which an infant is infected with a virus called cytomegalovirus before birth), Congenital  rubella  syndrome, Drugs that affect platelet function or clotting factors, Fragile blood vessels seen in older people (senile purpura),  Hemangioma  (abnormal buildup of blood vessels in the skin or internal organs), Inflammation of the blood vessels (vasculitis), such as  Henoch-Sch&#246;nlein purpura , which causes a raised type of purpura, Pressure changes that occur during vaginal childbirth,  Scurvy  (vitamin C deficiency), Steroid use, Certain infections, Injury ,  Thrombocytopenic purpura may be due to: Drugs that reduce the platelet count,  Idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura  (ITP) -- a bleeding disorder, Immune neonatal thrombocytopenia (can occur in infants whose mothers have ITP),  Meningococcemia  (bloodstream infection) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003305-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Purpura ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your health care provider for an appointment if you have signs of purpura.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003305-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Purpura ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>