<Document id="0003167" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001404.htm">
 
<Focus>Posterior fossa tumor</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0021432</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Infratentorial brain tumors</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Brainstem glioma</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003167-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Posterior fossa tumor is a type of brain tumor located in or near the bottom of the skull.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003167-2" qtype="causes">What causes Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>The posterior fossa is a small space in the skull, found near the brainstem and cerebellum. The cerebellum is the part of the brain responsible for balance and coordinated movements. The brainstem is responsible for controlling vital body functions, such as breathing. If a tumor grows in the area of the posterior fossa, it can block the flow of spinal fluid and cause increased pressure on the brain and spinal cord. Most tumors of the posterior fossa are primary brain cancers. They start in the brain, rather than spreading from somewhere else in the body. Posterior fossa tumors have no known causes or risk factors.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003167-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms occur very early with posterior fossa tumors and may include: 
   Drowsiness
   , 
   Headache
   , Imbalance, Nausea, Uncoordinated walk ( ataxia ), 
   Vomiting
   ,  Symptoms from posterior fossa tumors also occur when the tumor damages local structures, such as the cranial nerves. Symptoms of cranial nerve damage include: Dilated pupils, Eye problems, Face muscle weakness, Hearing loss, Loss of feeling in part of the face, Taste problems, Unsteadiness when walking, Vision problems, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003167-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Diagnosis is based on a thorough medical history and physical exam, followed by imaging tests. The best way to look at the posterior fossa is with an  MRI scan . CT scans are not helpful to see that area of the brain in most cases. The following procedures may be used to remove a piece of tissue from the tumor to help with diagnosis: Open brain surgery, called a posterior  craniotomy , Stereotactic biopsy , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003167-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most tumors of the posterior fossa are removed with surgery, even if they are not cancerous. There is limited space in the posterior fossa, and the tumor can easily press on delicate structures if it grows. Depending on the type and size of the tumor, radiation treatment may also be used after surgery.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003167-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can ease the stress of illness by joining a  support group  whose members share common experiences and problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003167-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>A good outlook depends on finding the cancer early. A total blockage in the flow of spinal fluid can be life threatening. If tumors are found early, surgery can lead to long-term survival.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003167-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Cranial nerve palsies, Herniation,  Hydrocephalus ,  Increased intracranial pressure , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003167-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Posterior fossa tumor ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your health care provider if you have regular headaches that occur with nausea, vomiting, or vision changes.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>