<Document id="0003945" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000877.htm">
 
<Focus>Tinea corporis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040252</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Fungal infection - body</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Infection - fungal - body</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tinea of the body</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tinea circinata</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ringworm - body</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003945-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tinea corporis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ringworm  is a skin infection that is caused by fungi. It is also called tinea. Related skin fungus infections may appear: On the  scalp , In a man's beard, In the groin ( jock itch ), Between the toes ( athlete's foot ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003945-2" qtype="causes">What causes Tinea corporis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fungi are germs that can live on the dead tissue of the hair, nails, and outer skin layers. Ringworm of the body is caused by mold-like fungi called dermatophytes. Ringworm of the body is common in children, but can occur in people of all ages. Fungi thrive in warm, moist areas. A ringworm infection is more likely if you: Have wet skin for a long time (such as from sweating), Have minor skin and nail injuries, Do not&#160;bathe or wash your hair often, Have close contact with other people (such as in sports like wrestling) ,  Ringworm can spread quickly. You can catch it if you come into direct contact with an area of ringworm on someone's body. You can also get it by touching items that have the fungi on them, such as: Clothing, Combs, Pool surfaces, Shower floors and walls ,  Pets can also spread ringworm. Cats are common carriers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003945-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tinea corporis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The rash begins as a small area of red, raised spots and pimples. The rash slowly becomes ring-shaped, with a red, raised border and a clear center. The border may look scaly. The rash may occur on the arms, legs, face, or other exposed body areas.  The area may be itchy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003945-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tinea corporis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider can often&#160;diagnose ringworm by looking at your skin. You may also need the following tests: Examination of a skin scraping from the rash under a microscope using a  special test ,  Skin culture  for fungus,  Skin biopsy , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003945-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Tinea corporis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep your skin clean and dry. Use creams that treat fungal infections. Creams that contain miconazole, clotrimazole, ketoconazole, terbinafine, or oxiconazole, or other antifungal medicines, are often useful in controlling ringworm., You can buy some of these creams over-the-counter, or your provider may give you a prescription. ,  To use this medicine: Wash and dry the area first., Apply the cream, beginning just outside the area of the rash and moving toward the center. Be sure to wash and dry your hands afterward., Use the cream twice a day for 7 to 10 days., Do not&#160;use a bandage over ringworm. ,  Your provider may prescribe medicine to take by mouth if your infection is very bad. A child with ringworm can return to school once treatment has started. To prevent the infection from spreading: Wash clothing, towels, and bedding in hot, soapy water and then dry them&#160;using the hottest heat recommended on the care label., Use a new towel and washcloth every time you wash., Clean sinks, bathtubs, and bathroom floors well after each use., Wear clean clothes every day and do not share clothes., If you play contact sports, shower right away afterward. ,  Infected pets should also be treated.&#160;This is because ringworm can spread from animals to humans by contact.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003945-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tinea corporis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ringworm often goes away within 4 weeks when using antifungal creams. The infection may spread to the feet, scalp, groin, or nails.&#160;
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003945-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Tinea corporis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Two complications of ringworm are: Skin infection from scratching too much , Other skin disorders that require further treatment, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003945-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Tinea corporis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if ringworm does not get better with self-care.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>