<Document id="0003122" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001371.htm">
 
<Focus>Pleurisy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032231</CUI>
			<CUI>C0497354</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pleuritis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Pleuritic chest pain</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003122-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pleurisy is an inflammation of the lining of the lungs and chest (the pleura) that leads to chest pain when you take a breath or cough.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003122-2" qtype="causes">What causes Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pleurisy may develop when you have lung inflammation due to infection, such as a viral infection,  pneumonia , or  tuberculosis .  It may also occur with: Certain cancers, Chest trauma, Blood clot ( pulmonary embolus )
   ,  Rheumatoid arthritis ,  Lupus  (systemic lupus erythematosus), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003122-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>The main symptom of pleurisy is pain in the chest. This pain often occurs when you take a deep breath in or out, or cough. Some people feel the pain in the shoulder. Deep breathing, coughing, and chest movement make the pain worse. Pleurisy can cause fluid to collect inside the chest. As a result, the following symptoms can occur: Coughing,  Shortness of breath , Rapid breathing, Pain with deep breaths, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003122-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>When you have pleurisy, the normally smooth surfaces lining the lung (the pleura) become rough. They rub together with each breath. This results in a rough, grating sound called a friction rub. Your health care provider may hear this sound with the stethoscope. Your provider may order the following tests: 
   Complete blood count ( CBC ),  X-ray of the chest ,  CT scan of the chest ,  Ultrasound of the chest , Removal of pleural fluid with a needle ( thoracentesis ) for analysis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003122-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment depends on the cause of the pleurisy. Bacterial infections are treated with antibiotics. Surgery or insertion of a tube in the chest may be needed to drain infected fluid from the lungs. Viral infections normally run their course without medicines. Taking acetaminophen or ibuprofen can help reduce pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003122-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recovery depends on the cause of the pleurisy and your general health condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003122-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Health problems that may develop from pleurisy include: Breathing difficulty, Fluid buildup between chest wall and lung, Complications from the original illness, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003122-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have symptoms of pleurisy. If you have breathing difficulty or your skin turns blue ( cyanosis ), seek medical care right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003122-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Pleurisy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Early treatment of bacterial respiratory infections can prevent pleurisy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>