<Document id="0003236" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002527.htm">
 
<Focus>Promethazine overdose</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0747980</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Phenergan overdose</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003236-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Promethazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Promethazine is a medicine used to treat nausea and vomiting. Promethazine overdose occurs when someone takes too much of this medicine. It is in a class of drugs called phenothiazines, which were developed to treat psychiatric disturbances. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual  overdose . If you or someone you are with overdoses, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003236-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Promethazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bladder and kidneys: Urinary hesitancy, Inability to urinate ,  Heart and blood vessels: Rapid heartbeat , Weakness from low blood pressure ,  Nervous system: Drowsiness  or&#160; coma &#160;(lack of responsiveness),  Agitation , nervousness, confusion, excitation, disorientation, hallucinations,  Depression , Fever,  Unsteadiness , Restlessness, including inability to sit still and involuntary repetitive movements, Seizures, Tremor (unintentional trembling) ,  Other: Dry mouth,  Flushed skin , Involuntary tongue movement, Large (dilated) pupils with vision difficulty, Muscle stiffness and spasms in face or neck , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003236-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Promethazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>If the person survives the first 24 hours, recovery is likely. People who experience heart rhythm irregularities and seizures are at highest risk for a serious outcome. Few people actually die from promethazine overdose.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003236-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Promethazine overdose ?</Question>
			<Answer>If the person survives the first 24 hours, recovery is likely. People who experience heart rhythm irregularities and seizures are at highest risk for a serious outcome. Few people actually die from promethazine overdose.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>