<Document id="0003868" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003284.htm">
 
<Focus>Telangiectasia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0039446</CUI>
			<CUI>C1963248</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Vascular ectasias</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spider veins</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003868-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Telangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Telangiectasias are small, widened blood vessels on the skin. They are usually harmless, but may be associated with several diseases.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003868-2" qtype="causes">What causes Telangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Telangiectasias may develop anywhere within the body. But they are most easily seen on the skin, mucous membranes, and whites of the eyes. Usually, they do not cause symptoms. Some telangiectasias bleed and cause significant problems. Telangiectasias may also occur in the brain or intestines and cause major problems from bleeding. Causes may include: Rosacea (skin problem that causes the face to turn red), Aging, Problem with genes, Pregnancy, Sun exposure, Varicose veins, Overuse of steroid creams, Trauma to the area ,  Diseases associated with this condition include: Ataxia-telangiectasia  (disease that affects the skin, balance, coordination, and other areas of the body), Bloom syndrome (inherited disease that causes short stature, skin sensitivity to ultraviolet rays of the sun, and redness of the face), Cutis marmorata telangiectatica congenita (skin disease causing patches of redness),  Hereditary hemorrhagic telangiectasia  (Osler-Weber-Rendu syndrome), Klippel-Trenaunay-Weber syndrome (disease that causes port-wine stain, varicose veins, and soft tissue problems),  Nevus flammeus  such as  port-wine stain ,  Rosacea  (skin condition that causes redness of the face),  Sturge-Weber disease  (disease that involves port-wine stain and nervous system problems),  Xeroderma pigmentosum  (disease in which the skin as well as the tissue covering the eye are extremely sensitive to ultraviolet light),  Lupus  (immune system disease), CREST syndrome (a type of  scleroderma  that involves the buildup of scar-like tissue in the skin and elsewhere in the body and damages the cells that line the walls of small arteries) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003868-3" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Telangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your health care provider if you notice enlarged vessels in the skin, mucous membranes, or eyes. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003868-4" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Telangiectasia ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>