<Document id="0003775" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000797.htm">
 
<Focus>Substance use - phencyclidine (PCP)</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0237123</CUI>
			<CUI>C2919094</CUI>
			<CUI>C1535939</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Substance abuse - phencyclidine</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Drug abuse - phencyclidine</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Drug use - phencyclidine</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003775-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Substance use - phencyclidine (PCP) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Phencyclidine (PCP) is an illegal street drug that usually comes as a white powder, which can be dissolved in alcohol or water. It can be bought as a powder or liquid.  PCP can be used in different ways: Inhaled through the nose (snorted), Injected into a vein (shooting up), Smoked, Swallowed ,  Street names for PCP include angel dust, embalming fluid, hog, killer weed, love boat, ozone, peace pill, rocket fuel, super grass, and wack.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003775-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Substance use - phencyclidine (PCP) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment begins with recognizing there is a problem. Once you decide you want to do something about your PCP use, the next step is to get help and support. Treatment programs use behavior change techniques through counseling (talk therapy). The aim is to help you understand your behaviors and why you use PCP. Involving family and friends during counseling can help support you and keep you from going back to using (relapsing). If you have severe withdrawal symptoms, you may need to stay at a live-in treatment program. There, your health and safety can be monitored as you recover. Medicines may be used to treat withdrawal symptoms. At this time, there is no medicine that can help reduce the use of PCP by blocking its effects. But scientists are researching such medicines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003775-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Substance use - phencyclidine (PCP) ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>