<Document id="0003335" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007198.htm">
 
<Focus>Rapid shallow breathing</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0425488</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Tachypnea</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Breathing - rapid and shallow</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Fast shallow breathing</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Respiratory rate - rapid and shallow</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003335-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Rapid shallow breathing ?</Question>
			<Answer>A normal breathing rate for an adult at rest is 12 to 20 breaths per minute. For an infant, a normal rate is 30 to 60 breaths per minute. Tachypnea is the term that your health care provider uses to describe your breathing if it is too fast, especially if you have fast, shallow breathing from a lung disease or other medical cause. The term  hyperventilation  is usually used if you are taking rapid, deep breaths. This can be due to lung disease or because of anxiety or panic. The terms are sometimes used interchangeably.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003335-2" qtype="causes">What causes Rapid shallow breathing ?</Question>
			<Answer>Shallow, rapid breathing has many possible medical causes, including: Asthma , Blood clot in an artery in the lung, Choking, Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease ( COPD ) and other chronic lung diseases,  Heart failure , Infection in the smallest air passages of the lungs in children ( bronchiolitis ),  Pneumonia  or other lung infection,  Transient tachypnea  of the newborn,  Anxiety  and panic, Other serious lung disease, such as interstitial lung disease or  bronchiectasis , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003335-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Rapid shallow breathing ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003335-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Rapid shallow breathing ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call 911 or the local emergency number, or go to the emergency room if you are breathing rapidly and you have: Bluish or grayish color to the skin, nails, gums, lips, or the area around the eyes ( cyanosis ), Chest pain, Chest wall is pulling in with each breath (intercostal retractions), Fever, Labored or difficult breathing, Never had rapid breathing before, Symptoms that are getting more severe , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003335-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Rapid shallow breathing ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>