<Document id="0003526" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000668.htm">
 
<Focus>Septic shock</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0036983</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bacteremic shock</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Endotoxic shock</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Septicemic shock</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Warm shock</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003526-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Septic shock is a serious condition that occurs when a body-wide infection leads to dangerously low blood pressure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003526-2" qtype="causes">What causes Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Septic shock occurs most often in the very old and the very young. It may also occur in people with weakened immune systems.  Any type of bacteria can cause septic shock. Fungi and (rarely) viruses may also cause the condition. Toxins released by the bacteria or fungi may cause tissue damage. This may lead to low blood pressure and poor organ function. Some researchers think that blood clots in small arteries cause the lack of blood flow and poor organ function.  The body has a strong inflammatory response to the toxins that may contribute to organ damage. Risk factors for septic shock include: Diabetes , Diseases of the genitourinary system,  biliary system , or intestinal system, Diseases that weaken the immune system, such as AIDS, Indwelling catheters (those that remain in place for extended periods, especially intravenous lines and urinary catheters, and plastic and metal stents used for drainage), Leukemia, Long-term use of antibiotics, Lymphoma, Recent infection, Recent surgery or medical procedure, Recent or current use of steroid medicines, Solid organ or bone marrow transplantation, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003526-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Septic shock can affect any part of the body, including the heart, brain, kidneys, liver, and intestines. Symptoms may include: Cool, pale arms and legs, High or very low temperature, chills, Lightheadedness,  Little or no urine , Low blood pressure, especially when standing, Palpitations, Rapid heart rate, Restlessness,  agitation , lethargy, or confusion, Shortness of breath, Skin rash or discoloration,  Decreased mental status &#160;and confusion, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003526-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Blood tests may be done to check for: Infection around the body,  Complete blood count (CBC)  and blood chemistry, Presence of bacteria or other organisms, Low blood oxygen level, Disturbances in the body's acid-base balance, Poor organ function or organ failure ,  Other tests may include: A chest x-ray to look for pneumonia or fluid in the lungs (pulmonary edema), A urine sample to look for infection ,  Additional studies, such as  blood cultures , may not become positive for several days after the blood has been taken, or for several days after the shock has developed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003526-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Septic shock is a medical emergency. In most cases, people are admitted to the intensive care unit of the hospital. Treatment may include: Breathing machine (mechanical ventilation), Dialysis, Drugs to treat low blood pressure, infection, or blood clotting, High volume of fluids given directly into a vein (intravenously), Oxygen, Sedatives, Surgery to drain infected areas, if needed, Antibiotics or other agents to treat viral or fungal infections,  The pressure in the heart and lungs may be checked. This is called hemodynamic monitoring. This can only be done with special equipment and intensive care nursing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003526-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Septic shock has a high death rate. The death rate depends on the person's age and overall health, the cause of the infection, how many organs have failed, and how quickly and aggressively medical therapy is started.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003526-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Respiratory failure,  cardiac failure , or any other organ failure can occur. Gangrene may occur, possibly leading to amputation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003526-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Go directly to an emergency department if you develop symptoms of septic shock.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003526-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Septic shock ?</Question>
			<Answer>Prompt treatment of bacterial infections is helpful. Vaccination could help prevent some infections. However, many cases of septic shock cannot be prevented.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>