<Document id="0003757" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001426.htm">
 
<Focus>Sturge-Weber syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0038505</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Encephalotrigeminal angiomatosis</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003757-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Sturge-Weber syndrome (SWS) is a rare disorder that is present at birth. A child with this condition will have a port-wine stain birthmark (usually on the face) and may have nervous system problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003757-2" qtype="causes">What causes Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>
In many people, the cause of Sturge-Weber is due to a mutation of the  GNAQ  gene. This gene affects small blood vessels called capillaries in some but not all body cells. Problems in the capillaries cause the  port-wine stains  to form. Sturge-Weber is not thought to be passed down (inherited) through families.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003757-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of SWS include: Port-wine stain (more common on the upper face and eye-lid than the rest of the body),  Seizures , Headache,  Paralysis  or weakness on one side, Learning disabilities, Glaucoma (very high fluid pressure in the eye), Low thyroid ( hypothyroidism ) , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003757-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer> 
 The health care provider should check all birthmarks, including a port-wine stain. Glaucoma  may be one sign of the condition. Tests may include: CT scan ,  MRI scan , X-rays, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003757-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment is based on the person's signs and symptoms, and may include: Anticonvulsant medicines for seizures, Eye drops or surgery to treat glaucoma,  Laser therapy  for port-wine stains, Physical therapy for paralysis or weakness, Possible brain surgery to prevent seizures, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003757-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>SWS is usually not life threatening. The condition does need regular lifelong follow-up. The person's quality of life depends on how well their symptoms (such as seizures) can be prevented or treated. The person&#160;will need to visit an eye doctor (ophthalmologist) at least once a year to treat glaucoma. They also will need to see a neurologist to treat seizures and other&#160;nervous system&#160;symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003757-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>These complications can occur: Abnormal blood vessel growth in the skull, Continued growth of the port-wine stain, Developmental delays, Emotional and behavioral problems, Glaucoma, which may lead to blindness, Paralysis, Seizures, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003757-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Seizures, vision problems, paralysis, and changes in alertness or mental state may mean the coverings of the brain are involved. These symptoms should be evaluated right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0003757-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Sturge-Weber syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known prevention.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>