<Document id="0003547" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000771.htm">
 
<Focus>Sexual abuse in children - what to know</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0282350</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T048</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Sexual abuse - children</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003547-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Sexual abuse in children - what to know ?</Question>
			<Answer>One in four girls and one in ten boys are sexually abused before they turn 18. Sexual abuse of children is any activity that the abuser does to get sexually aroused, including: Touching a child's genitals, Rubbing the abuser's genitals against a child's skin or clothing, Putting objects into a child's anus or vagina, Tongue kissing, Oral sex, Intercourse ,  Sexual abuse can also happen without physical contact, such as: Exposing one's own genitals, Having a child pose for pornography, Having a child look at pornography, Masturbating in front of a child , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003547-2" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Sexual abuse in children - what to know ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003547-4" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Sexual abuse in children - what to know ?</Question>
			<Answer>Get the child any needed medical care. Also get mental health counseling for the child. Active support groups that can help include: Childhelp --  www.childhelp.org , Rape, Abuse &amp; Incest National Network --  www.rainn.org ,  Know that providers, teachers, and child care workers are required by law to report sexual abuse. If abuse is suspected, child protection agencies and the police will investigate. The child must be protected from abuse. The child may be placed with a non-abusing parent, another relative, or in a foster home.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>