<Document id="0003964" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001043.htm">
 
<Focus>Tonsillitis</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040425</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0003964-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Tonsillitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tonsillitis is inflammation (swelling) of the tonsils.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0003964-2" qtype="causes">What causes Tonsillitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>The tonsils are lymph nodes in the back of the mouth and top of the throat. They help to filter out bacteria and other germs to prevent infection in the body. A bacterial or viral infection can cause tonsillitis.  Strep throat  is a common cause.  The infection may also be seen in other parts of the throat. One such infection is called  pharyngitis. Tonsillitis is very common in children.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0003964-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Tonsillitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Common symptoms may be: Difficulty swallowing ,  Ear pain ,  Fever  and  chills ,  Headache , Sore throat, which lasts longer than 48 hours and may be severe, Tenderness of the jaw and throat ,  Other problems or symptoms that may occur are: Problems breathing, if the tonsils are very large, Problems eating or drinking , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0003964-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Tonsillitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will look in the mouth and throat.  The tonsils may be red and may have white spots on them., The lymph nodes in the jaw and neck may be swollen and tender to the touch. ,  A  rapid strep test  can be done in most providers' offices. However, this test may be normal, and you can still have strep. Your provider may send the throat swab to a laboratory for a  strep culture . Test results can take a few days. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0003964-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Tonsillitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Swollen tonsils that are not painful or do not cause other problems do not need to be treated. Your provider may not give you an antibiotic. You may be asked to come back for a checkup later to assess your progress. If tests show you do have strep, your provider will give you an antibiotic. It is important to finish all of your antibiotic doses as directed, even if you feel better. If you do not take them all, the infection can return.  The following tips may help your throat feel better:  Drink cold liquids or suck on fruit-flavored frozen bars., Drink fluids, and mostly warm (not hot), bland fluids., Gargle with warm salt water., Suck on lozenges (containing benzocaine or similar ingredients) to reduce pain (these should not be used in young children because of the choking risk)., Take over-the-counter (OTC) medicines, such as acetaminophen (Tylenol) or ibuprofen to reduce pain and fever. DO NOT give a child aspirin. Aspirin has been linked to  Reye syndrome . ,  Some people who have repeated infections may need surgery to remove the tonsils ( tonsillectomy ).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0003964-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Tonsillitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tonsillitis symptoms due to strep will often get better within 2 or 3 days after you start the antibiotics. Children with strep throat should be kept home from school or day care until they have been on antibiotics for 24 hours. This helps reduce the spread of illness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0003964-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Tonsillitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications from strep throat may be severe. They&#160;may include: Abscess in the area around the tonsils , Kidney disease caused by strep,  Rheumatic fever  and other heart problems , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0003964-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Tonsillitis ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if there is: Excess drooling in a young child, Fever, particularly 101&#176;F (38.3&#176;C) or higher, Pus in the back of the throat, Red  rash  that feels rough, and increased redness in the skin folds, Severe problems swallowing or breathing, Tender or swollen lymph glands in the neck , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>