<Document id="0004256" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003118.htm">
 
<Focus>Vomiting blood</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0018926</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Hematemesis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Blood in the vomit</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004256-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Vomiting blood ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vomiting blood is regurgitating (throwing up) contents of the stomach that contains blood. Vomited blood may appear bright red, dark red, or look like coffee grounds. The vomited material may be mixed with food or it may be blood only.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004256-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Vomiting blood ?</Question>
			<Answer>It may be hard to tell the difference between vomiting blood and  coughing up blood  (from the lung) or a nosebleed. Conditions that cause vomiting blood can also cause  blood to appear in the stool .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004256-3" qtype="causes">What causes Vomiting blood ?</Question>
			<Answer>The upper GI (gastrointestinal) tract includes the mouth, throat, esophagus (swallowing tube), stomach and the duodenum (first part of the small intestine). Blood that is vomited may come from any of these places. Vomiting that is very forceful or continues for a very long time may cause a tear in the small blood vessels of the throat. This may produce streaks of blood in the vomit. Swollen veins in the walls of the lower part of the esophagus, and sometimes the stomach, may begin to bleed. These veins (called varices) may be present in people with severe liver damage. Repeated vomiting and retching may cause bleeding and damage to the lower esophagus called  Mallory Weiss tears . Other causes may include: Bleeding ulcer in the stomach, first part of the small intestine, or esophagus, Blood clotting disorders, Defects in the blood vessels of the GI tract, Swelling, irritation, or inflammation of the esophagus lining ( esophagitis ) or the stomach lining ( gastritis ), Swallowing blood (for example, after a nosebleed), Tumors of the mouth, throat, stomach or esophagus, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004256-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Vomiting blood ?</Question>
			<Answer>It may be hard to tell the difference between vomiting blood and  coughing up blood  (from the lung) or a nosebleed. Conditions that cause vomiting blood can also cause  blood to appear in the stool .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004256-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Vomiting blood ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider or go to the emergency room if vomiting of blood occurs. You will need to be examined right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004256-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Vomiting blood ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>