<Document id="0004013" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/007457.htm">
 
<Focus>Transplant services</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0478647</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004013-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Transplant services ?</Question>
			<Answer>Transplant surgery is typically done to replace a diseased body part with a healthy one. SOLID ORGAN TRANSPLANTS Auto islet cell transplant is done after a person has their pancreas removed due to long-term (chronic) pancreatitis. The procedure takes insulin-producing cells from the pancreas and returns them to the person's body.,  Corneal transplant  replaces a damaged or diseased cornea. The cornea is the clear tissue on the front of the eye that helps focus light on the retina. It is the part of the eye on which a contact lens rests.,  Heart transplant  is an option for someone with congestive heart failure that has not responded to medical treatment., Intestinal transplant is an option for people with short bowel or short gut syndrome or advanced liver disease, or who must  receive all nutrients through a feeding line .,  Kidney transplant  is an option for someone with long-term (chronic) kidney failure. It may be done with a kidney- pancreas transplant .,  Liver transplant  may be the only option for someone with liver disease that has led to liver failure.,  Lung transplant  may replace one or both lungs. It may be the only option for someone with lung disease who has not gotten better using other medicines and therapies, and is expected to survive for less than 2 years. ,  BLOOD/BONE MARROW TRANSPLANTS (STEM CELL TRANSPLANTS) You may need a stem cell transplant if you have a disease that damages the cells in bone marrow, or if you received high doses of chemotherapy or radiation. Depending on the type of transplant, your procedure may be called a  bone marrow transplant , a cord blood transplant, or a peripheral blood stem cell transplant. All three use stem cells, which are immature cells that give rise to all blood cells. Stem cell transplants are similar to blood transfusions and generally do not need surgery. There are two different types of transplants: Autologous transplants use your own blood cells or bone marrow., Allogeneic transplants use a donor's blood cells or bone marrow. A syngeneic allogeneic transplant uses cells or bone marrow from the person's identical twin. ,  THE TRANSPLANT SERVICES TEAM The transplant services team includes carefully selected experts, including: Surgeons who specialize in performing organ transplants, Medical doctors, Radiologists and medical imaging technologists, Nurses, Infectious disease experts, Physical therapists, Psychiatrists, psychologists, and other counselors, Social workers, Nutritionists and dietitians ,  BEFORE AN ORGAN TRANSPLANT You will have a complete medical exam to identify and treat all medical problems, such as kidney and heart disease. The transplant team will evaluate you and review your medical history to determine if you meet the criteria for organ transplantation. Most types of organ transplants have guidelines detailing what type of person is most likely to benefit from a transplant and will be able to manage the challenging process. If the transplant team believes you are a good candidate for a transplant, you will be put on a national waiting list. Your place on a waiting list is based on a number of factors, which depend on the type of transplant you are receiving. Once you are on the waiting list, the search for a matching donor begins. Types of donors depend on your specific transplant, but include: A living related donor is related to you, such as a parent, sibling, or child., A living unrelated donor is a person, such as a friend or spouse., A deceased donor is someone who has recently died. The heart, liver, kidneys, lungs, intestines, and pancreas can be recovered from an organ donor. ,  After donating an organ, living donors can live a normal, healthy life. You should identify family, friends, or other caregivers who can offer help and support during and after the transplant process. You will also want to prepare your home to make it comfortable for when you return after being released from the hospital. AFTER A TRANSPLANT How long you stay in the hospital depends on the type of transplant that you have. During your stay in the hospital, you will be seen daily by the transplant services team. Your transplant services coordinators will arrange for your discharge. They will discuss with you plans for care at home, transportation to clinic visits, and housing, if needed. You will be told how to take care of yourself after the transplant. This will include information about: Medicines, How often you need to visit the doctor or clinic, What daily activities are allowed or off-limits ,  After leaving the hospital, you will return home. You will have periodic follow-ups with the transplant team, as well as with your primary care doctor and any other specialists that may be recommended. The transplant services team will be available to answer any questions that you may have.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004013-2" qtype="information">What is (are) Transplant services ?</Question>
			<Answer>Transplant surgery is typically done to replace a diseased body part with a healthy one. SOLID ORGAN TRANSPLANTS Auto islet cell transplant is done after a person has their pancreas removed due to long-term (chronic) pancreatitis. The procedure takes insulin-producing cells from the pancreas and returns them to the person's body.,  Corneal transplant  replaces a damaged or diseased cornea. The cornea is the clear tissue on the front of the eye that helps focus light on the retina. It is the part of the eye on which a contact lens rests.,  Heart transplant  is an option for someone with congestive heart failure that has not responded to medical treatment., Intestinal transplant is an option for people with short bowel or short gut syndrome or advanced liver disease, or who must  receive all nutrients through a feeding line .,  Kidney transplant  is an option for someone with long-term (chronic) kidney failure. It may be done with a kidney- pancreas transplant .,  Liver transplant  may be the only option for someone with liver disease that has led to liver failure.,  Lung transplant  may replace one or both lungs. It may be the only option for someone with lung disease who has not gotten better using other medicines and therapies, and is expected to survive for less than 2 years. ,  BLOOD/BONE MARROW TRANSPLANTS (STEM CELL TRANSPLANTS) You may need a stem cell transplant if you have a disease that damages the cells in bone marrow, or if you received high doses of chemotherapy or radiation. Depending on the type of transplant, your procedure may be called a  bone marrow transplant , a cord blood transplant, or a peripheral blood stem cell transplant. All three use stem cells, which are immature cells that give rise to all blood cells. Stem cell transplants are similar to blood transfusions and generally do not need surgery. There are two different types of transplants: Autologous transplants use your own blood cells or bone marrow., Allogeneic transplants use a donor's blood cells or bone marrow. A syngeneic allogeneic transplant uses cells or bone marrow from the person's identical twin. ,  THE TRANSPLANT SERVICES TEAM The transplant services team includes carefully selected experts, including: Surgeons who specialize in performing organ transplants, Medical doctors, Radiologists and medical imaging technologists, Nurses, Infectious disease experts, Physical therapists, Psychiatrists, psychologists, and other counselors, Social workers, Nutritionists and dietitians ,  BEFORE AN ORGAN TRANSPLANT You will have a complete medical exam to identify and treat all medical problems, such as kidney and heart disease. The transplant team will evaluate you and review your medical history to determine if you meet the criteria for organ transplantation. Most types of organ transplants have guidelines detailing what type of person is most likely to benefit from a transplant and will be able to manage the challenging process. If the transplant team believes you are a good candidate for a transplant, you will be put on a national waiting list. Your place on a waiting list is based on a number of factors, which depend on the type of transplant you are receiving. Once you are on the waiting list, the search for a matching donor begins. Types of donors depend on your specific transplant, but include: A living related donor is related to you, such as a parent, sibling, or child., A living unrelated donor is a person, such as a friend or spouse., A deceased donor is someone who has recently died. The heart, liver, kidneys, lungs, intestines, and pancreas can be recovered from an organ donor. ,  After donating an organ, living donors can live a normal, healthy life. You should identify family, friends, or other caregivers who can offer help and support during and after the transplant process. You will also want to prepare your home to make it comfortable for when you return after being released from the hospital. AFTER A TRANSPLANT How long you stay in the hospital depends on the type of transplant that you have. During your stay in the hospital, you will be seen daily by the transplant services team. Your transplant services coordinators will arrange for your discharge. They will discuss with you plans for care at home, transportation to clinic visits, and housing, if needed. You will be told how to take care of yourself after the transplant. This will include information about: Medicines, How often you need to visit the doctor or clinic, What daily activities are allowed or off-limits ,  After leaving the hospital, you will return home. You will have periodic follow-ups with the transplant team, as well as with your primary care doctor and any other specialists that may be recommended. The transplant services team will be available to answer any questions that you may have.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>