<Document id="0004186" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001510.htm">
 
<Focus>Vaginal tumors</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0750081</CUI>
			<CUI>C0042258</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Vaginal cancer</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Cancer - vagina</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tumor - vaginal</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004186-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vaginal cancer is cancer of the vagina, a female reproductive organ.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004186-2" qtype="causes">What causes Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most vaginal cancers occur when another cancer, such as  cervical , vulvar, or  endometrial cancer , spreads. This is called secondary vaginal cancer. Cancer that starts in the vagina is called primary vaginal cancer. This type of cancer is rare. Most primary vaginal cancers start in skin-like cells called squamous cells. This cancer is known as squamous cell carcinoma. The other types include: Adenocarcinoma, Melanoma, Sarcoma,  The cause of squamous cell carcinoma of the vagina is unknown. But a history of cervical cancer is common in women with squamous cell carcinoma of the vagina. So it may be associated with human papilloma virus (HPV) infection. Most women with squamous cell cancer of the vagina are over 50.  Adenocarcinoma of the vagina tends to affect younger women. The average age at which this cancer is diagnosed is 19. Women whose mothers took the medicine diethylstilbestrol (DES) to prevent  miscarriages  during the first 3 months of pregnancy are more likely to develop vaginal adenocarcinoma. Sarcoma of the vagina is a rare cancer that mainly occurs in infancy and early childhood.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004186-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms of vaginal cancer can include any of the following: Bleeding after having sex, Painless vaginal bleeding and discharge not due to normal period, Pain in the pelvis or vagina,  Some women have no symptoms.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004186-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>In women with no symptoms, the cancer may be found during a routine pelvic exam and  Pap test . Other tests to diagnose vaginal cancer include: Biopsy ,  Colposcopy ,  Other tests that may be done to check if the cancer has spread include: Chest x-ray ,  CT scan  and  MRI  of the abdomen and pelvis ,  PET scan ,  Other tests that may be done to know the stage of the vaginal cancer include: Cystoscopy ,  Barium enema ,  Intravenous urography  (x-ray of kidney, ureters and bladder using contrast material), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004186-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treatment of vaginal cancer depends on: The type of cancer, How far the disease has spread,  Surgery is sometimes used if the cancer is small and located at the upper part of the vagina. Most women are treated with  radiation . If the tumor is cervical cancer that has spread to the vagina, radiation and  chemotherapy  are both given. Sarcoma may be treated with a combination of chemotherapy, surgery, and radiation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004186-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>You can ease the stress of illness by joining a  support group  whose members share common experiences and problems.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004186-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outlook for women with vaginal cancer depends on the size and the stage of disease and the specific type of tumor.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004186-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vaginal cancer may spread to other areas of the body. Complications can occur from radiation, surgery, and chemotherapy.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004186-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call for an appointment with your health care provider if: You notice bleeding after sex, You have persistent vaginal bleeding or discharge, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0004186-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Vaginal tumors ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no definite ways to prevent this cancer. The  HPV vaccine  is approved to help prevent cervical cancer. This vaccine may also decrease the risk of getting some other HPV-associated cancers, such as vaginal cancer. You can increase your chance of early detection by getting regular pelvic examinations and Pap smears.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>