<Document id="0004074" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000203.htm">
 
<Focus>Ulcerative colitis - discharge</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0009324</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Inflammatory bowel disease - ulcerative colitis - discharge</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Ulcerative proctitis - discharge</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Colitis - discharge</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004074-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Ulcerative colitis - discharge ?</Question>
			<Answer>You were in the hospital to treat ulcerative colitis. This is a swelling (inflammation) of the inner lining of your colon and rectum (also called your large intestine). This article tells you how to take care of yourself when you return home.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004074-2" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Ulcerative colitis - discharge ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004074-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Ulcerative colitis - discharge ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider may give you some medicines to help relieve your symptoms. Based on how severe your ulcerative colitis is and how you respond to treatment, you may need to take one or more of these medicines: Anti-diarrhea drugs can help when you have very bad diarrhea. You can buy loperamide (Imodium) without a prescription. Always talk to your provider before using these drugs., Fiber supplements may help your symptoms. You can buy psyllium powder (Metamucil) or methylcellulose (Citrucel) without a prescription., Always talk to your provider before using any laxative medicines., You may use acetaminophen (Tylenol) for mild pain. Drugs such as aspirin, ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin), or naproxen (Aleve, Naprosyn) may make your symptoms worse. Talk to your provider before taking these medicines. You may also need a prescription for stronger pain medicines. ,  There are many types of drugs your provider may use to prevent or treat attacks of your ulcerative colitis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004074-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Ulcerative colitis - discharge ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>