<Document id="0004278" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003084.htm">
 
<Focus>Weight gain - unintentional</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0043094</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004278-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Weight gain - unintentional ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unintentional weight gain is when you gain weight without trying to do so and you are not eating or drinking more.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004278-2" qtype="causes">What causes Weight gain - unintentional ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gaining weight when you are not trying to do so can have many causes.  Metabolism slows down as you  age . This can cause weight gain if you eat too much, eat the wrong foods, or do not get enough exercise. Drugs that can cause weight gain include:  Birth control pills , Corticosteroids , Some drugs used to treat bipolar disorder, schizophrenia, and depression, Some drugs used to treat diabetes,  Hormone changes or medical problems can also cause unintentional weight gain. This may be due to: Cushing syndrome, Underactive thyroid, or low thyroid (hypothyroidism), Polycystic ovary syndrome, Menopause, Pregnancy,  Bloating, or swelling due to a  buildup of fluid in the tissues  can cause weight gain. This may be due to menstruation, heart or kidney failure, preeclampsia, or medicines you take. A rapid weight gain may be a sign of dangerous fluid retention. If you quit smoking, you might gain weight. Most people who quit smoking gain 4 to 10 pounds (2 to 4.5 kilograms) in the first 6 months after quitting. Some gain as much as 25 to 30 pounds (11 to 14 kilograms). This weight gain is not simply due to eating more.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004278-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Weight gain - unintentional ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004278-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Weight gain - unintentional ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you have the following symptoms with the weight gain:  Constipation , Excessive weight gain without a known cause,  Hair loss , Feel cold more often than before, Swollen feet and  shortness of breath , Uncontrollable  hunger  accompanied by  palpitations , tremor, and  sweating , Vision changes , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004278-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Weight gain - unintentional ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>