<Document id="0004174" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003156.htm">
 
<Focus>Vaginal bleeding between periods</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3163625</CUI>
			<CUI>C0025874</CUI>
			<CUI>C2979982</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Bleeding between periods</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Intermenstrual bleeding</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Spotting</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Metrorrhagia</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004174-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Vaginal bleeding between periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>This article discusses vaginal bleeding that occurs between a woman's monthly menstrual periods. Such bleeding may be called "intermenstrual bleeding." Related topics include: Dysfunctional uterine bleeding , Heavy, prolonged, or irregular menstrual periods , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004174-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Vaginal bleeding between periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Normal menstrual flow lasts about 5 days. It produces a total blood loss of 30 to 80 mL (about 2 to 8 tablespoons), and occurs normally every 21 to 35 days. Vaginal bleeding that occurs between periods or after menopause can be caused by various problems. Most are benign and can be easily treated. Sometimes, vaginal bleeding may be due to cancer or pre-cancer. Therefore, any unusual bleeding should be evaluated right away. The risk&#160;for cancer increases to about 10% in women with postmenopausal bleeding. Make sure that bleeding is coming from the  vagina  and is not from the rectum or the urine. Inserting a tampon into the vagina will confirm the vagina, cervix, or uterus as the source of bleeding. A careful exam by your health care provider is most often the best way to find the source of the bleeding. This exam can be done even while you are bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004174-3" qtype="causes">What causes Vaginal bleeding between periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Causes may include: Uterine fibroids or cervical or uterine polyps, Changes in hormone levels, Inflammation or infection of the cervix (cervicitis)&#160;or uterus (endometritis), Injury or disease of the vaginal opening (caused by intercourse, trauma, infection, polyp,  genital warts , ulcer, or varicose veins), IUD use (may cause occasional spotting),  Ectopic pregnancy , Miscarriage, Other pregnancy complications, Vaginal dryness due to lack of estrogen after  menopause , Stress, Using hormonal birth control irregularly (such as stopping and starting or skipping birth control pills, patches, or estrogen rings)&#160;, Underactive thyroid (low thyroid function), Use of blood thinners (anticoagulants), Cancer or pre-cancer of the cervix, uterus, or (very rarely) fallopian tube, Pelvic exam, cervical biopsy,&#160;endometrial biopsy, or other procedures , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004174-4" qtype="considerations">What to do for Vaginal bleeding between periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Normal menstrual flow lasts about 5 days. It produces a total blood loss of 30 to 80 mL (about 2 to 8 tablespoons), and occurs normally every 21 to 35 days. Vaginal bleeding that occurs between periods or after menopause can be caused by various problems. Most are benign and can be easily treated. Sometimes, vaginal bleeding may be due to cancer or pre-cancer. Therefore, any unusual bleeding should be evaluated right away. The risk&#160;for cancer increases to about 10% in women with postmenopausal bleeding. Make sure that bleeding is coming from the  vagina  and is not from the rectum or the urine. Inserting a tampon into the vagina will confirm the vagina, cervix, or uterus as the source of bleeding. A careful exam by your health care provider is most often the best way to find the source of the bleeding. This exam can be done even while you are bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004174-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Vaginal bleeding between periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if: You are pregnant., There is any unexplained bleeding between periods., There is any bleeding after menopause., There is heavy bleeding with periods., Abnormal bleeding is accompanied by other symptoms, such as pelvic pain, fatigue, dizziness. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004174-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Vaginal bleeding between periods ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>