<Document id="0004271" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003036.htm">
 
<Focus>Watery eyes</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C3257803</CUI>
			<CUI>C0152227</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Epiphora</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Tearing - increased</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004271-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Watery eyes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Watery eyes means you have too many tears draining from the eyes. Tears help keep the surface of the eye moist. They wash away particles and foreign objects in the eye.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004271-2" qtype="causes">What causes Watery eyes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your eyes are always making tears. These tears leave the eye through a small hole in the corner of the eye called the tear duct.  Causes of watery eyes include: Allergy to mold, dander, dust,  Blepharitis  (swelling along the edge of the eyelid), Blockage of the tear duct,  Conjunctivitis , Smog or chemicals in the air or wind, Bright light, Eyelid turning inward or outward, Something in the eye (such as dust or sand), Scrape on the eye, Infection, Inward-growing eyelashes, Irritation ,  Increased tearing sometimes happens with: Eyestrain, Laughing,  Vomiting ,  Yawning ,  One of the most common causes of excess tearing is  dry eyes . Drying causes the eyes to become uncomfortable, which stimulates the body to produce too many tears. One of the main tests for tearing is to check whether the eyes are too dry.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004271-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Watery eyes ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004271-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Watery eyes ?</Question>
			<Answer>Tearing is rarely an emergency. You should seek help right away if: Chemicals get into the eye, You have severe pain, bleeding, or loss of vision, You have a severe injury to the eye ,  Also, contact your health care provider if you have: A scratch on the eye, Something in the eye, Painful, red eyes, A lot of discharge coming from the eye, Long-term, unexplained tearing, Tenderness around the nose or sinuses , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004271-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Watery eyes ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>