<Document id="0004175" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000614.htm">
 
<Focus>Vaginal bleeding in early pregnancy</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C2979982</CUI>
			<CUI>C0156604</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T046</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004175-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Vaginal bleeding in early pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vaginal bleeding during pregnancy is any discharge of blood from the vagina. It can happen any time from conception (when the egg is fertilized) to the end of pregnancy. Some women have vaginal bleeding during their first 20 weeks of pregnancy. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004175-3" qtype="information">What is (are) Vaginal bleeding in early pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Vaginal bleeding during pregnancy is any discharge of blood from the vagina. It can happen any time from conception (when the egg is fertilized) to the end of pregnancy. Some women have vaginal bleeding during their first 20 weeks of pregnancy. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004175-4" qtype="causes">What causes Vaginal bleeding in early pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Bleeding in the 1st trimester is not always a problem. It may be caused by: Having sex., An infection., The fertilized egg implanting in the uterus., Hormone changes., Other factors that will not harm the woman or baby., A threatened miscarriage. Many threatened miscarriages do not progress to pregnancy loss.,  More serious causes of first-trimester bleeding include: A  miscarriage , which is the loss of the pregnancy before the embryo or fetus can live on its own outside the uterus. Almost all women who miscarry will have bleeding before a miscarriage., An ectopic pregnancy, which may cause bleeding and cramping., A  molar pregnancy , in which a fertilized egg implants in the uterus but will not come to term., Formation of a blood clot between the amniotic sac and the wall of the womb called a subchorionic hematoma., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004175-5" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Vaginal bleeding in early pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004175-7" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Vaginal bleeding in early pregnancy ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most of the time, the treatment for bleeding is rest. It is important to see your provider and have testing done to find the cause of your bleeding. Your provider may advise you to: Take time off work, Stay off your feet, Not have sex, Not douche (NEVER do this during pregnancy, and also avoid it when you are not pregnant), Not use tampons ,  Very heavy bleeding may require a hospital stay or surgical procedure. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>