<Document id="0004103" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001271.htm">
 
<Focus>Urethral stricture</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0041974</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T190</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004103-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Urethral stricture is an abnormal narrowing of the urethra. The urethra is the tube that carries urine out of the body from the bladder.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004103-2" qtype="causes">What causes Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>A urethral stricture may be caused by swelling or scar tissue from surgery. It can also occur after an infection or injury. Rarely, it may be caused by pressure from a growing tumor near the urethra. Other factors that increase the risk for this condition include: Sexually transmitted infection (STI), Procedures that place a tube into the urethra (such as a catheter or  cystoscope ),  Benign prostatic hyperplasia  (BPH), Injury to the pelvic area, Repeated  urethritis ,  Strictures that are present at birth (congenital) are rare. The condition is also rare in women. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004103-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms include: Blood in the semen , Discharge from the urethra, Bloody or  dark urine , Strong urge to urinate and  frequent urination ,  Inability to empty bladder &#160;(urinary retention), Painful urination or  difficulty urinating , Loss of bladder control, Increased frequency or urgency to urinate, Pain in the lower abdomen and pelvic area, Slow urine stream (may develop suddenly or gradually) or spraying of urine, Swelling of the penis, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004103-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>A physical exam may show the following: Decreased urinary stream, Discharge from the urethra, Enlarged bladder, Enlarged or tender lymph nodes in the groin, Enlarged or tender prostate, Hardness on the under surface of the penis, Redness or swelling of the penis,  Sometimes, the exam reveals no abnormalities. Tests include the following: Cystoscopy , Postvoid residual (PVR) volume, Retrograde urethrogram, Tests for  chlamydia  and  gonorrhea ,  Urinalysis , Urinary flow rate,  Urine culture , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004103-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>The urethra may be widened (dilated) during cystoscopy. Topical numbing medicine will be applied to the area before the procedure. A thin instrument is inserted into the urethra to stretch it. You may be able to treat your stricture by learning to dilate the urethra at home. If urethral dilation cannot correct the condition, you may need surgery. The type of surgery will depend on the location and length of the stricture. If the narrowed area is short and not near the muscles that control the exit from the bladder, the stricture may be cut or dilated.&#160;One procedure uses a drug-coated balloon, which is inserted and opened up to dilate the urethra and deliver the medicine to the area. After several minutes, the balloon is deflated and removed. The medicine helps the stricture remain open. A surgery called an open urethroplasty may be done for longer strictures. This surgery involves removing the diseased area. The urethra is then rebuilt. The results vary, depending on the size and location of the stricture, the number of treatments you have had, and the surgeon's experience. In acute cases when you cannot pass urine, a  suprapubic catheter  may be placed. This is an emergency treatment. This allows the bladder to drain through the abdomen. There are currently no drug treatments for this disease. If no other treatments work, a urinary diversion called an appendicovesicostomy (Mitrofanoff procedure) or another type of surgery may be done. This lets you drain your bladder through the wall of the abdomen using a catheter or a stoma bag.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004103-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>The outcome is often excellent with treatment. Sometimes, treatment needs to be repeated to remove scar tissue. A urethral stricture may totally block urine flow. This can cause sudden urinary retention. This condition must be treated quickly. Long-term blockage can lead to permanent bladder or kidney damage.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004103-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004103-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if you have symptoms of urethral stricture. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004103-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Urethral stricture ?</Question>
			<Answer>Practicing safer sex may decrease the risk of getting STIs that may cause a urethral stricture. Treating urethral stricture quickly may prevent kidney or bladder complications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>