<Document id="0004002" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001486.htm">
 
<Focus>Trachoma</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0040592</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Granular conjunctivitis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Egyptian ophthalmia</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Conjunctivitis - granular</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004002-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Trachoma is an infection of the eye&#160;caused by bacteria called chlamydia.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004002-2" qtype="causes">What causes Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Trachoma is caused by infection with the bacteria  Chlamydia trachomatis .  The condition occurs around the world. It is most often seen in rural areas of developing countries. Children are often affected. However, the scarring caused by the infection may not be noticed until later in life. The condition is rare in the United States. However, it is more likely to occur in crowded or unclean living conditions.  The bacteria that cause trachoma are spread through direct contact with infected eye, nose, or throat fluids. They can also be passed by contact with contaminated objects, such as towels or clothes. Certain flies can also spread the bacteria.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004002-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms begin 5 to 12 days after being exposed to the bacteria. The condition begins slowly. It first appears as inflammation of the tissue lining the eyelids ( conjunctivitis , or "pink eye"). Untreated, this may lead to scarring. Symptoms may include: Cloudy cornea , Discharge from the eye, Swelling of lymph nodes just in front of the ears, Swollen eyelids, Turned-in eyelashes , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004002-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>The health care provider will do an eye exam to look for scarring on the inside of the upper eye lid, redness of the white part of the eyes, and new blood vessel growth into the cornea. Lab tests are needed to identify the bacteria and make an accurate diagnosis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004002-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Antibiotics can prevent long-term complications if used early in the infection. In certain cases, eyelid surgery may be needed to prevent long-term scarring, which can lead to blindness if not corrected.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004002-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Outcomes are very good if treatment is started early before scarring and changes to the eyelids develop.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004002-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>If the eyelids become very irritated, the eyelashes may turn in and rub against the cornea. This can cause corneal ulcers, additional scars, vision loss, and possibly, blindness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004002-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider if you or your child recently visited an area where trachoma is common and you notice symptoms of conjunctivitis.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004002-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Trachoma ?</Question>
			<Answer>Spread of the infection can be limited by washing your hands and face often, keeping clothes clean, and not sharing items such as towels.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>