<Document id="0004210" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000203.htm">
 
<Focus>Venous insufficiency</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0042485</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T047</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Chronic venous insufficiency</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic venous stasis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Chronic venous disease</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004210-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Venous insufficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Venous insufficiency is a condition in which the veins have problems sending blood from the legs back to the heart.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004210-2" qtype="causes">What causes Venous insufficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Normally, valves in your deeper leg veins keep blood moving forward toward the heart. With long-term (chronic) venous insufficiency, vein walls are weakened and valves are damaged. This causes the  veins to stay filled with blood , especially when you are standing. Chronic venous insufficiency is a long-term condition. It is most commonly due to malfunctioning (incompetent) valves in the veins. It may also occur as the result of a past blood clot in the legs. Risk factors for venous insufficiency include: Age, Family history of this condition, Female sex (related to levels of the hormone progesterone), History of  deep vein thrombosis  in the legs, Obesity, Pregnancy, Sitting or standing for long periods, Tall height , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004210-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Venous insufficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pain or other symptoms include: Dull aching, heaviness, or cramping in legs, Itching and tingling, Pain that gets worse when standing, Pain that gets better when legs are raised,  
Skin changes in the legs include: Swelling of the legs , Irritated or cracked skin if you scratch it,  Red or swollen, crusted, or weepy skin  (stasis dermatitis),  Varicose veins  on the surface, Thickening and hardening of the skin on the legs and ankles (lipodermatosclerosis), Wound or  ulcer  that is slow to heal on the legs or ankles, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004210-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Venous insufficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your health care provider will do a physical exam and ask about your symptoms and medical history. Diagnosis is often made based on the appearance of leg veins when you are standing or sitting with your legs dangling. A  duplex ultrasound  exam of your leg may be ordered to: Check how blood flows in the veins, Rule out other problems with the legs, such as a blood clot, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004210-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Venous insufficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your provider may suggest that you take the following self-care steps to help  manage venous insufficiency : Do not sit or stand for long periods. Even moving your legs slightly helps keep the blood flowing., Care for wounds if you have any open sores or infections., Lose weight if you are overweight., Exercise regularly. ,  You can wear compression stockings to improve blood flow in your legs. Compression stockings gently squeeze your legs to move blood up your legs. This helps prevent leg swelling and, to a lesser extent, blood clots. When more advanced skin changes are present, your provider: Should explain which  skin care treatments  can help, and which can make the problem worse, May recommend some drugs or medicines that may help,  Your provider may recommend more invasive treatments if you have: Leg pain, which may make your legs feel heavy or tired, Skin sores caused by poor blood flow in the veins that do not heal or recur, Thickening and hardening of the skin on the legs and ankles (lipodermatosclerosis),  Choices of procedures include: Sclerotherapy  -- Salt water (saline), a chemical solution, or foam is injected into the vein. The vein hardens and then disappears., Phlebectomy -- Small surgical cuts (incisions) are made in the leg near the damaged vein. The vein is removed through one of the incisions., Procedures that can be done in a provider's office or clinic, such as using a  laser, radiofrequency ablation , or a technique that uses a glue/foam to seal the vein.,  Varicose vein stripping  -- Used to remove or tie off a large vein in the leg called the superficial saphenous vein., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004210-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Venous insufficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chronic venous insufficiency tends to get worse over time. However, it can be managed if treatment is started in the early stages. By taking self-care steps, you may be able to ease the discomfort and prevent the condition from getting worse. It is likely that you will need medical procedures to treat the condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004210-7" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Venous insufficiency ?</Question>
			<Answer>Call your provider if: You have varicose veins and they are painful., Your condition gets worse or does not improve with self-care, such as wearing compression stockings or avoiding standing for too long., You have a sudden increase in leg pain or swelling, fever, redness of the leg, or leg sores., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>