<Document id="0004129" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003145.htm">
 
<Focus>Urination - painful</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0030193</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Dysuria</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Painful urination</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004129-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Urination - painful ?</Question>
			<Answer>Painful urination is any pain, discomfort, or burning sensation when passing urine.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004129-2" qtype="considerations">What to do for Urination - painful ?</Question>
			<Answer>Pain may be felt right where the urine passes out of the body. Or, it may be felt inside the body, behind the pubic bone, or in the bladder or prostate. Pain with urination is a fairly common problem. People who have pain with urination also may have the urge to  urinate more often .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004129-3" qtype="causes">What causes Urination - painful ?</Question>
			<Answer>Painful urination is most often caused by an infection or inflammation somewhere in the urinary tract, such as: Bladder infection (adult) ,  Bladder infection (child) ,  Swelling and irritation of the tube that carries urine out of the body (urethra) ,  Painful urination in women and girls may be due to: Changes in the vaginal tissue during menopause ( atrophic vaginitis ),  Herpes infection  in the genital area, Irritation of the vaginal tissue caused by bubble bath, perfumes, or lotions,  Vulvovaginitis , such as yeast or other infections of the vulva and vagina ,  Other causes of painful urination include: Interstitial cystitis , Prostate infection ( prostatitis ), Radiation cystitis - damage to the bladder lining from radiation therapy to the pelvis area, Sexually transmitted infections (STIs), such as  gonorrhea  or  chlamydia , Bladder spasms, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004129-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Urination - painful ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your health care provider if: There is drainage or a discharge from your penis or vagina., You are pregnant and are having any painful urination., You have painful urination that lasts for more than 1 day., You notice blood in your urine., You have a fever. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004129-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Urination - painful ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>