<Document id="0004026" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/patientinstructions/000849.htm">
 
<Focus>Treatment for childhood cancer - long-term risks</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0278704</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T191</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Childhood cancer - late effects</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004026-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Treatment for childhood cancer - long-term risks ?</Question>
			<Answer>Today's cancer treatments help cure most children with cancer. These treatments also may cause health problems later on. These are called "late effects." Late effects are treatment side effects that appear several months or years after treatment for cancer. Late effects can impact one or more areas of the body. Effects can be mild to severe. Whether your child will have late effects depends on the type of cancer and the treatments your child has. Being aware of your child's risk of long-term health problems can help you follow-up with health care providers and detect any problems early. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004026-2" qtype="causes">What causes Treatment for childhood cancer - long-term risks ?</Question>
			<Answer>Some cancer treatments damage healthy cells. The damage is not seen during treatment, but as the child's body grows, changes in cell growth or function appear.  The medicines used for  chemotherapy  and the high-energy rays used in  radiation therapy  can harm healthy cells. This damage can change or delay the way cells grow. Radiation therapy has a more direct effect on long-term growth than chemotherapy. Your child's health care team will come up with a treatment plan to avoid harming healthy cells as much as possible. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004026-3" qtype="susceptibility">Who is at risk for Treatment for childhood cancer - long-term risks? ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004026-4" qtype="information">What is (are) Treatment for childhood cancer - long-term risks ?</Question>
			<Answer>Today's cancer treatments help cure most children with cancer. These treatments also may cause health problems later on. These are called "late effects." Late effects are treatment side effects that appear several months or years after treatment for cancer. Late effects can impact one or more areas of the body. Effects can be mild to severe. Whether your child will have late effects depends on the type of cancer and the treatments your child has. Being aware of your child's risk of long-term health problems can help you follow-up with health care providers and detect any problems early. </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004026-5" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Treatment for childhood cancer - long-term risks ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>