<Document id="0004272" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/002815.htm">
 
<Focus>Wax poisoning</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0032343</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T037</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Crayons poisoning</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004272-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Wax poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Wax is a greasy or oily solid that melts in heat. This article discusses poisoning due to swallowing large amounts of wax or crayons. This article is for information only. DO NOT use it to treat or manage an actual poison exposure. If you or someone you are with has an exposure, call the local emergency number (such as 911), or the local poison control center can be reached directly by calling the national toll-free Poison Help hotline (1-800-222-1222) from anywhere in the United States.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004272-4" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Wax poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>In general, wax is not poisonous. If a child eats a small amount of crayon, the wax will pass through the child's system without causing a problem. However, eating large amounts of wax or crayons can lead to  intestinal obstruction . People attempting to smuggle illegal drugs across international borders sometimes swallow packets of illegal substances that are layered in wax. If the packaging ruptures the drug is released, usually causing severe poisoning. The wax can then cause intestinal obstruction as well.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004272-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Wax poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recovery is very likely.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004272-8" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Wax poisoning ?</Question>
			<Answer>Recovery is very likely.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>