<Document id="0004183" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003159.htm">
 
<Focus>Vaginal itching and discharge - child</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0042256</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T184</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Pruritus vulvae</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Itching - vaginal area</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Vulvar itching</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004183-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Vaginal itching and discharge - child ?</Question>
			<Answer>Itching, redness, and swelling of the skin of the  vagina  and the surrounding area ( vulva ) is a common problem in girls before the age of puberty. Vaginal discharge may also be present. The color, smell, and consistency of the discharge can vary, depending on the cause of the problem.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004183-2" qtype="causes">What causes Vaginal itching and discharge - child ?</Question>
			<Answer>Common causes of vaginal itching and discharge in young girls include: Chemicals such as perfumes and dyes in detergents, fabric softeners, creams, ointments, and sprays may irritate the vagina or the skin around the vagina.,  Vaginal yeast infection .,  Vaginitis . Vaginitis in girls before puberty is common. If a young girl has a sexually transmitted vaginal infection, however, sexual abuse must be considered and addressed., A foreign body, such as toilet paper or a crayon that a young girl may place in the vagina. An infection with a discharge may occur if the foreign object remains in the vagina.,  Pinworms  (a parasite infection mainly affecting children)., Improper cleaning and hygiene, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004183-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Vaginal itching and discharge - child ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004183-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Vaginal itching and discharge - child ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your child's provider right away if: Your child complains of pelvic or lower abdominal pain or has a fever., You suspect sexual abuse.,  Also contact the provider if:  There are blisters or ulcers on the vagina or vulva., Your child has a burning feeling with urination or other problems urinating., Your child has  vaginal bleeding , swelling, or  discharge ., Your child's symptoms get worse, last longer than 1 week, or keep coming back. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004183-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Vaginal itching and discharge - child ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>