<Document id="0004080" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000987.htm">
 
<Focus>Umbilical hernia</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0019322</CUI>
			<CUI>C1306503</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T190</SemanticType>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004080-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>An umbilical hernia is an outward bulge in the area around the belly button. It occurs when internal organs or the abdominal lining bulges through the muscles near the belly button.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004080-2" qtype="causes">What causes Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>In the womb, the umbilical cord is attached to the baby through an opening in the baby's abdomen. After birth, this opening normally closes. When this area doesn't close completely, it leaves a weak spot in the abdomen, which can lead to a hernia. Hernias may be seen after birth or later in life. Umbilical hernias are common in infants. They occur slightly more often in African Americans. Most umbilical hernias are not related to disease. Some umbilical hernias are linked with rare conditions such as  Down syndrome .</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004080-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>A hernia can vary in width from less than 1 centimeter (cm) to more than 5 cm (about 1/2 to 2 inches). There is a soft swelling over the belly button that often bulges when the baby sits up, cries, or strains. The bulge may be flat when the infant lies on the back and is quiet. Umbilical hernias are usually painless.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004080-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>A hernia is usually found by the health care provider during a physical exam.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004080-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most hernias in children heal on their own.  Surgery  to repair the hernia is needed only in the following cases: The hernia does not heal after the child is 3 or 4 years old., The intestine or other tissue bulges out and loses its blood supply (becomes strangulated). This is an emergency that needs surgery right away. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004080-6" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Most umbilical hernias get better without treatment by the time the child is 3 to 4 years old. If surgery is needed, it is usually successful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004080-7" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Strangulation of the intestines can occur. This complication is rare but serious and needs surgery right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004080-8" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>Contact your provider or go to the emergency room if: Your baby is very fussy, Your baby seems to have bad abdominal pain, The hernia becomes tender, swollen, or discolored, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004080-9" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Umbilical hernia ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is no known way to prevent an umbilical hernia. Taping or strapping an umbilical hernia will not make it go away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>