<Document id="0004142" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003147.htm">
 
<Focus>Urine output - decreased</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C1287298</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T033</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Oliguria</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004142-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Urine output - decreased ?</Question>
			<Answer>Decreased urine output means that you produce less urine than normal. Most adults make at least 500 milliliters of urine in 24 hours (a little over 2 cups).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004142-2" qtype="causes">What causes Urine output - decreased ?</Question>
			<Answer>Common causes include: Dehydration  from not drinking enough fluids and having vomiting, diarrhea, or fever, Total urinary tract blockage, such as from an  enlarged prostate , Medicines such as anticholinergics and some antibiotics ,  Less common causes include: Blood loss, Severe infection or other medical condition that leads to  shock , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004142-3" qtype="considerations">What to do for Urine output - decreased ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004142-4" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Urine output - decreased ?</Question>
			<Answer>A large decrease in urine output may be a sign of a serious condition. In some cases, it can be life threatening. Most of the time, urine output can be restored with prompt medical care.  Contact your provider if:  You notice that you are producing less urine than usual., Your urine looks much darker than usual., You are vomiting, have diarrhea, or have a high fever and cannot get enough fluids by mouth., You have dizziness, lightheadedness, or a fast pulse with decreased urine output. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004142-5" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Urine output - decreased ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>