<Document id="0004025" source="ADAM" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/001659.htm">
 
<Focus>Treacher Collins syndrome</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Disease</Category>
	<UMLS>
		<CUIs>
			<CUI>C0242387</CUI>
		</CUIs>
		<SemanticTypes>
			<SemanticType>T019</SemanticType>
		</SemanticTypes>
		<SemanticGroup>Disorders</SemanticGroup>
	</UMLS>
	<Synonyms>
		<Synonym>Mandibulofacial dysostosis</Synonym>
		<Synonym>Treacher Collins-Franceschetti syndrome</Synonym>
	</Synonyms>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0004025-1" qtype="information">What is (are) Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Treacher Collins syndrome is a genetic condition that leads to problems with the structure of the face. Most cases are not passed down through families.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0004025-2" qtype="causes">What causes Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Changes to one of three genes,  TCOF1 ,  POLR1C , or  POLR1D , can lead to Treacher Collins syndrome. The condition can be passed down through families (inherited). However, most of the time, there is not another affected family member. This condition may vary in severity from generation to generation and from person to person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0004025-3" qtype="symptoms">What are the symptoms of Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Symptoms may include: Outer part of the ears are abnormal or almost completely missing, Hearing loss, Very small jaw ( micrognathia ), Very large mouth, Defect in the lower eyelid, Scalp hair that reaches to the cheeks,  Cleft palate , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0004025-4" qtype="exams and tests">How to diagnose Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>The child most often will show normal intelligence. An exam of the infant may reveal a variety of problems, including: Abnormal eye shape, Flat cheekbones, Cleft palate or lip, Small jaw,  Low-set ears , Abnormally formed ears, Abnormal ear canal,  Hearing loss , Defects in the eye, Decreased eyelashes on the lower eyelid,  Genetic tests can help identify gene changes linked to this condition.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0004025-5" qtype="treatment">What are the treatments for Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hearing loss is treated to ensure better performance in school. Being followed by a plastic surgeon is very important, because children with this condition may need a series of operations to correct birth defects. Plastic surgery can correct the  receding chin  and other changes in face structure.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0004025-6" qtype="support groups">Where to find support for people with Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>More information and support for people with Treacher Collins syndrome and their families can be found at: FACES: The National Craniofacial Association --  www.faces-cranio.org/ , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0004025-7" qtype="outlook">What is the outlook for Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Children with this syndrome typically grow to become functioning adults of normal intelligence.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0004025-8" qtype="complications">What are the complications of Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Complications may include: Feeding difficulty, Speaking difficulty, Communication problems,  Vision problems , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0004025-9" qtype="when to contact a medical professional">Do I need to see a doctor for Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>This condition is most often seen at birth.  Genetic counseling can help families understand the condition and how to care for the person.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0004025-10" qtype="prevention">How to prevent Treacher Collins syndrome ?</Question>
			<Answer>Genetic counseling is recommended if you have a family history of this syndrome and wish to become pregnant.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>