<Document id="0000926" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a610022.html">

<Focus>Oxymorphone</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000926-1" qtype="important warning">What important warning or information should I know about Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oxymorphone may be habit forming, especially with prolonged use. Take oxymorphone exactly as directed. Do not take a larger dose, take it more often, or take it for a longer period of time, or in a different way than prescribed by your doctor. While taking oxymorphone, discuss with your health care provider your pain treatment goals, length of treatment, and other ways to manage your pain. Tell your doctor if you or anyone in your family drinks or has ever drunk large amounts of alcohol, uses or has ever used street drugs, or has overused prescription medications, or has had an overdose, or if you have or have ever had depression or another mental illness. There is a greater risk that you will overuse oxymorphone if you have or have ever had any of these conditions. Talk to your healthcare provider immediately and ask for guidance if you think that you have an opioid addiction or call the U.S. Substance Abuse and Mental Health Services Administration (SAMHSA) National Helpline at 1-800-662-HELP. Oxymorphone may cause serious or life-threatening breathing problems, especially during the first 72 hours of your treatment and any time your dose is increased. Your doctor will monitor you carefully during your treatment. Tell your doctor if you have or have ever had slowed breathing, or asthma. Your doctor will probably tell you not to take oxymorphone tablets. Also tell your doctor if you have or have ever had lung disease such as chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD; a group of lung diseases that includes chronic bronchitis and emphysema), a head injury, brain tumor, any condition that increases the amount of pressure in your brain,  or sleep apnea (condition in which breathing stops or becomes shallow during sleep). The risk that you will develop breathing problems may be higher if you are an older adult or are weak or malnourished due to disease. If you experience any of the following symptoms, call your doctor immediately or get emergency medical treatment: slowed breathing, long pauses between breaths, or shortness of breath. Taking certain medications other medications with oxymorphone may increase the risk that you will develop serious or life-threatening breathing problems, sedation, or coma. Tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are taking or plan to take any of the following medications: benzodiazepines such as alprazolam (Xanax), chlordiazepoxide (Librium), clonazepam (Klonopin), diazepam (Diastat, Valium), estazolam, flurazepam, lorazepam (Ativan), oxazepam, temazepam (Restoril), and triazolam (Halcion);medications for mental illness or nausea; other narcotic pain medications; muscle relaxants; sedatives; sleeping pills; and tranquilizers. Also tell your doctor or pharmacist if you are taking any of the following medications or have stopped taking them within the past 2 weeks: monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitors such as isocarboxazid (Marplan), linezolid (Zyvox), phenelzine (Nardil), rasagiline (Azilect), selegiline (Emsam, Eldepryl, Zelapar), and tranylcypromine (Parnate).Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medication and will monitor you carefully. If you take oxymorphone with any of these medications and you develop any of the following symptoms, call your doctor immediately or seek emergency medical care: unusual dizziness, lightheadedness, extreme sleepiness, slowed or difficult breathing, or unresponsiveness. Be sure that your caregiver or family members know which symptoms may be serious so they can call the doctor or emergency medical care if you are unable to seek treatment on your own. Drinking alcohol, taking prescription or nonprescription medications that contain alcohol, or using street drugs during your treatment with oxycodone increases the risk that you will experience serious, life-threatening side effects. Do not drink alcohol, take prescription or nonprescription medications that contain alcohol, or use street drugs during your treatment. Do not allow anyone else to take your medication. Oxymorphone may harm or cause death to other people who take your medication, especially children. Store oxymorphone in a safe place so that no one else can take it accidentally or on purpose. Be especially careful to keep oxymorphone out of the reach of children. Keep track of how many tablets, or capsules are left so you will know if any medication is missing. Tell your doctor if you are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. If you take oxymorphone regularly during your pregnancy, your baby may experience life-threatening withdrawal symptoms after birth. Tell your baby's doctor right away if your baby experiences any of the following symptoms: irritability, hyperactivity, abnormal sleep, high-pitched cry, uncontrollable shaking of a part of the body, vomiting, diarrhea, or failure to gain weight. Talk to your doctor about the risks of taking oxymorphone. Your doctor or pharmacist will give you the manufacturer's patient information sheet (Medication Guide) when you begin treatment with oxymorphone and each time you fill your prescription. Read the information carefully and ask your doctor or pharmacist if you have any questions. You can also visit the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) website ( http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/DrugSafety/ucm085729.htm ) or the manufacturer's website to obtain the Medication Guide.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000926-2" qtype="indication">Who should get Oxymorphone and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oxymorphone is used to relieve moderate to severe pain in people whose pain is not controlled with other medications. Oxymorphone is in a class of medications called opiate (narcotic) analgesics. It works by changing the way the body responds to pain.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000926-3" qtype="usage">How should Oxymorphone be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oxymorphone comes as a tablet and as an extended-release (long-acting) tablet to take by mouth on an empty stomach, at least 1 hour before or 2 hours after meals. It is usually taken every 4 to 6 hours. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Take oxymorphone exactly as directed. Do not take more or less of it or take it more often than prescribed by your doctor. Swallow the extended-release tablets whole; do not chew or crush them. Your doctor will probably start you on a low dose of oxymorphone and gradually increase your dose until your pain is controlled. Your doctor may adjust your dose at any time during your treatment if your pain is not controlled. If you feel that your pain is not controlled, call your doctor. Do not change the dose of your medication without talking to your doctor. Do not stop taking oxymorphone without talking to your doctor. Your doctor will probably decrease your dose gradually. If you suddenly stop taking oxymorphone, you may experience withdrawal symptoms such as restlessness; watery eyes; runny nose; yawning; sweating; chills; muscle, joint, or back pain; enlarged pupils (black circles in the centers of the eyes); irritability; anxiety; weakness; stomach cramps; difficulty falling asleep or staying asleep; nausea; vomiting; diarrhea; loss of appetite; fast heartbeat; and fast breathing.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000926-5" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking oxymorphone, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to oxymorphone, oxycodone (OxyContin, in Percocet, in Roxicet, others), codeine (in many pain relievers and cough medications), hydrocodone (Zohydro, in Anexsia, in Norco, in Reprexain, in Rezira, in Vicoprofen, in Vituz, others), dihydrocodeine (in Synalgos-DC), hydromorphone (Dilaudid, Exalgo), any other medications, or any of the ingredients in oxymorphone tablets. Ask your pharmacist or check the Medication Guide for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention the medications listed in the IMPORTANT WARNING section and any of the following: antihistamines; buprenorphine (Buprenex, Butrans, Zubsolv, in Suboxone); butorphanol (Stadol); cimetidine (Tagamet), diuretics ('water pills'), ipratropium (Atrovent, in Combivent); medications for irritable bowel disease, motion sickness, Parkinson's disease, or urinary problems; nalbuphine; and pentazocine (Talwin). Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have any of the conditions mentioned in the IMPORTANT WARNING section, liver disease, blockage in your stomach or intestine, or paralytic ileus (condition in which digested food does not move through the intestines). Your doctor may tell you not to take oxymorphone., tell your doctor if you have or have ever  seizures; problems urinating, or kidney, pancreas, thyroid, or gall bladder disease., tell your doctor if you are breastfeeding. If you are breastfeeding while taking oxymorphone, watch your baby closely for any unusual sleepiness, slowed breathing, or limpness., you should know that this medication may decrease fertility in men and women. Talk to your doctor about the risks of taking oxymorphone., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are taking oxymorphone., you should know that oxymorphone may make you drowsy, dizzy, or lightheaded. Do not drive a car or operate machinery until you know how this medication affects you., you should know that oxymorphone may cause dizziness, lightheadedness, and fainting when you get up too quickly from a lying position. To avoid this problem, get out of bed slowly, resting your feet on the floor for a few minutes before standing up., you should know that oxymorphone may cause constipation. Talk to your doctor about changing your diet or using other medications to prevent or treat constipation while you are using oxymorphone., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000926-6" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000926-7" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Take the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not take a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000926-8" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oxymorphone may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 dry mouth, stomach pain or swelling, nausea, vomiting, gas, excessive sweating, flushing, fast heartbeat, red eyes, headache, feeling anxious or confused, itching,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of the following symptoms or those mentioned in the IMPORTANT WARNING section, call your doctor immediately:
 agitation, hallucinations (seeing things or hearing voices that do not exist), fever, sweating, confusion, fast heartbeat, shivering, severe muscle stiffness or twitching, loss of coordination, nausea, vomiting, or diarrhea, nausea, vomiting, loss of appetite, weakness, or dizziness, inability to get or keep an erection, irregular menstruation, decreased sexual desire, changes in heartbeat, seizures, rash, hives, itching, nausea, vomiting, hoarseness, difficulty breathing or swallowing, chest pain. or swelling of the hands, eyes, face, lips, mouth, tongue or throat, extreme drowsiness, fainting,  Oxymorphone may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while taking this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000926-9" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). You must immediately dispose of any medication that is outdated or no longer needed through a medicine take-back program. If you do not have a take-back program nearby or one that you can access promptly, flush any medication that is outdated or no longer needed down the toilet so that others will not take it. Talk to your pharmacist about the proper disposal of your medication. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000926-10" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. While taking oxymorphone, you should talk to your doctor about having a rescue medication called naloxone readily available (e.g., home, office). Naloxone is used to reverse the life-threatening effects of an overdose. It works by blocking the effects of opiates to relieve dangerous symptoms caused by high levels of opiates in the blood. Your doctor may also prescribe you naloxone if you are living in a household where there are small children or someone who has abused street or prescription drugs. You should make sure that you and your family members, caregivers, or the people who spend time with you know how to recognize an overdose, how to use naloxone, and what to do until emergency medical help arrives. Your doctor or pharmacist will show you and your family members how to use the medication. Ask your pharmacist for the instructions or visit the manufacturer's website to get the instructions. If symptoms of an overdose occur, a friend or family member should give the first dose of naloxone, call 911 immediately, and stay with you and watch you closely until emergency medical help arrives. Your symptoms may return within a few minutes after you receive naloxone. If your symptoms return, the person should give you another dose of naloxone. Additional doses may be given every 2 to 3 minutes, if symptoms return before medical help arrives. Symptoms of overdose may include the following:
 difficulty breathing or slow or shallow breathing, bluish-tinged skin, lips, or fingernails, cold, clammy skin, increase or decrease in pupil (dark circle in the eye) size, limp or weak muscles, extreme sleepiness, unusual snoring, slowed heartbeat, unable to respond or wake up, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000926-11" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. This prescription is not refillable. If you are taking oxymorphone to control your pain on a long term basis, be sure to schedule appointments with your doctor regularly so that you do not run out of medication. If you are taking oxymorphone on a short term basis, call your doctor if you continue to have pain after you finish the medication. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000926-12" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Oxymorphone ?</Question>
			<Answer>Opana &#174; , Opana &#174;  ER &#182; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>