<Document id="0000848" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a601243.html">

<Focus>Nedocromil Ophthalmic</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000848-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Nedocromil Ophthalmic and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ophthalmic nedocromil is used to treat itchy eyes caused by allergies. Symptoms of allergies occur when cells in your body called mast cells release substances after you come in contact with something to which you are allergic. Nedocromil is in a class of drugs called mast cell stabilizers. It works by stopping the release of these substances.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000848-2" qtype="usage">How should Nedocromil Ophthalmic be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ophthalmic nedocromil comes as a solution (liquid) to instill in the eyes. It is usually instilled twice daily. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Use nedocromil exactly as directed. Do not use more or less of it or use it more often than prescribed by your doctor. Your allergy symptom (itchy eyes) should improve when you instill the eye drops. If your symptoms do not improve or they worsen, call your doctor. Continue to use nedocromil even if your eyes feel better. Continue to use it until you are no longer exposed to the substance that causes your symptoms, allergy season is over, or your doctor tells you to stop using it. To instill the eye drops, follow these steps:
 Wash your hands thoroughly with soap and water., Check the dropper tip to make sure that it is not chipped or cracked., Avoid touching the dropper tip against your eye or anything else; eye drops and droppers must be kept clean., While tilting your head back, pull down the lower lid of your eye with your index finger to form a pocket., Hold the dropper (tip down) with the other hand, as close to the eye as possible without touching it., Brace the remaining fingers of that hand against your face., While looking up, gently squeeze the dropper so that a single drop falls into the pocket made by the lower eyelid. Remove your index finger from the lower eyelid., Blink you eye a few times to help spread the solution over your entire eye., Close your eye for 2 to 3 minutes and tip your head down as though looking at the floor., Place a finger on the tear duct and apply gentle pressure., Wipe any excess liquid from your face with a tissue., If you are to use more than one drop in the same eye, wait at least 5 minutes before instilling the next drop., Replace and tighten the cap on the dropper bottle. Do not wipe or rinse the dropper tip., Wash your hands to remove any medication., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000848-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Nedocromil Ophthalmic ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before using nedocromil eye drops, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to nedocromil or any other medications., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications you are taking, including vitamins or herbal products., tell you doctor if you wear contact lenses; you should not wear contact lenses while your eyes are itchy and red due to allergies., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000848-5" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Nedocromil Ophthalmic ?</Question>
			<Answer>Instill the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not instill a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000848-6" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Nedocromil Ophthalmic ?</Question>
			<Answer>Nedocromil may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 stinging or burning of the eyes, blurred vision, increased eye redness or itching, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000848-7" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Nedocromil Ophthalmic ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000848-8" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Nedocromil Ophthalmic ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Do not let anyone else use your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000848-9" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Nedocromil Ophthalmic ?</Question>
			<Answer>Alocril &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>