<Document id="0000544" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a689014.html">

<Focus>Ganciclovir Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000544-1" qtype="important warning">What important warning or information should I know about Ganciclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>The manufacturer warns that ganciclovir injection should only be used for treatment and prevention of cytomegalovirus (CMV) in people with certain diseases because the medication may cause severe side effects and there is currently not enough information to support safety and effectiveness in other groups of people.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000544-2" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Ganciclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your doctor may order eye exams while you are taking this medication. Keep all appointments with your doctor, eye doctor, and the laboratory. Your doctor will order certain lab tests to check your body's response to ganciclovir injection. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000544-3" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Ganciclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before using ganciclovir injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to ganciclovir, acyclovir (Sitavig, Zovirax), any other medications, or any of the ingredients in ganciclovir injection. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention any of the following: doxorubicin (Adriamycin), amphotericin B (Abelcet, AmBisome), cyclosporine (Gengraf, Neoral, Sandimmune), dapsone, flucytosine (Ancobon), imipenem&#8211;cilastatin (Primaxin); medications to treat human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) including didanosine (Videx) or zidovudine (Retrovir, in Combivir, in Trizivir); pentamidine (Nebupent); probenecid (Benemid; in Colbenemid) trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole (Bactrim, Septra), vinblastine, or vincristine (Marqibo Kit). Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had a low number of red or white blood cells or platelets or other blood or bleeding problems, eye problems other than CMV retinitis, or kidney disease., tell your doctor if you are pregnant or plan to become pregnant. Ganciclovir injection may cause infertility (difficulty becoming pregnant). However, if you are a female and can become pregnant, you should use effective birth control while receiving ganciclovir injection. If you are a male and your partner can become pregnant, you should use a condom while receiving this medication and for 90 days after your treatment. If you become pregnant while receiving ganciclovir injection, call your doctor immediately., tell your doctor if you are breastfeeding. You should not breastfeed while receiving ganciclovir injection. Talk to your doctor about when you may safely begin breastfeeding after you stop receiving ganciclovir injection., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are receiving ganciclovir injection., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000544-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Ganciclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ganciclovir injection may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 diarrhea, loss of appetite, vomiting, tiredness, sweating, itching, redness, pain, or swelling at the injection site,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, call your doctor immediately:
 unusual tiredness or weakness, pale skin, fast or irregular heartbeat, shortness of breath, numbness, pain, burning, or tingling in the hands or feet, vision changes, decreased urination,  Ganciclovir injection may increase the risk that you will develop other cancers. Talk to your doctor about the risks of receiving this medication. Ganciclovir injection may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while receiving this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000544-6" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Ganciclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000544-7" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Ganciclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000544-9" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Ganciclovir Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cytovene &#174;  I.V. &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>