<Document id="0000112" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a687010.html">

<Focus>Aztreonam Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000112-1" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Aztreonam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory. Your doctor may order certain lab tests to check your body's response to aztreonam injection. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000112-2" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Aztreonam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before using aztreonam injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to aztreonam, cephalosporins such as cefaclor (Ceclor), cefadroxil (Duricef), or cephalexin (Keflex), beta-lactam antibiotics such as penicillin or amoxicillin (Amoxil, Trimox, Wymox), carbapenem antibiotics such as doripenem (Doribax), ertapenem (Invanz), or meropenem (Merrem), any other medications, or any of the ingredients in aztreonam injection. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had liver or kidney disease., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breastfeeding. If you become pregnant while using aztreonam injection, call your doctor., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000112-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Aztreonam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Aztreonam injection may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 nausea, vomiting, diarrhea, stomach pain, redness, irritation, or swelling at the injection site,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, call your doctor immediately or get emergency medical treatment:
 severe diarrhea (watery or bloody stools) that may occur with or without fever and stomach cramps (may occur up to 2 months or more after your treatment), hives, itching, rash, difficulty breathing or swallowing, blisters on the skin, mouth, nose, and eyes,  Aztreonam injection may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while taking this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000112-5" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Aztreonam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000112-6" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Aztreonam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000112-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Aztreonam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Azactam &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>