<Document id="0000743" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a682287.html">

<Focus>Meclofenamate</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000743-1" qtype="important warning">What important warning or information should I know about Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>People who take nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) (other than aspirin) such as meclofenamate may have a higher risk of having a heart attack or a stroke than people who do not take these medications. These events may happen without warning and may cause death. This risk may be higher for people who take NSAIDs for a long time. Tell your doctor if you or anyone in your family has or has ever had heart disease, a heart attack, or a stroke, if you smoke, and if you have or have ever had high cholesterol, high blood pressure, or diabetes. Get emergency medical help right away if you experience any of the following symptoms: chest pain, shortness of breath, weakness in one part or side of the body, or slurred speech. If you will be undergoing a coronary artery bypass graft (CABG; a type of heart surgery), you should not take meclofenamate right before or right after the surgery. NSAIDs such as meclofenamate may cause ulcers, bleeding, or holes in the stomach or intestine. These problems may develop at any time during treatment, may happen without warning symptoms, and may cause death. The risk may be higher for people who take NSAIDs for a long time, are older in age, have poor health, or drink large amounts of alcohol while taking meclofenamate. Tell your doctor if you take any of the following medications: anticoagulants ('blood thinners') such as warfarin (Coumadin); aspirin; other NSAIDs such as ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin) and naproxen (Aleve, Naprosyn); or oral steroids such as dexamethasone (Decadron, Dexone), methylprednisolone (Medrol), and prednisone (Deltasone). Also tell your doctor if you have or have ever had ulcers, bleeding in your stomach or intestines, or other bleeding disorders. If you experience any of the following symptoms, stop taking meclofenamate and call your doctor: stomach pain, heartburn, vomit that is bloody or looks like coffee grounds, blood in the stool, or black and tarry stools. Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory. Your doctor will monitor your symptoms carefully and will probably order certain tests to check your body's response to meclofenamate. Be sure to tell your doctor how you are feeling so that your doctor can prescribe the right amount of medication to treat your condition with the lowest risk of serious side effects. Your doctor or pharmacist will give you the manufacturer's patient information sheet (Medication Guide) when you begin treatment with meclofenamate and each time you refill your prescription. Read the information carefully and ask your doctor or pharmacist if you have any questions. You can also visit the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) website ( http://www.fda.gov/Drugs ) to obtain the Medication Guide.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000743-2" qtype="indication">Who should get Meclofenamate and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meclofenamate is used to relieve pain, tenderness, swelling, and stiffness caused by osteoarthritis (arthritis caused by a breakdown of the lining of the joints) and rheumatoid arthritis (arthritis caused by swelling of the lining of the joints). It is also used to relieve other types of mild to moderate pain, including menstrual pain (pain that happens before or during a menstrual period). It also may be used to decrease bleeding in women who have abnormally heavy menstrual blood loss. Meclofenamate is in a class of medications called NSAIDs. It works by stopping the body's production of a substance that causes pain, fever, and inflammation.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000743-3" qtype="usage">How should Meclofenamate be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meclofenamate comes as a capsule to take by mouth. It is usually taken three or four times a day for arthritis, three times a day for heavy menstrual blood loss, or every 4 to 6 hours as needed for pain. Meclofenamate may be taken with food or milk to prevent nausea. If you take meclofenamate regularly, take it at the same times every day. Follow the directions on your prescription label carefully, and ask your doctor or pharmacist to explain any part you do not understand. Take meclofenamate exactly as directed. Do not take more or less of it or take it more often than prescribed by your doctor. If you are taking meclofenamate to reduce heavy menstrual bleeding, your bleeding should decrease during your treatment. Call your doctor if your bleeding does not decrease or if you experience spotting or bleeding between menstrual periods. If you are taking meclofenamate to relieve the symptoms of arthritis, your symptoms may begin to improve within a few days. It may take 2 to 3 weeks or longer for you to feel the full benefit of meclofenamate.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000743-5" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking meclofenamate, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to meclofenamate, aspirin, or other NSAIDs such as ibuprofen (Advil, Motrin) and naproxen (Aleve, Naprosyn), any other medications, or any of the inactive ingredients in meclofenamate capsules. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the inactive ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention the medications listed in the IMPORTANT WARNING section and any of the following: angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors such as benazepril (Lotensin), captopril (Capoten), enalapril (Vasotec), fosinopril (Monopril), lisinopril (Prinivil, Zestril), moexipril (Univasc), perindopril (Aceon), quinapril (Accupril), ramipril (Altace), and trandolapril (Mavik); diuretics ('water pills'); lithium (Eskalith, Lithobid); and methotrexate (Rheumatrex). Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had any of the conditions mentioned in the IMPORTANT WARNING section or asthma, especially if you also have frequent stuffed or runny nose or nasal polyps (swelling of the lining of the nose); swelling of the hands, feet, ankles, or lower legs; or liver or kidney disease., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, especially if you are in the last few months of your pregnancy, you plan to become pregnant, or you are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while taking meclofenamate, call your doctor., talk to your doctor about the risks and benefits of taking meclofenamate if you are 75 years of age or older. Do not take this medication for a longer period of time or at a higher dose than recommended by your doctor., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are taking meclofenamate., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000743-6" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000743-7" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Take the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not take a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000743-8" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meclofenamate may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 diarrhea, constipation, gas, sores in the mouth, headache, ringing in the ears,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of the following symptoms, or those mentioned in the IMPORTANT WARNING section, call your doctor immediately. Do not take any more meclofenamate until you speak to your doctor.
 blurred vision, unexplained weight gain, fever, blisters, rash, itching, hives, swelling of the eyes, face, lips, tongue, throat, arms, hands, feet, ankles, or lower legs, hoarseness, difficulty breathing or swallowing, yellowing of the skin or eyes, excessive tiredness, unusual bleeding or bruising, lack of energy, nausea, loss of appetite, pain in the upper right part of the stomach, flu-like symptoms, pale skin, fast heartbeat, cloudy, discolored, or bloody urine, back pain, difficult or painful urination,  Meclofenamate may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while taking this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000743-9" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep this medication in the container it came in, tightly closed, and out of reach of children. Store it at room temperature and away from excess heat and moisture (not in the bathroom). It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000743-10" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. Symptoms of overdoses may include:
 behavior that does not make sense, agitation, seizures, decreased urination, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000743-11" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Do not let anyone else take your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="12">
			<Question qid="0000743-12" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Meclofenamate ?</Question>
			<Answer>Meclodium &#174; &#182; , Meclomen &#174; &#182; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>