<Document id="0000069" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a601132.html">

<Focus>Amphotericin B Lipid Complex Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000069-1" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Amphotericin B Lipid Complex Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory. Your doctor will order certain lab tests during your treatment to check your body's response to amphotericin B lipid complex injection. Do not let anyone else use your medication. Ask your pharmacist any questions you have about refilling your prescription. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000069-2" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Amphotericin B Lipid Complex Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before receiving amphotericin B lipid complex injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to amphotericin B, any other medications, or any of the ingredients in amphotericin B lipid complex injection. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take while receiving amphotericin B lipid complex injection. Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects.  , The following nonprescription products may interact with amphotericin B lipid complex: antifungals [clotrimazole, ketoconazole (Nizoral), miconazole (Monistat)]. Be sure to let your doctor and pharmacist know that you are taking these medications before you start receiving amphotericin B lipid complex. Do not start any of these medications while receiving amphotericin B lipid complex without discussing with your healthcare provider., tell your doctor if you are receiving leukocyte (white blood cell) transfusions., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had kidney disease., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while receiving amphotericin B lipid complex injection, call your doctor. Do not breast-feed while receiving amphotericin B complex lipid injection., if you are having surgery, including dental surgery, tell the doctor or dentist that you are receiving amphotericin B lipid complex injection., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000069-4" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Amphotericin B Lipid Complex Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Amphotericin B lipid complex injection may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 stomach pain or cramping, heartburn, diarrhea, weight loss, loss of appetite, muscle or joint pain, injection site redness or swelling, pale skin, shortness of breath, dizziness, headache, coldness in the hands and feet,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, call your doctor immediately or get emergency medical treatment:
 rash, skin blisters, wheezing, difficulty breathing, itching, swelling of the face, throat, tongue, lips, eyes, bloody vomit, black and tarry stools, blood in stool, yellowing of the skin or eyes, decreased urination,  Amphotericin B lipid complex injection may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while receiving this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000069-5" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Amphotericin B Lipid Complex Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000069-6" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Amphotericin B Lipid Complex Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000069-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Amphotericin B Lipid Complex Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Abelcet &#174; , Amphotec &#174; &#182; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>