<Document id="0000224" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a684044.html">

<Focus>Cefuroxime Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000224-1" qtype="indication">Who should get Cefuroxime Injection and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cefuroxime injection is used to treat certain infections caused by bacteria including pneumonia and other lower respiratory tract (lung) infections; meningitis (infection of the membranes that surround the brain and spinal cord); gonorrhea (a sexually transmitted disease); and skin, blood, bone, joint, and urinary tract infections. Cefuroxime injection may also be used before, during, and sometimes for a brief period after surgery in order to prevent the patient from getting an infection. Cefuroxime injection is in a class of medications called cephalosporin antibiotics. It works by killing bacteria. Antibiotics such as cefuroxime injection will not work for colds, flu, or other viral infections. Using antibiotics when they are not needed increases your risk of getting an infection later that resists antibiotic treatment.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000224-2" qtype="usage">How should Cefuroxime Injection be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cefuroxime injection comes as a powder to be mixed with liquid to be injected intravenously (into a vein) or intramuscularly (into a muscle). Cefuroxime injection is also available as a premixed product to be injected intravenously. It is usually given every six or eight hours for five to ten days. You may receive cefuroxime injection in a hospital or you may administer the medication at home. If you will be receiving cefuroxime injection at home, your healthcare provider will show you how to use the medication. Be sure that you understand these directions, and ask your healthcare provider if you have any questions. You should begin to feel better during the first few days of treatment with cefuroxime injection. If your symptoms do not improve or get worse, call your doctor. Use cefuroxime injection until you finish the prescription, even if you feel better. If you stop using cefuroxime injection too soon or skip doses, your infection may not be completely treated and the bacteria may become resistant to antibiotics.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000224-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Cefuroxime Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before taking cefuroxime injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to cefuroxime; other cephalosporin antibiotics such as cefaclor, cefadroxil,cefazolin (Ancef, Kefzol), cefdinir, cefditoren (Spectracef), cefepime (Maxipime), cefixime (Suprax), cefotaxime (Claforan), cefotetan, cefoxitin (Mefoxin), cefpodoxime, cefprozil, ceftaroline (Teflaro), ceftazidime (Fortaz, Tazicef, in Avycaz), ceftibuten (Cedax), ceftriaxone (Rocephin), and cephalexin (Keflex); penicillin antibiotics; or any other medications. Also tell your doctor if you are allergic to any of the ingredients in cefuroxime injection. Ask your pharmacist for a list of the ingredients., tell your doctor and pharmacist what prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention any of the following: amikacin, anticoagulants ('blood thinners') such as warfarin (Coumadin, Jantoven), chloramphenicol, gentamicin, kanamycin, neomycin (Neo-Fradin), probenecid (Probalan), streptomycin, and tobramycin . Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects., tell your doctor if you have or have ever had any kind of allergies, gastrointestinal disease (GI; affecting the stomach or intestines), especially ulcerative colitis (condition that causes swelling in the lining of the colon [large intestine]), or kidney or liver disease., you should know that cefuroxime injection also decreases the effectiveness of some oral contraceptives ('birth control pills). You will need to use another form of birth control while taking this medication. Talk to your doctor about other ways to prevent pregnancy while you are taking this medication., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breast-feeding. If you become pregnant while taking cefuroxime injection, call your doctor., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000224-5" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Cefuroxime Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000224-6" qtype="forget a dose">What should I do if I forget a dose of Cefuroxime Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Use the missed dose as soon as you remember it. However, if it is almost time for the next dose, skip the missed dose and continue your regular dosing schedule. Do not use a double dose to make up for a missed one.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000224-7" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Cefuroxime Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cefuroxime injection may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 vaginal itching, diarrhea, pain, redness, swelling, or bleeding near the place where cefuroxime was injected,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms, stop taking cefuroxime injection and call your doctor immediately or get emergency medical treatment:
 watery or bloody stools, stomach cramps, or fever during treatment or for up to two or more months after stopping treatment, seizures, rash, hives, swelling of the face, throat, tongue, lips, and eyes, difficulty swallowing or breathing, hoarseness, decreased urination, swelling in legs and feet, peeling, blistering, or shedding skin, a return of fever, sore throat, chills, or other signs of infection, hearing loss, if you are being treated for meningitis,  Cefuroxime injection may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while taking this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000224-8" qtype="storage and disposal">What should I know about storage and disposal of Cefuroxime Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Your healthcare provider will tell you how to store your medication. Store your medication only as directed. Make sure you understand how to store your medication properly. Unneeded medications should be disposed of in special ways to ensure that pets, children, and other people cannot consume them.  However, you should not flush this medication down the toilet. Instead, the best way to dispose of your medication is through a medicine take-back program. Talk to your pharmacist or contact your local garbage/recycling department to learn about take-back programs in your community.  See the FDA's Safe Disposal of Medicines website ( http://goo.gl/c4Rm4p ) for more information if you do not have access to a take-back program. It is important to keep all medication out of sight and reach of children as many containers (such as weekly pill minders and those for eye drops, creams, patches, and inhalers) are not child-resistant and young children can open them easily. To protect young children from poisoning, always lock safety caps and immediately place the medication in a safe location &#8211; one that is up and away and out of their sight and reach.  http://www.upandaway.org</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000224-9" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Cefuroxime Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. Symptoms of overdose may include:
 seizures, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000224-10" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Cefuroxime Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor and the laboratory. Your doctor may order certain lab tests to check your body's response to cefuroxime injection. Before having any laboratory test, tell your doctor and the laboratory personnel that you are taking cefuroxime injection. If you are diabetic and test your urine for sugar, use Clinistix or TesTape (not Clinitest) to test your urine while taking this medication. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="11">
			<Question qid="0000224-11" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Cefuroxime Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Kefurox &#174; &#182; , Zinacef &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>