<Document id="0000798" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a609014.html">

<Focus>Midazolam Injection</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000798-1" qtype="important warning">What important warning or information should I know about Midazolam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Midazolam injection may cause serious or life-threatening breathing problems such as shallow, slowed, or temporarily stopped breathing that may lead to permanent brain injury or death. You should only receive this medication in a hospital or doctor's office that has the equipment that is needed to monitor your heart and lungs and to provide life-saving medical treatment quickly if your breathing slows or stops. Your doctor or nurse will watch you closely after you receive this medication to make sure that you are breathing properly. Tell your doctor if you have a severe infection or if you have or have ever had any lung, airway, or breathing problems or heart disease. Tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are taking any of the following medications: antidepressants; barbiturates such as secobarbital (Seconal); droperidol (Inapsine); medications for anxiety, mental illness, or seizures; opiate medications for cough such as codeine (in Triacin-C, in Tuzistra XR) or hydrocodone (in Anexsia, in Norco, in Zyfrel) or for pain such as codeine, fentanyl (Actiq, Duragesic, Subsys, others), hydromorphone (Dilaudid, Exalgo), meperidine (Demerol), methadone (Dolophine, Methadose), morphine (Astramorph, Duramorph PF, Kadian), oxycodone (in Oxycet, in Percocet, in Roxicet, others), and tramadol (Conzip, Ultram, in Ultracet); sedatives; sleeping pills; or tranquilizers.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000798-2" qtype="indication">Who should get Midazolam Injection and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Midazolam injection is used before medical procedures and surgery to cause drowsiness, relieve anxiety, and prevent any memory of the event. It is also sometimes given as part of the anesthesia during surgery to produce a loss of consciousness. Midazolam injection is also used to cause a state of decreased consciousness in seriously ill people in intensive care units (ICU) who are breathing with the help of a machine. Midazolam injection is in a class of medications called benzodiazepines. It works by slowing activity in the brain to allow relaxation and decreased consciousness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000798-3" qtype="usage">How should Midazolam Injection be used and what is the dosage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Midazolam injection comes as a solution (liquid) to be injected into a muscle or vein by a doctor or nurse in a hospital or clinic. If you receive midazolam injection in the ICU over a long period of time, your body may become dependent on it. Your doctor will probably decrease your dose gradually to prevent withdrawal symptoms such as seizures, uncontrollable shaking of a part of the body, hallucinations (seeing things or hearing voices that do not exist), stomach and muscle cramps, nausea, vomiting, sweating, fast heartbeat, difficulty falling asleep or staying asleep, and depression.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000798-5" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Midazolam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Before receiving midazolam injection, tell your doctor and pharmacist if you are allergic to midazolam or any other medications., tell your doctor if you are taking certain medications for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) including amprenavir (Agenerase), atazanavir (Reyataz), darunavir (Prezista), delavirdine (Rescriptor), efavirenz (Sustiva, in Atripla), fosamprenavir (Lexiva), indinavir (Crixivan),lopinavir (in Kaletra), nelfinavir (Viracept), ritonavir (Norvir, in Kaletra), saquinavir (Invirase), and tipranavir (Aptivus). Your doctor may decide not to give you midazolam injection if you are taking one or more of these medications., tell your doctor and pharmacist what other prescription and nonprescription medications, vitamins, nutritional supplements, and herbal products you are taking or plan to take. Be sure to mention the medications listed in the IMPORTANT WARNING section and any of the following: aminophylline (Truphylline); certain antifungals such as itraconazole (Sporanox) and ketoconazole (Nizoral); certain calcium channel blockers such as diltiazem (Cartia, Cardizem, Tiazac, others) and verapamil (Calan, Isoptin, Verelan, others); cimetidine (Tagamet); dalfopristin-quinupristin (Synercid); and erythromycin (E-mycin, E.E.S.). Your doctor may need to change the doses of your medications or monitor you carefully for side effects. Many other medications may also interact with midazolam, so be sure to tell your doctor about all the medications you are taking, even those that do not appear on this list., tell your doctor if you have glaucoma (increased pressure in the eyes that may cause gradual loss of vision). Your doctor may decide not to give you midazolam injection., tell your doctor if you have recently stopped drinking large amounts of alcohol or if you have or have ever had kidney or liver disease., tell your doctor if you are pregnant, plan to become pregnant, or are breastfeeding., talk to your doctor about the risks and benefits of receiving midazolam injection if you are 65 years of age or older. Older adults should usually receive lower doses of midazolam injection because higher doses are more likely to cause serious side effects., you should know that midazolam may make you very drowsy and may affect your memory, thinking, and movements. Do not drive a car or do other activities that require you to be fully alert for at least 24 hours after receiving midazolam and until the effects of the medication have worn off. If your child is receiving midazolam injection, watch him or her carefully to be sure that he or she does not fall while walking during this time., you should know that alcohol can make the side effects from midazolam injection worse., you should know that some studies in young children have raised concerns that repeated or lengthy use (&gt;3 hours) of general anesthetic or sedation drugs such as midazolam in infants and children younger than 3 years of age or in women in the last few months of their pregnancy may affect the child's brain development. Other studies in infants and toddlers show that a single, short exposure to anesthetic and sedation drugs is unlikely to have negative effects on behavior or learning. However, further research is needed to fully understand the effects of exposure to anesthesia on brain development in young children. Parents and caregivers of children younger than 3 years of age and pregnant women should talk to their doctors about the risks of anesthesia on brain development and appropriate timing of procedures that require general anesthetic or sedation medications., </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000798-6" qtype="dietary">What special dietary instructions should I follow with Midazolam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Unless your doctor tells you otherwise, continue your normal diet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000798-7" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Midazolam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Midazolam injection may cause side effects. Tell your doctor if any of these symptoms are severe or do not go away:
 headache, drowsiness, nausea, vomiting, hiccups, coughing, pain, redness, or hardening of the skin at the injection site,  Some side effects can be serious. If you experience any of these symptoms or those listed in the IMPORTANT WARNING section, call your doctor immediately:
 agitation, restlessness, uncontrollable shaking of a part of the body, stiffening and jerking of the arms and legs, aggression, seizures, uncontrollable rapid eye movements, hives, rash, itching, difficulty breathing or swallowing,  Midazolam injection may cause other side effects. Call your doctor if you have any unusual problems while receiving this medication. If you experience a serious side effect, you or your doctor may send a report to the Food and Drug Administration's (FDA) MedWatch Adverse Event Reporting program online ( http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch ) or by phone (1-800-332-1088).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000798-8" qtype="emergency or overdose">What to do in case of emergency or overdose of Midazolam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>In case of overdose, call the poison control helpline at 1-800-222-1222. Information is also available online at  https://www.poisonhelp.org/help . If the victim has collapsed, had a seizure, has trouble breathing, or can't be awakened, immediately call emergency services at 911. Symptoms of overdose may include the following:
 drowsiness, confusion, problems with balance and movement, slowed reflexes, slowed breathing and heartbeat, coma (loss of consciousness for a period of time), </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="9">
			<Question qid="0000798-9" qtype="other information">What other information should I know about Midazolam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep all appointments with your doctor. Ask your doctor or pharmacist if you have any questions about midazolam injection. It is important for you to keep a written list of all of the prescription and nonprescription (over-the-counter) medicines you are taking, as well as any products such as vitamins, minerals, or other dietary supplements. You should bring this list with you each time you visit a doctor or if you are admitted to a hospital. It is also important information to carry with you in case of emergencies.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="10">
			<Question qid="0000798-10" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Midazolam Injection ?</Question>
			<Answer>Versed &#174;  Injection, </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>