<Document id="0001298" source="MPlusDrugs" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/meds/a607030.html">

<Focus>Yellow Fever Vaccine</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0001298-1" qtype="information">What is Yellow Fever Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Yellow fever is a serious disease caused by the yellow fever virus. It is found in certain parts of Africa and South America. Yellow fever is spread through the bite of an infected mosquito. It cannot be spread person to person by direct contact. People with yellow fever disease usually have to be hospitalized. Yellow fever can cause:
 fever and flu-like symptoms, jaundice (yellow skin or eyes), bleeding from multiple body sites, liver, kidney, respiratory and other organ failure, death (20 to 50% of serious cases),  Yellow fever vaccine is a live, weakened virus. It is given as a single shot. For people who remain at risk, a booster dose is recommended every 10 years. Yellow fever vaccine may be given at the same time as most other vaccines.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0001298-3" qtype="indication">Who should get Yellow Fever Vaccine and why is it prescribed ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anyone with a severe (life-threatening) allergy to any component of the vaccine, including eggs, chicken proteins, or gelatin, or who has had a severe allergic reaction to a previous dose of yellow fever vaccine should not get yellow fever vaccine.  Tell your doctor if you have any severe allergies. , Infants younger than 6 months of age should not get the vaccine., Tell your doctor if: you have HIV/AIDS or another disease that affects the immune system; your immune system is weakened as a result of cancer or other medical conditions, a transplant, or radiation or drug treatment (such as steroids, cancer chemotherapy, or other drugs that affect immune cell function); or your thymus has been removed or you have a thymus disorder, such as myasthenia gravis, DiGeorge syndrome, or thymoma. Your doctor will help you decide whether you can receive the vaccine., Adults 60 years of age and older who cannot avoid travel to a yellow fever area should discuss vaccination with their doctor. They might be at increased risk for severe problems following vaccination., Infants 6 through 8 months of age, pregnant women, and nursing mothers should avoid or postpone travel to an area where there is risk of yellow fever. If travel cannot be avoided, discuss vaccination with your doctor.,  If you cannot get the vaccine for medical reasons, but require proof of yellow fever vaccination for travel, your doctor can give you a waiver letter if he considers the risk acceptably low. If you plan to use a waiver, you should also contact the embassy of the countries you plan to visit for more information.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0001298-4" qtype="contraindication">Who should not get Yellow Fever Vaccine and what are its contraindications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Anyone with a severe (life-threatening) allergy to any component of the vaccine, including eggs, chicken proteins, or gelatin, or who has had a severe allergic reaction to a previous dose of yellow fever vaccine should not get yellow fever vaccine.  Tell your doctor if you have any severe allergies. , Infants younger than 6 months of age should not get the vaccine., Tell your doctor if: you have HIV/AIDS or another disease that affects the immune system; your immune system is weakened as a result of cancer or other medical conditions, a transplant, or radiation or drug treatment (such as steroids, cancer chemotherapy, or other drugs that affect immune cell function); or your thymus has been removed or you have a thymus disorder, such as myasthenia gravis, DiGeorge syndrome, or thymoma. Your doctor will help you decide whether you can receive the vaccine., Adults 60 years of age and older who cannot avoid travel to a yellow fever area should discuss vaccination with their doctor. They might be at increased risk for severe problems following vaccination., Infants 6 through 8 months of age, pregnant women, and nursing mothers should avoid or postpone travel to an area where there is risk of yellow fever. If travel cannot be avoided, discuss vaccination with your doctor.,  If you cannot get the vaccine for medical reasons, but require proof of yellow fever vaccination for travel, your doctor can give you a waiver letter if he considers the risk acceptably low. If you plan to use a waiver, you should also contact the embassy of the countries you plan to visit for more information.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0001298-5" qtype="side effects">What are the side effects or risks of Yellow Fever Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>A vaccine, like any medicine, could cause a serious reaction. But the risk of a vaccine causing serious harm, or death, is extremely low. Mild Problems Yellow fever vaccine has been associated with fever, and with aches, soreness, redness or swelling where the shot was given. These problems occur in up to 1 person out of 4. They usually begin soon after the shot, and can last up to a week. Severe Problems Severe allergic reaction to a vaccine component (about 1 person in 55,000)., Severe nervous system reaction (about 1 person in 125,000)., Life-threatening severe illness with organ failure (about 1 person in 250,000). More than half the people who suffer this side effect die.,  These last two problems have never been reported after a booster dose.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0001298-6" qtype="severe reaction">What to do in case of a severe reaction to Yellow Fever Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>What should I look for? Look for any unusual condition, such as a high fever, behavior changes, or flu-like symptoms that occur 1 to 30 days after vaccination. Signs of an allergic reaction can include difficulty breathing, hoarseness or wheezing, hives, paleness, weakness, a fast heartbeat, or dizziness within a few minutes to a few hours after the shot. What should I do? Call  a doctor, or get the person to a doctor right away.,  Tell  the doctor what happened, the date and time it happened, and when the vaccination was given.,  Ask  your doctor to report the reaction by fi ling a Vaccine Adverse Event Reporting System (VAERS) form. Or you can file this report through the VAERS website at  http://www.vaers.hhs.gov , or by calling  1-800-822-7967 .  VAERS does not provide medical advice. , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0001298-7" qtype="how can i learn more">How can I learn more about Yellow Fever Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ask your doctor. He or she can give you the vaccine package insert or suggest other sources of information., Call your local or state health department., Contact the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) by calling  1-800-232-4636  (1-800-CDC-INFO), or by visiting CDC websites at  http://www.cdc.gov/travel ,  http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dvbid/yellowfever , or  http://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/vpd-vac/yf ,  Yellow Fever Vaccine Information Statement. U.S. Department of Health and Human Services/Centers for Disease Control and Prevention National Immunization Program. 3/30/2011.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0001298-8" qtype="brand names">What are the brand names of Yellow Fever Vaccine ?</Question>
			<Answer>YF-VAX &#174; , </Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>