<Document id="0000014" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/97.html">

<Focus>Black psyllium</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000014-1" qtype="information">What is Black psyllium ?</Question>
			<Answer>Black psyllium comes from the seed husks of the Plantago arenaria plant. It contains high amounts of soluble dietary fiber.  

Black psyllium adds bulk to the stool which might help with constipation, diarrhea, and irritable bowel syndrome (IBS). It also controls how quickly sugars are absorbed from the gut, which might help control blood sugar levels in people with diabetes.  

People commonly use black psyllium for treating and preventing constipation. It is also used for diarrhea, obesity, diabetes, high blood pressure, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses. 

Don't confuse black psyllium with blond psyllium. These are not the same. 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000014-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Black psyllium ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  BLACK PSYLLIUM  are as follows: Effective for... Constipation . Consuming soluble dietary fiber by mouth, including black psyllium, is effective for short-term constipation. It's found in over-the-counter (OTC) products for this use.,  Likely effective for... 
 Heart disease . Consuming foods high in soluble fiber, including black psyllium, as part of a low-fat, low-cholesterol diet, might help prevent heart disease. At least 7 grams of psyllium husk must be consumed daily., 
 

There is interest in using black psyllium for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000014-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Black psyllium and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000014-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Black psyllium ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000014-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Black psyllium and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Carbamazepine (Tegretol) Black psyllium contains large amounts of fiber. Fiber can decrease how much carbamazepine the body absorbs. This might decrease the effects of carbamazepine. Lithium Black psyllium contains large amounts of fiber. Fiber can decrease how much lithium the body absorbs. This might decrease the effects of lithium. To avoid this interaction, take black psyllium at least 1 hour after lithium. Metformin (Glucophage) Black psyllium contains large amounts of fiber. The fiber in psyllium might increase how much metformin the body absorbs. This might increase the effects of metformin. To avoid this interaction, take black psyllium 30-60 minutes after medications you take by mouth. Olanzapine (Zyprexa) Black psyllium contains large amounts of fiber. Fiber can decrease how much olanzapine the body absorbs. This might decrease the effects of olanzapine. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Digoxin (Lanoxin) Black psyllium is high in fiber. Fiber can decrease how much digoxin the body absorbs. This might decrease the effects of digoxin. Ethinyl estradiol Ethinyl estradiol is a form of estrogen. Psyllium can decrease how much ethinyl estradiol the body absorbs. But it is unlikely that this will reduce the effects of ethinyl estradiol. Medications taken by mouth (Oral drugs) Black psyllium contains large amounts of fiber. Fiber can decrease, increase, or have no effect on how much medicine the body absorbs. Taking black psyllium along with medicine you take by mouth can impact the effects of your medicine. To prevent this interaction, take black psyllium 30-60 minutes after medications you take by mouth.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000014-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Black psyllium and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Iron Taking black psyllium with iron supplements can reduce the amount of iron that the body absorbs. To avoid this interaction, take iron supplements one hour before or four hours after black psyllium. Riboflavin Psyllium seems to slightly reduce the amount of riboflavin that the body absorbs. But this probably isn't a big concern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000014-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Black psyllium and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Taking psyllium can make it difficult to digest fat from the diet. This can increase the amount of fat lost in the stool. Taking psyllium with meals over a long period of time might also affect nutrient absorption. In some cases, it might be necessary to take vitamin or mineral supplements.  </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000014-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Black psyllium ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>