<Document id="0000057" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/326.html">

<Focus>L-tryptophan</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000057-1" qtype="information">What is L-tryptophan ?</Question>
			<Answer>L-Tryptophan is an essential amino acid that is necessary for making proteins. It is naturally found in red meat, poultry, eggs, and dairy.  

L-tryptophan is important for many organs in the body. L-tryptophan is not made by the body and must be consumed from the diet. After absorbing L-tryptophan from food, the body converts some of it to 5-HTP and then to serotonin. Serotonin is a hormone that transmits signals between nerve cells. Changes in serotonin levels in the brain can affect mood. 

People use L-tryptophan for severe PMS symptoms, depression, insomnia, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support any of these uses.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000057-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is L-tryptophan ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  L-TRYPTOPHAN  are as follows: Possibly ineffective for... 

 Depression . Taking L-tryptophan by mouth doesn't seem to be beneficial in patients with depression. Also, it may increase the risk of side effects of some medications. , 

 

There is interest in using L-tryptophan for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000057-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of L-tryptophan and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000057-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about L-tryptophan ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000057-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between L-tryptophan and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Sedative medications (CNS depressants) L-tryptophan might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Some medications, called sedatives, can also cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking L-tryptophan with sedative medications might cause breathing problems and/or too much sleepiness. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Serotonergic drugs L-tryptophan might increase a brain chemical called serotonin. Some medications also have this effect. Taking L-tryptophan along with these medications might increase serotonin too much. This might cause serious side effects including heart problems, seizures, and vomiting.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000057-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between L-tryptophan and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements with sedative properties L-tryptophan might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking it along with other supplements with similar effects might cause too much sleepiness and/or slowed breathing in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include hops, kava, melatonin, and valerian. Herbs and supplements with serotonergic properties L-tryptophan increases a brain chemical called serotonin. Taking it along with other supplements that have this effect might cause serious side effects, including heart problems, seizures, and vomiting. Examples of supplements with this effect include 5-HTP, black seed, SAMe, and St. John's wort.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000057-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between L-tryptophan and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000057-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of L-tryptophan ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>