<Document id="0000068" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/644.html">

<Focus>Oregano</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000068-1" qtype="information">What is Oregano ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oregano (Origanum vulgare) is an herb used to flavor foods. It is considered safe in common food amounts, but has little evidence of health benefits. 

Oregano has olive-green leaves and purple flowers. It is closely related to other herbs, including mint, thyme, marjoram, and basil. Oregano contains chemicals that might help reduce cough. Oregano also might help with digestion and with fighting against some bacteria and viruses.  

People use oregano for wound healing, parasite infections, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000068-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Oregano ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using oregano for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000068-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Oregano and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000068-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Oregano ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000068-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Oregano and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Oregano might lower blood sugar levels. Taking oregano along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Oregano might slow blood clotting. Taking oregano along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000068-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Oregano and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Copper Oregano might decrease the absorption of copper into the body. But it isn't clear if this is a big concern. Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Oregano might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Oregano might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng. Iron Oregano might decrease the absorption of iron into the body. But it isn't clear if this is a big concern. Zinc Oregano might decrease the absorption of zinc into the body. But it isn't clear if this is a big concern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000068-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Oregano and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000068-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Oregano ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>