<Document id="0000070" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1139.html">

<Focus>Palm Oil</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000070-1" qtype="information">What is Palm Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>Palm oil is an edible oil that comes from the fruit of the oil palm tree (Elaeis guineensis). Crude palm oil, or "red palm oil," is high in beta-carotene. 

Palm oil contains saturated and unsaturated fats. Some types of palm oil contain vitamin E and beta-carotene. These types of palm oil might have antioxidant effects. Refined palm oil is made by bleaching, deodorizing, and neutralizing crude palm oil. 

People use palm oil for preventing and treating vitamin A deficiency. It is also used for malaria, heart disease, cancer, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these other uses.
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000070-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Palm Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  PALM OIL  are as follows: Likely effective for... Vitamin A deficiency . Adding red palm oil to the diets of children or during pregnancy in developing countries reduces the chance of having low vitamin A levels. It also seems to help increase vitamin A levels in those who already have low levels. ,  

There is interest in using palm oil for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000070-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Palm Oil and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000070-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Palm Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000070-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Palm Oil and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Palm oil might slow blood clotting. Taking palm oil along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000070-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Palm Oil and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Beta-carotene Palm oil contains beta-carotene. Taking beta-carotene supplements along with palm oil might result in too much beta-carotene. Vitamin A Palm oil contains beta-carotene, which is a building block of vitamin A. Taking a vitamin A or beta-carotene supplement along with palm oil might result in too much vitamin A.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000070-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Palm Oil and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000070-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Palm Oil ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>