<Document id="0000033" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/984.html">

<Focus>Devil's claw</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000033-1" qtype="information">What is Devil's claw ?</Question>
			<Answer>Devil's claw (Harpagophytum procumbens) is an herb. It has been used by mouth for back pain and arthritis, but there is little evidence to support these uses. 

Devil's claw is native to south Africa, including the Kalahari Desert, where it's been used traditionally for many conditions. Devil's claw contains chemicals that might decrease swelling. Because of this, it is often used to treat conditions that involve both pain and inflammation. 

Devil's claw is most commonly used for back pain and osteoarthritis. It is also used for rheumatoid arthritis (RA) and other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. There is also no good evidence to support using devil's claw for COVID-19.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000033-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Devil's claw ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  DEVIL'S CLAW  are as follows: Possibly effective for... Back pain . Taking devil's claw by mouth seems to reduce lower back pain. Devil's claw seems to work about as well as some non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)., 

 Osteoarthritis . Taking devil's claw by mouth alone, with other ingredients, or along with nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) seems to help reduce osteoarthritis pain. Some people taking devil's claw seem to be able to lower the dose of NSAIDs taken for pain relief.,  

There is interest in using devil's claw for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000033-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Devil's claw and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000033-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Devil's claw ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000033-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Devil's claw and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2C19 (CYP2C19) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Devil's claw might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2C9 (CYP2C9) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Devil's claw might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Devil's claw might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Warfarin (Coumadin) Warfarin is used to slow blood clotting. Devil's claw might increase its effects and the chances of bruising and bleeding. Be sure to have your blood checked regularly. The dose of your warfarin might need to be changed. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Medications moved by pumps in cells (P-glycoprotein Substrates) Some medications are moved in and out of cells by pumps. Devil's claw might change how these pumps work and change how much medication stays in the body. In some cases, this might change the effects and side effects of a medication. Medications that decrease stomach acid (H2-blockers) H2-blockers are used to decrease stomach acid. Devil's claw can increase stomach acid. Taking Devil's claw might decrease the effects of H2-blockers.  

Some common H2-blockers include cimetidine (Tagamet), ranitidine (Zantac), and famotidine (Pepcid). Medications that decrease stomach acid (Proton pump inhibitors) Proton pump inhibitors are used to decrease stomach acid. Devil's claw can increase stomach acid. Taking devil's claw might decrease the effects of proton pump inhibitors.  

Some common proton pump inhibitors include omeprazole (Prilosec), lansoprazole (Prevacid), rabeprazole (Aciphex), pantoprazole (Protonix), and esomeprazole (Nexium).</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000033-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Devil's claw and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000033-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Devil's claw and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000033-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Devil's claw ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>