<Document id="0000003" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/967.html">

<Focus>American ginseng</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000003-1" qtype="information">What is American ginseng ?</Question>
			<Answer>American ginseng (Panax quinquefolius) is an herb that grows mainly in North America. It's an endangered species in some states due to high demand. 

American ginseng is considered an adaptogen. Adaptogens are a class of substances that are believed to stimulate the body's resistance to physical, environmental, and emotional stressors. American ginseng also contains chemicals called ginsenosides, which seem to affect insulin levels and lower blood sugar. 
 
People take American ginseng for stress, to boost the immune system, for upper airway infections, diabetes, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses. 

Don't confuse American ginseng with Asian ginseng (Panax ginseng) or Eleuthero (Eleutherococcus senticosus). These are different plants with different effects.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000003-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is American ginseng ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  AMERICAN GINSENG  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 


 Upper airway infection . Taking a specific American ginseng extract called CVT-E002 (Cold-FX, Afexa Life Sciences) by mouth during flu season might prevent cold or flu symptoms in some adults. ,  

There is interest in using American ginseng for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000003-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of American ginseng and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000003-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about American ginseng ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000003-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between American ginseng and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Warfarin (Coumadin) Warfarin is used to slow blood clotting. American ginseng has been reported to decrease the effects of warfarin. This might increase the risk of clotting. It is unclear why this interaction might occur. To avoid this interaction, do not take American ginseng if you take warfarin. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications for depression (MAOIs) American ginseng might stimulate the body. Some medications used for depression can also stimulate the body. Taking American ginseng along with these medications used for depression might cause side effects such as anxiousness, headache, restlessness, and insomnia. 

Some common MAOIs include phenelzine (Nardil), selegiline (Zelapar), and tranylcypromine (Parnate). Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) American ginseng might lower blood sugar levels. Taking American ginseng along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications that decrease the immune system (Immunosuppressants) American ginseng can increase the activity of the immune system. Some medications, such as those used after a transplant, decrease the activity of the immune system. Taking American ginseng along with these medications might decrease the effects of these medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000003-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between American ginseng and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar American ginseng might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000003-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between American ginseng and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000003-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of American ginseng ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>