<Document id="0000038" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1051.html">

<Focus>Gelatin</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000038-1" qtype="information">What is Gelatin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Gelatin is a protein made from animal collagen, usually from cows and pigs. It's commonly used to make capsules, cosmetics, ointments, and foods. 

Collagen is one of the materials that make up cartilage, bone, and skin. Taking gelatin might increase the production of collagen in the body.  

People use gelatin for aging skin, osteoarthritis, osteoporosis, brittle nails, obesity, diarrhea, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 

Don't confuse gelatin with collagen type I (native), collagen type II (native), or collagen peptides. These are not the same.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000038-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Gelatin ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  GELATIN  are as follows: Possibly ineffective for... 
 Diarrhea . Taking gelatin tannate by mouth doesn't benefit infants and young children with diarrhea., 
 

There is interest in using gelatin for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000038-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Gelatin and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000038-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Gelatin ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000038-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Gelatin and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000038-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Gelatin and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000038-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Gelatin and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000038-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Gelatin ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>