<Document id="0000065" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/814.html">

<Focus>Oats</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000065-1" qtype="information">What is Oats ?</Question>
			<Answer>Oat (Avena sativa) is a type of cereal grain. People often eat the plant's whole seeds (oats), outer seed layers (oat bran), and leaves and stems (oat straw). 

Oats might reduce cholesterol and blood sugar levels, and help control appetite by making you feel full. Oat bran might work by keeping the gut from absorbing substances that can lead to heart disease, high cholesterol, and diabetes. Oats seem to reduce swelling when applied to the skin. 

Oat bran and whole oats are used for heart disease, high cholesterol, and diabetes. They are also used for high blood pressure, cancer, dry skin, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these other uses.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000065-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Oats ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  OATS  are as follows: Likely effective for... 

 Heart disease . Oats contain fiber. Eating a diet high in fiber, such as 3.6 grams of oats daily, reduces the risk for heart disease. , 

 High cholesterol . Eating oats, oat bran, and other soluble fibers can somewhat reduce total and low-density lipoprotein (LDL or "bad") cholesterol when consumed as part of a diet low in saturated fat., 

 

 Possibly effective for... 

 Diabetes . Eating a diet rich in whole grains, including oats and oat bran, might help prevent diabetes. It might also help improve blood sugar control and lower cholesterol levels in people with diabetes. , 


 Stomach cancer . Eating high-fiber foods, such as oats and oat bran, seems to lower the risk of stomach cancer., 

 

 Possibly ineffective for... 

 Colon cancer, rectal cancer . Regularly eating oat bran or oats doesn't seem to lower the risk of colon or rectal cancer., 


 

There is interest in using oats for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000065-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Oats and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000065-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Oats ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000065-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Oats and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Insulin Oats might reduce the amount of insulin needed for blood sugar control. Taking oats along with insulin might cause your blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. The dose of insulin might need to be changed. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Oats might lower blood sugar levels. Taking oats along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000065-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Oats and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Oats might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000065-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Oats and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000065-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Oats ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>