<Document id="0000025" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/773.html">

<Focus>Cascara</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000025-1" qtype="information">What is Cascara ?</Question>
			<Answer>Cascara sagrada (Frangula purshiana) is a shrub. The dried bark used to be FDA approved as an OTC laxative for constipation. It's now used in supplements. 

Cascara sagrada contains chemicals that stimulate the bowel and have a laxative effect. 


People use cascara sagrada for constipation, emptying the colon before a colonoscopy, and other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 

Cascara sagrada used to be approved by the US FDA as an over-the-counter (OTC) drug for constipation, but this approval was taken away in 2002 due to a lack of evidence. Today, you can buy cascara sagrada as a dietary supplement, but not as a drug
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000025-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Cascara ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  CASCARA SAGRADA  are as follows: Possibly ineffective for... Emptying the colon before a colonoscopy . Taking cascara sagrada by mouth, along with magnesium sulfate or milk of magnesia, does not improve bowel cleansing in people who are having a colonoscopy.,  

There is interest in using cascara sagrada for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000025-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Cascara and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000025-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Cascara ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000025-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Cascara and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Digoxin (Lanoxin) Cascara sagrada is a type of laxative called a stimulant laxative. Stimulant laxatives can decrease potassium levels in the body. Low potassium levels can increase the risk of side effects from digoxin. Medications for inflammation (Corticosteroids) Cascara sagrada is a type of laxative called a stimulant laxative. Stimulant laxatives can cause diarrhea and decrease potassium levels. Some medications for inflammation, called corticosteroids, can also decrease potassium levels. Taking these products together might cause potassium levels to drop too low. Stimulant laxatives Cascara sagrada is a type of laxative called a stimulant laxative. Stimulant laxatives can cause diarrhea and decrease potassium levels. Taking cascara sagrada with other stimulant laxatives might cause more diarrhea and very low potassium levels. Warfarin (Coumadin) Cascara sagrada can work as a laxative. In some people, cascara sagrada can cause diarrhea. Diarrhea can increase the effects of warfarin and increase the risk of bleeding. If you take warfarin, do not take large doses of cascara sagrada. Water pills (Diuretic drugs) Cascara sagrada is a laxative. Some laxatives can cause diarrhea and decrease potassium levels. "Water pills" can also decrease potassium levels. Taking cascara sagrada along with "water pills" might make potassium levels drop too low. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Cascara sagrada might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000025-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Cascara and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Chromium-containing herbs and supplements Cascara sagrada contains chromium. Taking it with other supplements that contain chromium can increase the risk of chromium poisoning.  Examples of supplements that contain chromium include bilberry, brewer's yeast, and horsetail. Herbs that contain cardiac glycosides Cascara sagrada contains chemicals that can affect the heart. These chemicals are called cardiac glycosides. Using it along with other supplements that also contain cardiac glycosides can increase the risk of heart damage. Examples of supplements that contain cardiac glycosides include black hellebore, foxglove, lily-of-the-valley, oleander, and pleurisy root. Horsetail Horsetail can act as a "water pill." "Water pills" can decrease potassium levels. Cascara sagrada is a laxative. Laxatives can also decrease potassium levels.  Taking cascara sagrada along with horsetail might make potassium levels drop too low. Licorice Licorice causes the body to lose potassium. Cascara sagrada is a laxative. Laxatives can also decrease potassium levels.  Taking cascara sagrada along with licorice might make potassium levels drop too low Stimulant laxative herbs Cascara sagrada s a type of laxative called a stimulant laxative. Stimulant laxatives can cause diarrhea and decrease potassium levels. Taking cascara sagrada with other supplements with similar effects might cause more diarrhea and very low potassium levels. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, alder buckthorn, gossypol, rhubarb, and senna.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000025-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Cascara and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000025-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Cascara ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>