<Document id="0000029" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1261.html">

<Focus>Coconut Water</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000029-1" qtype="information">What is Coconut Water ?</Question>
			<Answer>Coconut water is the clear liquid found inside immature coconuts (Cocos nucifera). As the coconut matures, the water is replaced by coconut meat.  

Coconut water is rich in carbohydrates and electrolytes such as potassium, sodium, and magnesium. Because of these electrolytes, there&#8217;s a lot of interest in using coconut water to treat and prevent dehydration. Coconut water is sometimes called green coconut water because the immature coconuts are green. 

People commonly use coconut water as a beverage and as a solution for treating dehydration related to diarrhea or exercise. It&#8217;s also used for high blood pressure and athletic performance, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 

Don&#8217;t confuse coconut water with coconut or coconut oil. These are not the same. Also, coconut water is different than coconut milk. Coconut milk is made from a mixture of the grated meat of a mature coconut.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000029-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Coconut Water ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using coconut milk for a number of purposes, but there isn&#8217;t enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000029-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Coconut Water and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000029-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Coconut Water ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000029-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Coconut Water and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications for high blood pressure (Antihypertensive drugs) Coconut water might lower blood pressure. Taking coconut water along with medications that lower blood pressure might cause blood pressure to go too low. Monitor your blood pressure closely. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Coconut water might lower blood sugar levels. Taking coconut water along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000029-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Coconut Water and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood pressure Coconut water might lower blood pressure. Taking it with other supplements that have the same effect might cause blood pressure to drop too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include andrographis, casein peptides, L-arginine, niacin, and stinging nettle. Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Coconut water might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000029-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Coconut Water and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000029-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Coconut Water ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>