<Document id="0000035" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/936.html">

<Focus>Dong quai</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000035-1" qtype="information">What is Dong quai ?</Question>
			<Answer>Dong quai (Angelica sinensis) is a plant that has been used for a variety of conditions, with little evidence. It may be unsafe when too much is consumed.
 

Dong quai is a member of the same plant family as parsley, celery, and carrots. It's popular in Chinese medicine for female health concerns. The root might affect estrogen and other hormones.  

People commonly use dong quai for menopausal symptoms, menstrual cramps, migraine, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000035-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Dong quai ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using dong quai for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000035-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Dong quai and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000035-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Dong quai ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000035-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Dong quai and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Warfarin (Coumadin) Warfarin is used to slow blood clotting. Dong quai might also slow blood clotting. Taking dong quai along with warfarin might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Be sure to have your blood checked regularly. The dose of your warfarin might need to be changed. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Estrogens Dong quai might act like the hormone estrogen. When taken together, dong quai might increase the risk of estrogen side effects. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Dong quai might slow blood clotting. Taking dong quai along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000035-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Dong quai and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Dong quai might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000035-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Dong quai and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000035-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Dong quai ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>