<Document id="0000063" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/522.html">

<Focus>MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane)</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000063-1" qtype="information">What is MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Methylsulfonylmethane (MSM) is a chemical that occurs naturally in humans, as well as some green plants and animals. It can also be made in a lab. 

MSM might supply sulfur to make other chemicals in the body. But there is no recommended dietary allowance (RDA) for MSM or sulfur, and sulfur deficiency is not a known condition. 

People commonly use MSM for osteoarthritis. It is also used for pain, swelling, aging skin, hay fever, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses. 

Don't confuse MSM with DMSO (Dimethylsulfoxide). They are not the same compound.
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000063-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane) ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  METHYLSULFONYLMETHANE (MSM)  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 


 Osteoarthritis . Taking MSM by mouth, alone or together with other ingredients such as glucosamine, can slightly reduce pain and swelling and improve function in people with osteoarthritis. ,  


 Possibly ineffective for... 

 Poor circulation that can cause the legs to swell (chronic venous insufficiency or CVI) . Applying MSM and EDTA to the skin can reduce swelling in people with CVI. But applying MSM alone seems to make swelling worse., 

 

There is interest in using MSM for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000063-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane) and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000063-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane) ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000063-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane) and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000063-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane) and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000063-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane) and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000063-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of MSM (Methylsulfonylmethane) ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>