<Document id="0000082" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/307.html">

<Focus>Resveratrol</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000082-1" qtype="information">What is Resveratrol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Resveratrol is a chemical mostly found in red grapes and products made from these grapes (wine, juice). It may be helpful for hay fever and weight loss.  


Resveratrol might have many effects in the body, including expanding blood vessels and reducing blood clotting. It may also decrease pain and swelling, reduce levels of sugar in the blood, and help the body fight against disease.
 

Resveratrol is most commonly used for high cholesterol, cancer, heart disease, and many other conditions. But there is no strong evidence to support resveratrol for any use.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000082-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Resveratrol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  RESVERATROL  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 
 Hay fever . Using a nasal spray containing resveratrol three times daily for 4 weeks seems to reduce allergy symptoms in adults with seasonal allergies. Using a nasal spray containing resveratrol and beta-glucans three times daily for 2 months also seems to reduce allergy symptoms in children with seasonal allergies.  , 

 Obesity . Taking resveratrol by mouth seems to increase weight loss in overweight and obese adults. But it doesn't seem to improve blood pressure, glucose control, or levels of cholesterol and other fats., 

 
 Possibly ineffective for... 

 Heart disease . People who consume higher amounts of dietary resveratrol do not seem to have a lower risk of heart disease compared to people who consume lower amounts. Also, taking resveratrol by mouth does not seem to improve levels of cholesterol or blood fats called triglycerides in people at risk for heart disease.  , 

 High cholesterol . Taking resveratrol by mouth does not seem to improve levels of cholesterol or blood fats called triglycerides.   , 

 A grouping of symptoms that increase the risk of diabetes, heart disease, and stroke (metabolic syndrome) . Taking resveratrol by mouth doesn't seem to lower blood pressure, blood sugar, or cholesterol in people with metabolic syndrome.  , 

 Build up of fat in the liver in people who drink little or no alcohol (nonalcoholic fatty liver disease or NAFLD) . Taking resveratrol by mouth doesn't seem to improve liver function, liver scarring, or cholesterol levels in people with NAFLD. , 
 
There is interest in using resveratrol for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000082-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Resveratrol and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000082-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Resveratrol ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000082-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Resveratrol and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 1A1 (CYP1A1) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Resveratrol might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 1A2 (CYP1A2) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Resveratrol might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 1B1 (CYP1B1) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Resveratrol might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2C19 (CYP2C19) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Resveratrol might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2E1 (CYP2E1) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Resveratrol might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Resveratrol might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Resveratrol might slow blood clotting. Taking resveratrol along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000082-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Resveratrol and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Resveratrol might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000082-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Resveratrol and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Resveratrol can be taken with or without food. But taking resveratrol with fatty foods might reduce how much the body absorbs.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000082-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Resveratrol ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>