<Document id="0000096" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/955.html">

<Focus>Willow Bark</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000096-1" qtype="information">What is Willow Bark ?</Question>
			<Answer>Willow bark comes from several varieties of willow tree, including white (Salix alba or European), black (Salix nigra or pussy), crack, and purple willow. 

Willow bark contains a chemical called salicin, which is similar to aspirin. It has pain and fever reducing effects in the body. 

People commonly use willow bark for back pain, osteoarthritis, fever, flu, muscle pain, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses. There is also no good evidence to support using willow bark for COVID-19.

 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000096-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Willow Bark ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  WILLOW BARK  are as follows: Possibly effective for... Back pain . Taking willow bark by mouth seems to reduce lower back pain. Higher doses seem to be more effective than lower doses, and it may take up to a week to help.,  

There is interest in using willow bark for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000096-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Willow Bark and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000096-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Willow Bark ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000096-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Willow Bark and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Major Do not take this combination. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Willow bark might slow blood clotting. Taking willow bark along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Acetazolamide Willow bark contains chemicals that might increase the amount of acetazolamide in the blood. Taking willow bark along with acetazolamide might increase the effects and side effects of acetazolamide. Aspirin Willow bark contains chemicals similar to aspirin. Taking willow bark along with aspirin might increase the effects and side effects of aspirin. Choline Magnesium Trisalicylate (Trilisate) Willow bark contains chemicals that are similar to choline magnesium trisalicylate. Taking willow bark along with choline magnesium trisalicylate might increase the effects and side effects of choline magnesium trisalicylate. Salsalate (Disalcid) Salsalate is a type of medicine called a salicylate. It's similar to aspirin. Willow bark also contains a salicylate similar to aspirin. Taking salsalate along with willow bark might increase the effects and side effects of salsalate.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000096-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Willow Bark and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Willow bark might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng. Herbs that contain chemicals similar to aspirin (salicylates) Willow bark contains chemicals called salicylates. Salicylates are similar to aspirin. Taking it with other supplements that contain salicylates might increase their effects and side effects. Examples of supplements that contain salicylates include aspen, black haw, poplar, and meadowsweet.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000096-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Willow Bark and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000096-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Willow Bark ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>