<Document id="0000050" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/856.html">

<Focus>Hops</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000050-1" qtype="information">What is Hops ?</Question>
			<Answer>Hops are the dried, flowering parts of the hop plant (Humulus lupulus), commonly used in brewing beer. They have limited evidence of health benefits. 

The term "hops" comes from the Anglo-Saxon term "hoppan", which means "to climb." Hops contain many chemicals, including bitter acids, which contribute to its bitter flavor. Some chemicals in hops seem to act similarly to the hormone estrogen and some seem to cause sleepiness. 
 
People commonly use hops for anxiety, sleep disorders, restlessness, symptoms of menopause, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000050-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Hops ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using hops for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000050-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Hops and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000050-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Hops ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000050-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Hops and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Estrogens Hops might have some of the same effects as estrogen. Taking hops along with estrogen might decrease the effects of estrogen. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 1A2 (CYP1A2) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Hops might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Hops might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Sedative medications (CNS depressants) Hops might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Some medications, called sedatives, can also cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking hops with sedative medications might cause breathing problems and/or too much sleepiness.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000050-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Hops and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements with sedative properties Hops might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking it along with other supplements with similar effects might cause too much sleepiness and/or slowed breathing in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include kava, L-tryptophan, melatonin, and valerian. Herbs that might act like estrogen Hops might have the same effects as estrogen. Using it along with other supplements with similar effects might increase estrogen-like effects and side effects. Examples of supplements with this effect include black cohosh, kudzu, peony, and red clover.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000050-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Hops and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000050-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Hops ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>