<Document id="0000084" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/752.html">

<Focus>Roman chamomile</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000084-1" qtype="information">What is Roman chamomile ?</Question>
			<Answer>Roman chamomile (Chamaemelum nobile) is a plant native to Morocco and Europe. It's different from German chamomile, which is more commonly used in teas. 

Roman chamomile contains chemicals that might have anticancer, anti-diabetes, and anti-inflammatory effects. 

People take Roman chamomile for hay fever, anxiety, eczema, stress, insomnia, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000084-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Roman chamomile ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using Roman chamomile for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000084-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Roman chamomile and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000084-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Roman chamomile ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000084-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Roman chamomile and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000084-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Roman chamomile and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000084-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Roman chamomile and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000084-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Roman chamomile ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>