<Document id="0000039" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/985.html">

<Focus>Ginseng, Siberian</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000039-1" qtype="information">What is Ginseng, Siberian ?</Question>
			<Answer>Eleuthero (Eleutherococcus senticosus) is a woody shrub sometimes called Siberian ginseng. It is not a true ginseng. It is sometimes used as an adaptogen.  

Eleuthero is often considered an adaptogen. Adaptogens are a class of substances that are believed to stimulate the body's resistance to physical, environmental, and emotional stressors. Eleuthero contains many chemicals that affect the brain, immune system, and certain hormones. 

People use eleuthero for genital herpes, diabetes, athletic performance, memory and thinking skills, the common cold, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses. 

Don't confuse eleuthero with other herbs called "ginseng," including American Ginseng, Blue Cohosh, Canaigre, Codonopsis, Panax Ginseng, and Panax Notoginseng. These are not the same.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000039-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Ginseng, Siberian ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  ELEUTHERO  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 


 Genital herpes . Taking a specific eleuthero extract (Elagen) by mouth might help reduce genital herpes outbreaks., 
 

There is interest in using eleuthero for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000039-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Ginseng, Siberian and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000039-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Ginseng, Siberian ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000039-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Ginseng, Siberian and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Digoxin (Lanoxin) There is some concern that eleuthero might increase levels of digoxin. This could increase the effects and side effects of digoxin. If you are taking digoxin, speak with a healthcare provider before taking eleuthero. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 1A2 (CYP1A2) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Eleuthero might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2C9 (CYP2C9) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Eleuthero might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Eleuthero might lower blood sugar levels. Taking eleuthero along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications moved by pumps in cells (Organic anion-transporting polypeptide substrates) Some medications are moved in and out of cells by pumps. Eleuthero might change how these pumps work and change how much medication stays in the body. In some cases, this might change the effects and side effects of a medication. Medications moved by pumps in cells (P-glycoprotein substrates) Some medications are moved in and out of cells by pumps. Eleuthero might change how these pumps work and change how much medication stays in the body. In some cases, this might change the effects and side effects of a medication. Medications that decrease the immune system (Immunosuppressants) Eleuthero can increase the activity of the immune system. Some medications, such as those used after a transplant, decrease the activity of the immune system. Taking eleuthero along with these medications might decrease the effects of these medications. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Eleuthero might slow blood clotting. Taking eleuthero along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2D6 (CYP2D6) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Eleuthero might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Eleuthero might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000039-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Ginseng, Siberian and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Eleuthero might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Eleuthero might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000039-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Ginseng, Siberian and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000039-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Ginseng, Siberian ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>