<Document id="0000021" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/894.html">

<Focus>Boron</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000021-1" qtype="information">What is Boron ?</Question>
			<Answer>Boron is an element. Boron has been consumed for menstrual cramps and boric acid has been used vaginally for yeast infections, but evidence is limited. 

Boron seems to affect the way the body handles other minerals such as calcium, magnesium, and phosphorus. It also seems to increase estrogen levels post-menopause. Boric acid, a common form of boron, can kill yeast that cause vaginal infections. Boron may have antioxidant effects.  

People commonly use boron for boron deficiency and vaginal yeast infections. It is also used for athletic performance, menstrual cramps, osteoarthritis, osteoporosis, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support many of these uses.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000021-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Boron ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  BORON  are as follows: Likely effective for... Boron deficiency . Taking boron by mouth treats and prevents boron deficiency.,  Possibly effective for... 

 Skin damage caused by radiation therapy (radiation dermatitis) . Applying boron gel to the skin might help prevent skin damage caused by radiation therapy. , 

 Vaginal yeast infections . Applying boric acid inside the vagina can help treat yeast infections (candidiasis), including infections that do not seem to get better with other medications and treatments., 

 

 Possibly ineffective for... Athletic performance . Taking boron by mouth doesn't seem to improve body mass, muscle mass, or testosterone levels in male bodybuilders.,  

There is interest in using boron for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000021-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Boron and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000021-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Boron ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000021-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Boron and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>It is not known if this product interacts with any medicines.    Before taking this product, talk with your health professional if you take any medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000021-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Boron and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Magnesium Boron supplements can increase how much magnesium stays in the body. This can increase blood levels of magnesium. But it's not clear if this is a big concern.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000021-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Boron and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000021-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Boron ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>