<Document id="0000032" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/808.html">

<Focus>Deer Velvet</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000032-1" qtype="information">What is Deer Velvet ?</Question>
			<Answer>Deer velvet covers the growing bone and cartilage that becomes deer antlers. It's sometimes used as medicine in Western countries. 

Deer velvet contains multiple substances including the female sex hormones estrone and estradiol. It also contains substances that might help cells grow and function. 

People use deer velvet for athletic performance, high blood pressure, increasing sexual desire, asthma, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.
 </Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000032-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Deer Velvet ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using deer velvet for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000032-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Deer Velvet and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000032-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Deer Velvet ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000032-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Deer Velvet and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Minor Be watchful with this combination. Birth control pills (Contraceptive drugs) Some birth control pills contain the hormone estrogen. Deer velvet contains hormones. Taking deer velvet along with birth control pills might change the effects of birth control pills. If you take birth control pills along with deer velvet, use an additional form of birth control such as a condom. Estrogens Deer velvet contains a small amount of hormones. Taking deer velvet along with estrogen pills might change the effects of estrogen pills.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000032-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Deer Velvet and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000032-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Deer Velvet and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000032-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Deer Velvet ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>