<Document id="0000072" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/488.html">

<Focus>Papaya</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000072-1" qtype="information">What is Papaya ?</Question>
			<Answer>Papaya (Carica papaya) is a tropical tree. Its ripe fruit is considered safe, but unripe papaya fruit contains papain and can damage the esophagus. 

Unripe papaya contains a chemical called papain. Papain breaks down proteins, carbohydrates, and fats. But papain is changed in the stomach, so it's not clear if it's effective as medicine when taken by mouth. Papaya also contains a chemical called carpain, which seems to be able to kill certain parasites and might affect the central nervous system. 

People use papaya for cancer, diabetes, dengue fever, HPV, and many other conditions, but there's no good scientific evidence to support these uses.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000072-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Papaya ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using papaya for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000072-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Papaya and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000072-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Papaya ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000072-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Papaya and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Amiodarone (Cordarone) Taking papaya extract by mouth along with amiodarone might increase the amount of amiodarone in the body. This might increase the effects and adverse effects of amiodarone.  Levothyroxine (Synthroid, others) Eating large amounts of papaya might reduce the effects of levothyroxine.  Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Papaya might lower blood sugar levels. Taking papaya along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Warfarin (Coumadin) Warfarin is used to slow blood clotting. Papaya might increase the effects of warfarin and increase the chances of bruising and bleeding. Be sure to have your blood checked regularly. The dose of your warfarin might need to be changed.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000072-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Papaya and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Papaya might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000072-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Papaya and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000072-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Papaya ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>