<Document id="0000016" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/726.html">

<Focus>Bladderwrack</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000016-1" qtype="information">What is Bladderwrack ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fucus vesiculosus is a type of brown seaweed that grows in the Baltic Sea, Atlantic Ocean, and North Pacific Ocean. The whole plant is used as medicine. 

Fucus vesiculosus contains varying amounts of iodine. Iodine might help prevent or treat some thyroid disorders. Fucus vesiculosus also might have antidiabetic effects and affect hormone levels.  

People use Fucus vesiculosus for thyroid disorders, obesity, aging skin, constipation, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.  

Don't confuse Fucus vesiculosus with algin, bladderwort, blue-green algae, ecklonia cava, or laminaria. These are not the same.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000016-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Bladderwrack ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using Fucus vesiculosus for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000016-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Bladderwrack and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000016-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Bladderwrack ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000016-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Bladderwrack and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Amiodarone (Cordarone) Fucus vesiculosus and amiodarone both contain iodine. Taking fucus vesiculosus with amiodarone might increase the levels of iodine in the blood. Too much iodine in the blood can cause side effects that affect the thyroid. Lithium Fucus vesiculosus can contain large amounts of iodine. Large amounts of iodine can change thyroid function. Lithium can also change thyroid function. Taking Fucus vesiculosus along with lithium might increase the risk of thyroid function changes. Medications for an overactive thyroid (Antithyroid drugs) Fucus vesiculosus can contain large amounts of iodine. Iodine can increase or decrease thyroid function. Taking Fucus vesiculosus along with medications for an overactive thyroid might change the effects of these medications. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Fucus vesiculosus might slow blood clotting. Taking Fucus vesiculosus along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Thyroid hormone Fucus vesiculosus contains iodine. Iodine can increase or decrease thyroid function. Taking Fucus vesiculosus along with thyroid hormone medications might increase the effects of these medications. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2C8 (CYP2C8) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Fucus vesiculosus might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2C9 (CYP2C9) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Fucus vesiculosus might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 2D6 (CYP2D6) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Fucus vesiculosus might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications. Medications changed by the liver (Cytochrome P450 3A4 (CYP3A4) substrates) Some medications are changed and broken down by the liver. Fucus vesiculosus might change how quickly the liver breaks down these medications. This could change the effects and side effects of these medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000016-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Bladderwrack and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Fucus vesiculosus might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng. Iodine-containing herbs and supplements Fucus vesiculosus contains iodine. Taking Fucus vesiculosus with other products that contain iodine might cause iodine levels to go too high. This can cause side effects, such as changes in thyroid function. Examples of supplements that contain iodine include seaweed products, such as dulse and laminaria. Strontium Fucus vesiculosus contains alginate. Alginate can reduce the absorption of strontium. Taking Fucus vesiculosus with strontium supplements might reduce the absorption of strontium.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000016-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Bladderwrack and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000016-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Bladderwrack ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>