<Document id="0000059" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/554.html">

<Focus>Lycopene</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000059-1" qtype="information">What is Lycopene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Lycopene is a type of organic pigment called a carotenoid. It is related to beta-carotene and gives some vegetables and fruits (e.g., tomatoes) a red color. 

Lycopene is a powerful antioxidant that might help protect cells from damage. It's found in tomato, watermelon, red orange, pink grapefruit, apricot, rose hip, and guava.  

Lycopene is used for high blood pressure, high cholesterol, cancer, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses.
 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000059-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Lycopene ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  LYCOPENE  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 

 Prostate cancer . Taking lycopene by mouth might slightly reduce the risk of developing prostate cancer. It might also slightly reduce the risk of prostate cancer returning.  , 
 Possibly ineffective for... 

 Bladder cancer . People who eat more lycopene in their diet don't seem to have a lower risk for bladder cancer., 

 Diabetes . People who eat more lycopene in their diet don't seem to have a lower risk of developing diabetes. Also, people with diabetes who eat more lycopene don't seem to have a lower risk of dying from heart disease. , 

 

There is interest in using lycopene for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000059-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Lycopene and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000059-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Lycopene ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000059-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Lycopene and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Lycopene might slow blood clotting. Taking lycopene along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000059-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Lycopene and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Beta-carotene Taking beta-carotene along with lycopene may alter the amount of lycopene that is absorbed from the gut. Calcium Taking calcium along with lycopene may decrease the amount of lycopene that is absorbed from the gut. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Lycopene might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng. Lutein Taking lutein along with lycopene may alter the amount of lycopene that is absorbed from the gut.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000059-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Lycopene and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Fat substitutes such as olestra might reduce the amount of lycopene that is absorbed by the body. Olestra seems to lower lycopene levels in healthy people by about 30%.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000059-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Lycopene ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>