<Document id="0000052" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/843.html">

<Focus>Horsetail</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000052-1" qtype="information">What is Horsetail ?</Question>
			<Answer>Horsetail refers to various plant species of the Equisetum genus. It may help reduce fluid retention, but might cause vitamin B1 deficiency when used long-term.
 

The chemicals in horsetail might have antioxidant and anti-inflammatory effects. They might also work like "water pills" (diuretics) and increase urination. 

People use horsetail for fluid retention, urinary tract infections (UTIs), osteoporosis, loss of bladder control, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses. 
 

</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000052-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Horsetail ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using horsetail for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000052-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Horsetail and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000052-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Horsetail ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000052-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Horsetail and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Efavirenz (Sustiva) Efavirenz is a drug used to treat HIV. Taking horsetail with efavirenz might reduce the effects of efavirenz. Talk with your healthcare provider before using horsetail if you are taking efavirenz. Lithium Taking horsetail might decrease how well the body gets rid of lithium. This could increase how much lithium is in the body and result in serious side effects. Talk with your healthcare provider before using this product if you are taking lithium. Your lithium dose might need to be changed. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Horsetail might lower blood sugar levels. Taking horsetail along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications for HIV/AIDS (Nucleoside reverse transcriptase inhibitors (NRTIs)) Taking horsetail with NRTIs might reduce the effects of these drugs. Talk with your healthcare provider before using horsetail if you are taking an NRTI. Water pills (Diuretic drugs) Horsetail can decrease potassium levels. "Water pills" can also decrease potassium levels. Taking horsetail along with "water pills" might make potassium levels drop too low.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000052-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Horsetail and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Betel nut Horsetail and betel nut both reduce the amount of thiamine available for the body to use. Using these herbs together might increase the risk for thiamine deficiency. Chromium-containing herbs and supplements Horsetail contains chromium. Taking it with other supplements that contain chromium can increase the risk of chromium poisoning. Examples of supplements that contain chromium include bilberry, brewer's yeast, and cascara sagrada. Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Horsetail might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Silicon Horsetail contains large amounts of silicon. Taking horsetail along with silicon supplements might increase the risk of adverse effects from silicon. Thiamine Crude horsetail contains a chemical that breaks down thiamine. Taking horsetail might cause thiamine deficiency.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000052-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Horsetail and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000052-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Horsetail ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>