<Document id="0000008" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/531.html">

<Focus>Belladonna</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000008-1" qtype="information">What is Belladonna ?</Question>
			<Answer>Belladonna (Atropa belladonna) is a plant that grows from Western Europe to the Himalayas. It&#8217;s also grown in the US. All parts of the plant are poisonous. 
Belladonna has chemicals that can alter the function of the body's nervous system and cause changes to saliva, sweat, pupil size, urination, digestive functions, and others. Belladonna can also cause increased heart rate and blood pressure. 

Despite known safety concerns, people use belladonna for asthma, the common cold, hemorrhoids, Parkinson disease, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support these uses.  

Since 2010, the FDA has issued several warnings about homeopathic teething tablets and gels for infants that contain belladonna. Serious side effects including seizures, breathing problems, and agitation have been reported in infants taking these products, and some have died. 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000008-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Belladonna ?</Question>
			<Answer>There is interest in using belladonna for a number of purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000008-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Belladonna and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000008-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Belladonna ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000008-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Belladonna and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Cisapride (Propulsid) Belladonna contains atropine. Atropine can reduce the effects of cisapride. Taking belladonna with cisapride might reduce the effects of cisapride. Drying medications (Anticholinergic drugs) Belladonna can block a chemical in the body called acetylcholine, which has many important functions. Some medications, called anticholinergic drugs, also block acetylcholine. There is some concern that taking them together might increase the risk for confusion, blurred vision, increased sweating, and increased heart rate.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000008-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Belladonna and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with herbs and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000008-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Belladonna and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000008-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Belladonna ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>