<Document id="0000078" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1019.html">

<Focus>Pycnogenol</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000078-1" qtype="information">What is Pycnogenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Maritime pine trees (Pinus pinaster) grow in countries on the Mediterranean Sea. Its bark may be helpful for asthma and improved leg circulation. 

Maritime pine contains chemicals that might improve blood flow, stimulate the immune system, reduce swelling, prevent infections, and have antioxidant effects. Maritime pine trees that grow in southwest France are used to make Pycnogenol, the trademarked name for a specific maritime pine bark extract.  

Maritime pine bark extract is used for asthma, high cholesterol, decline in memory, ADHD, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support many of these uses.
 

</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000078-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Pycnogenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  MARITIME PINE  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 

 Asthma . Taking a specific maritime pine bark extract (Pycnogenol) by mouth daily, along with asthma medications, seems to decrease asthma symptoms and the need for rescue inhalers in children and adults with asthma. Keep in mind that maritime pine bark extract shouldn't be used in place of asthma medicine., 


 Poor circulation that can cause the legs to swell (chronic venous insufficiency or CVI) . Taking a specific maritime pine bark extract (Pycnogenol) by mouth seems to reduce leg pain and heaviness, as well as swelling, in people with circulation problems. , 

 Osteoarthritis . Taking a specific maritime pine bark extract (Pycnogenol) by mouth might improve some symptoms of knee osteoarthritis. It also might reduce the need for pain medications in some people. , 

 Possibly ineffective for... 

 High cholesterol . Taking a specific maritime pine bark extract (Pycnogenol) doesn't lower low-density lipoprotein (LDL or "bad") cholesterol in people with high cholesterol., 

 

There is interest in using maritime pine bark for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000078-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Pycnogenol and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000078-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Pycnogenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000078-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Pycnogenol and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Maritime pine might lower blood sugar levels. Taking maritime pine along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications that decrease the immune system (Immunosuppressants) Maritime pine can increase the activity of the immune system. Some medications, such as those used after a transplant, decrease the activity of the immune system. Taking maritime pine along with these medications might decrease the effects of these medications. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Maritime pine might slow blood clotting. Taking maritime pine along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000078-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Pycnogenol and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Maritime pine might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Maritime pine might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000078-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Pycnogenol and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000078-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Pycnogenol ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>