<Document id="0000062" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/1081.html">

<Focus>Mangosteen</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000062-1" qtype="information">What is Mangosteen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Mangosteen (Garcinia mangostana) is a plant that grows in Southeast Asia. The fruit is dark purple or red. The fruit pulp is slightly acidic and sweet.  

Mangosteen contains chemicals that might act as antioxidants and fight infections.  

People use mangosteen for serious gum infections, obesity, muscle strength, diarrhea, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses.  

Don't confuse mangosteen with garcinia. These are not the same.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000062-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Mangosteen ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  MANGOSTEEN  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 


 A serious gum infection (periodontitis) . Taking mangosteen by mouth or applying a gel containing mangosteen to the gums might help improve gum health., 


 
There is interest in using mangosteen for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000062-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Mangosteen and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000062-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Mangosteen ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000062-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Mangosteen and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Mangosteen might slow blood clotting. Taking mangosteen along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding. Minor Be watchful with this combination. Donepezil (Aricept) Mangosteen might increase the effects of donepezil.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000062-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Mangosteen and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Mangosteen might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000062-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Mangosteen and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000062-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Mangosteen ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>