<Document id="0000088" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/909.html">

<Focus>Shark cartilage</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000088-1" qtype="information">What is Shark cartilage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Shark cartilage is the tissue that provides support for fins in sharks (Squalus acanthias). It mainly comes from sharks caught in the Pacific Ocean.  

Shark cartilage became a popular medicine in the 1970s. But its popularity led to a decline in shark numbers. It was previously suggested that sharks don't get cancer, so consuming their cartilage might help prevent cancer in humans. But it is now clear that sharks do get cancer, and research hasn't shown benefits for cancer in humans. 

People use shark cartilage for cancer, scaly itchy skin (psoriasis), osteoarthritis, and many other conditions, but there is no good scientific evidence supporting these uses. 
 
Don't confuse shark cartilage with bovine cartilage, or with chondroitin, which can be sourced from shark cartilage.
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000088-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Shark cartilage ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  SHARK CARTILAGE  are as follows: Likely ineffective for... Cancer . Taking shark cartilage by mouth does not benefit people with advanced, previously treated cancers, including breast, colon, lung, prostate, and brain cancer. ,  

There is interest in using shark cartilage for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000088-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Shark cartilage and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000088-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Shark cartilage ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000088-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Shark cartilage and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications that decrease the immune system (Immunosuppressants) Shark cartilage can increase the activity of the immune system. Some medications, such as those used after a transplant, decrease the activity of the immune system. Taking shark cartilage along with these medications might decrease the effects of these medications.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000088-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Shark cartilage and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Calcium Shark cartilage contains calcium and might raise calcium levels. Using it along with calcium supplements might make calcium levels too high.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000088-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Shark cartilage and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Acidic fruit juices such as orange, apple, grape, or tomato, can lower the strength of shark cartilage. If shark cartilage is added to a fruit juice to improve flavor, it should be consumed right away.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000088-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Shark cartilage ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>