<Document id="0000020" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/923.html">

<Focus>Blue-green algae</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000020-1" qtype="information">What is Blue-green algae ?</Question>
			<Answer>Blue-green algae are a group of bacteria. They can be used as a source of protein, but contain no more protein than meat or milk. 

Blue-green algae produce blue-green colored pigments and are high in protein, iron, and other minerals. They grow in saltwater and some large freshwater lakes. They have been used for food for several centuries in Mexico and some African countries. In the US, they've been sold in supplements since the late 1970s. 

People use blue-green algae for treating high blood pressure and as a protein supplement. It's also used for high levels of cholesterol or other fats (lipids) in the blood, diabetes, obesity, and many other conditions. But there is no good scientific evidence to support these other uses. 

Some blue-green algae products are grown under controlled conditions. Others are grown in a natural setting, where they're more likely to be contaminated. Only use products that have been tested and are free of contaminants such as heavy metals, liver toxins called microcystins, and harmful bacteria. Don't confuse blue-green algae with other algaes, like Ascophyllum nodosum, Ecklonia cava, Fucus Vesiculosis, or Laminaria. 
</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000020-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Blue-green algae ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  BLUE-GREEN ALGAE  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 
 High blood pressure . Taking blue-green algae by mouth seems to reduce blood pressure in some people with high blood pressure., 
 

There is interest in using blue-green algae for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000020-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Blue-green algae and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000020-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Blue-green algae ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000020-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Blue-green algae and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Blue-green algae might lower blood sugar levels. Taking blue-green algae along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications that decrease the immune system (Immunosuppressants) Blue-green algae can increase the activity of the immune system. Some medications, such as those used after a transplant, decrease the activity of the immune system. Taking blue-green algae along with these medications might decrease the effects of these medications. Medications that slow blood clotting (Anticoagulant / Antiplatelet drugs) Blue-green algae might slow blood clotting. Taking blue-green algae along with medications that also slow blood clotting might increase the risk of bruising and bleeding.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000020-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Blue-green algae and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood sugar Blue-green algae might lower blood sugar. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might lower blood sugar too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include aloe, bitter melon, cassia cinnamon, chromium, and prickly pear cactus. Herbs and supplements that might slow blood clotting Blue-green algae might slow blood clotting and increase the risk of bleeding. Taking it with other supplements with similar effects might increase the risk of bleeding in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include garlic, ginger, ginkgo, nattokinase, and Panax ginseng. Iron Blue-green algae can decrease the amount of iron the body can absorb. Taking blue-green algae with iron supplements might decrease the effects of the iron supplement.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000020-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Blue-green algae and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>Keep in mind that taking blue-green algae can decrease the amount of iron the body can absorb from food and supplements.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000020-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Blue-green algae ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>