<Document id="0000005" source="MPlusHerbsSupplements" url="https://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/druginfo/natural/953.html">

<Focus>Ashwagandha</Focus>
<FocusAnnotations>
	<Category>Drug</Category>
</FocusAnnotations>
<QAPairs>
	<QAPair pid="1">
			<Question qid="0000005-1" qtype="information">What is Ashwagandha ?</Question>
			<Answer>Ashwagandha is an evergreen shrub that grows in Asia and Africa. It is commonly used for stress. There is little evidence for its use as an "adaptogen."  

Ashwagandha contains chemicals that might help calm the brain, reduce swelling, lower blood pressure, and alter the immune system. 

Since ashwagandha is traditionally used as an adaptogen, it is used for many conditions related to stress. Adaptogens are believed to help the body resist physical and mental stress. Some of the conditions it is used for include insomnia, aging, anxiety and many others, but there is no good scientific evidence to support most of these uses. There is also no good evidence to support using ashwagandha for COVID-19. 

Don't confuse ashwagandha with Physalis alkekengi. Both are known as winter cherry. Also, don't confuse ashwagandha with American ginseng, Panax ginseng, or eleuthero.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="2">
			<Question qid="0000005-2" qtype="how effective is it">How effective is Ashwagandha ?</Question>
			<Answer>Natural Medicines Comprehensive Database  rates effectiveness based on scientific evidence according to the following scale:  Effective, Likely Effective, Possibly Effective, Possibly Ineffective, Likely Ineffective, Ineffective, and Insufficient Evidence to Rate. The effectiveness ratings for  ASHWAGANDHA  are as follows: Possibly effective for... 
 A type of persistent anxiety marked by exaggerated worry and tension (generalized anxiety disorder or GAD) . Taking ashwagandha by mouth seems to improve anxiety in people with persistent anxiety. , 

 Insomnia . Taking ashwagandha by mouth seems to improve overall sleep and sleep quality in some people., 

 Stress . Taking ashwagandha by mouth seems to help reduce stress in some people. It might also help reduce stress-related weight gain., 

 

There is interest in using ashwagandha for a number of other purposes, but there isn't enough reliable information to say whether it might be helpful.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="3">
			<Question qid="0000005-3" qtype="how does it work">What is the action of Ashwagandha and how does it work ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="4">
			<Question qid="0000005-4" qtype="precautions">Are there safety concerns or special precautions about Ashwagandha ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="5">
			<Question qid="0000005-5" qtype="interactions with medications">Are there interactions between Ashwagandha and other medications ?</Question>
			<Answer>Moderate Be cautious with this combination. Medications for diabetes (Antidiabetes drugs) Ashwagandha might lower blood sugar levels. Taking ashwagandha along with diabetes medications might cause blood sugar to drop too low. Monitor your blood sugar closely. Medications for high blood pressure (Antihypertensive drugs) Ashwagandha might lower blood pressure. Taking ashwagandha along with medications that lower blood pressure might cause blood pressure to go too low. Monitor your blood pressure closely. Medications that decrease the immune system (Immunosuppressants) Ashwagandha can increase the activity of the immune system. Some medications, such as those used after a transplant, decrease the activity of the immune system. Taking ashwagandha along with these medications might decrease the effects of these medications. Sedative medications (Benzodiazepines) Ashwagandha might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Some medications, called sedatives, can also cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking ashwagandha with sedative medications might cause breathing problems and/or too much sleepiness. Sedative medications (CNS depressants) Ashwagandha might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Some medications, called sedatives, can also cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking ashwagandha with sedative medications might cause breathing problems and/or too much sleepiness. Thyroid hormone The body naturally produces thyroid hormones. Ashwagandha might increase how much thyroid hormone the body produces. Taking ashwagandha with thyroid hormone pills might cause too much thyroid hormone in the body, and increase the effects and side effects of thyroid hormone.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="6">
			<Question qid="0000005-6" qtype="interactions with herbs and supplements">Are there interactions between Ashwagandha and herbs and supplements ?</Question>
			<Answer>Herbs and supplements that might lower blood pressure Ashwagandha might lower blood pressure. Taking it with other supplements that have the same effect might cause blood pressure to drop too much. Examples of supplements with this effect include andrographis, casein peptides, L-arginine, niacin, and stinging nettle. Herbs and supplements with sedative properties Ashwagandha might cause sleepiness and slowed breathing. Taking it along with other supplements with similar effects might cause too much sleepiness and/or slowed breathing in some people. Examples of supplements with this effect include hops, kava, L-tryptophan, melatonin, and valerian.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="7">
			<Question qid="0000005-7" qtype="interactions with foods">Are there interactions between Ashwagandha and foods ?</Question>
			<Answer>There are no known interactions with foods.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
	<QAPair pid="8">
			<Question qid="0000005-8" qtype="dose">What is the dosage of Ashwagandha ?</Question>
			<Answer>No information found.</Answer>
	</QAPair>
</QAPairs>
</Document>